<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Correspondence Between Richard Leopold and George Kennan,
                    February-March 1957</title>
                <title type="short">Leopold-Kennan Correspondence, 1957</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1957-03-21">March 21, 1957</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1957-03-21-kennan-to-leopold.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 570 KB, 5pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 1, Advisory Committee on the Foreign
                    Relations Series 1961-1964.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 7, <ref
                    target="../chapter-7#fn81">Footnote 81</ref></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="leopold-to-kennan">
                <head>Richard W. Leopold to George F. Kennan</head>
                <dateline>3 February 1957</dateline>
                <p>I would be grateful if you could steal some time from your busy schedule to think
                    about the future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, a
                    problem I mentioned to you briefly on Friday evening. With your background and
                    knowledge you can be most helpful, I am sure, to the historical guild on this
                    matter; and I have already taken the liberty of suggesting your name as a most
                    appropriate member of two committees which will have to consider this problem.
                    One is a committee of the American Historical Association known as the Committee
                    on the Historian and the Federal Government. That group is already in existence
                    and I have been a member of it. The other is an Advisory Committee of the
                    Department of State, a body just now being formed.</p>
                <p>The problem, as I see it, is what principle of selection should govern the
                    printing of documents relations to American foreign policy as we reach the
                    period of the Second World War. Can that story be reconstructed from the files
                    of the Department of State alone? The answer must surely be in the negative. To
                    a certain extent, such has always been the case. Never could the official
                    archives tell us everything. But beginning in 1941 the problem becomes more
                    acute because, presumably, more and more key documents never came to rest in the
                    Department's archives. These are to be found either in the private papers of key
                    figures or in the records of other departments, notably the Army and Navy.</p>
                <p>Until recently the editors of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    did not feel obliged to reproduce anything that could not be found in the files
                    of the Department of State. This was the policy that underlay those extremely
                    useful supplements on the First World War and Russia, 1918-1919. Now some
                    attempt is being made to gather materials from Hyde Park and elsewhere. In one
                    sense this new approach is commendable, for it enriches the record. In another
                    sense it is both futile and dangerous: futile because there are obvious limits
                    to the amount of material from private collections that can be reprinted, and
                    dangerous because it exposes the editors to the charge of selectivity and
                    intentional distortion or suppression. I have expressed my fears on this point
                    in my brief review of the Yalta volume which appeared in the December issue of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi>.</p>
                <p>There is still another facet of this problem. It involves the official papers in
                    the Department of Defense. The editors of the series have done little with
                    these, and yet they obviously shed much light on the formulation of foreign
                    policy. Here the Department of State has to deal with another and coordinate
                    branch of the executive.</p>
                <p>My own feeling, for what it is worth, is that the time has come to take the
                    compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series out of the
                    hands of the Department of State and make it the responsibility of some
                    inter-departmental agency. But how this can be done and where it should be
                    located puzzles me. Such a transfer may create more problems than it solves.</p>
                <p>I would like very much to have your views on these questions, if not now, at some
                    future date when you have had the leisure to ponder them. I have had them very
                    much on my mind ever since 1951, when I first began to write brief notices of
                    the volumes for the <hi rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical
                    Review</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="woodward-to-kennan">
                <head>L.E. Woodward to George F. Kennan</head>
                <dateline>8 March 1957</dateline>
                <p>Dear Kennan: Here are a few stray notes on Prof. L's most interesting letter.
                    LEW.</p>
                <p>I can of course speak on this question only from the point of view of my English
                    experience. In the Documents on British Foreign Policy we limited ourselves to
                    printing <hi rend="underline">in the text</hi> documents contained in the
                    Foreign Office Archives (exceptionally we have printed <hi rend="underline">in
                        the text</hi> a few documents from other archives - mainly Cabinet Archives
                    - but these exceptions are only in cases where, for some reason or other, a
                    document which ought to have been registered in the F.O. archives was not there,
                    and we were able to get a copy from elsewhere). We have printed in the
                    appendices, or given extracts in footnotes, from documents in other archives. We
                    have been very sparing about this - for the reason which Professor Leopold
                    mentions - Once you get away from the F.O. archives, there is no end to the
                    amount of material you might include, and you are - as Professor Leopold says -
                    risking the charges of selectivity, distortion, and suppression. (This is, by
                    the way, one reason why we did not follow Gooch and Temperley - our predecessors
                    in editing F.O. volumes of documents - in printing - as they did - a <hi
                        rend="underline">selection</hi> of minutes. It is impracticable to print <hi
                        rend="underline">all</hi> minutes and undesirable to <hi rend="underline"
                        >select</hi> from them* [*Our rule has been to include minutes only when
                    they state <hi rend="underline">facts</hi> not mentioned in the text of a
                    document.]) We took the view that it was better to limit ourselves to the F.O.
                    archives - scholars who use our material will then know that, although they are
                    not getting all the story, they <hi rend="underline">are</hi> getting all that
                    the F.O. archives can tell them in the form of documents received and
                    transmitted. In any case the bulk and number of such documents is such that - if
                    you aim at completeness within these limits - it is not easy to print much more
                    without making the collection unwieldy. The British collection differs to some
                    extent from the U.S. collection in that it does not aim at covering the whole
                    field of activities of British diplomacy. It singles out certain major subjects
                    and countries and tries to be complete on those subjects; other subjects and
                    countries are not given a place at all - viz. we have not, as far as I remember,
                    published a single despatch or telegram to or from central or South America. We
                    have thereby saved a good deal of space, and though we have been criticized by
                    people interested in Portugal or Siam, our method has been generally
                    approved.</p>
                <p>I have myself found - in using For. Relations volumes - the inclusion of material
                    from outside the archives of the State Dept. a little disconcerting because I
                    have always felt that - in dealing with this “outside” material - the editors
                    were unable to apply the same standards of “completeness” which they would apply
                    to the material in the S.D. archives. You thus had a kind of “double standard” -
                    but this is just what you don't want in a collection of documents.</p>
                <p>The question of material in the archives of the Service depts is an obvious
                    difficulty, though less difficult - on the British side - than one might expect.
                    For one thing all the reports from senior attachés go through the ordinary
                    embassy or legation channels, and are in the F.O. archives - but more important
                    is the fact that practically all the main issues, though not technical details,
                    in which defense consideration are of importance are discussed in the F.O
                    despatches. I should guess that to some extent this must also be the case in the
                    S. Dept. documents - though there may be some differences because important
                    despatches to ambassadors explaining British policy are nearly always approved -
                    at least in general terms - by the Cabinet, and therefore cover the whole field
                    - including the views of the Service Ministers on the defence aspects.</p>
                <p>I would not feel competent to say much about the idea of putting the compilation
                    of the Foreign Relations series into the hands of an inter-departmental agency,
                    but I can see endless difficulties in this if it were applied in Great Britain.
                    For one thing no single dept would feel that the production of the volumes was
                    its particular responsibility. We have found it most useful to be able to get
                    the Foreign Office to weigh in when there has been a question of publishing
                    documents which are in the F.O archives but are also in the Treasury archives
                    (e.g. correspondence about inter allied debts). The Treasury has no interest in
                    the publication of our volumes, and is inclined to say “keep off”, whereas the
                    F.O. can weigh-in - from the top - in the interest of making its volumes
                    complete and adequate. Unless U.S. depts are not as “departmental” in outlook as
                    British departments, I should be afraid that the interdepartmental organisation
                    would be regarded as nobody's child, and that it would in fact lose out in any
                    conflict with a particular dept. I should also be afraid that the editorial
                    supervision would get unwieldy. I may be biased about this but Rohan Butler and
                    I have often thought that the smallness of our staff - two editors, each with
                    one assistant, and one F.O. woman clerk between us to keep track of documents,
                    with our letters, etc. - has had certain advantages. We have had to do an
                    immense amount of work ourselves which - with a larger staff - we would have
                    delegated, but of the result is that, while the historical masterpieces we might
                    ourselves have written if we had not been tied down so much remain unwritten,
                    the actual selection and editing of F.O. documents has been done better because
                    we have had to do pretty well all of it ourselves. If the editors have to range
                    over the archives of half a dozen departments, they must delegate a great deal
                    of the work, and they must depend too much on their assistants. If you try to
                    avoid this by having a larger body of senior editors, it is harder to keep a
                    common standard. As I have just said, a historian who takes on the job of
                    editing modern documents will find that this work crowds out pretty well
                    everything else, but at least - if he is limited to one set of archives - he can
                    learn to master them. He could not possibly master more than one set. So I would
                    be inclined to say - let the S.D. keep the For. Rel. in its hands - and let it
                    be content to produce its own material - even if the historian will also have to
                    use other material - in any case the diplomatic record has its own very high
                    value and completeness. If other depts want to follow the example of the S.D.
                    and publish their records, let them do so - and any problems of policy - large
                    or small - can be discussed by the respective editors as and when such problems
                    arise.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="freund-to-kennan">
                <head>Freund to George F. Kennan</head>
                <dateline>13 March 1957</dateline>
                <p>Woodward's letter is a very interesting one, especially because he has so much
                    experience in this type of work in Britain. But the British experience is not
                    really analogous to the problems facing the U.S. in similar publication
                    ventures.</p>
                <p>For one thing, the scale of the work to be done here, if the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series is to continue and expand, is much greater.
                    This is not only so because the volume of diplomatic exchange is greater than
                    the F.O. has to deal with, but also because the S.D. would not be able to limit
                    publication to exchanges with only a small number of countries at specified
                    times, and, perhaps most important, because our government’s policy formulation
                    and implementation processes are more unwieldy than Great Britain's, and not as
                    well coordinated. For example, I do not believe that the decision and actions
                    leading to U.S. approval of German rearmament in 1950 can be revealed without
                    publication of Pentagon materials of which copies would, presumably, not be
                    available at the S.D. Other departments and agencies and certain coordinating
                    bodies would also have to give over materials if the published collection of
                    documents is to be of any real value.</p>
                <p>Woodward is undoubtedly right in saying that the efficient way of producing
                    volumes of documents is to give full responsibility to qualified historians who
                    will work with a very small staff. But this advice, it seems to me, is
                    incompatible with another of his suggestions, namely that the S.D. should keep
                    the series in its hands. Surely what the S.D. would do is to retain the services
                    of one or two “big name” historians (e.g. Langer and Gleason) who would <hi
                        rend="underline">supervise</hi> the work of a large staff of researchers and
                    interlopers. The work of such an aggregation would not inspire confidence in
                    their product. Nor would S.D. sponsorship tend to elicit cooperation with the
                    Defense and other department and agencies without whose contribution of material
                    (i.e. access to their archives by qualified historians) the volumes would be
                    incomplete at best, and very possibly misleading.</p>
                <p>Surely the S.D. and other departments much have a hand in producing these
                    volumes. But why not limit their involvement to approving or disapproving of the
                    documents to be published after they have been collected by historians who do
                    the actual research and editing with the help of a minimum number of civil
                    service personnel aid. Finally, it would seem to me much wiser to have the
                    project sponsored by a private source or sources (e.g. the Ford Foundation) than
                    to have the historians paid by and subjected to any sort of unusual loyalties to
                    the Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="kennan-to-leopold">
                <head>George F. Kennan to Richard W. Leopold</head>
                <dateline>21 March 1957</dateline>
                <p>I have been slow in replying to the questions in your letter of February 3 about
                    the future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series; but it is, as
                    you are aware, a difficult problem, to which ready answers do not present
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>I took the liberty of showing your letter to my colleague here at the Institute,
                    Sir Llewellyn Woodward, who is - as you know - one of the two editors of the
                    British series. I enclose a copy (or rather, a deciphered version - you know
                    what some British handwriting is) of his comment. I also enclose comments
                    written by Gerald Freund, whom you met here, on Woodward's paper.</p>
                <p>Will you permit me to continue to reserve my final comment until I have thought
                    about this further? Recognizing the good sense and authority of all that
                    Woodward says, I am impressed, as is Freund, with the differences in the
                    situation here from that which prevails in England. My own experiences,
                    particularly during the last war, lead me to doubt that a series of documents
                    confined to the State Department materials alone would be in any way adequate to
                    tell the story of America's involvement in any one of a number of important
                    issues. My thoughts run, at the moment, to the idea of the government's
                    contracting the documentary publication out to a semi-private academic unit -
                    along the lines (organizationally, not substantively) of the M.I.T. Center for
                    International Studies or the Rand Corporation, with the idea that this unit
                    would get out documentary series addressed to given subjects or episodes of
                    major importance rather than attempt to cover the field chronologically, by
                    countries. I am sure, too, that this thought will have many drawbacks. But it
                    would permit the assembling of the range of the material that would be necessary
                    to give any coherent concept of what transpired, and the intensive and highly
                    responsible selectivity that would have to be exercised if the final product
                    were to be kept to manageable dimensions.</p>
                <p>It might be necessary to take certain special precautions to assure high
                    scholarly capability, wisdom, and integrity on the part of those to whom this
                    really great responsibility would be given. I could conceive that it might be
                    desirable, for example, to establish a panel of representatives of such
                    organizations as the American Historical Association and the Council of Learned
                    Societies, merely for the purpose of making nominations from which the
                    government might select the scholars who would be entrusted with this work.
                    Surely, <hi rend="underline">some</hi> collaboration between public and private
                    effort would be necessary to implement any idea of this sort. But the
                    alternative would be to try to carry on with the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, as heretofore produced; and you have yourself set
                    forth the reasons why this would be difficult.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
