<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Bernard Noble to Melville Osborne, November
                    1958</title>
                <title type="short">Noble to Osborne, 1958</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-27">January 27, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1958-11-03">November 3, 1958</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1958-11-03-noble-to-osborne.pdf">PDF</ref>, 288 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-WW-9: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, Arthur
                    Kogan Files, 1945-1980 (83 D 230), Box 2, Foreign Classified Documents General.
                    Official Use Only. Drafted by E. Ralph Perkins. Posted from an uninitialed
                    carbon copy of the memorandum.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 7, <ref
                    target="../chapter-7#fn67">Footnote 67</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From G. Bernard Noble (Chief of the Historical Division) to
                    Melville Osborne (Office of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs)</head>
                <dateline>November 3, 1958</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Clearance with Foreign Governments of Reports of Conversations with
                    Foreign Officials prior to Publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</hi></p>
                <p>Your memorandum to me of September 22, 1958 raises the broad question of
                    Department policy regarding clearance of records of conversations with foreign
                    officials, not just the clearance of a specific <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volume or the clearance of papers with countries relations
                    with which are within the responsibility of the ARA area. As indicated in my
                    memorandum of September 15, 1958 to MID - Mr. Blanchard I feel that such an
                    extension of our clearance practices as you recommend would be most unfortunate
                    in circumscribing the freedom of our Government to publish its official records.
                    I am therefore offering the following comments on some of the points you
                    raised:</p>
                <p>1. You cite three cases as illustrations of embarrassments that can be caused if
                    reports on conversations by our diplomatic representatives with foreign
                    officials are not cleared with the respective foreign governments. It is
                    interesting that none of the three cases mentioned in paragraph (1) on the first
                    page of your memorandum of September 22 regarding the reluctance of Mexican
                    officials to have records of their conversations published are properly
                    connected with <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. You state that Mexican
                    officials are reluctant to confide in our representatives, “knowing, as they
                    inevitably do, that records of their conversations may be published by the
                    United States at will.” This generalization scarcely applies, however, to such
                    accounts as appear years later in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes as part of the official record of United States diplomacy. Comments on
                    the three cases cited follow:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(a) Mr. Crockett’s memorandum of September 2, 1957 (not October 4, 1957)
                        referred to apprehensions by a Mexican official resulting from a report that
                        United States backing was involved in his candidacy for President. This
                        report was originally mentioned in a private publication which was discussed
                        in Congressional hearings. Mr. Crockett appropriately pointed out that there
                        was a confusion of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> with the
                        publication of Congressional hearings on current matters, and that the
                        report which gave rise to the official’s apprehensions was entirely
                        unrelated to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Such
                        confusion is unfortunate but is hardly a reason for changing policy as to
                        publishing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</item>
                    <item>(b) The second case mentioned refers to a memorandum by the Ambassador in
                        Mexico on a conversation of January 29, 1958 with the Mexican Finance
                        Minister regarding a claims case. The Finance Minister remarked that he
                        might have a memorandum of a previous conversation although he did not like
                        to make memoranda of conversations and he did not usually do so. In this
                        case his secretary produced a memorandum which recorded what an American
                        official had told him, but not his own part in the conversation. No mention
                        was made of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> or any other
                        publication.</item>
                    <item>(c) The case reported in Report No. 664, September 29, 1949 involved a
                        meeting in which Mexican and United States officials took part to discuss
                        stationing customs inspectors at the Mexico City airport. A Mexican Foreign
                        Office official made certain changes in the language of a record of a
                        previous conversation, eliminating certain statements that he preferred not
                        to have in writing. The reason is not given, but it could as well have been
                        hesitation to give officially certain commitments regarding customs
                        inspection as fear of publication some years later. No mention of
                        publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> or elsewhere was
                        made.</item>
                </list>
                <p>2. You suggest that there is an inconsistency in our practice of clearing with
                    foreign governments papers originating with these governments and not clearing
                    with them the records made by our diplomatic officials of conversations with
                    officials of such foreign governments. The fact is, however, that documents
                    received from and originating with a foreign government are in an entirely
                    different category as far as responsibility for publication is concerned, for
                    reports by American officials on conversations with officials of foreign
                    governments. The former represent in most cases official government statements
                    for which the originating government must assume responsibility. It is entirely
                    proper therefore that clearance from the originating government should be
                    obtained. The report by an American officials of a conversation with a foreign
                    official is our own document for which the other government need assume no
                    responsibility. The foreign official may have been speaking on his own, not
                    presenting an official government view. Also, in case the issue is raised, it
                    can be said that the report is merely the interpretation of the American officer
                    reporting.</p>
                <p>3. It is suggested that foreign officials will not talk frankly for fear a report
                    of the conversation may be published some fifteen or more years hence. This
                    concern seems to be exaggerated, but if the danger exists it is doubtful that
                    foreign government clearance would be a real remedy. Permission to print is
                    requested not from the individual whose conversation is reported but from
                    foreign office officials at the time of clearance. It might be fully as damaging
                    to put the report in the hands of an official in the foreign office as to
                    publish it. At least, if it becomes known through publication in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> it will be in a proper context.</p>
                <p>4. Clearance with foreign governments of reports of conversation would often put
                    us in the dilemma of presenting small items of conversation out of context or
                    presenting the entire document containing the reported statements along with
                    additional comment by the American official. In effect, that would often give a
                    right of censorship to the foreign government over the entire document, in cases
                    where the real objection might well be to comments of the American official
                    rather than to what the foreign official is reported to have said. In objecting
                    to clearance this would not need to be stated. In many cases it would not be
                    feasible to cut out what the foreign official is reported to have said without
                    omitting the entire document or at least an important portion of the
                    document.</p>
                <p>5. The suggestion is made that documents reporting conversations could be
                    presented for clearance, but that if a government objected merely because it had
                    no record of the conversation or because its records differ “we should have to
                    inform it that we could not defer publication for these reasons”. This does not
                    seem to be practical. To submit a document to a foreign government and then to
                    publish it over such government’s objections would certainly cause far more
                    resentment than to publish it without asking for clearance.</p>
                <p>6. Although we may sometimes anticipate difficulties in obtaining clearance for
                    these documents from foreign government, it does not follow that publication by
                    us without such clearance would necessarily be contrary to the wishes of these
                    foreign governments. There is a real difference between giving consent to
                    publication and having no objection to publication if done entirely on the
                    responsibility of another government. It is also probably true that in many
                    foreign offices that are timid officials who would hesitate to give approval to
                    publication in the vague fear that there might be some repercussion for which
                    they would be held responsible.</p>
                <p>7. There may, of course, be exceptions to this long-standing rule that reports by
                    our officials on conversations with foreign officials are not normally submitted
                    to foreign governments for clearance. For example, when such reports contain
                    significant and apparently damaging quoted passages from statement of foreign
                    officials, these reports may, in general, be submitted for clearance. A
                    distinction can appropriately be made between documents which report
                    conversations in direct quotation and those which merely report the substance of
                    conversations. In the case of direct quotations the implication is that
                    stenographic notes were made and that the statements are quoted just as stated,
                    though in fact this may not be the case. It is difficult for the person quoted
                    to deny responsibility. Most reports of conversations, however, are written some
                    time after the conversation and they paraphrase only the substance of the
                    conversation, giving the writer’s interpretation. These are quite different from
                    direct quotations and may generally be published on our own responsibility.</p>
                <p>8. In exceptional cases, also, merely paraphrased reports may be submitted for
                    clearance. If, for example, such a report is in the nature of an agreed minute
                    of a conference discussion, it should be submitted. Conceivably there may be
                    other cases when shrewd judgement would require such reports to be submitted for
                    clearance, or possibly for information.</p>
                <p>9. In cases of this kind no hard and fast line can be drawn. In the last resort
                    tough-minded judgment is called for to determine whether a given set of facts
                    can justify the exclusion of a document of substantive importance from the
                    published record of our diplomacy. It seems clear, however, that to require that
                    all documents reporting on conversations with foreign officials be submitted to
                    foreign governments for clearance would not only be contrary to long-established
                    practice, but it would frequently cause unnecessary embarrassments in our
                    relations with such governments, and would also vastly complicate the over-all
                    problem of editing and publishing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
