<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Transcript of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1959</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Transcript, 1959</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2015-02-25">February 25, 2015</date>
                <date type="created" when="1958-11-07">November 6, 1959</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1959-11-06-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 3.4 MB, 187pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 1, 1959-Min. of Meeting 11/6-7/59.
                    Confidential. Hand-written corrections and some editorial annotations have been
                    applied to the transcript below. See the pdf for the original revisions to and
                    annotations on the document.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn29">Footnote 29</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Transcript of 1959 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 6-7, 1959</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p rend="underline">Members of the Committee:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Dexter Perkins, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Dr. Clarence A. Berdahl</item>
                    <item>Dr. Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                    <item>Dr. Fred H. Harrington</item>
                    <item>Dr. Richard W. Leopold</item>
                    <item>Dr. Philip W. Thayer</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Representing the Department of State:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Edwin M. J. Kretzmann, [<hi rend="italic">Deputy</hi>] Assistant
                        Secretary, Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>G. Bernard Noble, HD</item>
                    <item>Mrs. Velma J. Cassidy, HD</item>
                    <item>Rogers P. Churchill, HD</item>
                    <item>Olcott H. Deming, AF</item>
                    <item>Herbert Fine, HD</item>
                    <item>Jack M. Fleischer, EUR</item>
                    <item>William M. Franklin, HD</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, HD</item>
                    <item>Ralph R. Goodwin, HD</item>
                    <item>Douglas W. Houston, HD</item>
                    <item>John Rison Jones, Jr., HD</item>
                    <item>Frank P. Lockhart, FE</item>
                    <item>Gustave A. Nuermberger, HD</item>
                    <item>E. Ralph Perkins, HD</item>
                    <item>John Gilbert Reid, HD</item>
                    <item>Newton O. Sappington, HD</item>
                    <item>Harold Sims, NEA</item>
                    <item>William Slany, HD</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer, HD</item>
                    <item>Almon R. Wright, HD</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="right">Reported by:</p>
                <list rend="right">
                    <item>E. C. Richard</item>
                    <item>E. C. Moyer</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a table of contents</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">PROCEEDINGS</hi></p>
                <p>[The meeting was convened at 9:30 a.m., Dr. Dexter Perkins presiding.]</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: First I would like to have Ed Kretzmann speak to us.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, gentlemen, again it is my happy duty to welcome you to the
                    Department. I do this on behalf of Mr. Berding, whom you will see later. They
                    are all in the Secretary’s staff meeting this morning. I also welcome you on
                    half of the Secretary.</p>
                <p>I might say for your information that we had a little discussion in the
                    Secretary’s staff meeting of your pending visit yesterday, and they all
                    expressed great interest in this joint review of our problem here, also some
                    apprehensions about as our relations in the world become more complicated and
                    more diffuse, diverse, are the problems of keeping closer to events and foreign
                    relations becoming more and more acute. But I think we are all aware of
                    that.</p>
                <p>I’d like to say that we are grateful to you gentlemen for giving of your time and
                    this accommodation in coming in at this time, spending a few days with us.</p>
                <p>We will do all we can, on our part, the Department officers, to assist you in
                    your view of the problems you have. There are two details I would like to
                    mention and seek your consent on. The policy planning staff people would
                    like—as they said to me yesterday—with so many eminent brains in the
                    Department, to pick them. [Laughter] So they asked if it is convenient with you
                    in your schedule if they could come in at twelve this morning, just before we go
                    to lunch, and sort of discuss with you very briefly here, privately with the
                    Committee and Dr. Noble, some current aspects of foreign policy, and some ideas
                    that you may have bursting out of your minds about what we ought to do next.
                    [Laughter] And they felt that if you were agreeable, they would like very much
                    to take advantage of this.</p>
                <p>I discussed it with Bernard, and he thinks it is fine with him. If it is all
                    right with you, I will set it up.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: So I think that Dr. Morgan (?) and Mr. Carlton Savage would be
                    happy to come down and meet with you. They will come here at twelve o’clock.</p>
                <p>The Secretary will be in to see us briefly at the luncheon period. It is about
                    the only time he can get away from his present duties.</p>
                <p>I am looking forward very much to carrying on this discussion this evening at
                    supper at my house, in a less formal atmosphere, and perhaps with some other
                    stimulation; we will see.</p>
                <p>But I wish you success in your deliberations this morning, and I will be
                    available from time to time to talk with you today and tomorrow.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you very much.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Lunch is at 12:30?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes, so we don’t have to go any place from here except down
                    there.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Thank you very much.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The first order of business is a report on developments since last
                    year’s meeting, by Dr. Noble.</p>
                <p rend="underline">2. Report on developments since last year’s Meeting.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Mr. Chairman, some important things have happened since the last
                    meeting. One I suppose we ought to take notice of is the resignation of Tom
                    Bailey of Stanford from the Committee. He resigned because of his wife’s
                    condition, I believe a chronic condition, which required him to leave the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>This gives us the opportunity of welcoming Dr. Harrington, of Wisconsin. I was
                    very much interested in seeing Dr. Harrington’s biography in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Who’s Who</hi>. You other members of the Committee are doubtless better
                    acquainted with him than I am, but I have heard about him from time to time, and
                    notice that his career arose from Cornell, where he graduated, to New York
                    University, University of Wisconsin, University of Arkansas, University of West
                    Virginia, Cornell, and Oxford, as a Guggenheim Fellow, and a Ford Foundation
                    Fellow—I don’t know what that means, but—</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: They just give you your money, that is all.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: He is quite a writer, various histories, American civilization, and a
                    few other important books.</p>
                <p>And we ought to take note, obviously, also, of the recent death of Edgar
                    Turlington, a valiant member of the Committee, and I would like to raise the
                    question of whether the Committee would like to take some official note of it
                    and send Mrs. Turlington a letter. What do you think?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we might.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: If you would, I thought that Mr. Phil Thayer, also representing the
                    lawyers—</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I’d be glad to do that. Edgar and I have been friends for a good many
                    years.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Will you draft some kind of letter on behalf of the Committee?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I would be very happy to.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You may know Robert Wilson of Duke University, who has been appointed
                    to succeed Mr. Turlington, but Mr. Turlington’s passing occurred at such a late
                    date that it wasn’t possible for Wilson to accommodate his program to this, nor
                    would it have been possible for him to get clearance in time for the
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>I am sure Wilson will be a very good replacement for Turlington, although
                    Turlington certainly was an excellent member.</p>
                <p>After the close of the last meeting, as you know, you made two reports on the
                    work of the Committee, and the status of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, and I think that was a very good thing to do, to make a
                    report that could be made public, and one in which you could tell us somewhat
                    more intimately and confidentially the things that we ought to be doing that we
                    are not doing, but for which we probably ought not to be publicly spanked.</p>
                <p>I am sure all of us appreciate the tone of the report, and its reassurance that
                    we are at least doing a reasonably conscientious and competent job, even though
                    progress may not be as much as we all would like.</p>
                <p>One question about the publicity of the reports is I notice that the April issue
                    of the <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi> gave a very good
                    summary of the report, and I did not find any references to it in the <hi
                        rend="italic">American Political Science Review</hi>, or the <hi
                        rend="italic">American Journal of International Law</hi>. I think some
                    consideration might be given by our political scientists and our international
                    lawyers as to what can be done about that, and also by all the members, perhaps,
                    as to whether any notice ought to be taken at the annual meetings, historical
                    meetings. I don’t know whether you have thought about that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, I don’t know. What do you think about that, Dick?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Well, Boyd has mentioned it in his summary, that the American
                    Historical Association is represented on such a Committee. I think that is about
                    all he probably could do at that time.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: He has done that?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: He did at least one year, Bernard; I am not sure whether he did
                    both.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Your confidential report referred to a number of items. For instance,
                    you referred to the problem of documentation in the Cairo-Tehran volume, and
                    quite specifically to those on the Turkey, China and the post-war bases, and you
                    will read more about this in the memorandum which Mr. Franklin has prepared, and
                    the documents that will accompany that memorandum.</p>
                <p>We have had some success in getting some of those papers cleared and with others
                    we have had less success, as you will find out.</p>
                <p>Also, in regard to the Potsdam Conference papers, you will have noticed, I think,
                    in the report or in the paper which I have sent you that the Potsdam papers are
                    now in the clear, and you will be given, however, a review of the papers that
                    were omitted, significant papers that were omitted in the report which Mr.
                    Dougall has prepared and which will be read this afternoon.</p>
                <p>You in your report requested a speed-up of the regular series and requested that
                    the publication of these be brought up to the schedule of the Wartime Conference
                    volumes. You will, of course, see that the regular series has not yet been
                    brought abreast of the Wartime Conference volumes, if you are thinking about
                    Yalta and Potsdam, or even Cairo-Tehran. But it is on the other hand
                    approximately abreast, if not ahead in some respects of the early Wartime
                    Conferences, which were primarily military, and on which, shall we say, we have
                    been more dependent on Defense, and we have suffered very severely from our own
                    staffing inadequacies. We suffered heavily in our staffs in 1953, from
                    reductions in force at that time, and we haven’t yet recovered, and also owing
                    to priority assignments, which took the time of the staff from these other
                    papers. But, of course, they are of secondary importance. But still we are
                    anxious to get them out as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>As far as the China volumes were concerned, with which you were specifically
                    concerned last year, those from 1943 to 1949, as you probably have seen, are on
                    the shelf, and you heard eloquently explained last year by Mr. Robertson the
                    reasons for that.</p>
                <p>However, this afternoon you will be able to read, look at the volumes with what
                    we regard as the important, significant, or—if you want to use the word
                    “sensitive” passages, indicated, so that you can make your judgments on the
                    basis of the record before you.</p>
                <p>And the same applies to the volume of 1941, Volume V. You requested the release
                    of that volume. That, it is obvious, is in bound form, and you will see the
                    passages in that which are relevant and interesting, and will be able to make
                    some conclusions on the basis of your reading.</p>
                <p>You dealt with a number of other matters. You asked for a prefatory note
                    explaining the publication policy to be included in each volume, rather than
                    simply the first volume of each year. That, as you will have seen, perhaps, is
                    already adopted, and is made a practice in publication.</p>
                <p>You also requested more background material. That raises, of course, some very
                    difficult questions or problems and calls, I think, for detailed and very
                    careful discussion and consideration. It is a matter that goes to the roots of
                    our consideration of foreign relations here.</p>
                <p>[Mr. Goodrich entered the meeting.]</p>
                <p>[Off the record.]</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Shall we go on?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I was referring to the fact that you asked for background material,
                    and it is a matter of great interest to us. We are giving some consideration to
                    this, particular consideration at this time. And we would like to have
                    suggestions from you on that. It would be helpful if you have specific
                    suggestions for the type of background, whether you are more interested in
                    intra-Departmental memoranda, papers, or inter-Departmental, or whatever other
                    kind. This is a subject I hope we can discuss somewhat more fully in our
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>You suggested that the volume should include a digest of documents, by which you
                    mean what we call a “list of documents,” as well as a list of persons. Of
                    course, both these suggestions are very good suggestions, and they refer to
                    things which we have had before, except a general list of persons. We have
                    often, generally, in fact, until recently, had a list of documents. It is a
                    question of time and expense. We had to, or rather, we decided we should omit
                    the list of documents some several years ago, simply because of time and expense
                    involved.</p>
                <p>That is something which the professional members of the staff really should make,
                    and we estimate that it would take about a month of professional work to do the
                    list of persons and organize the list of documents.</p>
                <p>But, it is again worthy of consideration, and we don’t intend to say that the
                    last words have been said on this subject.</p>
                <p>As to the list of names, you will recall that I think we had decided to put names
                    in the index and I think that will be a great improvement, and it might take the
                    place, to a considerable degree at least, of the list of names. And you have
                    noted before the fact is that the identity of a person is given at the first
                    reference to him in each story, so that you can get it through the index and
                    through that reference.</p>
                <p>The question is whether you would feel strongly about having a list of names in
                    addition to the list of documents. I would say that the list of documents would
                    be next on the list of priority.</p>
                <p>Now, you referred to memoranda of conversations, a matter which has been of some
                    controversy, and said that direct quotations are undesirable in the memoranda of
                    conversations, supposedly referring in particular to statements by high foreign
                    officials, and the quotations, you said, should be paraphrased or
                    summarized.</p>
                <p>In general, we agree, that that is a good suggestion, although it might depend on
                    the sensitivity of the passage. On the question of principle, which was some
                    trouble several years ago, it is largely settled. Brazil raised the question and
                    has since receded a good deal from the insistence on exclusion of memoranda of
                    conversations by high officials.</p>
                <p>You made other suggestions. One was the suggestion that we meet two days. We were
                    delighted that you showed the interest in the work to suggest that the meeting
                    should be two days, and we will certainly, I think, provide you with the
                    material at this meeting that will keep you going for two days.</p>
                <p>You also have requested that we have representation of policy officers, and I
                    hope that we shall have. I am glad to see already this morning Mr. Lockhart
                    here, from FE, Far East; Mr. Sims, from Near East and Asia; and Mr. Fleischer,
                    from European Area.</p>
                <p>I think you will find on the last page of your little dossier a list of members
                    of the staff, the professional staff. I would like to name them:</p>
                <p>Of the General Section, Mr. Nuermberger, Chief of the General Section, Mrs.
                    Cassidy, over there, is a member of the staff, and Mr. John Rison Jones—would
                    you indicate who you are?—over there, and from the Eastern Section, Rogers
                    Churchill, Section Chief, Herbert Fine, and Ralph Goodwin at the end; also
                    Douglas Houston and John Gilbert Reid, members of that section.</p>
                <p>Western Section, Mr. Sappington, Chief; Mr. Glennon, Mr. Slany, Mr. Stauffer, and
                    Mr. Wright, members of the staff.</p>
                <p>Another thing I would like to refer to is a recent development. In an attempt to
                    save space, we are going to have the volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> on much thinner paper. That will begin with the 1942 volumes
                    and will save a considerable amount of shelf space. That is important, as well
                    as pages.</p>
                <p>We would also like to have some ideas—we thought of having type 1 point lead,
                    instead of 2. We would be glad to have your opinions. We are holding off on
                    that. The technical editors aren’t too fond of 1 point lead, as compared to 2
                    point lead.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Is the paper going to be transparent? [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Not exactly. I am sure it will last as long as this paper, fifty years
                    or so.</p>
                <p>I’d like to say how pleased I am personally—and I think all of us are—that you
                    have agreed that the members of the Committee should report on particular that
                    have come up during the year. Their acute and careful and severe attention to
                    all aspects of the publication will be helpful.</p>
                <p>I would like to call your attention to this document here [indicating] on the
                    principles and procedures for compilation and editing. The reason I do it is
                    this: I would like some time, if there were time here—it would be a fine
                    thing—to go over with you a part of that, the part which deals with the things
                    that are included, and things that are excluded from <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations.</hi></p>
                <p>I think it would be a very helpful exercise, of course, if you went over, very
                    carefully, this, first, and then we could discuss it. That would be fine. But
                    the subjects that are included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, the
                    subjects that are excluded in principle, and the types of papers that are used
                    and looked to and examined, and those that are not for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>—I hope that it may be possible to give some attention to
                    that. But there may not be time. I realize that this little interruption at
                    noon—which I am certainly all in favor of—may mean we may not get through our
                    proceedings this morning, as fully as we would like, and may likely prolong your
                    reading session this afternoon.</p>
                <p>I would like to say that I think our afternoon session ought to begin at two
                    o’clock, rather than 2:30, since luncheon will be at 12:30, and Miss LaBarr, my
                    secretary, will be over here at 2 o’clock, and will explain to all the members
                    of the Committee in careful detail problems in connection with travel.</p>
                <p>We have handed out, I believe—I am not sure—but we have these, if they haven’t
                    been handed out already and it will make it somewhat easier for you with
                    vouchers, etc.</p>
                <p>Now, Mr. Chairman, the next item on the program was the discussion of changing
                    the term of members. Would you like to postpone that until later, so we can get
                    on with the discussion?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Surely. I wonder if there are any questions for Dr. Noble in
                    connection with this report.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The point that Bernard brought up with regard to this sheet, in the
                    principles, if there seems to be some doubt in the minds of divisions, as to
                    whether there should be some rearrangement of the basic principles, on which
                    documents—this seems to me to be an item of transcendent importance.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is always subject to re-examination. My feeling is the Committee as
                    such has never addressed itself to it. We happen to be more aware this year than
                    before of the importance of careful examination, and I think that the Committee
                    ought to address itself to this.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: What would happen, on or off the record, if the Committee did come
                    up with a recommendation for changes? What would be the next step?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The next step would be to see if there was any reason why we couldn’t
                    comply with the Committee’s request.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we ought to have the time for the digestion of this
                    document before we discuss it. I think the point is well taken.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: A good many laymen don’t understand at all the principles on which
                    we have to operate.</p>
                <p>I will be glad, of course, to have other questions about Dr. Noble’s report.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: This particular question you had about saving space on the
                    shelves, I suppose this is quite important because of the additional volumes you
                    are bringing out and the size of them?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Are you fixed on the particular number of words you have per
                    page? In a great many document series they are putting many more words on a page
                    than you have. They put two columns in, or something like that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is all within the range of consideration, anything that you think
                    would improve the volume from the point of view of convenience or from any other
                    point of view, we’d be glad to have.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Assuming that the paper will not be so thin it won’t be easy to
                    handle.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No. Are you familiar with the so-called current documents? The same
                    paper is used in the <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy Current
                        Documents</hi>. It is the same that the Hill is using in its
                    publications.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We haven’t been able to, as Mr. Noble said, get the report of the
                    Committee published through journals last year. I think we ought to make the
                    effort. It means running interest, and not merely the first report. Perhaps with
                    our colleagues, and any other association—we did get it done by Boyd, in the
                    American Historical Association. We ought to try, if the report has substance,
                    to have it done in the American Political Science Association.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes. The first year they asked to write in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Science Review</hi>. Last year nothing was said about this. You
                    sent them a report.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I thought we were going to have more than one.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: They printed it the first year?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes; very inconspicuously put in the News and Notes, I think.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN:. There is a lot of important material in the report that members of
                    the profession ought to know about.</p>
                <p>Should we go on to the Report on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Was the public report printed in the State Department <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, Dexter?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is an embarrassing question. I must confess it was not, and I
                    think I should be given a vote of lack of confidence for not getting it in
                    there.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I wasn’t moving that motion; it was a question.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Has it been, in the past?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No; this is our Third Annual Meeting.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any other questions of Dr. Noble with regard to his
                    report?</p>
                <p>If not, I suppose we can pass to the next item on the agenda, which is the
                    analysis of the volumes that have been submitted to the Committee this year.</p>
                <p>First off will be the report from Professor Goodrich.</p>
                <p rend="underline">4. Report on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes by
                    members of the Committee:</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: The difficulty was I started reading it and I found the contents so
                    interesting that I spent more time reading it, learning something about the
                    substance, than I did taking a critical attitude. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>It seems to me that the first question that bothered me a bit, in looking through
                    the volume, was the heading of the material that is included in this, and part
                    of the following volume, “General,” and I didn’t find anywhere any indication of
                    what “general” is intended to cover.</p>
                <p>I take it, from the examination of the material itself, that it is intended to
                    cover, include documents relating to the law, particularly in—well, of course,
                    the war in the Far East hadn’t started, at least as far as the United States was
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Would you like Mr. Perkins to make a statement on that?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Either now or later. If he made a statement, it might save me from
                    saying some things.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It might help. Ralph, suppose you explain.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I think maybe you have a good point, and maybe we should explain in
                    the preface what is meant.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That was going to be one of my recommendations.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I should think that would be a good point. We print most of the
                    foreign relations by countries, direct relations with the countries. A good many
                    subjects come up, you can’t put under one country heading. We put those under
                    “general.” You find all these general stories relate to—they are multilateral
                    questions, really, and could we pin them down to US relations with any
                    individual country?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: [<hi rend="italic">An unknown hand marked the first half of this
                        paragraph in the left margin with an “x.”</hi>] I gathered that to be the
                    case, and I was going to make the suggestion that there should be in the preface
                    some statement indicating what was included under “general” and what was not. I
                    think that kind of breakdown is necessary and desirable. Inevitably it seems to
                    me there are many times a difficult choice to make, and I find, for example, in
                    examining this volume and the following volume—because it did seem to me rather
                    difficult to report on this volume alone, particularly since part of the general
                    material is in Volume II, and also because a lot of material that is
                    subsequently under countries is very closely related to some of the material
                    that is included under the heading of “general.”</p>
                <p>For example, just more or less by accident I found that a document on the
                    extension of the European war, invasion of Norway-Denmark by Germany, under the
                    heading of “general,” has to do with the establishment of diplomatic relations
                    with the Norwegian Government in London. Now, the question of the maintenance or
                    the establishment of diplomatic relations with the French Government in Vichy is
                    under “France,” in Volume II, as I remember.</p>
                <p>Just what is the reason for that, I don’t know, but it does raise the question, I
                    mean, why do you put it under “general,” relating to a comment on the war, or
                    under general relations with the country? I would think where there was any
                    doubt it ought to be put under the country. My inclination would be to group as
                    many documents as possible under the country heading.</p>
                <p>Now, there is another problem here, where you have, for example, a document
                    relating to the maintenance of diplomatic relations with Norway, under the
                    heading of “general,” in Volume I, and when you get to Volume II, where, as I
                    recall, NALA (?) appears—first of all, there are practically no documents
                    listed. In the second place, if you want to use that volume for the purpose of
                    finding out what relates to the establishment of diplomatic relations with NALA,
                    the index is of no value, because that covers that volume, and that particular
                    volume only.</p>
                <p>This also comes up in connection with the breakdown of countries, the adequacy of
                    the index for locating a document that deals with a particular subject matter.
                    While I think this probably is impracticable, it certainly would be desirable, I
                    think, if you could have an index, sort of a master index, for all the
                    volumes—very particularly here. If not for each volume, there ought to be a
                    very carefully prepared index which I think for the most part—I wouldn’t for
                    the most part, be critical of the index. I think it is very adequate. But
                    attention ought to be given, I think, in the index to listing under a particular
                    country subject matter all the documents that relate to a particular subject,
                    irrespective of the heading under which they appear, whether it is under, for
                    example, in the case of France, in the second volume, you have two headings,
                    extension of the European War, Invasion of France, and another heading of the
                    concern of the United States over the disposition of the French fleet.</p>
                <p>No, I don’t mean—I am confused. There are two headings in France, the concern of
                    the United States over the disposition of the French fleet, and maintenance of
                    relations of the United States with the French Government at Vichy.</p>
                <p>In the second volume you find a document that relates to concern with the
                    disposition of the French Fleet, and in this particular case you have one
                    listed, a memorandum of the Secretary of State, November 4th, on a conversation
                    with the French Ambassador, and under another heading, you have listed the
                    report of the Secretary of State to the Charge in France, Matthews, on the same
                    conversation, two documents on the same subject matter. But they are listed
                    under different headings. One of them is not referred to in the index, under the
                    heading of the French fleet, concern of the United States.</p>
                <p>These are details that I came upon more or less by accident, I suppose, and I
                    wouldn’t want to draw too many conclusions from them.</p>
                <p>I would emphasize that by and large it seems to me the volume is very well done.
                    I would simply call attention to the necessity of care, special care in
                    connection with the placing of documents and preparation of an index, to assist
                    the reader in finding a particular document.</p>
                <p>I think, too, even more use should be made of footnotes, and of cross-references.
                    One question I was supposed to comment on was adequacy of coverage of different
                    subjects, or adequacy of coverage of the field. I find it very difficult to
                    express any opinion that is really worth anything on that question because it
                    seems to me it is only on the basis of familiarity with documents from which the
                    selection is made that you can make any judgment of that kind. My general
                    impression is that the coverage is adequate. I think clearly in this particular
                    volume, in the area covered by this particular volume, you are up against the
                    problem of covering topics in the area of American foreign relations adequately,
                    making use principally of State Department documents, because as one learns from
                    reading the two volumes by Langer and Gleason, the material they make use of
                    very commonly, more often than not, is outside the State Department altogether,
                    so I don’t really think I can express any judgment on the adequacy of the use
                    made of the available documentation in the Department. My impression is that a
                    good job has been done.</p>
                <p>There is one technical point that I want to make that doesn’t relate to this
                    volume in particular, and it relates to something that Bernard has just been
                    commenting upon.</p>
                <p>I felt the need, as I used this volume—maybe this is not a good example of what
                    you are now doing, because it is 1940—of a name index, or a list of names, not
                    just an index, but a list of names that identifies the names that are referred
                    to in the documents, and I consulted two or three colleagues of mine who have
                    made use of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, and that was
                    the first thing they said, that there should be a list of names, because it
                    isn’t enough to have the identification the first time the name is referred
                    to.</p>
                <p>I haven’t looked at the latest volume that has been prepared. Maybe the index is
                    more adequate. I wouldn’t say that the index for Volume I, 1940, is fully
                    adequate.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think that is probably the first attempt to put that in, and the
                    others will be better.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think that is about all I have to say on this particular volume.
                    I would say I found it practically impossible to report on this volume alone. I
                    had to get into Volume II really—even Volume III—to get an over-all view.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would like to hear from Mr. Perkins with regard to some of the
                    comments that have been made.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Well, I don’t know of any special comment.</p>
                <p>As to the arrangement by subjects, obviously there is overlapping in subjects and
                    often it is difficult to know whether a paper should go in one story or another
                    story. Of course, those two documents you mentioned—maybe by doing that we
                    covered a point that was needed in each story.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I thought of that, but there should, in any case, have been
                    cross-references, because one was based on the other.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes. That is, of course, a big problem, and we do try to give a
                    considerable amount of cross-referencing. Of course, we can’t for every document
                    say, “here is something like it somewhere else.”</p>
                <p>You are right—in a subject like the European War in 1940, obviously you have to
                    have available the volumes which cover the material relating to the war. You
                    can’t use one volume entirely independent of another.</p>
                <p>Is there any special point you would like me to comment on?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I would like to ask him whether, in his reference to the placing of
                    documents, would you, Leland, think it better if the documents relating to one
                    country, regardless of the subject, were placed, say, chronologically under
                    France? Would that help solve this problem?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I refer to the particular case of NALA, where you had included
                    under the general heading all material relating to the establishment of
                    diplomatic relations with the Government in England. I think that is a
                    particular case where the documents had better be listed under the country.</p>
                <p>I would say where it makes any sense whatever to put the documents under the
                    country. I think it is better to put it there, rather than under the more
                    general heading.</p>
                <p>I recognize the need for having a general heading for material that falls into
                    this multilateral category, but I would keep this material, I think, to a
                    minimum.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I think one answer to your question about the split there on France
                    and keeping the Norwegian story together was the attack on Norway was a minor
                    story compared with the situation of France. The establishment of relations with
                    the government in exile in London was just a follow-up, incidental to the
                    government’s fleeing from Norway.</p>
                <p>In the case of France, the French Government stayed on in France, and there was a
                    most serious question of relations directly with France that made a very
                    substantial story under France.</p>
                <p>If we had, under Norway, taken that particular item, the problem of just that,
                    one or two papers, on Norway, that would have been all there was on that subject
                    I think that is probably the explanation.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The point that Leland made about the necessity of using more than
                    one volume at a given time is perfectly apparent. I was wondering if you would
                    repeat what you were suggesting about the index, because this problem is going
                    to become even greater, as we get more volumes for a given year, and as we get
                    into volumes for a given year in which there are sub-series.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I am making the suggestion with considerable hesitation, because I
                    know if accepted and carried out it would involve a great deal of time and
                    additional expense.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: You mean a general index for the whole?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: It does seem to me that a general index for all the volumes for a
                    given year would serve a useful purpose. As it is, the index only serves to
                    guide you to the documents that are contained in that volume, and if, for
                    example, you want to find out everything there is on the subject of US concern
                    with the disposition of the French fleet, you do not have adequate guidance
                    here, because part is in one volume and part is in another volume.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: If you recovered from the Pennsylvania Railroad, where would you put
                    this general index, in the last volume?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I should say the last volume.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: This problem is aggravated by the fact that they aren’t published in
                    chronological order, so it is much more difficult.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Yes; in fact, all my comments I make with great humility, because I
                    realize I don’t have all the information at my disposal. I haven’t before me all
                    the considerations that enter into this. But it does seem to me that this is one
                    gap. I don’t know how it can be filled.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: May I make one comment on that? Mr. Nuermberger called my attention
                    to this. I should think we would have to have a separate index, not in one
                    special volume. You say in the last volume. Do you mean the last volume we
                    finally get cleared? That may be Volume II.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I was thinking of a separate index volume to cover all the volumes.
                    That was what I was thinking of.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That would involve omission of the index from each particular volume.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I wouldn’t go that far. I would like to have my cake and eat it
                    too.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Perhaps we will eventually come to a five-year index or something,
                    not necessarily for every year, but an accumulative index, over special periods.
                    Meanwhile, we will have to deal as best we can.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would like to ask a question that relates somewhat to the matter
                    we have been discussing. I recall that for the First World War there were
                    supplementary volumes issued covering the First World War. I take it that for
                    the Second World War that practice is not being followed, that material is all
                    being put in the annual volumes and grouped for the most part under a general
                    heading; is that correct?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: No. We are, of course, having the Wartime Conferences, a different
                    series.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That is a little different.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: But otherwise, in the same series as you remember in World War I,
                    when they get out the regular annual volumes, they omit everything completely
                    connected with the war. It was rather routine diplomacy, which is found in the
                    regular volumes. We have tried to cover the whole range.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRIGH:; What they put in the supplementary volumes is roughly what you are
                    putting in these volumes?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Not necessarily in the supplementary volumes. There were bilateral
                    relations connected with the war.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I would like to stress this point on the index with reference to
                    the possibility of a five-year index. When you have logical periods, like the
                    period before World War II, then the period of the war, this would actually be
                    more useful, a several-year index, than one for every year. You would be
                    presented with the annual index with the same problem we now have in the
                    different parts of the annual index.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You might like to have an index covering the period from 1918.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We don’t like to ask for too much, but what historian wouldn’t
                    like to have an index of foreign relations between the wars? That would be
                    magnificent.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think we are here to ask for everything; are we not?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Also to get something. [Laughter] What is the status of that? Is
                    there any plan to go ahead with the index from where it left off?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There are so many problems involved in an index that from 1918 it
                    would be rather formidable. Of course, historian associations might take some
                    action.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes, that is a rather interesting thought; isn’t it?
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Would there be any greater merit in the idea of an accumulative index
                    over a period of a few years, as contrasted with one annually?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You mean from where we are now?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think we wouldn’t want to omit the index from each volume.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: We couldn’t do that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The initial index would be quite a considerable job. That is the
                    reason an over-all index hasn’t been made. And since 1918 is a big job.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: From the point of view of the historian there is great merit in the
                    five-year index.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What does this involve from the point of view of funds?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I wouldn’t want to say how many people it would take for how long, but
                    it would be a very big job. I am not good at estimates of that sort. Does
                    anybody have an idea?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: It requires something more than just merely looking and accumulating
                    previous indexes.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Is the thought behind the question that this would be merely
                    repetitive? Or would the accumulative index add new names and new material that
                    did not appear before?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Of course, indexes have varied some from each volume. This would be
                    one systematic index on one particular thesis, theme, principle.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any other comments?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I made the initial suggestion of a one-year one, but I would
                    thoroughly agree that a five-year index would be even better.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I would like to make one other statement with regard to references to
                    non-State Department material.</p>
                <p>I think your point may be very well taken. Did you have a feeling that some of
                    the things that occurred in these, that are included in these other volumes
                    ought to be in the State Department volumes?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Really I don’t think I am in a position to say. I think that may be
                    a question not fully explained, but I have the impression from the Langer and
                    Gleason volume that if you attempted to include in this all the
                    documentation—of course, they use memoirs and other things too—well, you
                    probably wouldn’t be able to get it all, to begin with, and secondly, the
                    volumes would become even more numerous and bulky than they are now. It would
                    be a pretty large undertaking.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That would be very much my impression. I think you establish a
                    reasonable limitation of activity outside the problem, and it would involve an
                    enormous extension of your task. Even in the Conferences, we know policy can to
                    some degree be followed. But you have a problem of selection. You have a problem
                    of selection anyway. You would complicate it that way.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I thought we discussed that point fully last year and we agreed that
                    for certain types of questions Defense Department documents, for example, would
                    preserve the integrity of the material or the recount, but we couldn’t really
                    insist upon these.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It complicates not only the problem of selection but the problem of
                    publication.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Clearance.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think it is a good question to discuss from the point of view of
                    the Committee. It doesn’t seem that it would be at all practicable.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: You have a special problem in a war period where the State
                    Department played a minor role.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes; we do.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Of course, during the Dulles period—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: As you have said, papers published outside the Department, but it
                    occurred to me, as the Presidential papers, now, the Truman papers will be
                    becoming available, and to what extent do you think they should support papers
                    found in the Department?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We discussed this thoroughly at the previous meeting. I think in the
                    case of the Yalta volume, where this practice had been followed to some extent,
                    we approved it and wished we had more. But my recollection was we ruled it out
                    except occasionally where if it could be done without difficulty, without
                    holding back the publication on clearance.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I just wanted to be sure we are clear.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I am not a bit sure that the profession generally or the historical
                    profession would approve of this, unless they knew all the problems involved. I
                    think it was in this connection that I brought it up the first time, that since
                    the task is an almost impossible one, that to safeguard the reputation of the
                    editors and historians it ought to be made perfectly clear what we are doing,
                    that we aren’t including these matters.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is entirely correct. I don’t think the layman understands the
                    complexity of the problem or what it is you are up against. I think we have
                    tried to be clear on that point, as Dick said.</p>
                <p>Are there any other questions or commentary on Mr. Goodrich’s report?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Dexter, I was just wondering if Fred, who is perhaps hearing this
                    for the first time, on this matter would have views, on this particular
                    problem.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes, I have them all right. I suppose that is the central part of
                    the problem that I see in these.</p>
                <p>Maybe I can run into this—if I am to report on this volume, and if you now turn
                    to me for Volume II—you will understand that I am new to this Committee and to
                    most members of this group, and therefore operate without—</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This is Volume II of 1941, not 1940?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes; 1940. This is the one I am supposed to report on. I have
                    Volume II of 1941 and you have Volume I of 1940, so they don’t fit together.
                    [Laughter] But that is all right.</p>
                <p>On the agenda I am listed as being the second one to speak. In connection with
                    this volume which I reviewed, therefore, I am operating without any knowledge
                    except what I have picked up through the years of working in the archives, as to
                    your methods of selection, so that the questions I raise may be questions which
                    you have considered and settled or decided they couldn’t be settled in years
                    past.</p>
                <p>Before I make any comments that are in any way critical, let me say, of course,
                    that all of us in America diplomatic history consider the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes to be excellent, much better than they used
                    to be.</p>
                <p>Those of us who work with them regret that the whole historical profession still
                    views them with suspicion. There is a rather genuine view of suspicion of these
                    volumes as being official and probably carefully selected so as to leave out a
                    great deal. Probably those of us in the profession who work with the documents
                    ought to work a little harder on our colleagues to make them see the merits of
                    this series. We have a lot to do certainly in publicizing the value of these
                    publications.</p>
                <p>Yet, at the same time, there are certainly some serious problems which are ahead,
                    and I ought to at least tell you what is in my mind. As I ran through this
                    volume I could see your difficulties all right. Obviously you can’t find in the
                    State Department all you want; for instance, I note that one of the Portuguese
                    documents, one of Salazar’s letters to Roosevelt, was available only in what the
                    State Department translator called a “nonguaranteed translation.” [Laughter] And
                    you had then to go back to the Portuguese to get a good translation. Of course,
                    that poses some problems, since policy was made on the basis of the
                    nonguaranteed translation, I suppose.</p>
                <p>You have other points, and I have probably too. As you can see, in French
                    correspondence, you had to go to Hyde Park to get things. I guess when you go to
                    Hyde Park you can’t always get them, because of the particular problems of using
                    that depository.</p>
                <p>But you have done an excellent job for all of this. This particular volume is on
                    Europe in 1941. Most of it is on France, more than half the volume. And the next
                    largest piece is on Greece. The rest is made up of smallish sections,
                    Yugoslavia, Germany, and Italy. Germany and Italy mainly show how little we had
                    to do with those countries, although, of course, you will have other material in
                    the general volumes on these points.</p>
                <p>The volume is mostly odds and ends outside of France and Greece, so you cant draw
                    general conclusions for it doesn’t hold together naturally, being a country
                    volume.</p>
                <p>But, as I looked at particular parts of the volume, I was confronted with the
                    quantity question, which is, of course, the one that distresses you all the
                    time. How much should you print? To take a couple of examples, the example of
                    our taking over Greenland, moving into Greenland, which of course involves
                    relations with the Danish Government in Denmark and the Danish Minister in
                    Washington, and the occupation of Dutch Guiana and Surinam.</p>
                <p>These are two cases of very important matters where you couldn’t get enough out
                    of the material here to write what you would want to write on American foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <p>Does this mean that you ought to publish more? Well, I suppose you have
                    limitations of money for one thing. And this certainly is going to be a very
                    distressing question, should you publish more? Yet I feel that with reference to
                    those particular questions which are important, as in fact almost everything is,
                    in 1941, there wasn’t enough quantity. The selection was good, but it was
                    inadequate.</p>
                <p>Maybe it wasn’t just not having enough money. Perhaps it was the fact that the
                    State Department doesn’t contain enough information and there you move right
                    into this question of inter-Department things. But before I move to the
                    inter-Department things—which I am sure in the case of Greenland and the case
                    of Dutch Guiana relate to military necessities and political problems—let me
                    talk a little about how the volume looks to a historian who has used State
                    Department materials after he has used <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    items.</p>
                <p>The method of selection, the basic document, rules out background studies, and I
                    suppose you have to do this, because how much background could you put in and
                    yet what you miss is the background knowledge which the people had when they
                    made the policy decision. The State Department is full of little bits of
                    background which are tossed in to the policy-maker when he makes his decision,
                    and although I would certainly not want background material that would give you
                    everything for the historian’s use, I would like to see a little about the
                    background which the policy-makers had when they made these particular
                    decisions.</p>
                <p>Perhaps another way of putting this is to say that, to take a couple of examples
                    like Greenland and Dutch Guiana, what you lack are your State Department memos,
                    which contain some kind of discussion as to what you ought to do, the choices,
                    and the basis of the decision.</p>
                <p>I have worked with State Department material with the help of people like Dr.
                    Wright, when he was in the National Archives. The things that I have found most
                    useful are the State Department backgrounds for those decisions. I suppose you
                    may sometimes have space questions. Sometimes you may have clearance questions
                    on this; I don’t know.</p>
                <p>But this strikes me as the major gap within the State Department. Perhaps such
                    memos sometimes have reference to other things, which you exclude, like
                    diplomatic public opinion reports, but which in this particular case are very
                    significant.</p>
                <p>Moving from that though to the stuff outside the State Department, I recognize
                    you couldn’t possibly put in all the Defense Department material and publish
                    less than 50 or 60 volumes a year. The material there, of course, is hard to
                    get, and hard to declassify and hard to use once you get it. It is so difficult,
                    of course, that the Defense Department and its subsidiaries aren’t publishing
                    documents because they feel there are too many, etc.</p>
                <p>Yet the State Department, in sending its instructions and in setting forth its
                    policies constantly obviously is moving with some background of what other
                    departments are doing, and this you don’t find; that is, in this volume, at
                    least you don’t find material about the inter-Departmental relationship, what
                    the Defense Department policy did that the State Department operated under, was
                    the State Department asked to do this by such-and-such a Department? Or was the
                    State Department acting with other Departments, moving forward on its front?</p>
                <p>You feel the isolation of diplomacy in a volume like that, in 1941, in quite an
                    astonishing way. I recognize you are entirely right, you certainly can’t cover
                    the whole range of our relations with the outside world. That is just
                    impossible, in a situation like that. But if you don’t have in your documents
                    some clues as to how the State Department was acting on what other Departments
                    wanted, or information that came from other Departments, you feel kind of that
                    you are seeing the official document without seeing much about what is behind
                    it.</p>
                <p>Those are the major points I wanted to make. Like Dr. Goodrich, I am bothered a
                    little by classification and index problems, but I am just bothered to the point
                    of being baffled. I haven’t anything at all to suggest, at this point.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you very much. Do you want to speak on this subject,
                    Ralph?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I don’t know that I have much to add. Obviously that question of the
                    background on which the Department acts is a very big question, and to a large
                    extent I think it cannot be documented. Sometimes you do have Department
                    memoranda that would show just why something was done, or the
                    inter-connections.</p>
                <p>Of course, a great many of these things, when policy officers get together and a
                    certain officer is instructed to draft a telegram or a communication to another
                    government, that states the policy. You see what the policy was that they
                    determined, but all the discussion that goes on in the Department and between
                    the Departments often you can’t give.</p>
                <p>On important questions, very important questions, we often do have a certain
                    limited amount of documentation of that kind. I think Greenland was important. I
                    think British Guiana was important, the Dutch colonies down there were
                    important. But how about their relative importance? How are we going to say? You
                    say to put in more on that, but where are we going to go?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I was using those as examples only. The major part of the
                    reference I made has referred to France, and the point I made I think would have
                    even more point there.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: There is something that comes up in this connection. In the American
                    Republics volume, we do have a chapter on Hemisphere Defense. When that volume
                    comes out, you will find it rather sketchy, because of the difficulties we run
                    into when we try to tell a military story.</p>
                <p>The Army is coming out with a history of that, of the war period, in connection
                    with Hemisphere Defense. I think that is scheduled for publication some time
                    next year. It is already in page proof. We have used it, but there we are
                    baffled, because the Army glides over some of these problems, you see.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I appreciate the difficulties, but I think we are in for them for
                    good and it isn’t just that we can see—we can present the State Department
                    story and that is all we can do, because we can’t get the military side in. The
                    fact is that nowadays diplomacy and military matters are not separate. They are
                    all the same. Maybe ultimately you will come to having military experts on your
                    staff. Maybe you have some. Maybe some of your people are.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: No.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: That would be very fine. I would hope that the military people
                    would have some diplomatic specialists on their staffs too.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: It might be possible, just to throw out this suggestion, to have an
                    inter-Departmental historical committee, or group, to work in coordination on
                    these problems, the same as we had, for example, a British-American team that
                    did documents on German foreign policy, well, with the aid of the French,
                    British, American, and French.</p>
                <p>I don’t think that the State Department by itself can undertake to assume the
                    responsibility of publishing records of the War Department.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I agree with that.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: And we do have to put in what background we have, but there is a
                    definite limitation, and very often there is a documentary limitation in the
                    files that we are up against.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I am interested in the point that Mr. Perkins makes about
                    memoranda. You feel you have used adequately Departmental memoranda, as
                    distinguished from—</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Well, I don’t know.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think that was a very important suggestion. I don’t know what you
                    are asking for.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Well, in my own use of State Department files, this is the most
                    valuable kind of material, at least, that is to say, as I have used State
                    Department materials down into the 30’s, the State Department memoranda are the
                    thing most valuable, that you don’t get in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I might say that particular point has been up for considerable
                    discussion and there has been a feeling against publishing memoranda at low
                    levels.</p>
                <p>Now, actually these studies that you find so valuable are generally not made by
                    the top officers of the Department. They are memos of the lower levels and their
                    recommendations.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes, but these are what some of the top officers would see.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes; that is true.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think that is the point Mr. Harrington is making.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: You see, I have defended presenting low level memos when they are
                    needed to give information, not to give the recommendation—we felt that the
                    recommendation of a lower officer is not important unless it is accepted as
                    Department policy. Then if you have the document that gives the Department
                    policy, you don’t need the recommendation of the lower officer, but often you
                    have to put in memos that gave information upon which action is based. And we do
                    that.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: When you have two possible policies set forth and top officers
                    select one, in some cases even the play between the possibilities is worth
                    attention. I recognize that there are limits as to how much stuff you print, and
                    these memoranda run very long. But we all know with reference to great
                    historical developments like Open Door Notes, that publication of documents
                    alone doesn’t begin to suggest really significant historical background.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I believe the editors of the documents of British foreign policy
                    have not gone anywhere near as far as we have. They have simply ruled out what
                    they call “minutes,” we call “chits,” in the documents.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think it ought to be useful to hear from Departmental officers on
                    some of these matters. We have a number here. Mr. Lockhart, have you anything to
                    say?</p>
                <p>MR. LOCKHART: Well, I would like to put in a special plea here for the interest
                    of the undergraduate. We have been talking about colleagues and historical
                    societies, etc. To this extent I would agree with your remark that additional
                    background—and, of course, as we approach the present day, there are more and
                    more classified background studies, country papers, etc., that will eventually
                    become useful.</p>
                <p>But as far as the undergraduate goes—and I understand that one of our principles
                    of education is to develop more advanced students and encourage their interest,
                    etc.—I think the undergraduate, having been one not so long ago, finds the
                    volumes a little bit heavy going, and if there were a background statement
                    somewhere in a country paper that would be basic, I think this would be very
                    helpful.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you. Have you anything to say on the subject of
                    memoranda?</p>
                <p>MR. LOCKHART: No, sir. On these particular volumes?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I might call on some of the other policy officers. Mr. Fleischer,
                    have you anything to add?</p>
                <p>MR. FLEISCHER: I don’t believe so,</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Sims?</p>
                <p>MR. SIMS: I am right here, but I don’t believe I have anything to add.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Deming?</p>
                <p>MR. DEMING: Well, I might add, as a Department officer, the importance attached
                    to the memoranda going up, forming policy. A good bureaucrat is supposed to have
                    a passion for anonymity. If he continues, it goes on as high as he goes. It
                    doesn’t mean that he doesn’t have pride of authorship in thinking, developing
                    his plan, which may be diametrically opposed to another fellow’s. The
                    satisfaction comes when it does come, but the ideas or position that you have
                    advocated finally gets incorporated in whatever it is, an agreement, dispatch to
                    a foreign post, or telegram, which may be basic policy. But I can see that you
                    can’t go very far down in that process.</p>
                <p>I think publishing memoranda, interesting though it would be, unless you get into
                    a completely different kind of publication—because it isn’t policy until it is
                    accepted. The processes by which it is formed are no doubt important. But to the
                    officer himself, it is part of the chore that is important to him but it doesn’t
                    weigh in the scales unless it is taken over by the fellows who are the deciders
                    of policy.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: But the analysis of policymaking to historians is fundamental,
                    how policy was made, not just a description of policy. So when you get into the
                    historical side of this, which this is, and of course we protect the present
                    policy people by not publishing for twenty years, later when you move it on to
                    the historical scale, the process by which you have reached a decision may be a
                    critical part.</p>
                <p>MR. DEMING: After a period of years they become available to archivists, not in
                    published form, but if you are there digging through a particular period.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think that is a point that needs to be made, no matter how
                    complete these volumes are as records of decisions, they would not be subject
                    for use as archives themselves. We have to draw the line somewhere, and
                    recognize that the historian of American policy is going back to these volumes
                    anyway.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we raised an important point with regard to the use of
                    memoranda. I wonder if there is anything more to be said. Are there any
                    questions or commentary?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: You used a very apt phrase about the feeling of isolation in which
                    diplomacy is carried on. An interesting thought also was in which instances, to
                    know if the isolation as you felt it was the correct impression of what took
                    place at the time, or what was merely not isolation, but in which you don’t have
                    the connective tissue.</p>
                <p>During wartime, there were a number of instances in which policy was developed in
                    complete isolation, perhaps in these volumes you will run across the plaintive
                    bleats from Secretary Hull, the White House, as I have heard. [Laughter]
                    Frequently these were in isolation. What is important is to know when it was and
                    when we can’t include the connective tissue from the Treasury, Commerce, the
                    Joint Chiefs, the White House, and you will never know until later.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Would it be possible to use more footnote references to the fact
                    that there are defense or other types of documents which would relate to the
                    point? Or is even that outlawed, perhaps?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You mean documents already published?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: No; where we can’t get the volumes.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: In Conference volumes we have anticipated heavily along that
                    line.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: If you have that volume of 1941, I happened to go through that last
                    week, and we have a number of cross-references on German foreign policy.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That is right, post-war foreign policy preparation, things like
                    that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is very valuable.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: If you don’t make cross-reference to unprinted documents, Clarence,
                    would it even be of some help to indicate those volumes in the Army series that
                    might deal with this particular issue? Have you done that?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: To some extent. In the China volume, I know that we have, in
                    connection with Stillwell’s mission, a number of cross-references to that, and
                    just recently—that is what I mentioned—the volume is coming out on Hemisphere
                    Defense. I was able, through Mr. Parks, to get a page proof, and Mr. Wright of
                    our staff, who is a specialist on American problems, went through that, made a
                    considerable number of footnotes on our volumes that we have in galley.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: This is Stedon’s (?) volume?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes; in that case we were able to get it in advance. In a good many
                    cases we haven’t found a volume to cover the particular circumstances we are
                    interested in.</p>
                <p>VOICE: On the Persian Corridor it is there.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Forty-one.</p>
                <p>VOICE: We have made references to the Army volumes in compilations after ’41,
                    when we get in, in ’42 and ’43, when they went in. As you know, they have a very
                    good volume on Malta, the Persian Corridor, the Aims of Russia. We have
                    references to that.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: In our Far Eastern volume, we have, in ’41, for example, references
                    to Congressional hearings, Pearl Harbor hearings, and to intercepted Japanese
                    telegrams, and also there again to the Army publication on that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Shall we go on to Leopold’s report?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I will be very brief, Mr. Chairman, because this is the second time
                    around, and most of the things I have to say I either said last year or
                    Professor Harrington has said it much better than I said it last year.</p>
                <p>There is the old problem you and I have been talking about for years, the point
                    Mr. Harrington made with regard to background. Certainly as I have read volumes
                    generally over the years, I have had the feeling that I know very much more
                    about the making of foreign policy in other countries than from what is going on
                    in the State Department. The reports from abroad tell us a good deal about
                    background deliberations, speculations from other countries, and not nearly so
                    much as what goes on in the State Department. So I would simply, by way of
                    opening my remarks, endorse everything that Mr. Harrington said, realizing that
                    sometimes documentation isn’t there, but simply reiterating a plea when it is
                    there, and if it is possible, at least, we would like more of it.</p>
                <p>With regard to this specific volume, Volume III for ’41, which deals with the
                    British Commonwealth and the Near East, I have very little to say. I checked
                    back on some notes about when I spoke last year. I did Volume III for ’40, with
                    some of the same countries represented.</p>
                <p>I found some of my impressions I had jotted down last year, particularly with
                    regard to the area of the Near East on the quality of the report, what they tell
                    us about internal conditions within those countries rather gibed with the
                    impressions I received that year, for instance, excellent reporting, I think,
                    judging from the documents from Iran. I no doubt made the same comment last
                    year.</p>
                <p>I think that all I need to say, since I am sure we can use the time to better
                    advantage, is to come back again in this volume to some of the points which Mr.
                    Goodrich and Mr. Harrington made, and which I have made before on this question
                    of the index and the index of names as a substitute or alternative to the list
                    of names.</p>
                <p>I am perfectly willing for the time being to go along with the index as a
                    substitute. I much prefer the list of names. I found it extremely useful in the
                    past.</p>
                <p>I think I made the point last year, when somebody is writing in this period and
                    you are confused as to what sort of spelling you are going to give to a man’s
                    name, I stand up and say, “If the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volume spells it that way, I am going to,” and any book reviewer can be referred
                    to this.</p>
                <p>I have one example that I pulled out of the blue, now, as we were talking, that I
                    had noted before, and just to show how useful this identification via the index
                    is. One of the most useful people to me in this volume was the head of the Near
                    Eastern Division, the Division of Near Eastern Affairs in this period, Wallace
                    Murray, who did for this area something as Mr. Orgibet did for the Far East. He
                    would speak his mind, talk with representatives, and reduce to paper memoranda
                    so that we get a little of what Mr. Harrington was asking for, what was going
                    through the mind of a particular person. If somebody wanted to know who Wallace
                    Murray was, just from this volume, there are many references. I don’t know how
                    many references, the index covers so much. You go instinctively to the first
                    one, Page 191, which doesn’t tell you very much about Mr. Murray. It doesn’t
                    even give his first name.</p>
                <p>If you look carefully the first number is in the middle there, at 176. There it
                    says that Wallace Murray is the Head of the Division of Near Eastern
                    Affairs.</p>
                <p>I wonder how much more trouble it would be to put in “Wallace Murray, Head of the
                    Division of Near Eastern Affairs,” and the years he served in that particular
                    post. As I recall in some of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes of the First World War sometimes, additional information identifying the
                    man was given, as the Prime Minister of so-and-so, 1914 to 1917.</p>
                <p>I have raised two questions. The first reference that hits the eye doesn’t always
                    give you the identification, and whether in identifying him in the footnote, you
                    could give more information about the period in which he served in that
                    office.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: The only comment I would have would be that that would be a
                    sizeable problem. If you have someone who has been a fixture over a period of
                    years in the State Department, it would be very easy. But when you go down the
                    list of American and foreign officers mentioned—I didn’t count up how many
                    there are listed in that index, but there are a great many people. It would be a
                    major research problem to find what their terms of office were.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I was not asking for their entire career—just the period that he
                    was holding the office discussed in this volume.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Often you will find a man at the top level, perhaps a minister, but
                    then—and often his terms may have changed, and in our State Department you can
                    use personnel records and find out, but for foreign officers you have
                    practically nothing to show when he did terminate his work or begin it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I simply raise the two things that have to be in the index, because
                    we have talked about this before.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I am still slightly confused, ever though we have discussed this
                    before, as to the extent to which this listing of names should be carried.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I stood like Horatio at the Bridge last year in saying it should
                    be.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Should all names or what names be listed? That is what I am confused
                    about—that is, how far this thought should go?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: We carried that very far, and only minor people mentioned
                    incidentally are left out. In the index you will see only one or two or three or
                    so page references in the whole volume.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: What criteria did you use in the list?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I was trying to recall. In the index we gave instructions that all
                    names, including those of fictitious and historical characters, were to be
                    included. They were—I don’t know how thoroughly, but that was what we aimed to
                    do. In the list of characters, I think it was only the principal ones.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I think this is the point. I don’t know if I was the only one, but I
                    was one who was a little skeptical about alternative listing of names rather
                    than an index. If it is an index, it seems to me it would be complete. If it is
                    an alternative listing, it would be incomplete. If both can be published, I
                    would be all for it.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I wanted to ask there, in preparing the list of names, whether you
                    would be satisfied if this index were confined to a subject index and we
                    included those in the list of names? The reason why I ask is because when we
                    raised the question with Publication Division of putting names in the index,
                    they said this would take more time and be more expensive, and it really is an
                    important factor. We could more easily have put in a list of names publicly and
                    less expensively, perhaps, than add the names to the index. If you can find it
                    through the subject index, then it would be possible to have a list of names.
                    Have you any preference, sir?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The list of names would be descriptive?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would favor a list of names.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: A descriptive list of names. I should think that would be the way
                    to go at it.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: In addition to the index?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That is what you use the index for primarily. I notice here, just
                    making a rough comparison, I think the Volume 2, 1921 index is much more
                    complete than the other index I was looking at.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are you through, Dick?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I will be through any time. If you don*t shut me up, I will never be
                    through.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I was wondering about the practice of summarizing the
                    dispatches.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think it was up to three or four years ago.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Has any member of the Committee anything to say on that
                    subject?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: That we haven’t said before?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I am new to the thing and very much confused, but I know that
                    when I use indexes, I don’t like to have two different indexes and have names
                    and subjects separately. I am irritated. Sometimes you will get indexes that
                    have names, and then places, and then subjects, and then you give it up and look
                    through the book because it is easier. So that I was rather impressed by this
                    combination practice. But I don’t mean to—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I don’t think what we were coming to a moment ago was two separate
                    indexes—a single index in which the names would be omitted—but in the front of
                    the list you would have a list of the alphabetical names, a list of the
                    principal people, which would make you turn to two different places.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I don’t feel strongly about it, but at the moment I don’t join
                    you in the concern for this.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: That really did evade the issue. You said you listed the principal
                    people. How did you determine the principal people?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Keep pushing me on this. I don’t remember in fact just now how we
                    determined that. It was a little different as to Malta, because this was one
                    delegation going to one conference. You could in fact include them all if you
                    wanted—and I believe in one place we did list the Filipino mess boys who served
                    the President on the Yalta and the Malta trips, but this is not applicable.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: But you are suggesting this would be impossible.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I can assure you that this would be a very difficult job—and
                    Churchill did the same thing on his, but we thought on these volumes it would be
                    sufficiently important to list those.</p>
                <p>MR. CHURCHILL: About those in the Soviet Union, very frequently it is done with
                    respect to foreigners—it was almost terrifically impossible to find the
                    beginning and ending date. They are liquidated sometimes, but when?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Those identifications always have to be somewhat less than perfect.
                    In every such list you will run into some foreigners that the entire facilities
                    of the U. S. Government can not identify precisely on date. We had a couple of
                    characters in the Yalta one, characters who appeared only by perennially lurking
                    in the background, and they came into the room with Stalin. We had difficulty
                    identifying as to whether one was Ambassador here or some Second Secretary over
                    there by the same name. Some of these took unconscionable amounts of man hours
                    to do.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is there anything to be added to the description on this point?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: One other point on Volume 3, which I wanted to mention, which we had
                    talked about in times past, and I suppose it will come up in connection with our
                    reading this afternoon, and that is omitted material—words here and there. On
                    the whole I found relatively few indications of omissions. Probably one document
                    there where something which dealt with some other subject, and some other places
                    where obviously somebody had put too much on paper, but it didn’t harm the
                    document, but that is just guessing without having seen the papers.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If there are no other comments, we will pass on to the next item on
                    the agenda, without trying to hurry you in any way.</p>
                <p rend="underline">3. Proposal for change of terms of service of members of the
                    Advisory Committee</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Noble has something to say on this subject. What are you
                    proposing to say to the members of the Committee? What are you proposing, and
                    how do you propose to do it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I thought, Mr. Chairman—in fact, I discussed this with Dick Leopold
                    on the way to the airport after the last meeting—that we ought to look at this
                    question of term and the question of rotation as involved in it. I believe at
                    the present time it is understood that the members are appointed for a
                    three-year period. It happens that the first year we met you were not
                    consultants—I forget precisely the innocuous title you had.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: You told us we were conferees.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: But not collaborators.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Definitely not. When you were appointed officially as consultants,
                    those appointments took effect last year, so that last year’s conference was the
                    first time you became consultants, and that appointment was for three years by
                    the Department. So, excluding Brother Harrington here, you are serving a second
                    year so far as the time is concerned on your appointment, and the Department
                    appointment will expire next year, but of course there will be no problem of
                    renewing that.</p>
                <p>But Dick and I were thinking about the value of greater length of service and
                    greater value therefore of the advice based on longer experience, and he also
                    said that the term, I believe, of the advisers on the military history is five
                    years. Isn’t that correct?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I am not sure. I think it is longer than three, but I think I
                    mentioned that the Navy Committee at the moment does not have any limit of
                    time.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: At any rate, we thought five years would be a good length of time, and
                    obviously some sort of rotation would be a good thing connected with it. I hope
                    you will agree. We wouldn’t want to see everybody go off at any one period. And
                    of course there is no reason why anybody should go off at the end of five years,
                    but in any case the rotation seemed desirable, so I drew up a little chart here
                    which would indicate how this might operate if you had it on a five-year
                    basis.</p>
                <p>We have three historians, two political scientists, and two international
                    lawyers. And it would seem reasonable that one historian might retire at the end
                    of one year—say, for the first, when we are setting this up—and another at the
                    end of three years, and another at the end of five, and one political scientist
                    and one international lawyer at the end of two, and the other two retire at the
                    end of four, so you would have a regular rotation there. So that at no time
                    would more than two members of the Committee go off in any one year, unless he
                    chooses to retire or for some other reason.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: The only objection I have to this is that it seems to suggest that
                    one political scientist and one international lawyer seem to equal one
                    historian.</p>
                <p>(Laughter)</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I thought of that, but do you have a better suggestion?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We historians know it takes more than one political scientist
                    plus one international lawyer to make a historian. (Laughter)</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If this idea were accepted, what would we do? We would draw for the
                    length of time?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is right. The three historians would draw to see which would have
                    the longer period of time.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We would have a straw, and our terms would be fixed by lot.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: And then the two political scientist would draw for the two-year and
                    the four-year, and the two international lawyers, unless you have a better
                    suggestion.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Except that in a sense, Bernard, we have already started to have a
                    rotation. That is, no matter how many years Dexter and I serve, we have served
                    more than Fred has.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: This is a relatively small problem, I hope. I am sure, unless you have
                    a way to solve this problem, we would like to have you carry on for five years
                    right now, of course, particularly In view of some of the suggestions you have
                    been making this morning. But I would envisage this as taking effect the year
                    after next. I would say next year the three-year term would expire, and then the
                    following year there will be a renewal of the original members.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is, we would all serve through 1960. Is that right?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: All serve through 1960.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: And then draw the lots.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: And then at that time say who would serve longer, for three or four or
                    five years.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We were nominated by the various associations, all of us, I mean,
                    for terms that expire there.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: In 1960 we would probably want to go back to the associations and say,
                    “Do you want to renominate these men, or nominate some other men?” Those are
                    details that will have to be worked out.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: For the associations. But if you did select three completely new
                    historians, they would draw lots for their terms?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is right.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The questions are separated, in a sense. The length of term is a
                    question, and the appointment by the association is separate.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: When you were nominated, no term was suggested.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t think so.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: So we don’t have to go back to them at all; do we?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: No.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Most of them don’t even know we are on this Committee.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Most of them don’t know this Committee is in existence.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You are saying the association does not need to consider the
                    question. We are here as long as we are here.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: That is, if you were nominated honestly and fairly originally.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Is that a statement of fact?</p>
                <p>(Laughter)</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is there anyone who opposes a system of rotation, as Mr. Noble
                    proposes? This seems reasonable enough to me. But we do not do anything about it
                    until next year.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No. We don’t worry about it until then.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would not worry about it anyway. (Laughter) That is all right.
                    That seems to have been easily settled.</p>
                <p>We are ahead of our program this morning. I have just been talking about it. I
                    think the best way to use our time until 12:00 would be to go over individually
                    the principles and procedures, because we will want to discuss that document
                    seriously, and it has just been presented to us.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Mr. Chairman, as I understand it, we are supposed to spend the
                    afternoon looking at the documents, and I think, that being the case, we ought
                    to be told what particular problems have come up in the course of the past year
                    and what we should have in mind.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Very good.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I would like to make one very brief statement. Bernard mentioned it,
                    but it seems to me in fairness it probably should be said by a member of the
                    Committee: namely, that most of the recommendations we made as to form last year
                    I believe were incorporated into these volumes, and I believe we should express
                    our satisfaction.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. Of course, I made a note of the points we discussed, and we
                    would want to discuss those naturally. Would you like to talk to the question of
                    what problems you think we will have to face in examining the documents?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Would you look at this document in your dossier entitled “References
                    to Documents or Portions of Documents Involved in Clearance of Certain <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Volumes.” Does everyone have that?</p>
                <p>Now, I think this discussion should be off the record.</p>
                <p>(Discussion off the record.)</p>
                <p>(Whereupon, at 12:00 p.m., the meeting went into executive session, which was not
                    recorded.)</p>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p rend="underline">Members of the Committee:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Dexter Perkins, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Dr. Clarence A. Berdahl</item>
                    <item>Dr. Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                    <item>Dr. Fred H. Harrington</item>
                    <item>Dr. Richard W. Leopold</item>
                    <item>Dr. Philip W. Thayer</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Representing the Department of State:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Edwin M. J. Kretzmann, [<hi rend="italic">Deputy</hi>] Assistant
                        Secretary, Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>J. Graham Parsons, Assistant Secretary, Far Eastern Affairs</item>
                    <item>G. Bernard Noble, HD</item>
                    <item>Clarence A. Boonstra, EST</item>
                    <item>Mrs. Velma J. Cassidy, HD</item>
                    <item>Rogers P. Churchill, HD</item>
                    <item>G. M. Richardson Dougall, HD</item>
                    <item>Herbert Fine, HD</item>
                    <item>Jack M. Fleischer, EUR</item>
                    <item>William M. Franklin, HD</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, HD</item>
                    <item>Ralph R. Goodwin, HD</item>
                    <item>John Rison Jones, Jr., HD</item>
                    <item>Frank P. Lockhart, FE</item>
                    <item>Gustave A. Nuermberger, HD</item>
                    <item>E. Ralph Perkins, HD</item>
                    <item>Richard I. Phillips, ARA</item>
                    <item>Newton O. Sappington, HD</item>
                    <item>Joseph A. Silberstein, WST</item>
                    <item>William Slany, HD</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer, HD</item>
                    <item>Ivan B. White, EUR</item>
                    <item>Almon R. Wright, HD</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="right">Reported by:</p>
                <list rend="right">
                    <item>E. C. Moyer</item>
                    <item>V. R. Voce</item>
                    <item>E. B. Wake</item>
                </list>
                <p>(The meeting was opened at 9:35 a.m., Mr. Dexter Perkins presiding.)</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Gentlemen, I would like to report to you on the deliberations of
                    the Committee yesterday. I am sure my colleagues will want to add to what I have
                    to say, but I will summarize briefly our deliberations.</p>
                <p>We met yesterday afternoon and divided into two groups which examined the
                    documents which are in question, and we have a report to make on those
                    materials.</p>
                <p>Before I indicate the nature of the report and the specifics, I should like to
                    quote from our observations last year in our confidential memorandum. Of course,
                    it seems to me that the principles on which we operate would be much the same as
                    those which applied last year.</p>
                <p>”The Committee recognizes that the most difficult questions are questions of
                    clearance. It is well aware of the fact that as the foreign relations of the
                    United States grow more complex, these questions will arise more and more often.
                    It also believes that there may be occasions when material must be deleted in
                    the preparation of the regular volumes for the press. It believes, however, that
                    if deletions are frequent, not only will the value of the material be much
                    reduced, but the prestige of the whole series will suffer. Too frequently the
                    desk officers of the Department oppose the inclusion of material, the substance
                    of which is common knowledge, or, if not common knowledge, is well known to
                    those interested in American foreign relations. It is true that what appears in
                    a government publication is in a somewhat different category from what appears
                    in the press, or even from the comments of our less discreet public men. But the
                    effects of a few lines in an official document on the large policies of the
                    United States can be easily exaggerated. The Committee reiterates its
                    generalization of a year ago that the emphasis should be placed on the integrity
                    of the record as against the exclusion of details which are highly unlikely to
                    have any important deleterious influence on our foreign relations.”</p>
                <p>This was our statement last year, and I think it represents our view this year.
                    The only new member is Mr. Harrington. Do you agree with that statement?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Entirely.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Let me go over briefly the various decisions and then leave it to
                    the members of the Committee to go further. We divided into two groups—Mr.
                    Harrington, Mr. Goodrich, and Mr. Leopold, who examined the China Volume and the
                    Far East Volume 5; and we—Mr. Thayer, Mr. Berdahl, and I—examined the Volumes
                    with respect to Latin America.</p>
                <p>Now let us take first the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Volume for the
                    Far East, the volume which was Volume 5 for the Far East, in which the principal
                    problem was the problem of the correspondence with respect to the Japanese
                    expansion toward Thailand and the flirtation of the Thai Government with the
                    Japanese. We said last year that this volume is ready for publication.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I am sorry to interrupt. Off the record.</p>
                <p>(Discussion off the record.)</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Noble says that all the people are not here who will be
                    interested in this, so I will take up the American Republics first, and this
                    will take only a short time. The questions involved in the American volumes are
                    of a different nature, particularly with regard to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> of 1940, Volume 5. Here most of the questions were questions
                    of detail. They did not go to the root of the problem as to whether the whole
                    volume should be published or not, and what we did was to read the
                    correspondence individually, the three of us here—Mr. Thayer, Mr. Berdahl, and
                    I—and we found that we agreed almost exactly as to the items which might be
                    retained and as to the items which might be eliminated.</p>
                <p>I have of course a list of those which I would naturally present when we write
                    our written report. It hardly seems necessary to go into each one of them in
                    detail. Generally speaking, of course, we recognize that documents which are
                    objected to by another Government can hardly be included. One that I suppose is
                    a very striking case one might make an issue and try to exert pressure on the
                    Government concerned, but in the questions here we were perfectly ready to
                    acquiesce in the request of the foreign government in this case, in most cases
                    the Government of Brazil, with regard to the record.</p>
                <p>I will provide you with a list there, but our general mode of approach to the
                    matter is that there have been in here more numerous deletions than we think
                    necessary from the point of view of protecting the interests of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>In many of these questions it seems to us that they were ones which would not
                    have a very profound effect on international relations.</p>
                <p>The only thing to be said about the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi>, Volume 6, for 1941, is that there are a certain number
                    of questions of detail there, and again we have to read them individually and we
                    have arrived at a reasonable consensus with regard to them, and this list will
                    be tabulated and provided for the use of the Division and for the use of the
                    desk officers, I suppose.</p>
                <p>And we have also reviewed the correspondence with regard to the
                    Ecuadorian-Peruvian boundary. This is the only case where a considerable body of
                    correspondence is involved, and our view of that correspondence, as we reviewed
                    it yesterday afternoon, is that it ought not, or that there is nothing in it
                    which ought to delay publication.</p>
                <p>This is about what we have to say in general terms with regard to the American
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>If we have a moment more, do you want me to talk about the Potsdam and Tehran
                    ones?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think we ought to have an opportunity to discuss some of the
                    particular items.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, if you bring us the volumes, we can do that, of course.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think you have the references there.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: These are all in galley form.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. Those are the references to them, and I thought you might have
                    particular items.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: In the general galley I can tell you what conclusions we came
                    to.</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: This is Volume 5.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I don’t have the Peruvian boundary.</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: Do you want that?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We can take, for example, the reference to the conversation with
                    Mr. Aranha of the 1 of January of 1940, in which he raises some problems with
                    regard to the proposals of the American Government and the enforcement of
                    neutrality regulations. “We believe nothing should be said about paragraph 3
                    until we see how the Committee works. This was not excluded. He does not like
                    paragraph 4, says that Brazil could not agree to a court with five Spanish
                    Americans, one Brazilian and one American. He says they would gang up on us.
                    They have always opposed these courts for that reason.” We agreed that that
                    sentence might be deleted.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Was that from the Brazilian Government?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: In this case the objection did not come from the Government of
                    Brazil; did it? It came from the Department. Yes.</p>
                <p>But now if we were to go over this record in detail, the next one we would come
                    to would be on Galley 50, and here the statement that was made, to which
                    objection was taken by the Department and not by the Government, was, “The
                    Department is confident that they will be able to delay action by the Cuban
                    Government on these two draft decrees.” This seemed a statement which was not of
                    a very exciting character, and we thought that that might well be left in. These
                    events are ones which occurred in 1940. It didn’t appear to us that that was a
                    sensitive matter.</p>
                <p>If we go on to 1953?—incidentally, what was stricken out was, “Incidentally,
                    just to keep the record straight your Legal Adviser did not ... sealed mail
                    which of course I would not dream of doing, but there were too many other
                    matters .... correcting the error.” This involves some criticism of the Legal
                    Adviser as of 1940, but it didn’t seem to us to affect fundamentally the
                    interests of the United States. We left that in.</p>
                <p>The 1954? was a long statement as to the declaration of Panama, a memorandum by
                    Mr. Bonsall of the policy of the Department, and we had read that, and again we
                    could not understand what the objection was to publication at the present
                    time.</p>
                <p>In 1956?, to take another example, the question here was a question again of a
                    memorandum by Mr. Bonsall, a letter from the Acting Secretary of State, Chief of
                    the Division Mr. Duggan, and a memorandum by Mr. Bonsall, and he again we failed
                    to find anything in the context which was dangerous to the interests of the
                    United States at the present time.</p>
                <p>When we came on the other hand to 1959?, in this case there was a phrase in the
                    dispatch, in the communication: “While it is probable that the three mile rule
                    has outlived its usefulness”—we proposed this for deletion and we recommended
                    deletion because it might be embarrassing to the United States at some future
                    time.</p>
                <p>Now I can go over all of these, but it seems to me that without the documents
                    before them, Mr. Noble—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I thought possibly they might comment on the overall subjects. I think
                    they ought to maybe discuss it, but maybe, unless as you said they have the
                    documents before them on each point, it might not be too helpful. I would like
                    to ask Mr. Phillips and Mr. Boonstra to say whether with reference to the
                    subject of American neutrality, the American Neutrality Committee, whether your
                    recollection would be such that you could discuss it. Of course, how we can
                    profitably get onto this matter and handle it substantively and get the benefit
                    of your comments for the benefit of the Committee—the members of the Advisory
                    Committee might want to change their recommendations. I don’t think it is final,
                    perhaps, now.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, that is quite true.</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: On the list of problems you presented us with the other day, Mr.
                    Noble, I checked with a number of the office directors, and for instance on this
                    Neutrality Act I couldn’t find who in the Bureau had reviewed the galley proofs
                    in the first place. As Public Affairs Adviser I am not in a position to speak to
                    the substance of any of these matters, and I have brought the Office Directors
                    for the East Coast and West Coast countries of South America. They may be of
                    some help in those items relating to the specific countries. But on these
                    areawide matters I checked with Ambassador Dwyer, and he frankly was not in a
                    position to speak to the substance himself. I wonder whether some of these
                    things were not reviewed in the Legal Division?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Some of them, yes.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: The notations indicate that.</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: They might be better able to defend their deliberations than we
                    are.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: But you have accepted their recommendations and by and large we have,
                    too. Isn’t that true?</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: On that, Mr. Noble, the area office ... (inaudible) also on the
                    Legal Adviser. On those two you mentioned, on Mr. Bonsall, Miss Whiteman in the
                    Legal Office, with whom I spoke yesterday and urged her to come if she
                    could—but she said, “I know about this but I have been traveling about so much
                    I will have to beg off.” But she said whatever the Committee thinks she should
                    reconsider, she will reconsider.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, as I say, all three of us have read those memoranda, and we
                    don’t understand that. I think that is all I can say there. Don’t you think so,
                    Phil? We don’t see what is sensitive in them.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: We of course have to admit that we don’t have the background of
                    intimate knowledge of those particular matters, but we saw no danger there.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: This Bonsall matter you are referring to is simply a fairly long
                    memorandum by him, giving his conclusions and recommendations to the
                    Inter-American Neutrality Committee, and it is difficult to see what in the
                    world can be difficult.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: She said in one sentence that these were tentative and informal
                    conclusions. That was one remark she made.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t know. I can’t speak for my colleagues, but if the document
                    is interesting from the historical point of view, even though it is not final,
                    we would rather see it included than omitted. Wouldn’t you agree?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I would certainly agree.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I could not see anything sensitive about it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: These are not enormous matters, but I think the question of the
                    maximum publication is an important matter, and I was looking at it from that
                    point of view. I don’t think any one of these individual items is terribly
                    exciting.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The thing I am concerned about, Mr. Chairman, is getting the most
                    benefit out of the interchange of views, and there is a question how that can be
                    done. One way might be for your Committee to make a report indicating each
                    particular item, and you see you have done that. And then let us take this up
                    with the policy officers afterward, because they obviously have to be taken into
                    account and have the last word. The ideal way, if we had the time, would be to
                    take each item here and get the policy officers’ views on each item. Now there
                    may not be time for that. I would like to see it done as far as possible.
                    Perhaps some of the larger items like the Ecuador-Peru boundary, can be
                    discussed with reference to the group of papers, since there are so many of them
                    that are out. And there may be several subjects which can be treated in that way
                    and the views of the policy officers could be obtained. It is a question of how
                    we can make the best use of our time.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Frankly on these individual items it seems to me a cumbersome
                    process to discuss them one by one. There are fifty or sixty of them. I
                    believe—but I can’t speak for my colleagues—we could list our conclusions.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Even if these items take only several minutes each, it would take
                    several hours.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We would like to keep our views clearly in mind. It is this: If
                    we are to have the historical publication, it must be the document pretty much
                    as it was. If there are a great many minor changes, this makes a great deal of
                    difference to the historian, and the historian might very well prefer a longer
                    delay in publication, instead of using the fifteen or twenty year period to use
                    a longer one if the documents are going to be cut apart.</p>
                <p>This is a strong view on our part, and it covers these minor points. The
                    historical profession has gradually come to have a greater affection and deeper
                    respect for this <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series as it has
                    become more useful to historians. Way back fifty years ago it used to be cut all
                    to pieces, and now it is a good set of documents, well presented. If there are
                    many minor changes, the profession will not want to use this series.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think possibly though the political scientist and international
                    lawyer would be a little uneasy if there was too much delay in publication.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I would agree with everything Mr. Harrington says, but it seems to
                    me that in addition that we as political scientists and international lawyers
                    have to stand as witness to the fact that to delay these is necessary sometimes.
                    I think on these particular issues, together with some we will talk about in the
                    Far East, we could not go and say to our colleagues, “Well, the Department is
                    justified in holding these up.”</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would agree with that, of course. It would seem to me quite wrong
                    to delay publication on the reasons of these minor questions that we have
                    discussed with regard to Volume 5, for example, of 1940, and we do feel strongly
                    that the tendency is to delete a little bit too much, really. We are not taking
                    any dogmatic position on this, as I think even a brief review of those six or
                    seven items indicates, but I do feel we must keep our sense of humor with
                    respect to these matters and as to the importance of some items of experience of
                    eighteen or twenty years ago. There may be a case for deletion now and then, but
                    this is—</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I don’t think any one of us felt that any one of these individual
                    items was of particular consequence at all, but what we did feel, I am sure, was
                    that a proliferation of this kind of excision tends to produce loss of
                    confidence in the over-all result.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: Mr. Noble, may I make a remark. I did not delete but I approved
                    deletion of some of those by our desk officer. In quite a few of them, there
                    would be no objection about publication let’s say in 1961. The problem arose
                    from the fact that 1960 is an election year in Brazil, and since Axel Aranha is
                    very much on the scene himself— Many other things that are in here could be
                    used to substantiate charges against Aranha in a political year. In 1961 this
                    problem would disappear.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You understand that with regard to those particular documents we
                    recommend deletion. In most of these cases—and I can’t speak for all of them
                    without looking at the record again, but in most of these cases the request for
                    deletion came from the Brazilian Government. In most of those cases where
                    another Government objected, it would be only in rare cases you would go against
                    the request of another Government. But we accepted that on Brazil. We agree to
                    it although we did not recommend it.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I like your last language: We agreed to it although we did not
                    recommend it.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: One of the difficulties was a passionate addiction to deleting direct
                    quotation, which I think ought to be discouraged.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: We ought to have as full reporting as possible.</p>
                <p>In reviewing some of these things, we have in mind the fact that we are dealing
                    with an area which I think has given us many evidences that this area is going
                    through a very great nationalist surge, and everything and anything is subject
                    to this nationalist scrutiny, plus the fact that we have people just looking for
                    tinder to throw on the fire. There is that element.</p>
                <p>There is another element of timing, too. Sometimes a matter which would not be
                    potentially explosive one year may be explosive in a particular year, and it may
                    not be explosive in the following year. For instance, the Peru-Ecuador border.
                    Right now we are passing through a period where the future, for instance, of the
                    Ponce Administration in Ecuador is just balanced practically on the head of a
                    pin on this border issue, and if anybody sneezes too loudly it can blow that
                    right off right now. Maybe eight months from now, after the election, after the
                    Eleventh Inter-American Conference, this would be no more than a controversial
                    issue but not of earthshaking proportions.</p>
                <p>Again you have this fact that we sometimes objected to material which is public
                    knowledge, which has been in the press, and so on, and yet we object to it
                    appearing in this. There is, as you recognize, a difference between something
                    which is publicly known and something which quotes the United States Government
                    as specifically saying so. And to me the most dramatic article of this is this
                        <hi rend="italic">Time Magazine</hi> article which we went through in
                    Bolivia, and a quotation was made of a statement which was probably said by
                    somebody in some place maybe every day in the year for the last seventy-five
                    years. This was nothing new, and yet on this particular day when it appeared and
                    was quoted allegedly by an American official as having said it, all hell broke
                    loose. These are the things we have in mind when we look at these things.</p>
                <p>We feel, and especially at moments when the lives of Americans may be at stake as
                    a result of what is published, and at the time we know that while historians may
                    be largely the people who use this and use it in a responsible way, some
                    enterprising reporter when this comes out may look through this like a boy
                    looking for a dirty word in a book, and put it in a provocative wire and mail it
                    out and there it is. These are the things which go through our minds as we read
                    these.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, no one will deny the existence of nationalistic feeling
                    in the states of Latin America. But this feeling exists. It is going to be
                    excited by many incidents more important than a line or two in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of 1940.</p>
                <p>But with regard to the Peru-Ecuador boundary, which is the important thing, in
                    reading the record yesterday afternoon we were not at all clear as to wherein
                    lay the danger of those communications. It may be we haven’t got the whole
                    story, but we could not see that the correspondence was such as to give much of
                    a handle to a nationalist feeling. Perhaps we were wrong about that. We will
                    consider more information. But I think we stated the view we all had.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Perhaps you could be more specific.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: I didn’t review personally this material, but I think that we
                    all felt that the whole subject itself was at this time especially explosive,
                    and we should avoid saying anything, and rather than to try to excise a lot
                    which would leave you with a chopped-up affair we would delay the publication of
                    anything. I think this was our point of view. I believe we just objected to the
                    whole series; didn’t we?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: No, but so much was out.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But you excised so much it would certainly affect the integrity of
                    the record.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Ralph, as I understand it the objection was based on the principle
                    that we wanted to avoid putting the United States on one side or the other. Was
                    that your point of view?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes. As I remember it—of course, as you know, Peru occupied some of
                    the disputed area, moved over into Ecuadorian territory, and there was some
                    fighting there, and some of the documents show that we definitely did put the
                    blame on Peru. And so I think that was the idea—that Peru could use that to
                    show that the United States was not an impartial mediator in the dispute. There
                    were only a few documents—actually, if you pinned those down, it would be only
                    a few documents stating that, but maybe it was right, that if you were going to
                    cut out any document that would seem to throw the blame on Peru—maybe some
                    disparaging remarks were about Ecuador in the story, too—that it wouldn’t mess
                    up the story, so we finally agreed that that wasn’t an important enough issue to
                    hold up that publication, and so I believe you saw the bracketed remark we put
                    in. In other words, we don’t conceal that we are holding out material, but we
                    put in a bracketed statement that we left out some documents regarding the
                    efforts to settle that fight.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The record as we had it here was a very large number of excisions,
                    many of them which seemed to us quite trivial.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Oh, yes, there were. I would agree. There were a number of
                    deletions, but there were some statements there that did—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think if we examined it from the point of view of each individual
                    item there—which was not what we did in that case, we were looking at the
                    general picture—it may well be that there are one or two items which we feel
                    might be eliminated.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I think that is what caused it—the fact that there were certain
                    items. That is one thing that we were interested in, your reaction to that. It
                    was one of those things where a rather important decision had to be made. There
                    were three courses, you see. One would be to leave that part in, chopped up,
                    with lots of deletions, leave that whole phase of the controversy out and put in
                    a bracketed note there saying we were leaving it out, or to delay publication
                    completely. We decided to put in the bracketed note and say we were leaving that
                    section out, and then go back to the policy boys and see if they would let us
                    print it with that arrangement, which they agreed to do.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But you have agreed to the excision of all that material?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes. But there is a bracketed note, as I think you saw, explaining
                    that we were leaving it out. That is one thing—if we are leaving out things we
                    think should probably go in, we do try to let the reader know that we are
                    leaving it out.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: In this case I can’t be sure in my own recollection, but it seems to
                    me it was at least half the galley, probably more.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes; it is.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: That seemed like an extraordinarily large amount to exclude and
                    still preserve the integrity of the record. We have two objectives: to preserve
                    the integrity of the record, which you people want to do, of course, and to
                    expedite publication. You have to choose sometimes between these.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: The reason for leaving so much of that out is that in that year they
                    started to discuss the boundary. Then they got into this fighting. They got into
                    the fighting and the issue of Peru sending troops over the line, and occupying
                    the Ecuadorian territory—until they got that straightened out they couldn’t go
                    on with the rest of it. And actually, so far as the documentation on that goes,
                    there is more documentation on that phase than there is on the merits of the
                    dispute itself. I am simply trying to explain what we did. As I said, it was one
                    of those doubtful decisions as to what we should do in this case. We wanted to
                    get that volume out and we certainly didn’t want to leave it out without letting
                    the reader know we were leaving that out, that important stuff.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I did not see this and I am asking this question from ignorance.
                    Suppose someone wanted to make a study of the Ecuador-Peru boundary dispute and
                    the role of the United States as mediator—was that the position of the United
                    States in the whole matter?—with this material left out, the record would be
                    far from complete, would it not? I mean, this material has a direct relevance to
                    the subject. It is not just an interesting little side story.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: How would you answer? I would simply say some of it was simply
                    sideshow.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: There is a good deal of it that is not directly related to the
                    mediation directly.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Quite a few of the matters with regard to the supposed attitude of
                    the United States, though, were of some importance, I felt, bearing on the
                    dispute.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think this question of expedition of publication is an important
                    thing for all of us to remember. Where questions of clearance are delayed over a
                    long period of time, this is damaging to the reputation of the series. It is all
                    very well to say matters should be postponed, but there are always more reasons
                    for postponement to come up. I think all of us would say, and I am sure my
                    colleagues would correct me at any time, because I don’t represent them, that it
                    is important for us to maintain the tempo of these things and not fall
                    behind.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: But the decision has been taken and we are simply asked to express
                    an opinion on the decision.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think Mr. Perkins said the decision was taken.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Yes. And it is one of those things where we would like to know
                    whether you think we did right. The only reason we accepted that was that if we
                    didn’t the whole volume would be held up indefinitely.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Indefinitely or until this dispute is settled.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Already, you see, every other volume from 1940 is out and we simply
                    don’t know—that boundary dispute has been going on for years and years and
                    years. We don’t know.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: It might be indefinite.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I suppose the judgment on that is an evaluation of the problem, but
                    I think you did right from my angle of vision.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: This is the ’40 volume?</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: This is ’40.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: No; ’41.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: You see, the 1940 volume isn’t even out yet.</p>
                <p>On this matter of delay again it seems to me the Historical Division’s hands are
                    rather tied in not being able to explain why these delays are made. We faced
                    this with the China volumes last year, in suggesting if they were going to hold
                    up the volumes that some statement should be made by a higher level. And I am
                    sure the average political scientist and international lawyer and historian can
                    not understand why the 1940 and 1941 volumes on Latin America are not out.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But there are many points of view.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: Mr. Chairman, just one other thing. We have accepted—of course,
                    this volume is still in a clearance stage. The Committee could come back and say
                    “You ought to reconsider.” I am not saying you should, but I just want to get
                    the record straight that this volume is still out. We did say we would accept
                    that, but the volume is still in clearance stage.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I hadn’t quite understood. I am glad to know that. In other words,
                    you are asking us to approve a decision already made.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: We made that decision.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: But we could ask you to reconsider this.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: (Inaudible) ... if we were on one side of the issue or the other, so
                    it is a matter of substance, and so it is a little different from most of the
                    other questions. Most of the other deletions have been accepted with the idea
                    that it does not profoundly affect the substance of the matter. This evidently
                    does, so the decision on this is an important one.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: It would seem to me you are taking out a very essential part of the
                    substance if you cut that out. And I would have the further question whether the
                    possible influence of publication on a political development in that country is
                    a valid reason. There are always elections in each country, and if we start
                    gauging publication—</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: I was not talking about the next election. I was talking about
                    the political set-up right now.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That question will be with us, will be wish us a long time, and it
                    won’t be settled tomorrow or the day after.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: When I spoke of the next election I was speaking of a man like
                    Aranha, a man actually participating in an election.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: You referred to a particular person, and no particular individual is
                    involved here.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: Not on each issue.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is a matter that the delicacy of the situation, as to whether it
                    becomes known that we were on Peru’s side, whether hell would be raised in
                    Ecuador, or vice versa. It is a question of how seriously that would affect the
                    political situation in one country or another, and it is not easy, I think, to
                    have a clear view on that.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: We have today an active role. It is not what we were in 1942. We
                    have today a position of being an impartial guarantor of this issue. We are
                    still today actively involved in this issue.</p>
                <p>MR. BOONSTRA: I should like to submit a question which has not been clear to me
                    on this matter. To some extent the attitude of the desk officers and
                    geographical officers concerned is always colored by the fact that a decision
                    may involve a responsibility in a riot in Guayaquil, in which people will be
                    killed. If somebody in the Department is willing to take this off our shoulders
                    and make this decision, our attitude changes somewhat. We are trying to protect
                    certain U. S. policy objectives and trying to protect U. S. citizens in many
                    cases, and so I think sometimes it is impossible to argue this out. It is
                    sometimes simply a matter of executive responsibility and decision. The people
                    who are asked to clear these things make the recommendation but do not take
                    responsibility for the ultimate consequences.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: There is another point that has been raised. I think you suggested
                    that this is still an active matter.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: By all means.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: The United States is still mediator?</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: We are guarantors; every day in the week we have calls, every
                    day, from the Peruvian and Ecuadorian Ambassador. We have talked about this the
                    day before yesterday, and the day before that, and the day before that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we can agree with this, but it would seem to me if the
                    actions reflect on the impartiality of the United States we would agree those
                    should be deleted; but as we looked at the record yesterday we thought a lot of
                    deletion had gone on. On the specific problem we recognize that there are
                    sensitive areas and sensitive problems.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Isn’t there also the question as to whether this is still going on,
                    as to whether this should be published now anyway? I think that is probably one
                    of the questions raised.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: We have had, for instance, under consideration the possibility
                    of the guarantor’s making a moderate impartial statement on this issue at this
                    time as an aid to the situation. We have had five different visits from the
                    Ecuadorian Ambassador imploring us, “Please don’t say anything. If you do it can
                    be seized upon in either country and implications distorted and twisted, and it
                    can destroy our Foreign Minister, and possibly topple the Government, or at
                    least cause serious disturbance at the Eleventh Inter-American Conference to be
                    held in Quito in February.” These are things, even though they are history, with
                    which we are living today.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Do you think this would make any difference if this came out next
                    year sometime?</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: Possibly it would—especially if there has been some progress in
                    settling the issue.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Has the Committee considered the advantages or regularity in
                    appearance of these volumes as a priority goal? This question of timing is a
                    question of extremely slippery rationalization which can speed one volume up,
                    and this happened notoriously a few years ago, and it can also slow some down.
                    Then the whole world knows that these appearances of these volumes are timed for
                    political advantages, and foreign views are that these can be timed to help this
                    foreign government or that foreign prince. This is the worst possible situation.
                    Some volumes have been pushed out and some slowed up. So that the whole idea
                    that this is a regular program has been slowed up and has just about been lost.
                    It seems to me that we should get this back to where five or six volumes will
                    appear regularly each year, so that the newshawks will not pounce on each one
                    but we hope will be thoroughly uninterested in each one of these, because this
                    is just another volume of each of these series that is coming along.</p>
                <p>It may take some time to re-establish this, but I think Mr. Perkins will agree
                    that that used to be the condition, and they were accepted in that
                    framework.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: True. If a volume is held up several years, two questions arise when
                    it does come out: Why has this volume been held up so long? And then they begin
                    to study and dig in to see what caused it to be held up, and that might cause
                    unfavorable publicity. Secondly, if this volume has been held up so many years,
                    why is it brought out at this particular time? What is the State Department
                    aiming at in dropping this out now? And then they think that there is some
                    political purpose behind it.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: They all become “white papers.”</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I raised a question yesterday which was intended to carry this same
                    implication.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: I don’t see how anybody can raise that question.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I would like to talk to this point, because I think this is
                    extremely important from the Public Affairs point of view, because the first
                    question I am asked when any volume comes out is that the reporters call me and
                    say, “Why did you put it out now?”</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think what you say is very true. We would all agree with it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The second point is, it is bad to confuse publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes with publications such as in
                        <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> on the Bolivian question. I don’t know of any
                    case where publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume
                    has precipitated riots any place. That is a totally different matter.</p>
                <p>MR. SILBERSTEIN: The volume itself wouldn’t, but if someone chose to look for a
                    story.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That is not a problem for this Committee. That is a problem for
                    the Public Affairs to try to put the volume in perspective and prevent this. I
                    am not saying we can do it, but it is our problem. It is not relevant to this
                    discussion, which is focused on other matters, of maintaining a record and if
                    possible a continuity which I would hope would have a regular timing, so that
                    this whole issue does not arise.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Let us consider in going over the South American thing again, who
                    would maintain that the general trend of relations with the Chinese Nationalists
                    have been vitally affected by the publication of the “White Paper”? This must be
                    very offensive to General Chiang Kai-shek from any point of view. This would be
                    a question which could easily be raised, but on the whole we stagger along in
                    our relations with the Chinese Nationalists, and in spite of the fact that we
                    published a large volume which was full of criticism of the whole regime. And
                    not only that, but a former officer of the Department has published a volume on
                    the subject. There are many ways in which we know the disastrous results which
                    follow. I think it is so easy to exaggerate the significance of this or that
                    isolated sentence in a long dispatch. It is the business of policy officers to
                    watch the language, obviously, but when we are trying to think of it objectively
                    as historians we can see that it may not be quite as important as we think.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think we are getting into a bottomless pit as far as this
                    Committee is concerned. Mr. Kretzmann and Frank have clarified the issue. The
                    only thing this Committee can do is to give our opinion about particular
                    documents which have been deleted or suggested for deletion. We give our
                    opinion, and I think this is where it stops. If there is a conflict between
                    policy of publication and regularity of publication by the State Department as
                    embodied in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series as between
                    immediate instances, this is not in our purview.</p>
                <p>We have asked about the record and have fairly strong feelings on what has been
                    presented to us. We know the problems which have been presented, but we can’t
                    solve your problems any more than you can solve ours.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Within that framework we do obviously endorse regular
                    publication.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: And of course, if times have changed, as they have, if they have
                    changed so much that we won’t be able to publish any significant part of the
                    record of twenty years ago, the question is whether we should not publish at
                    all.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Whether we should not say so and put it on a perfectly open
                    basis.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any other comments on the Latin American volumes? We
                    don’t want to foreclose discussion. What has been said is true. We can give you
                    our ideas as to what can or can not be published with propriety. The decision
                    does not rest with us. I can only say we are discussing this and approaching it
                    from the point of view of scholarship with a due regard for the interests of the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I might say for the benefit of all, including the desk officers,
                    that the new procedures I have instituted, that Bernard has helped on, that the
                    final decision of do we publish now is made by the Under Secretary for Political
                    Affairs, and I suppose at times he might want to consult the Secretary; so there
                    is always the last stop where a question of something that has happened in the
                    last few months would stop this. And it used to be Mr. Murphy. Bernard calls my
                    attention to some of the items that may be particularly sensitive, and we don’t
                    put it downstairs until we get the okay. So there are plenty of precautions. I
                    am assuring the officers that this is not done automatically, that we do take a
                    last look. That is a new process instituted this last year.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Shall we go on?</p>
                <p>I wish to thank the officer who came in to help us with that discussion.</p>
                <p>Now we have the Cairo, Tehran, and Potsdam Conferences here. We have a memorandum
                    in regard to the Cairo-Tehran Conference, and we have some deletions that were
                    made and accepted by the editors, and so on, that were deletions suggested by
                    the Defense Department. With regard to the deletions made by the Department of
                    State we have some comments to be made.</p>
                <p>There is a long statement here with regard to relations between Dreyfus and
                    President Roosevelt at Tehran, to which Dreyfus gave the number 754, a very
                    sharp exchange. “This was not through usual channels ... and because the subject
                    ... is more ... to the United States-Iranian relations than to the United
                    States, United Kingdom ... Conference at Tehran.”</p>
                <p>(The Chairman read the above quotation in full, but it was inaudible to the
                    reporter.)</p>
                <p>We concurred in that deletion.</p>
                <p>The other was a series of deletions with regard to the remarks that Roosevelt
                    made at Tehran, and in one, for example, Roosevelt to Stalin regarding the
                    political situation, he added jokingly that when the “ ... Eden intended to go
                    to war with the Soviet Union on this point ... Soviet Union.”</p>
                <p>On another statement, speaking to Stalin, the President agreed that no person
                    over forty who had taken part in the French Government should be allowed to
                    return to public life in the future.</p>
                <p>These remarks may be somewhat damaging to President Roosevelt, but we didn’t
                    think that they should be excluded from the record.</p>
                <p>And then that quotation went on: “He said ... become citizens.”</p>
                <p>And finally there was a Department of State memorandum on the status of certain
                    specific items: “United States legal claims ... are less strong than those of
                    the British Government.” And on that we felt possibly an omission might be
                    made.</p>
                <p>These are small matters in the Cairo-Tehran Conference, really, that we had to
                    consider, but I think you can see the attitude with which we approached the
                    problem from the deletions that were made.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We might add, though, Dexter, that the other deletions, where it
                    involved the Defense Department, we were individually regretful that these
                    deletions had to be made but we were not going to raise the issue after those
                    who had been already over the ground—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We can’t raise an issue there, really. If I am wrong, correct me.
                    How about that? Didn’t we think the statements with regard to the French might
                    be left in? That was my impression.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes. Perhaps we did not have full agreement about it, but that
                    was my feeling.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I thought that was the majority view.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Would you agree also that deletion would not affect the substance of
                    the record? If we had to delete it, it would not be serious damage to the
                    record? If it is against the Governmental policy, it would not affect it
                    seriously if we did delete it.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: This is kind of a tough one, because you can say this about
                    almost any small statement, but when you begin adding them up, supposing there
                    had been ten deletions of this sort, and of course there were a good many
                    because of the Defense Department and what not, and we would be inclined to
                    think that deletions ought not to be made unless we feel they are absolutely
                    necessary—absolutely necessary—because who is to know how important these
                    things are? It is true that these are points that don’t get to the heart of the
                    policy decisions that were made, but Roosevelt’s position on the Baltic and
                    Roosevelt’s position on the French are both matters of great importance.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Bernard, check my memory on this: Wasn’t this largely because of
                    the personal references to de Gaulle and not to Roosevelt?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: This is a little different.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: De Gaulle comes into the category of being over forty.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: But this has a particular importance at this time.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I take it the Division felt it should be more careful of protecting
                    the reputations of persons in other countries than in our own.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Mr. Roosevelt had a habit of making offhand remarks, and this is one
                    of the offhand remarks where I doubt whether it represents Government policy.
                    It, I think, has to be judged in that light.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But we would take them as offhand remarks.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: They would be so taken.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Opposition had originally been raised to about two dozen such
                    remarks in these galleys. We fought it down to these.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We are glad.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: That leaves then these as the last ones we gave up on. Personally I
                    am much more concerned about what the critical reviewers would think was in
                    there instead of the dots, than what actually was, and there would be no
                    explaining it.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Are you resigned on the other deletions?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: It is as indicated in the memorandum.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We are pleased to see that you did try hard on those.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you want to review what our comments are on the Potsdam
                    Conference at this time?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: There is one point we haven’t covered on the Cairo one, on the two
                    maps.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That issue is not closed. The two you have given me.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We thought they ought to know about it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Shall I tell where it stands at the moment? I have it in hand at
                    the moment, and I have talked to Defense twice about this. That is, our contact,
                    the Public Affairs Section, they are not directly responsible for—what is his
                    name? Mr. Winnacker, the Historian—but they do have a sort of lateral pressure
                    line, and they have agreed with us that it is worth trying to have him let these
                    come through.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They have a link with the Joint Chiefs.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I have talked with both Snyder and Chauncey Robbins about this to
                    see if we could help break this out.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It might be helpful to know the views of this Committee.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes, it would be helpful. It would give me another reason to raise
                    it once more.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I don’t know what the position is on that particular issue.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: On what?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: These are the two maps about the post-war bases.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If I am correct in my recollection, we thought that that might be
                    omitted, since it involved legal questions which couldn’t possibly—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I was not altogether clear on the matter, so we didn’t have much
                    discussion. Very little discussion. But certainly if Mr. Kretzmann would fight
                    again on it, I would say, please do.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We would support him. If this group feels, and you say so here,
                    that the documents in Tab B, and particularly the two maps, are necessary to
                    what Mr. Hopkins had in mind in raising this question, we would be strongly
                    inclined to support your position and hope you could get the right to publish
                    it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The point at issue is that this whole consideration of allied
                    bases in the interim period before the United Nations had been set up and had
                    its security forces, and so on, always in that context is that this is an
                    interim measure to maintain stability until the United Nations police
                    force—which never came into being—could take it over. It is in that context
                    that we see no reason why this should not be published. Defense, possibly
                    because of a guilty conscience, does not feel the same way about the bases that
                    are still being maintained around the world. We may lose this argument, but we
                    will try.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. But you look for a moment at the Potsdam Conference. This is a
                    memorandum, and on the items beginning on page 1 we have agreed to the point of
                    view which omits a dozen British position papers. We were not sure that the
                    single text on Spain needed to be omitted.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We were stronger than not being sure. We thought it ought to be
                    included. That is my recollection.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: We saw no reason why it should not be published.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We saw no reason why it should not be published.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The same applies, and we agreed to three and to four and to five.
                    Then there are at the end of the memorandum a number of points.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Appendix F.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. Short passages were deleted. We agreed to one. We thought that
                    two, and three, and four and five indicated excessive caution. We agreed to six
                    and seven, and we believe that eight and nine ought to be published. In other
                    words, we agreed to the deletion of numbers one and six and seven. Is that
                    correct?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: And you object to the deletion of the paper on Spain?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. We say very decidedly it should be included.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Ivan, do you want to talk to these points?</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: I was not in the Department at the time of the previous go-round. I
                    think it is our basic feeling that our position on Spain at that time was set
                    forth in other public documents and is well known, and perhaps in this form of
                    an internal document we used language which we certainly would not have used in
                    quite the same nomenclature if we had had any idea it might be published.
                    Actually there was printed in the State Department <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulletin</hi> just a few months, I think, previous to the date listed here
                    a speech by Livingston Merchant, who at that time was head of our Eastern
                    Hemisphere operations, which said much the same thing as far as the policy
                    stands.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. The substance of this is well known; don’t you think so? The
                    substance of this memorandum.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: That is why we could not see any damage could be done by
                    this.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Nor do I see that this language used here is so difficult.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The argument is used both ways, Everybody knows it, so why publish
                    it? And, everybody knows it, so why not publish it? (Laughter)</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That comes out again and again, of course. When facts are stated
                    that are so well known, the argument is in favor of publication.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: You could put a note in that the policy paper, is here omitted
                    because everybody knows it anyway.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think it goes a little deeper than what Mr. Harrington said
                    yesterday, that this was in the briefing book and was under consideration at
                    this time.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: This is one of the papers that we fought the hardest on. We finally
                    narrowed down to on about eight papers, mostly regarding Poland, on which we as
                    the Division and the Bureau of Public Affairs said we can’t accept the view of
                    the Bureau of European Affairs without higher decision. And those eight papers
                    did go to Mr. Murphy, who was the Deputy Under Secretary for Political Affairs,
                    and his decision was that we could print seven of the eight, and the paper on
                    Spain we should not. Theoretically we can fight it higher, but it is rather
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Not much higher. (Laughter)</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: And at that point we said, “Yes, sir,” and left it out.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: It is a good score.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: It seems to me, if I can help you out, the best argument is our
                    changing circumstances of our relations with the Spanish, and little words like
                    “we can’t have any cordial relations with Franco”—</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: That is certainly obvious, too, to the extent that you bring this out
                    into the open again and revive it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We can’t take back the speech that Mr. Merchant made, but we
                    needn’t rub it in, by adding another document.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: You would not expect Mr. Merchant to make the same speech today.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Nor to write such a document as this.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: So you have to take it in context.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: But given Spanish sensitivities.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: They are more than that; they are hypersensitive.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Mr. Chairman, we are here again, and it seems to me that the
                    Committee thinks we ought to, and this is it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We can mark time for a moment. Mr. Parsons is going to arrive;
                    isn’t he?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMAN: Don’t you want to take these up? These are the ones under F. Do you
                    want to take them up while Mr. White is here?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Under F actually we deplored all the omissions by State
                    Department action, and we went along only with those which foreign governments
                    or which Department of Defense insisted on.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Even granting all the sensitivity in the world, it is difficult
                    to see why we should omit something like, “The Turks are inclined ...”</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That might be said of almost any country.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Including the United States and Russia.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I am one who went along with this, I am sorry to say.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: You were the one who insisted that this one be taken out.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I can’t remember why now.</p>
                <p>MR. HARTINGTON: Maybe you will change your position.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I am no longer in NEA, so I am no longer competent to make that
                    decision. I don’t think this is really very serious. We can get them to back on
                    it, I think. What do you think?</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: I think we could. I think we could go at it again.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If we are really going to spare people’s feelings, we have some
                    drastic things in this country. There are the expressions of Congressmen, for
                    example.</p>
                <p>Is there any comment on those? I think Mr. Harrington has summarized it, that
                    what we have done is accept deletions which came about through representations
                    of another Government, and recommended that there be included those portions
                    which the State Department as a matter of fact suggested for deletion. Does Mr.
                    White want to talk on that?</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: Just to get things in their proper context, I think it should be
                    recalled that there are a vast number of instances in which we did have some
                    objection but concerning which we yielded to the views of the Historical
                    Division, so we are dealing here with the hard core of cases which we felt were
                    beyond the point of marginal doubt. I think in the case of the telegrams dealing
                    with the Poles, that we feel from the standpoint of our relationships with
                    Poland and what we are trying to evolve there, that the publication of these at
                    this juncture would be damaging. I will have to defer to Ed and his former
                    colleagues on the question of the remark about the Turks.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: What about the last two points, 8 and 9, Ivan? Was this deleted at
                    the time when Mr. Eden was in the Foreign Office?</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: It was.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Is it pertinent to review this?</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: Perhaps EUR might feel somewhat different about it now, but there
                    were three members of the British Cabinet involved at the time we accepted
                    deletion of that, and they have now all left, I guess, the active scene. We
                    might try again.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Not to return?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Not to return. Yes. Do you think EUR still feels strongly about
                    that remark?</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: I can check back on that one, but my own personal feeling is that they
                    would probably still object to it. He is still alive.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: But he has been to a psychologist.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: It is somewhat beyond being on the uncomplimentary side, really.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: The same charge has been made against him by the British
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Mr. Chairman, I gather you felt very strongly these two should be
                    published, 8 and 9?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: We can take another look at those two.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I suppose Mr. Eden is out for good insofar as politics.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: He was present at the dinner at 10 Downing Street, which was given by
                    Mr. Macmillan for the President. He got up and made a five-minute speech which
                    with great effort—he impressed us as being a dying man—and it was probably the
                    best speech made. And it was a very interesting gathering, because in addition
                    to Macmillan there were three Ex-Prime Ministers present—Churchill and Lord
                    Atlee and Eden. And Eden made, I thought, from our standpoint the best speech.
                    Certainly it was the most complimentary one towards the United States in terms
                    of both the Marshall Plan and NATO. And I would just hate like hell at this
                    juncture to come along and publish these views of him. That is my own personal
                    reaction.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: When you look at it again, Ivan, would you remember some of the
                    British General’s remarks about our President recently in public? (Laughter)</p>
                <p>MR. WHIE: Yes. I will. We will certainly keep that in mind.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Thank you.</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: Are you really advocating retaliatory action?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: No. (Laughter)</p>
                <p>MR. WHITE: We will be glad to have another look at that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we are ready now to discuss the two volumes that relate to
                    the Far East, Volume 5, 1941, and China Volume for 1943, and I think I ought to
                    really say that last year we considered Volume 5 for the Far East and
                    recommended that it be cleared for publication. With regard to the formulation
                    of the volume on China, there were extreme objections on the part of the Far
                    Eastern Office to publication, and we merely said in our confidential report
                    that we thought responsibility ought to be made clear as resting with the Far
                    Eastern Division and not with the Historical Division. Since then, as I stated
                    earlier this morning, our Committee divided, when we came to discuss this
                    question anew, and I will leave it to my colleagues who examined the volumes
                    carefully to state their position with regard to them. Do you want to do it?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I guess probably I examined the Thailand one most carefully, and I
                    will report on that, and you can take care of the China one.</p>
                <p>As I think we see it, in 1941, the Volume 5, <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> in the Far East, as far as that is concerned, the question
                    really is whether the volume is to be published or not on the basis of the
                    volume as it stands, whether it is to be published or not on the basis of the
                    Thailand material, because it has already been assembled and bound, and
                    therefore there is no question of eliminating certain documents so as to permit
                    the publication of the remainder. If that course were to be followed, you would
                    have to have a completely new preparation of the volume in question.</p>
                <p>Now there are a number of documents here, and I haven’t got the volume here.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Here it is. It is all clipped there.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I had your copy.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Where is the 1941 volume?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: It is 1940.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: My copy is clipped just like yours, Bernard. He can use mine.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Here it is.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: There are a number of documents here where Mr. Grant, who has been
                    the Minister to Bangkok makes some very specific and none-too-complimentary
                    references to the Prime Minister, who is now I believe still living, and Prince
                    Won, who is a respected figure currently, and an elder statesman of Thailand and
                    Representative of the United Nations in dealing with the Hungarian question. He
                    does not, I would think, hold any such damaging personal remark as was made with
                    respect to Eden in another question, as being a psychopathic case, and things
                    like that, but he does refer to him as being pro-Japanese and engaged in
                    activities from the point of view of American national interests which would
                    certainly not be commended. Here, for example:</p>
                <p>”As I inquired of the principals the public extent of Siamese claims to be
                    presented to the Tokio Mediation Conference, he replied he had been designated
                    by the Foreign Minister to study that very question” ... and he mentioned the
                    territories of Laos and Cambodia, and he is quoted in another connection in a
                    later document, Prince Won said, “We will try to get all that we can” and more
                    specifically he is quoted as saying, “We will try to get Laos and Cambodia.” In
                    another place he has referred to Prince Won as the front man for the present
                    regime, and another communication has a reference to the aggressive policy of
                    the Thailand Government, and the fact that the Thailand Government is filing a
                    protest along this line.</p>
                <p>Now, for the reasons which I am not familiar with, apparently Mr. Grant either
                    resigned or was recalled as Minister to Bangkok along about the end of August.
                    In any case he was replaced by Mr. Beck, and from that point on the reports
                    coming back were of a somewhat different nature, indicating a more sympathetic
                    view of the plight of Thailand and of what the Thailand Government was trying to
                    do. And then at the end you had the Japanese invasion and then after a very
                    sharp resistance the surrender and negotiation of a treaty of alliance, and then
                    the Thailand Minister in Washington, in a conversation with the Secretary of
                    State, practically says what Grant had earlier been reporting, that this was a
                    pro-Japanese group that now controls the Government. That, then, is the general
                    picture.</p>
                <p>Now, it would seem to me that all these things have to be taken in historical
                    perspective, and just because, let’s say, the person who was the Prime Minister
                    and Prince Won seem at that time and were reported by our Minister as having
                    followed a policy which was opposed to our national interests, and which we were
                    then condemning, and Secretary Hull was quite colorful on one or two occasions
                    in his condemnation, I don’t think that that should be a reason for excluding
                    the material from the historical record, because we admit President Roosevelt
                    said some things we wish he had not said. Our Government adopted some policies
                    which we wish they had not adopted. And these other people could have done the
                    same thing and still be on the side of the angels at the present time.</p>
                <p>So where so much is at stake, the publication of the whole volume, I would feel
                    particularly strongly that the material here in question is not so objectionable
                    as to warrant indefinite postponement, and I think that is the feeling of the
                    two other members of the Committee who looked this material over very
                    carefully.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you want to add anything?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: No; that represents our point of view.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: This is excellent.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think I should introduce Mr. Parsons to you. He is the Assistant
                    Secretary for Far Eastern Affairs.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: I am very grateful for the opportunity to appear before this group
                    and to try to put into perspective the point of view we bring to bear on
                    publication of this particular volume. I know that this has been a highly
                    controversial issue for several years and that the general feeling of your group
                    has been along the lines which have just been reaffirmed.</p>
                <p>In dealing with this problem I did not wish simply to reaffirm the position which
                    had been taken by other members of the Far Eastern Bureau or by my predecessor,
                    in whose judgment I have the greatest confidence, however. I thought that in
                    view of the fact that we would be discussing this with you sometime, that I
                    would prefer to have the whole issue reviewed by someone who had not been
                    involved in reviewing it before and who was reasonably fresh to the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>I have had it reviewed by my new Deputy Assistant Secretary for Far Eastern
                    Affairs, who just returned from being Consul General in Hong Kong and before
                    that Political Adviser to Admiral Stump and Admiral Felt in Honolulu. I also
                    sent a message to Ambassador Johnson in Bangkok to obtain his judgment in the
                    light of current circumstances.</p>
                <p>My own disposition in the abstract is to want to publish the maximum for obvious
                    reasons, because the understanding of our foreign policy and the development of
                    constructive attitudes depends on public opinion being well informed.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: [Continuing] It depends on the public being well informed and on
                    having a highly-sophisticated and intelligent and scholarly public opinion
                    brought to bear on the issues. It is, therefore, with considerable reluctance
                    that I have reached a contrary view on the publication of a volume relating to
                    events so many years in the past.</p>
                <p>Now at the risk of detaining you for a few minutes, I would like to try briefly
                    to relate the issue of the publication of this volume with the references to our
                    current foreign policy objectives in the Far East and most particularly in South
                    East Asia.</p>
                <p>As you all know, the defense of the free Far Eastern countries on the perimeter
                    of the great and dynamic Chinese land mass, the aggressive Chinese regime at the
                    present time, is our basic objective. The preservation of the freedom of these
                    countries, many of them new countries, countries still undergoing the birth
                    pangs after years of colonial rule, is highly important to basic United States
                    interests and to the balance of power in the free world. Nowhere is the arc of
                    free Asia weaker than in the South East Asian area. Furthermore, South East
                    Asia, unlike Western Europe, is not a well-knit and cohesive region with a
                    tremendous web of interrelationships which make possible and have made possible
                    the development of a relatively stable post-war Western Europe in the last few
                    years.</p>
                <p>South East Asia, when you look at it on the map, is not really a region. It has
                    been divided by many factors, including the very backwardness of those countries
                    and the lack of means for intercourse between them. In this area, the neighbors,
                    not only do not have an intricate web of relationships and therefore do not know
                    each other well in depth, but to the extent they do know each other it has been
                    largely as enemies. As one example, we might take Thailand and Cambodia. Much of
                    Thailand, as it exists at present, was carved out of Cambodia on the ruins of
                    the ancient Khmer Empire centered at Angkor Wat. When the French came to
                    Cambodia in 1863 and induced the King of Cambodia to accept a protectorate—it
                    was at the expense of Thai claims—both Thailand and the Annamite Kingdom
                    claimed suzerainty over what is now Cambodia.</p>
                <p>In 1867 the French forced the Thais to renounce claims to parts of Siem-reap and
                    Battambang Provinces. In 1883 they forced further relationships with the Thais.
                    In 1904 they forced the relinquishment of the northern area which included the
                    Temple of Preah Vihear, which in the years ever since has been a symbol for an
                    intense emotionalism on both sides. In 1907 the French wrested the Siem-reap,
                    the province in which is located Sisophon and Battambang, from the Thais. The
                    Thais have never been reconciled to this. In 1941 the Japanese forced the French
                    to accept them as mediators and the end result of that was that the Japanese
                    restored to Thailand the areas that Thailand had taken from them by the French
                    in 1904 and 1907 which is their Cambodian protectorate.</p>
                <p>In the 1947 treaty of Washington, the Thais were forced by the French to agree to
                    a reservation of the status quo; in other words, Cambodia bought back its pre-war
                    boundaries which were carved out at the expense of Thailand.</p>
                <p>When relations between Thailand and Cambodia are quiescent, very little is heard
                    of the old Irredentist plea that these provinces must be restored to Thailand.
                    However it is not often, unfortunately, that relations between Cambodia and its
                    neighbors are quiescent. Many of you are familiar with the policies and
                    attitudes and the rather spectacular initiatives of Prince Sihanouk, the present
                    Minister and former King of Cambodia. In 1958, without any warning whatever, he
                    broke off diplomatic relations with Thailand and the United States engaged in a
                    very delicate and difficult business of good offices—let’s say, rather than
                    mediation—seeking to calm the excitement and to restore the rupture.</p>
                <p>In 1959, in February of this year, Sihanouk accused both Vietnam and Thailand of
                    harboring his own enemies, Sansari and other individuals, and of fomenting
                    dissension in Cambodia, aimed at overthrowing him. The same month there was a
                    revolt headed by the Governor of Siem-reap Province, Dap Chhuon. His revolt was
                    overthrown and he was killed. However, the suspicions of Cambodia were directed
                    at Thailand, at Vietnam, and also at the United States, which was held
                    responsible in the sense that Prince Sihanouk couldn’t understand why, if we
                    were allied to Thailand and Vietnam, we couldn’t prevent them from taking steps
                    at this time. Therefore, we must have been abetting them.</p>
                <p>In November of this year, without previous warning, Prince Sihanouk submitted the
                    issue relating to the Temple of Preah Vihear to the World Court for
                    adjudication. This was without prior notification to the Thais. This has now
                    touched off a new wave of emotionalism in Thailand and we are reading such
                    things in our cables as the following: This is November 4, in the Chou Thai
                    newspaper: “The time has come when the return of Siem-reap, Battambang,
                    Sisophor, and Kompong ought to be taken up for consideration by the
                    Government.”</p>
                <p>In another paper, “Norodom”—that is Prince Sihanouk’s other name—“has led the
                    Thai people to arrange the return of Thai territory which Cambodia is now
                    ruling.”</p>
                <p>And in still another paper, “Our thoughts cannot help but turn back to the time
                    when the territories were taken away unjustly and are now ruled by Cambodia. The
                    time has come when we must demand their return.”</p>
                <p>And here’s a telegram from Phnom-penh on the 5th: “Accompanied by my Deputy Chief
                    of Mission I called on the Acting Prime Minister at his urgent request. He said
                    Sihanouk had instructed him to inform me of very disquieting information they
                    had received that the Royal Thai Government giving active encouragement and
                    support to Khmer dissidents. According to Cambodian information, the Thais had
                    asked dissident leaders to furnish the equipment”, etc. etc.</p>
                <p>And another article: “The Acting Prime Minister appeared genuinely concerned that
                    the Thais were planning to invade Cambodia”, and so on and so forth.</p>
                <p>I have here other telegrams reflecting the anxiety of the French about the
                    mounting wave of anti-Cambodian nationalism, quoting the French Ambassador in
                    Bangkok; and another one quoting a long conversation between the Australian
                    Ambassador and our Ambassador in Bangkok regarding Australian efforts to try to
                    calm this situation down.</p>
                <p>I think what I have said is enough to indicate that this is a highly volatile
                    situation and that our diplomatic agents are confronted with situations of the
                    utmost delicacy in trying to prevent disputes, deeply seated disputes, between
                    free world countries breaking out in a form which could benefit only one party,
                    namely, the Chinese Communists and the Communist bloc as a whole.</p>
                <p>The 1941 volume contains much historical information confirming the intentions of
                    the Thais and the attitude of the Thais toward this matter. In addition to the
                    passages which have just been quoted, there are passages of a generally similar
                    nature reflecting this type of attitude on pages 2, 7, 43, 47, 88, 113, 114,
                    117-118, 219, 237, and 343. They do center around primarily the attitudes of the
                    statesmen of the time, Prince Wan and Prime Minister Aphaiwong, both of whom are
                    still active and who may be influential figures again.</p>
                <p>But, in reaching a conclusion, which I am very sorry to reach, I have been
                    motivated in taking a position for our Far Eastern Bureau far more by the
                    broader factor of free world interest in the area than the fact that publication
                    of this volume now would be exploited by the Cambodians, it would be exploited
                    by the Communist bloc, and it would be to the detriment of an important free
                    world ally whose capital is also the center of the South East Asia Treaty
                    Organization, on which the collective security arrangements of the area depend.
                    I hope that in a future year or I hope that my successors would be able to
                    reverse the position that we take, but so far as our Bureau is concerned—and we
                    are very deeply concerned—our recommendation has to be contrary to publication
                    at this time.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Can I ask a question? Do you think that there is any information
                    contained in these documents regarding the policy of the Thailand Government
                    during this period or the reactions of the Thailand Government which is not
                    pretty general knowledge? I had the impression myself that it added very little
                    except in detail more than I already knew regarding what the Thailand Government
                    is trying to achieve during the war period. And, so far as the current situation
                    is concerned, I would think that Cambodian leaders and others would have ready
                    access to information indicating what the desires of Thailand were and what
                    their general feelings were with respect to these lost territories. If that is
                    true, if this adds very little to what is known, and particularly what’s known
                    by Cambodian leaders and others in that general group, I don’t quite see the
                    harm that would be done by the publication of a historical record and it has
                    been pointed out earlier, it seems to me, that along with the publication more
                    harm would be done if any harm is to be done. What we would like to see is
                    publication in due course without delay, calling attention to the fact that
                    there may be something here that we could study later.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: I think the documents reflect attitudes and suspicions and policies
                    perhaps that are pretty common knowledge. In that sense, it’s quite correct and
                    would certainly agree with you that there is very little that is new
                    Information. However, to have confirmation in official American documents that
                    this is indeed so is not a helpful element to introduce into the situation at
                    the present time. Furthermore, the very act of publication is certainly
                    something which would not increase our influence with the Thai Government. I
                    think it would confound our friends in that government, particularly those
                    elements who are close to us and who are the exponents of moderation and who
                    realize that unity in the area and development of regionalism there is an
                    important thing for the salvation of the whole area. The current Foreign
                    Minister, for instance, has been making efforts in this regard against rather
                    heavy odds. He is very well aware of the dangers to the area as a whole.</p>
                <p>I think publication by the United States would certainly be regarded as an
                    affront by the Thai Government and would not be a helpful factor in the context
                    either of our relations with the Thai Government or in the development of the
                    South East Asia Treaty Organization which is not merely a collective defense
                    organization but which is a vehicle for developing closer relationships of
                    various sorts between the countries.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: You don’t feel then that it’s possible to convince the Thai
                    authorities that the publication of that <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volume is not an instrument of our national policy, but
                    rather a record for scholars.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: Well, I’m not quite sure.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Well, to remove the significance of publication of a historical
                    record, that’s all.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We can’t even convince them about the <hi rend="italic">New York
                        Times</hi>. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: These are things that have happened that deeply affect the lives and
                    attitudes of people today, and when you’re dealing with a person as volatile as
                    Prince Sihanouk who is ready to exploit any weapon that he can seize, he feels
                    that he is the weaker party, I think it’s unfortunate to do something which
                    would hurt rather than help even in the current context. And I have no doubt
                    whatever that the Communist bloc would seize on the publication with
                    considerable satisfaction and we would find this exploited in Peiping and
                    Hanoi.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What would be exploited? I don’t understand. When you say, “This
                    will be exploited”, I’m not quite clear as to what you mean, because the facts
                    are not new facts. In what sense do you mean? Do you mean the publication would
                    be taken to be an act of discourtesy toward the Thai Government, or what?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: They would twist it and say, “Look here, even the United States
                    recognizes as long ago as 1941 that Thailand was imperialist and Prince Sihanouk
                    was quite right in recognizing the Chinese Communists and in calling on the
                    great Chinese Republic to defend.” You know how they exploit any issue they can
                    get a hold of.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I assume, Mr. Parsons, in line with your remarks that this future
                    year that you speak about is one to which maybe you or your successor could
                    recommend—maybe this isn’t very near—that this is going to continue to be the
                    situation in that area for many years to come. I say this because what’s
                    involved here, as you are well aware, is not only the publication of these
                    documents but documents which presumably you would have no objection to being
                    published and this is one of the issues, I think, that the committee has to
                    consider—how long this will be held up—for these reasons.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: May I speak to that point, Mr. Chairman? I must say quite frankly
                    that Mr. Parsons and Mr. Stephens and other people in FE have shown a full
                    appreciation of our problem with this particular volume. No one volume has been
                    the subject of more discussion between us and other bureaus than this one. We
                    have tried, I think, I hope Jeff will agree, to bring forward, Mr. Berding and I
                    from our side, an understanding of their problem. So there is no quarrel between
                    us, really.</p>
                <p>But I see here a real dilemma. This volume is a real dilemma for us because I
                    certainly support Bernard Noble’s position that we cannot publish a record of
                    this period which does not reflect what’s actually in here. This would be a
                    dishonest document if we deleted these things and it would not accurately and
                    correctly reflect the history of the period. Secondly, I share Mr. Leopold’s
                    fear that this could go on indefinitely being postponed.</p>
                <p>What I thought I’d be getting to is how do we solve this one? I can see one way,
                    which I would like to throw on the table for consideration of Mr. Parsons and
                    the rest of you, that at some point we really decide we are going to publish
                    this and then do, which will take a couple of months, the ground work, if our
                    relations with the governments in the area are such that we need to do. In other
                    words, for us to inform them that we are going to publish it, back it up very
                    carefully with a parallel record of the known facts that have already been
                    published in other volumes to show that this really isn’t anything new, and then
                    exert whatever pressures we can on, you see, Sihanouk and the others not to use
                    the document or exploit it or warn them if they do we will simply say we gave
                    them advance notice. That is the only way I can see we can finally break this
                    deadlock or else this whole volume is going to have to go on the shelf for “an
                    indefinite period”.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If this is true, what this really means, does it not, is that the
                    China volumes will be indefinitely held up? The argument you gave with regard to
                    this is innocent compared with the China volumes.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: At the moment there is no issue between the Bureau of Public
                    Affairs and FE. We agree we cannot publish this at this time because of the
                    things I think Mr. Parsons has very well presented here this morning. So,
                    although we have the recourse of going upstairs to the Under Secretary to settle
                    this—what I’m directing my attention to is how in the future can we break this
                    dilemma and this is one procedure that I think I would like to have FE think
                    about, in really careful preparation for the release of it, warning everybody in
                    advance and then being prepared to make public that we did warn them.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: Well, we would certainly be willing to look into the practicality of
                    that. I personally think that if it’s to the advantage of certain people in the
                    Far East to exploit the information or the act of publication regardless of
                    anything that we may try to do, they will do so. We have no control over
                    that.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: No, I agree, but we would have the counter information available
                    immediately with which to answer it.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: And certainly my device which would lead to getting rid of this
                    problem is one we should look into. I’m agreed to that, and am prepared to take
                    another look at it on that basis and in the context of things this would come
                    around to next year.</p>
                <p>To answer Dr. Leopold’s question in another way, I don’t think anybody can set a
                    time limit, but I don’t think it’s by any means inconceivable, that the
                    situation could evolve in such a way that this thing would look less important
                    to us and look less damaging. Rulers change in different countries. And Prince
                    Sihanouk might leave the scene. A different group might come to the fore in
                    Cambodia. The same way in Thailand.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, there are great influences at work in this whole area at the present
                    time. Take the prevailing attitudes towards Communist China today and some years
                    ago in that area, and the working upon these people of the common menace is
                    going to have its effect over a period of years. It has already had its effect.
                    The Taiwan Strait crisis of a year ago has opened people’s eyes throughout the
                    area, for instance, as to the importance of the United States role in the Far
                    East from the standpoint of their preservation of their independence on almost a
                    day-to-day basis.</p>
                <p>And there is our China policy, which to many of them is highly controversial as
                    well as to many of us too. They begin to see that in different dimensions in
                    terms of their own national survival and this is a factor making for unity. It
                    is also a factor making for a better position for the United States in what it’s
                    trying to accomplish there.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Could you tell us whether any of the chief figures in the present
                    government were involved back in 1941, and I’m thinking of the extent to which
                    the Cambodians might make a case against the present government which was a
                    different government. And also whether the present government has made any
                    gestures in the direction of taking, say, forcible action in the recovery of
                    this territory which is in controversy.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: In answer to the first part of the question, Prince Wan is one of
                    the two Deputy Prime Ministers in the present government. He is not in a
                    position of influence comparable to that which he exerted in previous
                    governments over a considerable period of years. However, in Thailand the
                    fortunes of individuals change rather rapidly and he may again be a very
                    important factor, particularly in the conduct of foreign relations. Phibun,
                    former Prime Minister, is living in Japan at the present time. He spanned half
                    the distance between us and Thailand now. A year ago he was living in exile in
                    California at the University, and he has now gotten half way back and we may see
                    him all the way back. In still another year his political fortunes might be
                    rehabilitating. These are people who might play an important part in the life of
                    their nation again.</p>
                <p>The Cambodian Government has taken no overt steps to recover any of these
                    territories and I do not take seriously, as the Acting Prime Minister of
                    Cambodia does, the threat that they will march against Cambodia. Nevertheless,
                    the Cambodians think this is a crisis and that is what they have to deal with
                    and what we have to deal with. They have taken, however, a pretty high attitude
                    toward the Preah Vihear issue. That, of course, involves religious emotions.
                    This is an ancient Buddhist temple which has been a Mecca for people in that
                    general neighborhood for a long, long time and it’s right on the current
                    boundary, the boundary set by the French in 1904 or 1907, I forget which. In the
                    case of the Preah Vihear, they are now building a road to it which didn’t exist
                    before. This is a very primitive area, with just paths into it. They are taking
                    steps to show that they intend to hang on to it, even though it’s a small
                    enclave actually within what the Cambodians claim to be their territory.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: You mean the Thais?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: The Thais are building the road. The Thais have possession. In
                    quiescent times, both the Thais and Cambodians use it. They have free access to
                    it and there is no problem.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I suppose nobody believes that SEATO or the United States or anyone
                    else would permit Thailand to move against Cambodia with force. Isn’t that true,
                    Mr. Parsons?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: We try awfully hard to prevent it, and I think we have lots of help
                    in that from the British, French, Australians and other countries in that
                    area.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I was wondering, in reading the documents, if perhaps the attitude
                    of the United States Government that was held or expressed at the time toward
                    the Thais ambitions being an important factor for not wanting the publication of
                    this volume.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: No, I would say that is a subsidiary, a very subsidiary factor. That
                    is 17 or 18 years back now. Other things being equal, I would like to get this
                    volume out. I think we could accept anything of that kind after that passage of
                    time. And I also regard the effect on the individuals as a less important matter
                    too, and one which even though these two individuals might come back in a more
                    prominent role, I regard that as a lessening factor as we go along. But it’s the
                    problem of the relationships in the area and the interaction of that on the
                    major problems of the Far East that concern me.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Does any other member of the committee have anything to say at the
                    moment? [None]</p>
                <p>I’d like to relate this problem, Mr. Parsons, to the one which also includes
                    China. In the case of the China volume we have had publication which was very
                    damaging.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: I have heard my predecessor, Mr. Robertson, discuss that.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: So have we.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you think it can be maintained that our relations with
                    Nationalist China have been fundamentally made for the worse by the publication
                    of the White Paper?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: I think it’s something which the Generalissimo and many of the
                    people and Taiwan have never really gotten over. They have partially gotten over
                    it, but they have never completely gotten over it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: They had to get over it.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: They have to live with it.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: But I think there is a residue of distrust and disquiet that we
                    might do another zig or another zag at any moment which would take the props out
                    from under them.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you think in a concrete way it has adversely affected the regime
                    of Chiang Kai-shek?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: Yes. I have always understood so.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Was there any comparable reaction, or any reaction, when the 1942
                    volume was released dealing with China?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: I’m afraid we have to get someone else here from the China office. I
                    can’t answer that right away.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We are inclined to think some damage was done with reference to
                    the White Paper and the publication of this whole series of 15 volumes would
                    just plow the same field.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Or rub more salt in the wound.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: This is the point, and I suppose we might as well come right to
                    it. The 1941 volume with the Thai material, while it doesn’t represent things
                    that are altogether novel, at least doesn’t tie into a publication like the
                    White Paper. We, therefore, feel much more strongly about the China ’43
                    publication. We feel that this definitely ought to move ahead. It, of course,
                    like the ’41 one is already printed, but the basic point here is that we feel
                    that the China White Paper, having been published, this series can go ahead
                    without raising these new questions. Now, along with our basic belief that the
                    historical record ought to be published, we have this further feeling with
                    reference to this particular series. While it is true, of course, that this ’43
                    China volume does contain a great deal of criticism of Chiang Kai-shek, there is
                    also some criticism of the Chinese Communists and I think of all the things we
                    looked at at this time—that is the American Republics material—the material on
                    the war-time conferences, Cairo, Tehran, Potsdam, the Thai material and the
                    China material, we felt most strongly about the publication of the China ’43
                    volume. We deplore very much it being held up. We recognize a decision is here
                    being made that we will have reference to these other 13 China volumes too,
                    several of which are ready, as I understand it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: But our recommendation at the moment is based on the reading of
                    these documents.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes. Last year this committee took a stand, and I was not a
                    member of the committee, but one in which I would certainly concur. But now we
                    follow this up by reading these documents and feel publication should
                    proceed.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: It is also clear that these volumes contain references to Chiang
                    Kai-shek with criticism but also to the Chinese Communists.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I believe we have been told that as you get along in later years
                    the documents become even more favorable to Chiang Kai-shek and particularly
                    more critical of the Chinese Communists. As I recall, the whole project was
                    initiated as sort of a reaction to the White Paper, with the belief if the whole
                    story was told it would put the Communists in a less favorable light.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: Well, I’m not too familiar with the project as a whole and the
                    elements that went into the decision to go ahead and work up this series, but
                    just speaking off the cuff, I could see an advantage of publishing all at the
                    same time, rather than publishing the one which might appear to the Government
                    of the Republic of China as sort of a sequel to the White Paper and perhaps an
                    indication of changing attitudes here.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think this is a very special problem because, let’s be frank
                    here, the publication of the White Paper on China had extraordinary motivations
                    and pressures on it and I think it was a mistake and I think practically
                    everybody in the Department today would admit that, quite apart from partisan
                    feelings on it. Because it has somewhat compromised the series. I don’t mean
                    this in too bad a way, Bernard, but it has cast a certain light on it. I have
                    been thinking along the same lines as Jeff has. The decision we made was to hold
                    up the publication. We didn’t say to stop them. I think the best thing we can do
                    is to put the whole series out at once when the thing comes into perspective. I
                    think that is the answer to the China series.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: When you say “most series”, what do you mean?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, bringing them down to the post-war period, ’49 perhaps.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: How many volumes will there be?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Fifteen.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: There will be a mass of volumes at the same time.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That will certainly confuse the newsmen.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Do you have them all in galley? Do you have the first 12 in
                    galley?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The last three.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: The last three, but all the rest are going in galley. They are
                    all in galley through ’48 and we have clearance from the Chinese Government
                    through 1945. As you will recall, this spring just sort of out of the blue, when
                    we asked for a clearance on some documents in the 1942 Volume I, when the reply
                    came back there also came back a clearance on a volume for 1945 on the China
                    series, which we had been trying to get a reply on for years and all of a sudden
                    out of the blue we get the clearance on the ’45 volume.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I wish you would restate that statement. You say you have had
                    clearance for what volumes?</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: From the Chinese Government we have submitted documents to them
                    and of those submitted to them we have clearance through ’45 now.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The ’44 volume is waiting Department clearance.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, do you mean that the Chinese Government does not object to
                    our 1943 volume?</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: Not their documents. It’s not their documents which we
                    submitted to them. The Chinese documents in all the volumes up through 1945 have
                    now been cleared by the Chinese Government.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: That doesn’t mean they approve the publication of the volume.</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: There is one point I’d like to make. The great objection, I
                    think, to the White Paper was not the publication of the documents. It was put
                    out as an instrument of policy at the time with a statement which was made by
                    the Secretary of State saying that this showed that the United States was not at
                    fault and the Chinese Nationalist Government was. That is far different from the
                    publication in proper time of the official documentary record issued not as a
                    national policy.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You say policy or politics?</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: Policy.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The rent for the storage of volumes while waiting for the last volume
                    would be more than the Department could bear.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We are considering billing this to FE.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Otherwise it’s an excellent suggestion.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is an unusual case in which I think perhaps our Foreign
                    Service and our Government matured in this whole process of dealing with the
                    situation. It was rather taken in, I think, in the first stages of this thing,
                    both people and generally, I think.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t know that we can do much more than reiterate the view which
                    was expressed in the committee: We are deeply concerned about delays in the
                    publication of these volumes, of course, and we certainly don’t want to see a
                    greater lag and we would like to see them published in order. What has troubled
                    us is that so many of these facts are known. This makes it difficult for us to
                    believe. But the effect of reiteration of the facts that are already known would
                    be very serious. This comes up again and again. That is our point of view. We
                    understand yours and we want you to understand ours. Without being at all
                    dogmatic about it and while recognizing the publication wouldn’t have a more
                    generalized effect on our relations with the Government on Formosa, I mean that
                    would be the point of view. Are we speaking correctly? But that would be the
                    point of view I would personally take. We have an alliance with the Government
                    on Formosa. It is a better government than it has ever been probably from some
                    points of view, and here we are.</p>
                <p>Now, if in the meantime we can only do in our capacity expressing ourselves on
                    the problem, the responsibility of course lies in the Department. We have to
                    bear the responsibility for this.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We have publicly announced we are going to postpone the
                    publication of the China series.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We have what?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We have announced publicly that we are going to postpone the
                    publication of the China series.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: What was the exact nature of the announcement? Did it say you
                    were going to postpone indefinitely or postpone this particular volume, or
                    what?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: No, this China series that we agreed on here last year, I
                    think.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course your suggestion in regard to the publication of all the
                    volumes at once would require some special financing, wouldn’t it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, I think that if we continue to get the appropriations as we have
                    been getting them for the publication, I think we could handle that alright.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The storage vaults?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What would be your position, Mr. Parsons, if we did handle the
                    publication of the volumes of ’43 to ’49? Would that make it easier from your
                    point of view in solving the problem?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: That is my off-hand opinion. I wouldn’t like to be committed to this
                    in a final way without studying it and talking to the people in our bureau who
                    are pretty knowledgeable on that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think, Mr. Chairman, with that opinion of Mr. Parsons, we might be
                    encouraged to go ahead and prepare them for publication in the hope that it
                    might be possible to release them, all 14.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: What can you suggest as the possible timing—a couple of years or
                    more than that? I assume it would take at least a couple of years.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think possibly three. What do you think, Mr. Nueremberger?</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: Well, they are all in galleys. We don’t know what clearances we
                    have with other foreign governments. I think we have some with the British.</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: You people in FE would have a tremendous mass of papers to go
                    through for clearance. I think we would be haggling over clearance for a long
                    time.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This gives the thing some perspective. That is my argument.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: That is one very strong argument in favor of it. Of course from that
                    point of view it would be our hope that we could carry the thing into the
                    post-Korean War operation, say 1950-51, but I gather this project just goes
                    through the ’41 year.</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: It goes through the over-throw of the government on the
                    Mainland of China.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: After that the intention is to put it back in the regular annual
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: You proposed last year that the volume would be brought out
                    currently as each year we go along year-by-year.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: In this connection, while I think I am individually involved in
                    getting this particular volume out, what I wanted to ask Bernard is if we should
                    come to this sort of an arrangement: all right, we are going to make a big mass
                    effort to get ’43 to ’49 out because by doing them we can get ’43. What’s going
                    to happen to your war-time conferences, what’s going to happen to your others?
                    Would this delay things that are now in process or about to be published if you
                    had to put all of your staff on to this?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, I think Ralph Perkins’ staff could handle the China volumes and
                    the war-time conferences by a rather unusual arrangement which would be
                    necessary by the exigencies of the case which are being handled by Dick
                    Dougall’s branch.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL:: The place where we would have scheduling problems would be where
                    the GPO and priorities would have to be assigned.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: War-time publications are pretty well in hand, aren’t they?</p>
                <p>MR. E. R. PERKINS: It’s not an automatic compilation at all. We would detail
                    anybody to work on it. It would entirely be throwing this massive program on
                    priority onto our technical editors. It will affect editing and indexing and all
                    that kind of work that would have to be given priority. The work is entirely, as
                    I said, compiled, so there is nothing we would have to do about it except just
                    as certain pressures came up we would set researchers to work on it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The committee did take the position last year, as I remember it,
                    that the committee didn’t like this shooting out here and shooting out there,
                    that we wanted to keep the progress pretty uniform and this would come back to
                    Bill Franklin’s point if things are published in regular order they attract less
                    attention. And I just wanted to be sure that if we did go down this line it
                    wouldn’t sacrifice something else that would come out in the normal order.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: If this is at all possible to get these out en masse, wouldn’t it
                    then be possible to get along with a single indexing, which would be put in the
                    last volume?</p>
                <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I assume it would be a volume in itself. It would come out a
                    long time after the volumes, are published.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I suppose it’s not very practical.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The practical problem would be a problem of clearance, wouldn’t
                    it?</p>
                <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: As far as our shop goes, it will be a clearance problem and
                    that would throw a big burden on FE of course for the clearance of all this
                    material.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Hire some people to do the reading.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This is a purely technical question. I guess Bernard is the one to
                    answer it. I notice in this statement here on status that Volume V, volume 1941
                    and the 1943 China volume are labelled “awaiting release”, and others are
                    “awaiting clearance.” What is that distinction?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, “waiting release” means that the volume is in bound form but
                    waiting clearance.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Then there was clearance already obtained?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Clearance obtained in galley.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I see.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Let’s not be unfair to them. I think there were circumstances that
                    arose. I was present when some of this hold-up took place, that arose just
                    before publication. This last review that was made arose just before
                    publication.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This last stage after the volume is assembled, then you have to get
                    a final release.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: And certain political factors arose which made it wise to
                    reconsider this and it was thought advisable by the Secretary to hold this
                    up.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is only in the past five years that we have had this problem of
                    releasing. But, according to the change in political circumstances the national
                    position was such, especially where the timing of the release has become
                    important, and a second look was taken at that time.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is a general problem I would like to discuss with you at a
                    later session, this whole question.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is there anything more to be said on this subject, or any decision
                    to be formulated? I think we understand Mr. Parsons’ point of view. I think we
                    are well aware of that, and our own. This proposal for publication of the thing
                    en masse is a proper subject for further consideration by the committee, I
                    suppose. And then your general attitude would be sympathetic.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: This is my off-the-cuff attitude, and I would like to be sympathetic
                    but I don’t want to be committed to it until I have looked into it and talked
                    with the people whose advice I ought to consider.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We won’t hold you to it until we get it in writing. On both cases,
                    I wish you would give thought to this device of getting this volume out, the ’41
                    Thailand volume, in the manner in which I suggest, if you think it has merit;
                    and also on the China series we would like to hear from FE on that.</p>
                <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I’m a little inclined to give my off-hand opinion, that
                    throwing all these volumes out as one big hunk would cause more reaction, much
                    more reaction, than it would if volumes come out one after another
                    gradually.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They will have to do a lot of reading first.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, the Congressional backers who first started this project are
                    of course gone, but they can return and we have always had a certain reluctance
                    in the Department of going against the wishes and intent of Congress even though
                    it was expressed back as far as ’53.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: We had a regular program. We could face both sides of the House
                    always with a clear conscience. As soon as we push here, hold here, of course we
                    are extremely vulnerable. I would say we would be defenseless.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Have you anything else you want to say on this, Mr. Parsons?</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: Well, thank you, sir. I haven’t really discussed this other volume,
                    but I think you know my attitude and it is probably no use going over a lot of
                    ground which has been gone over with you before.</p>
                <p>With regard to the China volume, I will say just this—and I hope it won’t sound
                    controversial because it’s just one of the factors that we have considered and a
                    factor which we have had to consider this year in going over the ’43 volume
                    again—the question is that of Tibet. The volume, for instance, reveals that
                    without the permission of the Chinese Government we sent an OSS mission in 1943,
                    and whereas the British gave us clearance for the British documents on Tibet in
                    this particular series, we might well have to re-clear with them because in the
                    context of the Chinese Communist suppression of Tibet this year the British have
                    several times made statements in regard to having always recognized that Tibet
                    was an autonomous region under the suzerainty of China.</p>
                <p>Their traditional position has been with the Chinese that they would recognize
                    the suzerainty of China if China, for its part, would regard Tibet as autonomous
                    and deal with it as autonomous. And in this volume they take positions which
                    indicate—I don’t think there is any direct statement to that effect—clearly
                    that beginning about 1912 they are regarded as a de facto independent country.
                    So the British have shown up as being somewhat inconsistent in this volume,
                    because what they have said now doesn’t correspond to what they said has always
                    been their position before. I don’t want to underline that, but Tibet is a hot
                    issue right now and many important things hang on the Tibetan issue, in fact
                    what is going to happen In India, etc. That is the only new factor in this
                    particular picture.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you very much, sir.</p>
                <p>MR. PARSONS: That is all. I’d just like to say it has been a pleasure to be with
                    you gentlemen, and even though I appeared in the role of Peck’s bad boy, and I
                    certainly wish you well in work which I have a full appreciation of the
                    importance of this, I can assure you.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you very much, sir. Is there any question you want to bring
                    up now, Mr. Noble?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: [Off the record]</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We will recess for lunch and reconvene at 1:30 this afternoon.</p>
                <p>[Whereupon the committee recessed at 12:05 p.m. to reconvene at 1:30 in the
                    afternoon.]</p>
                <p>[The meeting was reconvened at 2:15 p.m., Mr. Dexter Perkins, presiding.]</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What we did was discuss the question of personnel and the budgetary
                    question.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I would be glad to make some remarks on that subject. We were
                    discussing this outside. It is clear that as things are there is a tendency to
                    slip farther behind with the compilation of editing. The reasons are partly
                    clearance difficulties and partly in the nature of documents. The tremendous
                    growth of the so-called lots which are unindexed and have to be surveyed before
                    the compilation be regarded as complete complicated the problem very greatly,
                    and it is clear that to hope to keep up at our present level—keep up with the
                    present lag as it were, we would need three additional persons on this
                    staff.</p>
                <p>It is hard to make an exact estimate but our people feel sure they would be
                    required in the next year or two and of course there are some implications I
                    suppose for the publications side too but for the editing side I think we would
                    have to say we need three to give us any hope of our holding our own so to
                    speak, and we would want to bring them in at a nine level or an eleven level,
                    depending on their qualifications. That would mean approximately $18,000.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What can we do about that? What would you like this Committee to
                    do? Would you wish us to say in our report that we thought an increase in the
                    number of persons in the Department—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Say you have explored the problem in its various phases and noticed
                    the tendency for the gap to widen and say you find it is a basic problem of
                    staff.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We went at the problem in our discussion before you came in. We
                    thought it was fair to say the volume is going to be enormous and we thought it
                    would be worthwhile if at our next meeting we discussed the question. Even with
                    more staff you have a problem?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: A serious problem?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If we get down to the period of activity—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is hard to believe, and you can check on that, that we can expect
                    to get clearance on anything like an across-the-board basis under 19 or 20
                    years.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This was the major topic I wanted to talk about. I think a
                    recommendation from this Committee on this period of what is an acceptable
                    interim after these documents—I mentioned this at the Secretary’s staff meeting
                    Thursday, that you would come in and talk about this. This is an occasion to get
                    all the assistant secretaries together with top level authority behind them
                    because the Secretary and the Under Secretary are always there and I tried to
                    encourage them to be here today to discuss these with some good results but they
                    got into the discussion of length of time and I think this is worth passing on,
                    they wanted to know what the best period had been because if there was a time
                    when it was one year—I didn’t go into all the history of it but I mentioned the
                    12- or 15-year period up to 30.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Many people thought there was a 15-year gap. I would fix that as the
                    appropriate lag but no period had been set as a matter of policy.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: When you met with the congressional committees in 1953, did they
                    express a preference for a certain period of time?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They simply requested in their resolution that the gap be wiped out.
                    They didn’t indicate there should be any period, but—</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: It should be brought up to currency.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The feeling was among the top officers that we need to look at
                    this because of the many ramifications of our interests now and where we get so
                    closely involved, as was beautifully manifested in the Southeast Asian situation
                    this morning—we are involved in that—and we were not before, and you could
                    write this history of relations, but we are involved very much and the feeling
                    was—Mr. Reinhardt thought of a 20-year lapse as being desirable and I said I
                    thought we would have to settle for about 20.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you think we could?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think so and then try to settle on a schedule.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We are not far from that now if you get the China group.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Can we hold it at 20?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: That is the question.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We will have a stronger position if the Committee feels it would
                    like to make a recommendation and tie the 20-year period in with a regular
                    schedule of publications and then we can get away from this thing that was
                    bothering us this morning.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Do you mean a publication of all volumes and not simultaneously
                    perhaps?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I can make a strong argument that I think would be convincing if
                    we have a regular publication—sequence—that we abolish the business of looking
                    at it for final review. It would really have to be extraordinarily dangerous to
                    national security to stop it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you think an agreement of that kind would stick?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: If we get top level support which we have never had.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: You would not like to have the 20 accepted and not get the rest
                    of it?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Maybe I am on your side on this but I think the two should be
                    linked because the other problem is a Public Affairs Bureau problem. I think we
                    should tie the two. They would be pleased with the 20-year period because they
                    have always felt getting under that—the top people would—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Not Latin America. If we do the 20, and we are almost there, but we
                    would be doing it so you would not be constantly blocked by certain of the
                    areas,</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: I would be extremely skeptical.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: How is the Ecuador border and the Thai situation going to be any
                    different? Can they do it for 30 years?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: They would have to make a strong case to the Secretary to get the
                    exception.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Do you think the release question would not then arise?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I don’t think so.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This is a most important suggestion because we haven’t considered
                    it. It has not been presented to us. We talked about the same idea but how do we
                    all feel about that? Are you saying you think it would be useful if we adopted
                    this position?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: It would be useful to us because to me there are two problems
                    involved. One is the Historical Division problem of clearances and regular
                    publication, which puts us in better relations with the community academically
                    and we establish an expectation of regular volumes at certain times and it makes
                    better sense.</p>
                <p>The other is the Public Affairs problem as a whole of dealing with these things
                    when pulled out of sequence and a special significance is attached to them
                    because they are out of sequence and, therefore, from my point of view—the
                    Bureau’s point of view—which is broader than Bernard’s, there are two problems
                    I would like to lick with one big stone.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Let’s have an expression of opinion on this.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: If we adopted this I think we ought to make it clear something like
                    a 20-year period is a maximum period.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think so.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Not less than 20 years.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: I doubt if there is a great deal of difference in the 20-year
                    or 30-year lag.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Twenty is a good round number and something we can settle for.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We can’t go back to 15. It is too late.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This is an idea we were discussing among ourselves before and there
                    is a story with it. The only new element is the 20-year period.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: And the suggestion is something here could be sold.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would be quite willing to buy the package.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: If you start out about the regularizing of a publication, that is
                    what we want. If we get it we will tie the twenty years to it.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: If there is any probability we could help the Bureau by coming up
                    with a recommendation of this kind, it would be a good thing to do.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: With the top people a 20-year period would be acceptable.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you think if we had a 20-year period would the question of
                    deadline be minimized?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think so because it would become a Department directive and we
                    could see that it is done in that way by people under extraordinary
                    circumstances—that would be the publication date—and that moves every Bureau
                    up against the deadline in a way not done in the past.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I didn’t know there was a deadline.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This question of clearance is very annoying. If that is true you
                    made a strong point for your case. This would minimize the problem of
                    clearance.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: It would put them under deadlines which they have never had. We
                    have tried to set deadlines but they have been wishy-washy.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You imply this would be a Departmental decision and not for us and the
                    Advisory Committee?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That’s right. If we can get support in general we would try to get
                    a Departmental directive that lays it on the line for every Bureau.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is an important decision because the Department never had a
                    decision of that sort and it is a question whether you want to change the
                    presumption from the one that says we will get it out as soon as possible—as
                    soon as we can get clearance, but on the idea of regularizing it, it could be
                    based on the slowest volume. That is the problem we are up against there.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If we publish regularly every rear and get into a jam like the
                    China volume, everything would be held up but on questions of that kind if you
                    think that will arise, that is an important situation.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Would you welcome a resolution from us to this effect?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This could be accompanied by a number of actions on our part; for
                    example, this would become so vast—this regular publication—every twenty
                    years—it would be incumbent on the Bureau of Public Affairs to announce why
                    Volume X is not appearing and it puts the burden on us to say we have done
                    this— We will not go into our reasons but say for reasons of policy it is being
                    withheld.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If we do this what happens to the organs you regularly publish?
                    This is an extra case, isn’t it?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You still go on publishing Teheran, etc.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We have to make an exception because of the commitments already
                    made.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think the problem of selection is going to be a massive one and
                    that we thought would be a proper question to discuss next year. The members of
                    the division have devoted a good deal of attention on how to meet the volume
                    accurately and satisfactorily and what they have to eliminate. The problem will
                    become more difficult and not less as time goes on. I mean elimination for
                    reasons of space.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: By the nature of your appointment, you have the right to report to
                    the Secretary and make recommendations and that is why it would be helpful to us
                    but I would like to see the day arrive when the publication of a foreign
                    relations line does not stir a newsman’s blood any more than his income tax.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Accompanied by different emotions.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: When you were on the Hill with regard to the special series was the
                    question raised as to the normal publication procedure?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The question has been raised as to the period but we denied there was
                    a fixed period.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: When this matter was up before the Senate the individual Senators
                    didn’t care one way or another.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They didn’t have hearings with us on that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You will give us a statement on that.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: The attitude was we were always too far behind.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: To be frank, I think very strongly this is a decision—as to when
                    we publish these—an Executive Branch decision and if we announce it publicly we
                    will keep Congress’s hand out of our business.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Will it weaken the case if we attach a vote this 20-year period
                    might be shortened as soon as possible?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Don’t stir up the animals. I wouldn’t put it too strongly because
                    they would feel they were being pushed.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think we might make it clear that this was a bit of a concession
                    on our part that we are willing to make only because we believe it will result
                    in regularity of publication, etc.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think this is very useful to us and it seems as far as we have
                    all spoken that we are all of the same opinion.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: With the quid pro quo.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: Is that the maximum? We already have clearance on 1942 Volume
                    I and almost clearance on 1942 Volume II. We haven’t had serious trouble getting
                    them cleared. Will we stick those away for 1962.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I would think this would be the maximum but under the maximum you
                    should try to schedule—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: There will be a transition stage.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: That is why I raised the question.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You are now saying necessarily we wait to publish the volumes
                    simultaneously. You say the maximum period should be set and this decision would
                    be made at the Secretarial level that this would be accomplished.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That is my feeling. They are concerned. There is a push on to get
                    it under that and this would be acceptable to them.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That would be so much in advance of any other—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It must be borne in mind with the maximum twenty years there will be
                    criticism from some sources. There are certain individuals who have made some
                    criticism that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes twenty years
                    back are no longer any good—almost in those words—so in a mood of this sort we
                    would have to have the firm backing of this Committee to make clear that this
                    really has sound reasoning behind it.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: That is why it is important to attach to our recommendation, or
                    acceptance, a conviction the record be reasonably complete because you are
                    engaged in balancing advantages and disadvantages. To make the period long is a
                    disadvantage from the scholar’s point of view but to make it so short the record
                    is incomplete is another disadvantage. It seems to me the way you have the
                    current volumes coming out, the disadvantage of length is somewhat reduced.</p>
                <p>For those reasons I would be willing to accept the 20-year period if it assured
                    regularity and a more liberal clearance policy.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: There is likely to be some criticism and I believe in our own
                    profession—I believe there is a 15-year lag in policy.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: We assume some responsibility to defend this.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The historians are more willing to accept this than ten years
                    ago.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t think much of the criticism. There is criticism and this is
                    the result of ignorance more than anything else and you can’t avoid it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Leland’s point about the usefulness of the current documents should
                    be stressed because this does help a great deal.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: Those current documents are reprints. I can add anything at
                    all to the record. It is easier for you professors to do it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Some of the documents I reviewed yesterday were published in the
                    State Department <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: It isn’t the green series called <hi rend="italic">Foreign Service
                        Documents</hi> but a large number of documents appearing have been released
                    through the State Department <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> and we pull them
                    together. It isn’t the green series itself.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The average Congressman and Senator feel <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> should be out in a few years. You will not find one in a
                    hundred who would feel it would be reasonable to delay twenty years. Any new
                    statement of this sort will have to be explained.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think you can explain it on physical grounds. We are where we
                    are. You are not likely to be able to bridge it under any program. When we say
                    20 years you are asking a good deal considering the amount of documents coming
                    here.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think we should say we were discussing the problem of staffing, and
                    I have been discussing this with the boys outside, and we decided in order to
                    keep current on the present lag that we need approximately three more
                    individuals on the staff because of the tremendous problem arising out of the
                    enormous number of lots that are not indexed, etc. Just to keep current on the
                    mass of material it would require some increase in staff.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: As an outsider dealing with documents in another Department, I
                    wonder if you are not being too modest.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think that is right.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: You mentioned a point last night about the condition in which the
                    material is and that will involve a tremendous amount of work.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It seems to me this has been most helpful. Is there anything we
                    want to bring out that we haven’t discussed?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is the major problem. The thing bothering me is you can’t get
                    hold of it. There is no fixed past or present policy. The Secretary’s office
                    called to say: “What is this about 12 or 15 years?” They didn’t know where it
                    originated. I gave him your papers in which you had given us the whole
                    background of this.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: On the question of personnel, do you want an opinion from the
                    Committee?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That would be very helpful, Mr. Chairman.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We don’t know the problem in detail.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think you have looked into it enough to know there is that problem
                    because you raised the question. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: If I may interject. I think it is perfectly legal but it is
                    logical you should recommend an increase in staff—if it goes to Mr. Berding—
                    It is our problem to see that Barney has the staff he needs. If it goes to the
                    Secretary we catch h--- because we are not doing our job. I ask that you divide
                    these issues and we are perfectly happy to entertain support from you and we go
                    to the Budget Bureau and say they think they should have more staff and we do
                    too.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The question again— As you are aware, we make two reports, a small
                    public report which we hope the journals will publish, and a confidential
                    report. Would a statement on personnel be out of order or in order in the
                    reports?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think it would be out of order in either of your reports
                    assuming they would be to the Secretary. What you want to do is impress Berding
                    and, through us, the administrative people.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It would not be effective. That is not the way to do it. The place
                    to make an impact is address ourselves to somebody and not the general
                    public.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You might send a copy to Mr. Henderson. He can do something about
                    it.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: You spoke about a report to the Secretary. Our report has been to
                    the Historical Division.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You are appointed by the Secretary.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Were you thinking of going beyond that?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: For this meeting we have a third document which is a communication
                    to Mr. Berding and yourself.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I don’t know why it should not be forwarded to the Secretary.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: A confidential report should be addressed to the Secretary.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I think it would be a good idea.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Transmitted of course through you.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: As I understand it we ought to have, in addition to our public and
                    confidential report, a memo of some sort to Mr. Berding on the personnel matter
                    not included in the confidential report. Is that it?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes, that is an administrative matter on which your support is
                    useful.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t see how we can draw up a memo on a matter of such broad
                    terms. You can express the general principle.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We can make it plural.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: In your report to the Secretary you might wish to say we also
                    addressed a memo on staff and personnel to Mr. Berding. That would be all
                    right.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That goes to whom?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: To Mr. Berding.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, is there anything more you want to talk about then? You will
                    of course get a draft of our report.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There are several things I would like to talk about.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: One thing we wanted to raise was your suggestion about looking
                    ahead and planning the future publication program. That was suggested as a
                    possible topic for discussion at our next meeting. Wasn’t that your
                    suggestion?</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: Yes, we are impressed with the fact when you get into the 1940
                    you not only would be doubling but quadrupling the number of diplomatic
                    documents and having the complication of more stuff, so that obviously in the
                    next few years your Division will have to face the problem of handling many
                    times the number of documents you have had in the past.</p>
                <p>This is something we would like to know about and know your approach and
                    ultimately we will have to give our opinions on. How do you handle this much
                    larger volume of material? Do you turn out 20 or 30 books instead of 50 or cut
                    down on the number of books and perhaps do something like microfilm or
                    microcard. We would like to have your long-range thinking on this as a
                    preliminary for discussion next time.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: In other words, at next year’s meeting, at the morning session of
                    the first day, instead of having members of the Committee digest the volumes we
                    have done for two years, we would like, I think, to start in with a report from
                    you on the long-range program and then we would, in light of that and the study
                    of this thing we did not get around to this year, have discussion the first
                    morning on the principles of selection, etc., but we would like to have a report
                    from you people first.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We would like to have something ahead of time.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Would you like a report before you address yourself to this
                    question?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes and that should be the order of business for the first
                    morning.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: [Inaudible remarks]</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We cannot deal with either of those alone.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That was one question I wanted to raise about the question of
                    principles and procedures because we want a discussion that really goes to the
                    roots of the whole problem.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You thought the reading of the document was very important.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: On this meeting I would like your criticisms and observations and
                    comments right now if you could individually on the meeting. Could you do that
                    briefly?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What is that?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The way the meeting has gone.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think I would begin by summing up what we talked about. We
                    thought we did not value too highly the individual volumes, the principles
                    covering the Department, and the general plan for the future. We all thought the
                    examination of such volumes in the afternoon was very preferable. That procedure
                    should be continued. It has value. It is valuable to have the Desk Officer’s
                    comments on the problems.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: The morning program this morning was also very valuable.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Reading the documents gave us a basis for the comments we make. It
                    isn’t a matter of principle only.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: If I may comment, I was a little disturbed this morning. This
                    verges on being a hearing before a congressional committee in the minds of the
                    political officers. This is not an investigating committee.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I felt that too.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That is precisely the reason I raised and discussed it at the
                    Secretary’s meeting. I said that it wasn’t an investigation or hearing but an
                    attempt to work with an outside group which is on our side and they have their
                    own interests but we are working together on a common problem. They were
                    defending themselves. They have gotten into that habit.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: In some respects we put them in that position by saying: “We
                    don’t agree with you.”</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is a delicate question but I hope in the future we can have a
                    different atmosphere.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: How can we do that?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This question is really of educating the officers in the
                    Department that this is not an investigating group but a cooperative group.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: My own feeling, if I may be frank about that, is we got down to cases
                    more successfully on the two China and Far Eastern volumes than on the others. I
                    would like to see more discussion of particular problems. We did of course get
                    on two or three that were very good but I don’t think it was too helpful, if I
                    may be frank, just to say we disagree on these things or agree on those because
                    if that procedure had been followed they would not have been able to react at
                    all on the Latin American problems, and so I hope that we can, in following this
                    procedure, isolate particular problems, and the large issue of the Peru-Ecuador
                    boundary—the discussion on that was good, but on the others it wasn’t as good
                    as it could be.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: It was a question of time.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Perhaps we should do it in the way of raising questions merely.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: If, for example, you could give us a considerable number of these
                    selections to read and indicate a few you thought deserved special discussion,
                    that would be helpful.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: If we could center the discussion on six to ten instead of a
                    wider range, we would be better off.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: So many seem trivial.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: If I may raise a few questions that I have written down. About your
                    reports, will you consider how you can best handle this with your respective
                    associations?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: With regard to the next meeting, is it agreeable to all of you?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The first Friday and Saturday in November.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: What about the presidential election schedule?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I hope it won’t interfere.</p>
                <p>Are you making any comments in your report on this question of the list of papers
                    that we discussed with and without a final conclusion and the list of names? I
                    would like to get some of these things cleaned up. I don’t think they are at
                    present. Did I have an answer on that?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Not on the list of papers.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I thought we finally decided we would leave the list of names to
                    your discretion.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Or continue for awhile with the present practice.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You want the index as it is?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: If you want me to say anything in your report about this, please say
                    so. I intended to say in the opening remarks, but did not, that something came
                    up in your report about the names of the signing officers. You said the
                    appropriate political officer, his name should be given. The appropriate
                    political officer could be the name of the person signing the Secretary’s name
                    and putting his initials under it.</p>
                <p>We all agree there is no question about drafters. We don’t include those names.
                    The clearing officers—that would be impossible obviously, but do you mean to
                    imply the person whose initials are signed under the Secretary’s should take
                    responsibility for the document because in most cases the Secretary doesn’t see
                    it—that these initials should be filled out.</p>
                <p>There is a difference in practice. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes haven’t put in those full names of signing officers.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I think it is, at least to my mind, a matter of not attaching
                    signatures or responsibility through signatures to the underlings rather than
                    seeing these must be signed so that the responsibility is not attached to the
                    lower echelon drafter, etc., but the appropriate political officer assumes
                    responsibility and I personally would not feel that it is necessary to go beyond
                    what you are now doing in attaching initials.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Do you mean to say if the initials are given below the name of the
                    Secretary, the initials should be filled out?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: No. That is my personal reaction. I don’t think I would say the
                    signatures should be added. I don’t think we said that. We felt in certain
                    respects you were going too far in this.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would be inclined to follow the existing practice.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: In a few cases, and it happened occasionally, signatures were given
                    which would seem to mean attaching responsibility. It looked as though the
                    higher political officers were trying to throw the responsibility on others on
                    some of these sensitive matters—people asked to draft papers, etc.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No-one in the Department is trying to throw anything anywhere.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: It gave the impression.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: There were one or two cases where you brought in the Hiss case.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There are several questions. One involves higher levels, those higher
                    levels where the Secretary’s name or initials are on outgoing dispatches and
                    telegrams. There is only a question then in that case and those are mostly
                    office directors and above. It is a question whether we should fill in the
                    initials, and that arose on the Yalta papers where we had amateur historians on
                    our side who wanted to know who did what of each hour of each day and since some
                    were signed by Hull which Hull never saw, and Stettinius, which Stettinius never
                    say, but top officers in the Department who signed the Secretary’s name and put
                    their initials below. We filled out those initials.</p>
                <p>This is in line with practice in the Department in foreign relations of filling
                    out initials. This does not add a new practice except that previously we did not
                    give either the initials or the spell-out of initials in outgoing telegrams or
                    instructions. There were several of those in the Yalta volumes which we did fill
                    out.</p>
                <p>Secondly, on Yalta, there was a question of filling in some drafters names and in
                    that case we did quite a few of those that we would not have done otherwise
                    because they involved, or centered around Hiss and we couldn’t be made
                    responsible for concealing papers which Hiss drafted but not attaching his name.
                    Drafters names are concealed in other documents and have been for years. Perhaps
                    we could let that go as an exception.</p>
                <p>The other question is: Is it important to indicate the officers who take the
                    responsibility for sending out documents?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: We said the guiding principles should be: [Reading]</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You would not put the initials in?</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: Just the Secretary’s name and not the initials of the
                    person.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I have no views on that. I don’t care if you put initials or
                    not.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: It seems to me that it plays up the person initialing too
                    much. Very often the Secretary lays down a policy. A telegram is drafted in
                    accordance with that policy the Secretary laid down. The Secretary doesn’t do
                    paper work. Somebody else looks it over, a responsible high officer and he puts
                    his initials down. A good many readers would jump to the conclusion the
                    Secretary knew nothing about it if you put it that way.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I am not arguing for initials.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: If the Secretary delegates that power to somebody else he
                    still has the responsibility.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: It seems to me it is a Departmental matter. The usual practice is
                    a meeting and the Secretary says: “Okay, this is what we will do,” and probably
                    the man at the meeting who gets the responsibility, say, the European Secretary,
                    he doesn’t write the telegram but gets a boy in his office to write it and takes
                    the responsibility. If this is in line with what the Secretary does, he
                    authorizes the telegram.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Is it the Assistant Secretary putting his initials on—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We are getting some reaction on this.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: I don’t know that we can react to questions like that. We would
                    not direct you to put the initials on.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I think I raised this question at the first meeting and this seemed
                    to require explanation last year so we adopted an additional item and the whole
                    purpose in my mind was protecting the drafting officer and those people. I don’t
                    care personally whether you attach initials or signatures or anything else. I
                    assume always the Secretary must assume responsibility and it is to prevent that
                    responsibility from being attached to somebody else—</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think you can get this by command decision in the bureau.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I am expressing my personal feeling and not speaking for the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There is a question with regard to the placing of papers. I don’t know
                    whether you want to address yourself to the question of whether you would like
                    to have chronologically within a state or if you think the present method of
                    grouping according to subjects within a state and subjects beyond states in the
                    general area or not. I would like to know if you want to consider any further
                    that question of organization.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: My impression is the general view. We would like to have you
                    continue the present practice and simply make more use of cross references and
                    indexes and such devices to guide the reader.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think that was the general view of the Committee.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: If we were going back, and I think we did not discuss it among
                    ourselves, the question you raised earlier of digest of papers—we did not
                    discuss that this afternoon, and, therefore, presumably we will not fight the
                    digest, or I would say if a digest were added, this would allow you
                    flexibility.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That completes the list.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any other questions to come before the Committee?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I may add a footnote. I think It is perfectly appropriate for the
                    Committee, if it wishes, to say in view of increasing paper documentation for
                    the period after 1942, it is certainly appropriate that the Historical Division
                    be appropriately staffed and increased by the appropriate amount. I think this
                    would be very useful to us.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: There was one suggestion of a technical nature I made that I think
                    everybody on the Committee did agree with, that there should be an expression of
                    the scope of the general heading. I think Mr. Perkins said that that was agreed
                    and that probably would be done. So I don’t think we will follow it up any
                    more.</p>
                <p>MR. RALPH PERKINS: I think it was agreed that general means multilateral. It goes
                    better under a general heading.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: May I make some concluding remarks. I want to express the
                    appreciation of the Department and the Bureau particularly for your help in the
                    last two days. I am very pleased. I think there is better understanding of the
                    functioning of the Committee that has been created in the Department, and I
                    think some of these things moved forward.</p>
                <p>I hope that I will be with you at your next annual meeting. You can never tell. I
                    am coming to the end of my tenure in the Department but as long as I am here I
                    will try to move along the same lines I think you approve of to get these things
                    regularized.</p>
                <p>So far as the Bureau is concerned, if it is a Departmental instruction, they will
                    move along with it, and that has been one of our problems. It has not been a
                    Departmental instruction, and if we can get this into a more normal framework
                    for them, the kind of thing they are used to, it will be a great advantage.</p>
                <p>FROM THE FLOOR: I would like to say that Mr. Kretzmann took a lively interest in
                    this and was most helpful to us and we appreciate that and we certainly
                    appreciate the wonderful help all of you have been. This is the third annual
                    meeting and each one has been better than the previous one as far as I am
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think we might express to Mr. Kretzmann our appreciation for the
                    very fine cooperation he has given and also I would like to add our appreciation
                    of the work that was done by his staff—highly commendable.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
