<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Transcript of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1960</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Transcript, 1960</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-07-10">July 10, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1960-11-04">November 4, 1960</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1960-11-04-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 3.1 MB, 146pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 1, 1960-Min. of Meeting 11/4-5/60.
                    Confidential.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn31">Footnote 31</ref></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="friday-session">
                <head>Transcript of November 4 Session of the 1960 Meeting of the Advisory Committee
                    on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 4, 1960<lb/> 9:08 a.m. to 12:30 p.m.</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p rend="underline">Members of the Committee:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Dexter Perkins, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Dr. Clarence Arthur Berdahl</item>
                    <item>Dr. Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                    <item>Dr. Richard W. Leopold</item>
                    <item>Dr. Philip W. Thayer</item>
                    <item>Mr. Robert R. Wilson</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Representing the Department of State:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Andrew H. Berding, Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>Edwin M. J. Kretzmann, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>G. Bernard Noble, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Frances T. Bourne, RM/S</item>
                    <item>Velma J. Cassidy, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Rogers P. Churchill, P/HO</item>
                    <item>G. M. Richardson Dougall, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Herbert A. Fine, P/HO</item>
                    <item>William M. Franklin, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Ralph R. Goodwin, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Douglas W. Houston, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Gustave A. Nuermberger, P/HO</item>
                    <item>E. Taylor Parks, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Richard I. Phillips, ARA</item>
                    <item>John Gilbert Reid, P/HO</item>
                    <item>William Slany, P/HO</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Almon R. Wright, P/HO</item>
                </list>
                <p>Reported by:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>V. Voce</item>
                    <item>E. Koontz</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a table of contents</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">PROCEEDINGS</hi></p>
                <p>[The meeting was convened at 9:08 a.m., Dr. Dexter Perkins presiding.]</p>
                <p rend="underline">1. Opening Remarks</p>
                <p>MR. BERDING: We want to welcome Dr. Wilson to our committee. We are delighted to
                    have him join the Advisory Committee and I know Dr. Wilson will find any
                    contribution you can make both important to us and interesting to him.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Thank you very much.</p>
                <p>[Applause]</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Gentlemen, I think we might begin our session. I’d like first to
                    introduce the various persons here.</p>
                <p>[Whereupon those in attendance at the meeting were introduced by Mr. Noble.]</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Mr. Berding has officially welcomed you. I’d like to add to that
                    that we appreciate the time you have put in on this. I know how much it means to
                    take time off from other pressing duties of your own.</p>
                <p>I think, in the careful report that Mr. Noble has made on the results of your
                    consultations with us last year, you have reason to be at least 50 percent
                    satisfied. Some of the things he recommended have been done, others have not
                    been done, but he has explained both sides of it to you there. I think the paper
                    that Bernard has prepared on the editorial problems is one that I am
                    particularly interested in hearing you discuss because it raises most of our
                    problems. I trust that you won’t mind, in our discussions with you, if there
                    isn’t a solid front on the part of the Department because we ourselves are torn
                    on some of these issues, principally the one of nearness to publication, on
                    which there are quite some differences or opinion. But I hope that we can again
                    have the kind of a session we had last year, where I thought the exchanges were
                    extremely useful.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There is a bit of housekeeping first. In your folders you have not
                    only the dossier containing some of the things that are useful in our
                    discussions today but also some suggestions or instructions regarding travel. I
                    hope that they will be sufficiently clear so that we won’t have any
                    inconveniences or misunderstandings on anybody’s part and my secretary will be
                    glad to be of whatever service to you she can.</p>
                <p>I should like also to welcome you here to this 4th meeting. I suppose it’s
                    appropriate at this quadrennial period, as in our international life, to have a
                    big round-up and as the committee determined at its close last session we were
                    to have a kind of look-see at our operations more than we had in the previous
                    three meetings. In accordance with this, I sent out that report to the members,
                    which was prepared with the advice and help of the very able staff.</p>
                <p>I call your attention to the items in the dossier here and, first, will you
                    please turn to number 3, which gives on all external appearances at least a very
                    sad look, the falling off look of publication of our volumes. And I will ask
                    Ralph Perkins to say a little bit about that particular item.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Well, as you all know, you have received the one and only volume
                    which we have published this fiscal year, which is the 1942 volume, Volume I.
                    That was foretold by the time we had our meeting a year ago. Unless we can get a
                    volume cleared by this time, it is practically impossible to get it out during
                    the fiscal year. We would have to have high priority to do it. The process of
                    final editing and the indexing of the volume after it’s put into page proof and
                    the other editorial work and printing work that goes on takes more really than
                    half a year. So we have to be cleared by now practically, to get it out.</p>
                <p>I might mention as far as the printing is concerned, of course the Government
                    Printing Office is exceptionally busy during the last part of the fiscal year
                    because of Congressional action, which they give necessarily priority to. The
                    reason we have only one volume out is because of clearance difficulties. We have
                    had volumes in galley before which, if they had been cleared, we could have
                    gotten out. But there is really at present the nub of the problem.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, I think if you look at the next piece in the dossier, Item
                    Number 4, you will see that work here has not been at a stalemate during this
                    period. You will see two date coverages there—October 1, 1959 and October 1,
                    1960.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You’re directing our attention to Item Number 4 in the folder?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. If you go down the line there you will see how they have been in
                    most cases advanced from one stage of preparation to another. In those cases
                    there in the October 1, 1959 columns you notice they have already been released
                    so you see nothing in the October 1, 1960 column. But will you look that over
                    and see whether you have any questions to raise regarding it?</p>
                <p>Volume V, 1941, was awaiting release last year and it’s still awaiting release.
                    You know the history of that, I think.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Volume IV for the Far East has been released?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What area does that cover?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The Far East. There were two volumes on the Far East.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: 1940?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes, 1940-41. This one concerns Thailand particularly. </p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: On Volume V, awaiting release last year, I think there were certain
                    items there we considered last time and made certain recommendations.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You have my report on that.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: And can you say at the present time how many volumes will probably
                    be coming out in the next year?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I’m going to ask Ralph Perkins to report on that when you look down
                    this list.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Isn’t this CIA clearance something new?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is something new, yes.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: It’s new but it’s going to be with us from here on out.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I know. I hadn’t thought I had seen that term before.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: When you have page proof stage, it’s still awaiting clearance.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We get into trouble when you use the word “clearance”. We passed these
                    galleys around for clearance by the policy officers and so far as they are
                    concerned they are cleared for publication. But there is still the question of
                    finding quick release. We sometimes find that a volume has been cleared by
                    policy officers but when it comes up a year later to be released, there are
                    objections as to timing. So that is a problem we run into and will be discussing
                    somewhat here also.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: So the page proof stage is no guarantee of quick release?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It’s certainly a nine-tenths ordinary guarantee, but not wholly. Are
                    there any other questions on this? If not, I will ask Ralph Perkins to say
                    something about the prospects for this fiscal year 1961.</p>
                <p rend="underline">2. Reports on Developments During the Year</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: We have at the present time two volumes which have been cleared
                    and not yet published: 1942, Volume III, Europe, which is in page proof and will
                    come out without any reasonable doubt this fiscal year; and then there is 1940,
                    Volume V, the American Republics, which has recently been sent to the publishing
                    division for final editorial work to send to GPO to put into page proof and we
                    should have that published this fiscal year.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Which one was that?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Volume V, American Republics. The first one was 1942, Volume III,
                    Europe and then 1940, Volume V, American Republics.</p>
                <p>Then we expect to publish on the war-time conferences two volumes on the Potsdam
                    Conference. I believe, Noble, you still have the expectation of getting out the
                    Cairo-Tehran volume.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes, we will say a little more about that book later.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: That will be five volumes that should come out this fiscal year.
                    On the regular annual volumes, I’m taking the position I explained previously,
                    that unless we get clearance by this time we cannot expect to get it out this
                    fiscal year. So I’m listing those which will come out this fiscal year which we
                    have already cleared.</p>
                <p>Just to look ahead a bit, we do have six of the regular annual volumes in
                    clearance process at present. So with any good fortune we should be able to have
                    a better record the next fiscal year. I did not mention, of course, the volumes
                    you know about, 1941, Volume V, Far East and 1943, China, which could be
                    released at any time if the Department decided to release them, you see.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: They could be released, you say?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I say they are ready for release any time the Department decides
                    to release them. So we can not predict just when they will be released.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Next we come to the—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Bernard, excuse me, I take it there has been no discussion at any
                    level of the China series since we met last?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, there has been some discussion. And I want to say something to
                    you about that.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: All right.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Next we come to the committee recommendations with regard to the
                    regular annual volumes and if you will turn to Number 5 in your folder you will
                    note the reference to the recommendations and you will note that your
                    recommendations really had some good influence. So the committee has justified
                    itself very definitely and materially.</p>
                <p>Now, if you will look down the list, you might want to raise some questions. Mr.
                    Nuermberger can identify each one of these items, beginning under “General”, the
                    Inter-American Neutrality Committee—the first recommendation was reconsidered
                    favorably by ARA, our friends from Latin America and that area. If anybody wants
                    to raise a question what that was particularly, okay. Those three items under
                    “General” were reconsidered favorably.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: No, the second one was not.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I’m sorry. The second one was not.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What was that?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: That was a parenthetical remark by Mr. Fenwick to have the Under
                    Secretary remind GPO that the Legal Adviser did not examine his communication
                    sympathetically. The Legal Adviser just didn’t think a parenthetical remark such
                    as that should be printed. It really didn’t contribute anything. It was really
                    in the nature of a personal remark.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Under “Brazil” next.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: I’m sorry, it was a personal remark on what point?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: On not being notified with regard to a certain communication. It
                    didn’t relate to it. All of these will be available to you during your reading
                    period this afternoon in case you want to look at them personally.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: “Brazil, Assistance by the Department to the Government of Brazil in
                    establishing a steel industry.” That is (a). Then (b), “Good Offices of the
                    Department of State in settling the dispute between Brazil and the United
                    Kingdom concerning the detention of the Brazilian vessel SEQUEIRO CAMPOS”,
                    reconsidered favorably.</p>
                <p>“Colombia. a. Cooperation of the United States in the elimination of German
                    influence from Colombian airlines”, reconsidered favorably, and then one of them
                    unfavorably. Would you like to have that identified?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Apparently they are more interested in where they lost than where
                    they won. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: These happen to be references to personalities who were either
                    pro-German or not favoring the Colombian plan.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What is “WST” here?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: West Coast affairs.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Going on to the next one: “Ecuador, Cooperation of the United States
                    in elimination of German influence from Ecuadoran airlines,” considered
                    favorably.</p>
                <p>Mexico, one favorably, one reconsidered unfavorably. You want to identify that
                    one as reconsidered unfavorably, Gus?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: Well, that was with regard to the claim settlement and there was
                    a reference here, “in view of the arrogance and complete disregard of our rights
                    with which the appropriations were carried out,” that particular phrase, they
                    didn’t want to reconsider favorably. However, the point of it is later shown in
                    the next one, “We should insist upon a large measure of justice for the
                    claimant,” and what follows and which is left in really puts the viewpoint
                    across. So we didn’t really lose on not including that.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think the whole process of settlement of the Mexican claims has
                    become much more sensitive in view of the Cuban developments.</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: That is true.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Next is the “Preliminary negotiations for a general settlement of
                    outstanding questions between the United States and Mexico.” The first one was
                    reconsidered unfavorably.</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: That is in the same category.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That covers 1940.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Excuse me, this outstanding question: Does that cover more than
                    claims, Gus, or just claims?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: Entirely claims.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: I see.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I’d like to raise a question about Mr. Kretzmann’s remark. It’s
                    very interesting. I wonder if he will elaborate a little why the question of
                    Mexican claims has become more sensitive in the light of Cuban developments.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: The Mexicans have looked with great favor on the Cuban revolution
                    because they consider it a further repetition of their own and they can’t make
                    any dent on the Mexican Government in connection with this expropriation without
                    compensation, and so on. In view of the record of what we finally settled for on
                    the Mexican claims, this now becomes a little sensitive in connection with Cuba.
                    Dick Phillips has just arrived, who is much more of an expert. We are talking
                    about the certain passages in the Mexican claim settlement that were not changed
                    even though the committee had recommended the change last year. I pointed out
                    that this has become increasingly sensitive because of the Cuban developments.
                    Do you want to elaborate on that?</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: Well, I don’t know. I think everybody here is familiar with the
                    Cuban developments and the sensitivity of same.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: But we did finally settle with Mexico on five cents a dollar or
                    something like that.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: That wasn’t cut out. We got all that in.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I know, but some of these statements have become sensitive because
                    of the current problems with Cuba.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Here’s 1941 to consider. Do you have any questions?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That was reconsidered favorably, the first one. There was a discussion
                    with the Uruguayan and there is a reference here to the Uruguayan saying that
                    this was with regard to the support on the Uruguayan proposal and it also
                    involves the Uruguayan Foreign Minister and he said that Argentina would require
                    special handling, which he was arranging both for the Argentine Ambassador and
                    the Uruguayan Ambassador in Buenos Aires.</p>
                <p>Next is a proposal by the United States to certain American Republics that they
                    individually appeal to Spain not to become involved in the European conflict. We
                    considered it unfavorably. Any questions on that?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: The Department wished the various American Republic Governments
                    to have their Ambassadors in Madrid speak to the Spanish Foreign Office, and it
                    went on to say, “The Brazilian Government does not desire publicity on this,
                    however.” We put in a footnote to this and we said, “Ambassador Cafferty
                    reported that the Brazilian Government would take affirmative action through its
                    Ambassador in Spain,” which was acceptable.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Did that stay in?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: And that stayed in.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Next is under (c). The first we considered unfavorably. Do you want to
                    identify that?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: This was with regard to a series of measures that the Argentine
                    Government was going to use the exigencies of the war situation—this was in
                    December 1941—to bring some pressure on the internal situation. Here’s a
                    sentence, “In the ten years since the foregoing action was taken,” this is with
                    regard to certain war measures, “the Argentine Government has adopted a series
                    of measures and has in general maintained an attitude which served to cast
                    serious doubt on the genuine nature of its intentions towards us and toward the
                    problems of continental cooperation and defense.” Now, the sense of that is
                    brought out throughout the documents subsequently. It’s a small thing.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The final one on this list is Bolivia which was reconsidered
                    favorably. So, on the whole, Mr. Chairman, we did pretty well.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: I believe there were 26 in all and 19 of them were reconsidered
                    favorably.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I’d next like to call attention to the committee recommendations,
                    Volume V, 1941. The committee report recommended that this volume ought to be
                    released for publication, but we have taken this up from time to time and find
                    there is a fairly strong feeling in that area that the situation is such in that
                    part of the world that this would be harmful to our interests and therefore it
                    should not be released at this time. Do you want to resurvey that yourselves?
                    You probably may want to.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Didn’t we make an earlier, briefer recommendation before the more
                    thorough one last year on that?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You mean the previous year?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Yes. In other words, we have twice made a recommendation.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. Next, with reference to the committee recommendations on the
                    China volume, you will note that under Number 4 there the China volumes are
                    still, shall we say, on the shelf as a result of the action taken in 1957. The
                    committee said that it regrets that a large amount of useful material should
                    remain unavailable because of the reluctance of the Department to give clearance
                    of these volumes. And at that session, Assistant Secretary Parsons made a
                    statement to the effect that if we file these volumes and release them
                    simultaneously—well, nothing has been accomplished on that front because of the
                    difficulties of clearance. We would have to get clearance on these volumes as
                    you go along and the prospect of compiling and finally putting in case bound
                    form 14 volumes, one of them in case bound form already, there are extreme
                    difficulties of getting clearance as we go along.</p>
                <p>Unless we could have some guarantee that when they all are finally printed that
                    then they be published, it looks like a two-time operation, but something I
                    think we ought to follow up and discuss. What we would like, of course, would be
                    to be able to publish the volumes year by year with the other regular annual
                    volumes. The 1943 volume is now being held up. If we could publish that along
                    with the 1943 regular volumes that would be, I should think, reasonably
                    satisfactory.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: In that connection, I notice the last sentence of the preface to the
                    general volume, 1942, where you call attention to the fact that the Foreign
                    Relations series for 1942 also includes the unnumbered volume of China
                    previously published, is this the indication that some day maybe it will become
                    part of the regular numbering? Or is this just a discrete way of explaining what
                    the situation is?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: It is an announcement in the preface of the China volume of ’42,
                    but this is a special series and it was not given a number in the regular
                    series. In <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> 1942, China, period, and
                    presumably the remaining volumes of that series would come out as a special
                    series. I think that might be, if we reconsidered that in later years and put
                    them into the regular series we would have to have some editorial explanation of
                    that time.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The situation is substantially the same in regard to the China
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. Mr. Steeves, who is Deputy Assistant Secretary, Mr. Parsons not
                    being available now, will meet with the committee tomorrow at 11:30 for a
                    discussion of this question. He is in New York now and will be back tomorrow
                    morning. There has been some discussion of this matter. Senator Fulbright raised
                    the question in a letter of July 1 to the Department, in which he called
                    attention to the fact that: <quote rend="blockquote"><p>The Volume 1942, China,
                            contained a paragraph stating that it was the first in a special series
                            of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes covering the
                            relations of the United States with China covering the years 1942 to
                            1949. The preface to this volume is dated April 15, 1956. I understand
                            that no additional volumes have been released, although at least one
                            volume has been printed and is being stored. I should like to have a
                            detailed report on this publication program, including an explanation
                            for the delay.</p></quote></p>
                <p>Well, the Department replied to him saying: <quote rend="blockquote"><p>The China
                            Volume for 1943 was ready for release in 1957. On August 9, 1957, the
                            Secretary of State determined that release of the 1943 volume should be
                            postponed. The ground on which he based his decision was that we were
                            spending great effort and hundreds of millions of dollars to maintain
                            the security of Taiwan and to support our allies, the Republic of China.
                            At the same time, the Chinese Communists are using every available means
                            to discredit and destroy that government. The volumes contain material
                            highly derogatory to the Republic of China which could be used by the
                            Chinese Communists for their purpose. Publication of this material by
                            the United States Government at this time would confuse and depress the
                            people of Free China who look to the United States for support. This
                            continues to be the Department’s position.</p>
                        <p>The question of releasing the compiled volumes in the special China
                            series will be reviewed from time to time in the light of changing
                            conditions.</p></quote></p>
                <p>On the basis of that letter, Senator Fulbright approached the Department again on
                    September 20th and said: <quote rend="blockquote"><p>It would be helpful to me
                            to receive, on a confidential basis, of course, copies of the volumes
                            with an indication of the material which it was felt was derogatory of
                            the Republic of China.</p></quote></p>
                <p>So we replied saying: <quote rend="blockquote"><p>In view of your assurance that
                            these volumes will be received by you on a confidential basis, I am
                            pleased to send a copy of a paper-bound volume for 1943 and the page
                            proofs for the 1944 volume. Passages which might be regarded of special
                            interest particularly, because of their political sensitivity, are
                            indicated by clips on the pages.</p></quote> We said if he wanted to see
                    others we would send them along. But we haven’t received any requests.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That was September 20th, the current year?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. So we haven’t had any response to that last letter. And that is
                    the status of the China volumes and Mr. Steeves will be here tomorrow for you to
                    discuss this with him.</p>
                <p>I’d like to refer now to the Potsdam volumes. As you know, at that time there
                    were certain items involving clearance and suggested—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Excuse me, sir. But before we go on, has the committee taken a stand
                    on this question of incorporating them eventually, since there is going to be
                    this delay with the annual volumes?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think not. I think that is something for you to consider.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We might discuss that, Dexter.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: On the Potsdam volume, you said: “It is suggested that the briefing
                    paper on Spain might have been included. With regard to certain short passages
                    for deletion, it is suggested that items 2 to 5 might have been included as well
                    as 8 and 9.” This is covered in number 6, but I think I will ask Mr. Dougall to
                    speak up and put in brief the explanation of the situation.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGAL: The situation on Potsdam was a bit different from the ones you just
                    discussed in regard to the general volumes in that those were still in galley
                    proof, so that reinserting material or not deleting it, if it was already set in
                    type, was a simple process, whereas the Potsdam volumes were already in page
                    proof with the documents numbered. So that reinserting an entire document was a
                    major operation and reinserting some short passages would cause great editorial
                    difficulties, particularly since the volume is already partly indexed. We
                    decided, therefore, that we would not go back to the clearing officers on these
                    items.</p>
                <p>The Spanish paper had already been up to the Under Secretary level and he had
                    said absolutely no. We thought the chances of getting him or higher authority to
                    change his mind were practically nil, in spite of the view of you gentlemen. I
                    did try to assist the scholar who wanted to know what our position on Spain was
                    in the Spring of ’45 by including in a footnote instead of the text of President
                    Roosevelt’s instructions to Ambassador Armour about three months before the
                    Potsdam Conference, which had already been released by the Department some years
                    ago and which put very clearly the displeasure that our government had with the
                    Spanish Government; if anything, it put it a little stronger than the briefing
                    book paper. But it did not touch on a few other things which the Bureau of
                    European Affairs thought were sensitive. It did, however, deal with that portion
                    of our Spanish policy which was discussed at Potsdam and so in effect we have
                    that as a briefing paper instead of the short one which went along.</p>
                <p>The other passages we thoroughly agreed with you, that they might be included,
                    but even getting them through the reconsideration process would have meant
                    delays, and if it meant re-indexing, rechecking, moving things from page to
                    page, this sort of thing, that makes the delays much greater. So that we have
                    put them, in effect, in a dossier which we can use with clearing officers in
                    future arguments over whether such-and-such a thing can be cleared, together
                    with your views on the annual volumes. And I think the cumulative weight of your
                    views will be very useful in talking to clearing officers, where we can say, “No
                    this is the sort of thing which over the past some years you have been raked
                    over the coals for by the academic community which feels you’re being unduly
                    cautious on these things.”</p>
                <p>The status of the Potsdam volumes is roughly as follows: Volume I is off the
                    press. It is not yet bound, but it’s available in paperback, and if you want to
                    have a look at it during your reading period I will produce copies for you. We
                    have asked GPO to type in six pages on which they made errors after the pages
                    had been okayed for press. It said in Monotype, which has its own dangers,
                    including the possibilities of dropping out individual characters, individual
                    words which you can’t do very well in Linotype, and there were considerable
                    number of these errors in the press process, the worst of which we are asking
                    them to replace. It is ready any time, practically.</p>
                <p>Volume II is in revised page proof, 1600 pages of text, so it is almost the
                    equivalent of two regular volumes The front matter, which will run to well over
                    a hundred pages, is done but we do not yet have that in type. The index is going
                    to be the controlling factor on when the volume is ready to be released. We are
                    holding Volume I, which is all pre-conference material, until Volume II is ready
                    because without seeing what these particular documents were chosen as a preface
                    for, it does not seem to us advisable to put them out separately. We have not
                    been able to find out from the Division of Publishing Services how soon they
                    think the index will be ready. They have had their fingers burned a good many
                    times, I think, on being over-optimistic on estimates on this. They thought that
                    one person would have to do the indexing of both volumes since the subject
                    matter is largely the same in both of them, and I think they are right about
                    this. It would make a much better index. But it means indexing over 2600 pages
                    of rather tightly-packed material and that is a big job for one person to do. We
                    do expect both volumes will be released early next year.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Thank you, Dick.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: May I ask how many copies of Potsdam Volume I the committee would
                    like to have for perusal during their reading period?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I warn you there won’t be much spare time for reading that.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Are there any problems of clearance here?</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: This is now water over the dam except for your criticisms on it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Dick, I assume that the 1600-page monster will be in this thin
                    paper?</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: It will be on the thin paper so it will be approximately the same
                    thickness as our current documents, 1950 to ’55, which ran 1700 and some
                    pages.</p>
                <p>MR NOBLE: Some of you may have read in the papers the latter part of August
                    something—</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I have the clipping right here. [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: —something about the publication of highly secret documents and
                    articles which were highly sensationalized, I should say, and on that we have
                    had inquiries from the Hill also, both from the Chairman of the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee and from the House so-called Moss committee. Senator
                    Fulbright, on August 26th, wrote to the Secretary saying: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>On August 25th the committee discussed the subject of the current
                            newspaper series based on unpublished Potsdam conference documents. It
                            would be desirable for the report to include answers to the following
                            questions: On what terms were reporters Knebel and Bailey permitted
                            access to the Potsdam documents? In what respect, if any, did these
                            terms differ from the usual arrangements? Has there been any violation
                            of the terms of access or Department Regulations either by these
                            reporters or by employees of the Department of State? Are there reasons
                            for the delay in publication of the Potsdam documents in addition to
                            those given in the Department’s Press Release No. 483 of August 23,
                            1960? In view of questions as to whether or not the current newspaper
                            series presents a balanced historical analysis, has the Department
                            considered the desirability of publishing some part of the Potsdam
                            documents prior to the Presidential election?</p>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>Well, the reply to that was this: <quote rend="blockquote"><p>The publication of
                            the four articles by Messrs. Fletcher Knebel and Charles w. Bailey must
                            be viewed in the light of developments in the post-1945 years when
                            outside scholars or other qualified writers were occasionally permitted
                            to use <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> papers after they were
                            cleared for publication but before the volumes containing them were
                            actually published. Any qualified writer working on a book was thus, on
                            his application and without discrimination, given an opportunity to
                            check on Foreign Relations materials that were expected to be published
                            in the near future. It was assumed that the documents would be in the
                            public domain about the same time as the book would appear, and would
                            serve as a check on any statements in the book which might be open to
                            question.</p></quote> And he gave a list of occasions where access had
                    been give on situations of that kind.</p>
                <p>He went on to explain that these papers were made available to Knebel and Bailey
                    on the basis of their statements that they were preparing the book, just as
                    earlier we had made them available to Herbert Feis for the preparation of his
                    book which, as you know, is out on the Potsdam Conference, and then said that
                    they were doing the book, so we thought we couldn’t discriminate.</p>
                <p>The Feis case had been discussed at high level in the Department and it was
                    decided to show him these documents which had been given the regular clearance
                    by policy officers. On that basis, Knebel and Bailey were allowed to see them.
                    Unfortunately, the Potsdam papers had not been published before the appearance
                    of the two books, that is the Feis book and the Knebel-Bailey book, which now I
                    believe is being put in the <hi rend="italic">Reader’s Digest</hi>. The reason
                    for this was that the discovery of relevant additional material on the Potsdam
                    Conference in the late stage of the editorial work made it impossible to
                    complete the publication and the two volumes of the Potsdam Conference until
                    early in 19[6]1, because of extensive necessary revisions, page proof and the
                    requirements of new pagination and the complete review of the index.</p>
                <p>So we put out Press Release No. 483 to suspend the granting of access to such
                    material before official publication, which was done to prevent the recurrence
                    of such episodes, and in answer to his specific questions, which I think really
                    are comprehended in what I already stated.</p>
                <p>We also heard from the Walsh committee. A gentleman came down and had a long
                    conference on the subject and accused us of concealing information. And he asked
                    what the legal basis was for not making them fully available to anyone who might
                    inquire as following our press release, saying we were going to stop this
                    practice of being generous because of the possible abuse by newspapers. Our
                    policy had been to make them available to authors of books, not authors of
                    newspaper articles because a newspaper article, being a quickie, would be out of
                    perspective and documents would not be available to check on as to the veracity
                    and perspective of the article.</p>
                <p>So the Moss committee wanted to know what our legal basis was for concealing
                    these and we said, of course, it was the executive right to control papers and
                    then we were in the process of trying to put out this information as quickly as
                    we could and it had become administratively difficult to handle a situation of
                    this kind as many people came in seeking access to the papers. So that is where
                    this situation stands now.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: Bernard, I think the committee might like to know why we thought it
                    was worth while to do re-pagination, re-indexing on the new material, you
                    mentioned it, when we had thought that it wasn’t justified for the Spanish
                    briefing book paper. The new material which we found was in Mr. Bohlen’s
                    personal files. We had to talk to him about these for years, as a matter of
                    fact. We knew they existed. He was absolutely sure there was nothing of interest
                    to us in them. Eventually, however—and this was early this year after everything
                    was in page proof—he relented and said, “You’re welcome to look and satisfy
                    yourself.”</p>
                <p>Well, among the things which we found was a Taiwan map, which Bill Franklin is
                    putting in, with Marshal Stalin’s red pencil on it and Bohlen’s original
                    longhand notes, very rough ones, of President Truman’s first two private
                    conversations with Stalin at Potsdam, on which we have looked high, low, and
                    everywhere we could possibly think of for minutes. He assured us that he
                    prepared minutes. We have not found them anywhere. We had nothing on them. So we
                    came up with his original contemporary notes and are using them. We have also
                    put in an appendix since they are so rough and the reconstruction of the notes
                    which he made for us this year on the basis of the notes and his memory—I think
                    that they are very good reconstructions, but because they are done 15 years
                    later we thought it was necessary to put them in an appendix and draw a very
                    sharp distinction as to what they were so that scholars can use their own
                    judgment as to how valuable they are. The contemporary notes are also printed.
                    But just putting them in required a fair amount of rejuggling.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Those of you who read the newspaper article will recall Knebel and
                    Bailey used that particular information in that conference that Bohlen spelled
                    out between Stalin and President Truman.</p>
                <p>Now, with regard to the Cairo-Tehran volume, the committee also made several
                    suggestions. I will ask Mr. Franklin to discuss those and the status of the
                    Cairo-Tehran volumes.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Perhaps first it might be useful to point out a little further
                    elaboration of what Mr. Dougall said on the hazards of history. Mr. Feis, whose
                    name had been mentioned here, had access to some papers and in his book on
                    Churchill, Roosevelt and Stalin there was some reference to the Tehran
                    conference which I had never seen nor found. We looked for it with renewed vigor
                    in the Department and did not find it. Mr. Feis told me that it was a Bohlen
                    memo. He had found it in the Harry Mann papers. At this point we wrote again to
                    Mr. Bohlen saying, “Really, don’t you have anything else?” He said, “I have my
                    personal papers”. He has always been very clear with us and gave us all the
                    material he had of any official importance years ago. We found this mixed in
                    with personal papers, including this map on Taiwan that Dick referred to, and
                    his notes which Mr. Bohlen hadn’t thought it was necessary to give to us because
                    he thought he had transcribed all his notes—but he hadn’t. In all honesty, this
                    is one of the horrible hazards of this thing.</p>
                <p>On Cairo last year you recommended that we try to keep in a couple of lively
                    innocuous passages by F.D.R. in his first conversations with Stalin at Tehran.
                    You were not enthusiastic about our fighting any longer to try to keep in the
                    papers not negotiated internationally but behind the American scene of
                    discussions by F.D.R. were the Joint Chiefs of Staff with respect to post-war
                    military security basis and strong points.</p>
                <p>On the basis of your enthusiasm for keeping in the innocuous passages by F.D.R.,
                    which we shared, we appealed to Mr. Bohlen who took the original minutes which
                    other people had wished to make deletions from—and Mr. Bohlen had a certain
                    pride of authorship—and he said, “Of course they have to stay in.” In view of
                    your lack of enthusiasm, we already pushed that three times at the level of the
                    Secretary of Defense, we pushed it no further and they will not appear.
                    Presumably some of those papers will appear elsewhere, in a story where
                    admittedly they might be put in a better context, namely, a story of planning
                    for post-war military security. This could conceivably fit in better in some of
                    the military histories than ours,though at present I understand there are no
                    plans to pick those up as such, because this was a theoretical discussion which
                    did not materialize and they have taken the position that it’s just not worth
                    it. They have got too much to say. So that is where we stand.</p>
                <p>The volume has now been sent for page proofing, about the first third of it to
                    begin with, and I think it’s beyond the rocks and shoals. I hesitate to say
                    anything, but I think we are heading into the blue sea of page proof clearance.
                    It should be published in the winter or the spring.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I have no special episodes to report on Cairo or Tehran. So we will
                    pass on further, Mr. Chairman, to a few other of your recommendations.</p>
                <p>You made a recommendation with regard to paying more attention to memoranda and
                    background material and you made a similar recommendation, I believe, the
                    previous year. On this subject, I would like to defer discussion of it until
                    this afternoon when you will have read some material we are recommending for you
                    to read in addition to what you have read in the 1942 Volume I.</p>
                <p>With regard to accumulative index which you recommended, either for all the years
                    of a particular annual series or for all of the series over a period of years,
                    we are still putting in the index for you and we feel that that is indispensable
                    and because these volumes don’t all five or six or seven come out in the same
                    year at the same time, you see, we are just on the verge of getting the 1940
                    volume out, Volume V, the last of the 1940 volumes. So, personally, I doubt
                    whether it’s feasible to try to do it that way, unless of course after all the
                    volumes for the year were out with their own indexes. I think it deserves
                    further consideration.</p>
                <p>You will find, I think, that your final recommendation with regard to an increase
                    in staff is more relevant than it ever was before and that certainly is another
                    reason why nothing has been done thus far on this subject.</p>
                <p>Sir, I believe that covers the matters involved in your recommendations of last
                    year. In that connection, however, I’d like to mention what Leland Goodrich has
                    already mentioned, namely, the paper which is used in the 1942 Volume I, and I
                    think it would be interesting to have your individual and collective opinions on
                    this paper.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This is thinner paper.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: This is a volume of 950 some pages and here’s a volume of about 1050
                    pages (indicating). In other words, it had more pages, this one had a hundred
                    more pages but notice the difference in size of the two. The question is whether
                    the least attractive paper justifies the saving in space.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think Dick mentioned this, so he should be commenting on it. I
                    don’t see that it’s less attractive myself.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I’m all for it. The British, I think, would be outraged by it.
                    [Laughter]</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Will it last as long? I assume it will.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There is no question about it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: There doesn’t seem to be any objection to it.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: The expense isn’t considerable.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is this a substantial saving?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: In space, but no material saving in money.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Have you had any hostile reactions?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No, we haven’t had any letters or any verbal complaints. I’m
                    interested in your joint opinion.</p>
                <p>May I just make one other comment, Mr. Chairman. We have in our little file here
                    some additional materials. One is a critical review of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> Volume I, 1942, and we will hand out to you this
                    afternoon for your reading another review of the history of the world since
                    World War II. And we want to give you all the facts on our operation. Of course
                    we have thought of it with very highly favorable reviews. This is the first
                    highly critical review we have had and along with it are some comments by Mr.
                    Perkins. We would like you to read these this afternoon and you may want to have
                    some comments or questions about them.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Bernard, was this the volume that Fred Harrington had something to
                    say about last year, or was it another? He had some of the same feeling, I
                    remember, on one of the volumes he reviewed last year.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I don’t think so.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Maybe we can find out in looking back at our files.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: He will be here tomorrow.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: So now the question, Mr. Chairman, is the next item on the agenda.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I’d like to come back—perhaps there will be an opportunity later—to
                    the question Mr. Leopold asked about the China volumes and the committee’s
                    attitude. I have the distinct impression that we certainly discussed that point.
                    I don’t remember what was stated in the report, but I seem to have the
                    impression we had a strong feeling that if the China volumes could be
                    incorporated into the regular series there would be much less difficulty about
                    release and so forth. Because they wouldn’t attract quite the same attention as
                    if they were brought out separately. I’m not bringing it up for further
                    discussion right now.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It could be brought up tomorrow.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Probably this doesn’t show in the report.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think we ought to discuss it too.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I thought we were rather strongly of that opinion, that it would be
                    better if they could somehow be incorporated into the regular series.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: May I ask, Mr. Chairman, whether there will be further opportunity to
                    talk about the cumulative index later?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: On that cumulative index, there wasn’t any feeling on our part, was
                    there, that you should abandon it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We had to continue that. And there was the question of adding that
                    other on to Items 3 and 4. I realize that there is overlapping in the subject
                    matter there and there is a problem of how to handle it. I would like to suggest
                    for your consideration that we might have first preliminary discussions of
                    Volume I, but omitting certain items to be discussed in connection with the
                    report on editorial problems.</p>
                <p>For instance, on background material, I’m recommending that you leave all the
                    background questions until this afternoon after you have read some other
                    material which we are recommending for your reading. Aside from that, I would
                    like to suggest that we go ahead on a basis of trying to work the two together
                    after preliminary discussions of Volume II on China. Dick, would you go ahead
                    with that? That is, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, Volume
                    I.</p>
                <p rend="underline">3. Review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942,
                    Volume I.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I have nothing particularly, Dexter. My own feeling, you know, was
                    after our reading of reporting on these individual volumes the last couple of
                    years, that this didn’t perhaps serve too useful a purpose and—I am speaking
                    only for myself—I would be inclined to plunge immediately into the memorandum
                    that Bernard has so ably prepared and perhaps illustrate if any of us have
                    picked up things from the volume for ’42, but that is just my own personal
                    opinion.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think I would feel about the same as Dick. Looking over the
                    material in this volume did raise one question, and I don’t know whether it will
                    come up later or not, and that is the question of how the materials relating to
                    the preparation of some of these basic constitutions of international
                    organizations can best be handled. Now, you have here under “General” a
                    considerable amount of material relating to post war economic arrangements and a
                    lot of that is background material from the Bretton Woods conference. I was
                    wondering just how that kind of material is going to be handled, because there
                    will be more of it in the years ahead. That may be a question we take up later.
                    If we do, I think that is the time to discuss it. If it isn’t going to be taken
                    up later, conceivably we might now discuss it here. Because there are some very
                    long documents here bearing upon the general background of the Bank and the
                    Fund. And if there were to be separate volumes dealing with the preparation of
                    the articles of agreement, the constitution of various organizations, material
                    of this kind, I should think that could go into those volumes. If not, I suppose
                    this is the way to handle it.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Ralph, would you like to say something about that?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: The only thing I would say is that I must admit we have not
                    considered the question of leaving out the annual volumes at this stage of the
                    material on the basis of publication of the background of the various
                    organizations afterwards. We haven’t come to those organizations, so we haven’t
                    really taken up the question of the compilation of those records.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: When you get into part (e) 4 and part (e) 5, you are going to have
                    terrific messes.</p>
                <p>MR. NUEREMBERGER: We have the ’44 compilation completed and I think a couple
                    hundred pages on the Bretton Woods and the ancillary compilations that go along
                    with it. We have Dumbarton Oaks, which is really a preliminary course which
                    almost Yalta was. And it’s probably the biggest compilation we have ever
                    had.</p>
                <p>On San Francisco, it looks as though we probably should have a special volume or
                    even volumes. Looking at it very tentatively, we have given some consideration
                    to having Dumbarton Oaks and the whole San Francisco material put in a separate
                    volume. But we have the Dumbarton Oaks material already completed. Mrs. Cassidy
                    has done a monumental job to the pre-conference to San Francisco. That was
                    tremendous. When you get to the conference you have to really walk a tightrope
                    because you don’t want to get mixed up with what is really U.N. history, where
                    you want to have your eye on the ball which the U. S. Delegation is carrying
                    with regard to the questions that come up at the San Francisco conference. She
                    has been working about a year already on the preliminaries to that. It is a
                    tremendous job, as we will later bring out, not only getting the material we
                    find in the files but also the locked files and various files which are not
                    indexed. So I would say from my observation, it’s the biggest story we have ever
                    had, and complicated, as you say.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: We have been carrying on on a yearly basis so far. Whether, when
                    we get to that San Francisco conference, we put that in a separate volume, I was
                    thinking also of various other organizations like UNESCO and all those.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Well, the Bretton Woods conference, there must be a mass of
                    material there.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: We haven’t gone very extensively into the conference itself.
                    Those conference records will bring up another question, really, of
                    publication.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: But you also have the pre-conference negotiations.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: We have been carrying those.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Whether they should be included in these volumes or assembled along
                    with the record of the particular organization, I just raise the question.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I will say one thing on that. We have been carrying it year by
                    year. We are not yet ready to jump ahead and bring those out with the
                    background. I’d be very dubious as to the wisdom of leaving big gaps in our
                    yearly record on the supposition that those conferences would be covered later.
                    We got into that trouble on the war-time conferences, where we are already
                    getting out <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> for a period when these
                    conferences took place and there is a gap. And it seems to be better on this
                    kind of material to clean it up as we go along. Then what you do later, if you
                    publish separate volumes on various organizations, of course they could cite
                    back to this material. But I’m glad you brought that up because it’s something
                    we have not really gone into on a broad basis, the future planning of that
                    particular line of work.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Clarence, have you anything to say on the volume?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I have no critical comments. I was rather pleased to notice that the
                    volume contains a number of things that I think this committee has recommended,
                    such as inclusion of the Kellogg order and I was really glad to see them include
                    the Departmental organization for the purposes of publication, including the
                    staff responsibilities. I am not sure how far this should go, necessarily But I
                    thought it was rather well done.</p>
                <p>I’m not prepared to make comparison with other volumes, but it seemed to me that
                    it had a good deal of background information in the bracketed explanatory notes
                    and things of that sort. I was very pleased to see that. So I have no
                    unfavorable comment at all.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I have no special comment either. My general reaction was
                    favorable.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Wilson, have you anything to say about this volume?</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Not particularly. Mr. Chairman, I read with appreciation some
                    military agreements that the United States made with the Allied States in ’42. I
                    had occasion to run into that in commercial treaty work. On the latter point I
                    didn’t find the delight which I had expected to find.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Bernard, there is one document in here coming at the end, the very
                    end, which perhaps the compilers had a great deal of experience with. You would
                    probably be interested in it. It’s a report on Thailand on Page 917, where there
                    are four omissions. I didn’t feel knowing about it, that this—well, you can
                    probably guess what some of the things would be that were omitted.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I must say we want to discuss the memorandum as it is one we have
                    already discussed to some degree. I think the question is raised in view of the
                    immense number of documents that we will omit subjects and spread it thin or
                    that maybe we think it is a process of elimination. But there is a big question
                    there and it’s a question we ought to discuss in connection with your report.
                    But as far as the volume itself is concerned, I have no particular comment to
                    offer. It doesn’t apply to the broader considerations.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: If I may interrupt, if you’re interested in seeing the original
                    document so you can see what we did omit, we will be glad to produce it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: [Shaking his head]</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Could I ask a question there. Was consideration given to the
                    possibility of paraphrasing? I don’t know how much was omitted. But we did
                    discuss earlier the possibility of paraphrasing in some instances.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: No.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I was paraphrasing the Ambassador’s remarks</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: As you are aware, Thailand has been a very sensitive area. We
                    were lucky to get this thing through.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we might pass to the consideration of Bernard’s memorandum,
                    which no doubt we have all perused.</p>
                <p rend="underline">4. Discussion of Paper: “Some Editorial Problems”.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Correct me if I’m wrong, but we come to an expression of opinion on
                    page 3 with regard to the restricting of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, including the files of the Department itself. And that is a
                    question of policy on which I think we probably ought to have some discussion.
                    What do members of the committee have to say with regard to that problem? We
                    know, of course, that we do go outside the Departmental limits. Any comment on
                    that?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Well, again for what it’s worth, when this problem was first raised
                    at the time of the Yalta volumes, I thought that the Department, the
                    Histori[c]al Office, was perhaps exposing itself unduly to criticism from the
                    outside once they got outside especially on the question of private papers. If
                    we went to the Roosevelt Library, they will say, “Why didn’t you go to this or
                    that?” I was inclined to think that restriction as much as possible to the State
                    Department files was in the long run the wisest course for the editors to
                    pursue. And at that time <ref target="1957-03-21-kennan-to-leopold">I asked
                        George Kennan</ref>, whom I had known, what his views were and he got
                    Llewellyn Woodward to write up a memo in which he rather agreed with that,
                    restrict as much as possible for then you won’t expose yourself to criticism and
                    you will at least have the integrity. I must say since then I have changed my
                    own mind and I think the rather elastic policy which you elaborated here is
                    probably the wiser one. That is, you don’t set yourself any hard and fast rule.
                    So I would say that much out of historical background.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You take the position that a certain amount of flexibility was
                    desirable?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: That’s right.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It would be pretty difficult for us, would it not, to define the
                    principle involved as to how far you can go outside? I think we can tell you
                    whether or not you should go outside. Of course as to the relevance of a
                    particular document, we can hardly judge in advance or later on on any general
                    principle. How do you feel about this, Leland? Are you in general favorable of
                    some search outside for relevant material?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I don’t think we can define the line. But I’m impressed by the fact
                    that as we move on from the early ’40’s into the latter ’40’s and into the ’50’s
                    it’s going to become increasingly difficult, it seems to me, to present in these
                    volumes a record of the American Foreign Relations that is very complete,
                    limiting itself to the Departmental files. On the other hand, to try to tell the
                    whole story is going to be an impossible task.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course the other side of the matter is that this must be a time
                    element. Does this seriously retard publication, do you think, the search for
                    relevant material outside the Department? Does that seriously retard
                    publication? Certainly this is an element that has to be considered as to how
                    far one goes outside the Departmental files. How do you feel about that?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I feel it definitely. It makes a difference. You see, the Roosevelt
                    Library, in making and organizing this request for documents here, if you carry
                    on this precedent of using Presidential papers, we will have to send people out
                    to the Truman Library to spend possibly several weeks. But we must recognize
                    that they are very vital papers sometimes which frequently aren’t in the
                    Department files.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It’s difficult. I want the correct opinion of the committee. It
                    seems to me there is a time element involved which has to be scored against the
                    significance of the documents which you’re looking for. But I don’t see how we
                    can go much further than improving the principle of the idea. If we do agree on
                    it, what do you think about it?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: I fully agree with this idea that you must go outside. But you also
                    have to draw a line somewhere and what this means also is that we have got to
                    have confidence in the staff and in the judgment of the staff. They have got to
                    use more judgment than otherwise. On the other hand, it seems to me that the
                    developments are such that this can’t be avoided. It seems to me to some extent
                    it is a matter of accident whether the papers are State Department or
                    Presidential papers. In other words, if the President has conversed about some
                    things but otherwise the Secretary of State would enter into a somewhat more
                    formal conversation, they would be State Department papers. I don’t see how you
                    can avoid this problem. It’s difficult.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: May I just make a few comments on that?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Certainly.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: In the first place, with regard to the Presidential library,
                    Roosevelt’s Library and now the Truman Library—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: And assume the Eisenhower Library.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: When we come to that. We agreed in principle that we should
                    definitely try to include the Presidential papers and we have been using those
                    definitely over a considerable period of years, in fact, for the entire
                    Roosevelt period. Starting in 1933 we have used papers from Hyde Park. Now we
                    come to another problem which we have under consideration, access to the Truman
                    papers. I don’t want to discuss that at length now, but the present status of
                    the library is such that we have not been yet successful in making any effective
                    use of the library. We hope to be able to make some more progress on that
                    line.</p>
                <p>Now, in regard to the general principle, aside from the Presidential papers, the
                    big international problems that we deal with where we would need to go outside
                    primarily concern defense.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Concerns what?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Defense. And there we run up against the question of the
                    utilization of the records of the Defense Department. It’s a very practical
                    problem. To do this on any extensive scale we would have to get a different
                    attitude on the part of the Defense Department, which certainly at present would
                    not allow us to send researchers over going through their records hunting for
                    materials.</p>
                <p>We have in the material for you to read this afternoon a set of papers that we
                    did not put in but now which we are reconsidering and think very likely should
                    go in. I think probably you people will feel they should go in, but we would
                    like your opinion. When we compiled the record on North Africa for 1942 we did
                    not include the correspondence of Robert Murphy for a period from the middle of
                    October to the occupation of North Africa, for the reason which we explained in
                    a footnote, that during that period Mr. Murphy was working with the military
                    authorities. Dick was instructed, because of the secrecy of the North African
                    invasion, not to consult with the State Department. He did not report to the
                    State Department. He did not receive instructions from the State Department. So
                    we omitted those records, putting in a footnote explaining his position.</p>
                <p>Now we are under fire from two sides on our North African story. CIA has been
                    mentioned. That is a particular issue with CIA which wants very extensive
                    omissions. On the other hand, Mr. Murphy came to the Historical Office and has
                    been allowed to go over records and he was allowed to see what we have compiled.
                    He felt that our record was incomplete because we left out the most important
                    part of his work, which is true.</p>
                <p>So there is one set of documents we have not produced for you which definitely I
                    think should go in. Mr. Murphy at the time did not report his correspondence
                    with General Giraud. In 1943 the Department asked Murphy for that
                    correspondence, and he sent it in under a despatch. We have decided to include
                    that despatch with the enclosures, that is, put that all in as one document—the
                    agreement which constituted the agreements with General Giraud, if we can get
                    that cleared for publication; we have not yet submitted that for clearance, it
                    will have to be submitted to Defense, of course, too.</p>
                <p>Now we found the telegrams exchanged between the War Department and Mr. Murphy
                    went through the Department. But all the record we had were card records of a
                    telegram coming in and being transmitted to the War Department, no copy
                    whatsoever of these telegrams. I believe the War Department called. They were
                    not decoded in the State Department. So they were sent over to the War
                    Department and no deciphered telegrams were returned to the Department.</p>
                <p>Now, in regard to time, I may say it has taken weeks to obtain these telegrams
                    from the Defense Department.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Months.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I beg your pardon, months. But they are given to us for our use
                    in the Department. If they are to be published, we will have to go back to
                    Defense for clearance. We have those telegrams which I have selected as what I
                    think we might put in. We have made a number of copies of those so you can all
                    read them. If you are interested, we can produce the complete set of those
                    Murphy-War Department telegrams. I think you will be interested in reading that
                    material.</p>
                <p>Of course the reason I have said so much on this is that it is right on the point
                    you raised of the question of going beyond State Department records. Of course
                    this is a unique case, where a high ranking officer, Foreign Service Officer,
                    was involved but where it’s outside, I might say, our instructions. So I don’t
                    think any blame should come to the compiler of these volumes, who is now a
                    Foreign Service Officer, Mr. Prescott, who was carrying out our directive of
                    putting in those materials which came under the responsibility of the Department
                    of State. You see, during this period the State Department was not responsible
                    for Mr. Murphy. Well, that is an exceptional case, rather perhaps a unique
                    case.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You still have clearance yet to get?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Still have clearance yet to get.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That may be a long process.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: It very likely will.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Who has control over in Defense?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I believe the Joint Chiefs.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: On the general principle of documents, especially Defense documents,
                    I assume perhaps that it works something like this: You can’t, as you say, send
                    researchers over just to see what they have, but you get leads. You know about
                    certain materials that ought definitely to be included and I think that is the
                    kind of thing you should press for. There is one particular document we have
                    asked for months ago. We haven’t gotten it yet. They raise a question why does
                    the Department need this document? That was not a telegram that would lead in to
                    the Department itself. There was a reference to it in the Army history and it’s
                    on the same subject that the State Department was making recommendations. I
                    might say it was on unconditional surrender. The State Department sent a
                    recommendation to the President on a certain day. The Joint Chiefs sent a
                    recommendation on the same subject on the same day, we found from Army history.
                    So we have asked for a copy of it. We haven’t got it yet.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Can you get support from a high level in the State Department to a
                    high level in the Defense Department in regard to documents of this kind?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: On this we have not. Mr. Noble can tell you on our annual volumes
                    we have not gone to that stage yet.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: He means we haven’t asked for support yet.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I don’t want to give that impression.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But you can get support.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Certainly.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mr. Thayer, what do you want to say about this general problem of
                    going outside the Department?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I would suppose we are all agreed that under present conditions it’s
                    vitally necessary to go outside Department sources in order to be able to
                    present a complete picture. It would follow, it would seem to me, that it’s
                    important to have a policy of flexibility. It would be equally important, I
                    would suppose—but this is something more of an internal nature than external—to
                    be able to lay down certain guideposts in that connection, such as, for example,
                    the existence of obvious gaps in the State Department materials which need to be
                    filled; secondly, the importance of the materials which can be found outside.
                    But, subject to certain guideposts of that kind, I certainly would agree that
                    there must be flexibility.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Mr. Chairman, I think that the Department has to go outside for
                    material. I don’t mean to say that they should take everything from outside. I
                    suppose if they made a photographic reproduction of all the things that were
                    potentially significant you would have a large volume every year. But I think
                    that you have to do a lot of guessing here, do you not, as to whether an event
                    of a couple decades ago may, in the light of subsequent events to come, be of
                    significance. I don’t know how you’re going to construct these. I believe you
                    have to have some criteria, but I don’t see how you can have hard and fast
                    ones.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: May I ask one question of you members of the committee. In
                    talking about going outside, do you wish to go beyond our present Department
                    directive, that we take up those questions which are within the responsibility
                    of the Department of State? They may be international questions but do you want
                    to go beyond the responsibility of the Department?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Be careful how you answer that question.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: I’m not anxious.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Ralph, if you ask that specifically, directly and literally, you would
                    say you wouldn’t include the documents which we are proposing to include
                    because, as you explained, Murphy’s actions were specifically outside the
                    responsibilities of the Department but they are vastly of concern to the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I think the North African situation is a unique case and
                    especially because while it was outside the responsibility of the Department, it
                    was the work of a high ranking Department Foreign Service Officer. That is a
                    unique case and I think I could justify our omission. I wouldn’t think we were
                    reprehensible in leaving this material out but, since the question was raised by
                    Mr. Murphy himself and since there was that justification to complete the record
                    of an eminent Foreign Service Officer, I thought an exception might be made in
                    that case.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: You could say you cover all matters nominally within the
                    responsibility of the Department.</p>
                <p>MR. KPETZMANN: He is about to publish these in his own memoirs anyway.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: It seems to me we are in danger of getting involved in a question of
                    semantics here, whether a question of responsibility becomes a question of
                    concern, as was true in this instance.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: When does a question of concern becomes a question of
                    responsibility?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would think, for example, that we should distinguish between
                    Presidential papers, let’s say, and the records of some of the other
                    departments. I think what Mr. Perkins just said certainly should have our
                    support, that every effort should be made to get documents and material that are
                    considered relevant that are in the Roosevelt Library or the Truman Library or
                    the Eisenhower Library because of the special relations of the Department to the
                    President as a principal adviser in the field of foreign policy.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think one would have to be careful to lay down as rigid a rule as
                    you suggested a moment ago.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Following Leland’s thought here, what got me off on this originally
                    some years ago was not distinguishing between State Department papers and
                    Defense Department papers but when you start going into the personal
                    collections, such as the Roosevelt, the Truman, and so forth. Now, we know the
                    Hull papers and the Dulles papers are going to be part of a special collection
                    at Princeton. We are multiplying our problems there. Certainly the Secretary of
                    State is important. I would like to see some line at least to give you people a
                    feeling that there are limits beyond which you didn’t have to go into this.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: We have had some experience in war time conference business with
                    defining the scope of coverage from Defense and other departments. We tackled
                    this problem seven years ago, in 1953, to turn out the volume on Yalta in which
                    you will find papers from the Department of Defense, from Treasury and other
                    areas outside the Department of State, because in this case the responsibility
                    was so clearly that of the President of the United States to conduct the foreign
                    policy of the United States that there could be no serious thought given to
                    delimiting the field of interest, concern or responsibility of the Department of
                    State which was out on the fringes of that thing anyway and even more so in the
                    case of Cairo-Tehran where the Department as such is not even represented.</p>
                <p>So it was quite clear, as of seven years ago, that if we were going to tell the
                    story of these conferences we need to tell the stories of the foreign relations
                    of the United States, the policies of the United States as they were developed
                    for the President and brought by the President to bear at the table of
                    international negotiations at the conferences and since the President was also
                    the Commander-in-Chief and many of these problems were politico-military at the
                    most important levels, there could be no distinctions made artificially by us
                    between what we considered political and what were military.</p>
                <p>Thus, for instance, the question of the delineation of theatres of operation, war
                    theatres of operation in South East Asia, discussed with Chiang Kai-shek could
                    not be defined as either a political or military problem. It was to us a perfect
                    example of the complete fusion in war of the top level political-military
                    thinking. So these considerations dropped entirely by the Board, we had to go
                    outside.</p>
                <p>The question then was of scope. We worked out no arrangement of scope with the
                    Department of the Treasury or any other departments from which we begged and
                    borrowed particular papers for which we had leads. We had no problem with them.
                    On individual papers they were entirely willing. They hauled out batches of
                    papers; for instance, Morgenthau’s memo to the President.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This was true in Defense, you say?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: This was in other departments. They were very easy about it. We
                    said we would like to see certain memoranda or related papers and their file
                    people would take them out. And we indicated several we wanted to have photo
                    copies of and they did it and sent them to us.</p>
                <p>Defense, of course, was a far larger problem, one so different in quantity as to
                    become different in quality. Here the definition of scope was important at the
                    very outset, but there was no question of our getting access to the whole files
                    of the Department. In the first place, we did not approach them that way. We
                    didn’t want that. They had historical sections of their own, larger in some
                    cases than ours. What we asked for originally was would they please cooperate
                    with us and within the limits, as we defined them, of the conference as a whole
                    bring their historical research to bear to give us the contribution of the
                    military from their files. Their answer was, “Thank you, no, we don’t intend to
                    do that. We have our own programs.”</p>
                <p>They said, however, that they would cooperate with us if we would tell them what
                    we wanted. We told them a long list of documents we wanted, to which we have
                    picked up leads from the Army history, the memoirs, State Department documents
                    we had, etc., etc., etc. The question immediately came up then, well, you have
                    asked for a lot of stuff here which is way down the line. No, no, this is up. So
                    we had literally to define the scope. We defined it with satisfaction and it was
                    defined right at the top and in considering going beyond State Department files,
                    I think it’s correct to say we had never considered really going below this
                    careful definition that was worked out six or seven years ago.</p>
                <p>There is no question of publishing the files of the whole Department of Defense.
                    Let’s not talk about that. They won’t make any open doors for us to come
                    anywheres near that. But we got in Yalta, defined as those papers from military
                    sources which contained the advice and recommendations of the civilian
                    Secretaries of War and Navy and of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and of their top
                    assistants to the President or the Secretary of State or their top assistants on
                    problems that came before those conferences—Cairo, Tehran, Potsdam, Yalta, etc.
                    That is the way it has been defined very precisely.</p>
                <p>We have had some odd experiences of papers which are well below that level which,
                    however, come up and get precipitated on the table and become a document of more
                    importance than their original authorship would have warranted. Sometimes papers
                    of the Joint Planning Staff never actually formally approved by the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff were called upon at the last moment and brought into the table and
                    became the subject of negotiations at the top level. Although this was not a
                    formally approved, recommended paper by the Joint Chiefs of Staff to the
                    President, they had relented to the point of letting us have that kind of
                    paper.</p>
                <p>Occasionally an intelligence report, similarly, would not get the approval of the
                    Joint Chiefs but would be presented to the President for his consideration and
                    we have been able to get those. We have, however, had to haggle, haggle for
                    months on these peripheral items. The items which fall clearly within the scope
                    of the Defense contribution we get without too much trouble. I mean the usual
                    weeks and weeks, but they come. The others, however, are months and months, very
                    tightly contested.</p>
                <p>In answer to your question about support in the Department, yes. In connection
                    with the war-time conferences we have had at least a half dozen very high level
                    letters in the Department of State to the Office of the Secretary of
                    Defense.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The documents you get easily are the ones which—</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: That fall directly within the scope, as I define it, namely, the
                    papers which mention the recommendations and suggestions from the civilian
                    Secretaries of War and Navy, that is what we were talking about, or the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff to the President or the Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I see. If you go outside that area you have difficult, is that
                    right?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: That’s correct.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This is very important information.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: When we can point out that although the paper we have in mind that
                    we have asked for is a lower level paper and does not fall within this limited
                    scope that it, nevertheless, achieved a unique importance at the conference
                    because Marshall gave it to Leahy to give to the President and the President
                    talked about it to Stalin, we get the paper but we have to go back and
                    explain.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: May I make one comment on that, just to get it clear. This
                    agreement Mr. Franklin speaks of was in connection with publication of the
                    war-time conferences which the Department was committed to the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee to publish. And Defense was acting on the fact with the
                    realization that this was a special case on these conferences which if published
                    at all would have to include Defense records.</p>
                <p>The document I referred to before on unconditional surrender was a recommendation
                    from the Joint Chiefs to the President. And they say, “Why do you want it?”</p>
                <p>What I would like to have from this committee is this: Two or three years ago you
                    definitely made a recommendation limiting the scope that we should seek outside
                    records and our Department order defines our publication as within the
                    responsibility of the State Department with supplementary papers which we agree
                    would occasionally fill gaps. We have been acting on our directive and on your
                    recommendation. If you feel now we should go beyond that, it would have to be
                    rather carefully defined how far you would like to have us go.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: This is obviously a question for us to consider in deliberations
                    apart. But the light thrown on it is naturally very useful to us.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I wanted to ask Bill whether once you get by the war-time
                    conferences, we could use this general statement as a purpose. Do you think that
                    would persist in the 1946 volumes, or do you think the problem has changed such
                    that you would have to reformulate it?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I think the seriousness of the problem as we have it now, as we
                    have expressed it here at the table, is peculiar to the war-time situation,
                    peculiar to the fact that we had at that time no central coordinating agency at
                    the White House level. The President thought he could do it all, and he talked
                    first with Henry L. Stimson, and then he talked with Hull and that was it, no
                    formalized material at all for talking at the top level. So when you want to
                    coordinate for the conferences of the war-time period you have got to go back to
                    the files of Morgenthau, Stimson and Hull to pull these things together. These
                    are the people they had, that Roosevelt had. So there was no machinery.</p>
                <p>So, beginning in ’46-47, you get some machinery. Then the question will arise in
                    a slightly different form. We will get machinery then through SWNNC and SANAC
                    and on into the National Security Council of 1947. Then the question is whether
                    we are publishing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of the United States
                    or only papers of the State Department. So as Ralph can take a limited view and
                    make it stick, and it’s reasonable after ’47, the problem becomes at once more
                    difficult and more necessary either if we get the papers of the Security Council
                    which will reflect the United States policy or we don’t. And if we don’t, the
                    problem then is far worse than it was during the war-time period when there was
                    no such coordinating agency. But we have perhaps more justification for going
                    along and taking what was the Department of State responsibility.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I have two comments which may be helpful here looking toward the
                    future. First, the case Mr. Perkins raised, I’m afraid that is not going to be
                    an isolated incident because there is a strong trend in the Department and also
                    in other parts of the Government to exchange officers on what the British call a
                    secund basis and this has already started. We will be secunding some Foreign
                    Service Officers to other departments for a year, two years, or three years.
                    This is what happened to Murphy But this is going to happen regularly as a
                    matter of policy.</p>
                <p>Now, you’re going to have to, I think, in the future face that. They are being
                    detailed particularly in the foreign policy field because there is so much
                    involvement.</p>
                <p>That leads to the other, I think, more optimistic point, that in view of the
                    heavy involvement of other agencies of the Government in foreign relations,
                    there is a conscious effort here now to see to it that there is a better
                    coordination of papers. When you talk about the NAC papers, it’s true we haven’t
                    had direct access to them, but they are all in the Department. You don’t have to
                    go out to look for these. There is much greater attempt to draw these other
                    agencies into the Department at one stage or another. I think in a way we are
                    dealing here with a problem which I hope won’t recur.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: How do these come to the Department?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: By reason of participation in these conferences.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: The Department officers deposit it?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes. And it’s true now of a great deal of Defense stuff. They are
                    inter-agency boards. There is an exchange of documents and files in each of the
                    departments so that I don’t think the research problem will be so great. But you
                    still have the decision to make as to how much you’re going to do.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: There is a problem of clearance, I take it; if you use a National
                    Security Council document you have to have a clearance.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You have only one focal point where you have to get this. Once
                    you’re clear on the problem, I mean, the conduct of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is the President’s business in war and peace, when he wears
                    his other hat. And there is where you’re going to have to go for a decision when
                    you want accession to these things, if we’re going to make a record of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of the United States.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: But to whom do you go specifically. You wouldn’t go to the
                    President.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: To refer an Executive Order, if this is the decision. I’m not
                    arguing one way or the other because I know this is a—</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: In addition to these, do these Foreign Service Officers transferred
                    to other Departments function as qua-Foreign Service Officers or qua-Department
                    of State officials, or are they for the time being ex-officers?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: They will be Foreign Service Officers remaining in their career
                    status but they will be administratively and functionally and command-wise, if
                    you want to use that word, completely under the control of that other department
                    for that period.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: They don’t report to the State Department during that period?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: No.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: This is true of political advisers during the war, Davies, Murphy
                    and others.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we have a picture there. I rather suggest we take a
                    ten-minutes break, unless there is any other contribution to the problem from
                    any of the officers of the Department.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Mr. Noble has reproduced a sentence or two from a previous report of
                    this committee on a point which probably isn’t very helpful since essentiality
                    is the criterion.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Let’s stop for ten minutes and then go on to the next point of the
                    memorandum.</p>
                <p>[After a brief recess the meeting was reconvened at 11:10 a.m.]</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: [Referring to Mr. Noble’s Memorandum dated October 21, 1960 <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> - Some Editorial
                    Problems] I think the second point in the memorandum that seems to be of
                    importance is the question of the lot files and the post files which he [Mr.
                    Noble] considers on pages 4, 5 and 6. Coming to a conclusion he says: “In a time
                    when publication is falling off and the lag behind currency is lengthening,
                    there is danger that a proper balance will not be maintained and that the lot
                    and post files - which are more tedious and relatively less productive sources
                    of papers - may receive less favored treatment.”</p>
                <p>I think perhaps what we want, first, is the reaction of members of the staff here
                    on this problem for our own guidance before we try to make up our own minds on
                    it. I would be glad to hear from you, Bernard, or any member of the staff on
                    this problem.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think certain members of the staff that have worked particularly on
                    them ought to speak. Some of those are not around the table, but they worked
                    more on them than some of us at the table, and certainly would like to
                    speak.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Can I raise a preliminary question. Can we be particularly helpful
                    on the problems presented by these lot and post files? It seems to me that the
                    problems you have to face are the very practical problems.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: This, as a matter of fact, is a question on which we are giving you
                    information, explaining a problem, more than it is a question of policy on which
                    we want your advice.</p>
                <p>There are differences of opinion, I think, in our own staff as to how far we
                    should go, and how systematically we should undertake to use them. I think,
                    without much difference, that occasionally they are indispensable. In some cases
                    the lot files are more important—in some areas, that is, more than in others.
                    But the question of the use of them is a somewhat controversial one, and I think
                    we could profitably have some expressions of opinion—not only from Ralph and
                    Dexter, but from some of those who actually use them more fully and more
                    recently. These are comparatively new problems, you see—the lot files and the
                    post files.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: On item 5 where you have “Visit of Advisory Committee members to
                    Department files” are we going to see any of those?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. We are going to have a little explanation of a process, several
                    explanations. And, by the way, we were expecting to have a visit to Under
                    Secretary Dillon this afternoon at 2:10, but I understand he is home ill today
                    and will not be available, so we will be able to go to the files a little bit
                    sooner than we had expected. Whoever is to be in touch on the files—Miss Bourne
                    I think you ought to know about that.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: What time?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: About 2:00, I should say.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Well, the lot files and the post files present different
                    problems. In regard to the lot files you can get some idea of their use in the
                    very first chapter here in this 1942 volume I that you have on the “Declaration
                    of the United Nations.” We compiled that story originally from the regular
                    central files. It was obviously incomplete. Mr. Carlton Savage worked closely
                    with the Secretary on that, and I called him and he said he had a considerable
                    body of documents that had never been sent to the central files, and you will
                    note in the section here on the “Declaration of the United Nations” a memoranda
                    by Mr. Carlton Savage[.] Now those are all taken from his office.</p>
                <p>We sent these particular memorandums to the central files and had a file number
                    put on, so you would not know from reading this that we had not gotten them from
                    the central files. We didn’t do that to cover up, but so that a reader seeing
                    this document, if he wants to go to the original, would know where to find it—so
                    we had a copy put in the central files. That illustrates the lot files where
                    negotiations are carried on by an office, and a record of those negotiations are
                    not sent to the central files. And in some cases we find the central files
                    incomplete, and we have to go to the lot files.</p>
                <p>Now in regard to the post files, theoretically we should not need to go to those
                    except perhaps for checking or getting material for footnotes or something.
                    Because if any subject is important, it comes in the range of major decisions of
                    the Department of State, and the embassy would not be acting on its own
                    authority; the policy would be outlined in the instructions from the Department,
                    which should be in the Department files. If it is important enough to be a
                    foreign relations subject, the action should be reported by the embassy to the
                    Department, and so will be in the files. So we do not find the post files as
                    valuable except in some cases where there are missing records and we can trace
                    them in the post files. And then sometimes as a Department instruction when it
                    is not clear what action was taken from the reports that come in, we can check
                    in the post files to find that. Now that is just roughly the use we make of
                    these files.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I would like to add one word before Mr. Slany speaks. In the
                    conference files we made no distinction between use of the index files or the
                    lot files. We couldn’t, because, for instance in the index files of the
                    Department of State there were about four papers under Yalta—Miss Bourne will
                    bear me out—and these did not include the Bohlen minutes. So if you look at the
                    Yalta file you will see Bohlen’s papers, Mathew papers, Hiss papers, and several
                    others which are all outlined.</p>
                <p>Incidentally, instead of having these indexed we did run the explicit head notes
                    of the files that they came from because we were accused under the gun of some
                    people of covering up if belatedly we had these things taken out of their little
                    cubbyhole caches and indexed as though they had always been in the central files
                    of the Department. This was a peculiar case.</p>
                <p>Otherwise, you can—if it is just a few papers you would ordinarily have them
                    indexed when you run across them. But during the war this problem grew to such
                    tremendous proportions that it isn’t generally feasible to have them just
                    indexed.</p>
                <p>On post files, there is one notable exception to what Ralph has said, although
                    that is generally true—used only for checking. But in the case of conferences
                    where conferences took place overseas, where people from the mission were
                    involved, as in the case of Tehran, where the Declaration of Tehran was worked
                    out at Tehran and never went to the Department of State because the President
                    was there, the post files and the personal files of people at the post were
                    invaluable on this. Jernegan[?] was the man who wrote it. He went right from
                    Moscow to Tehran—never went to the Department at all. So you can never tell. We
                    have found in connection with conferences that no artificial distinctions were
                    reasonable at all as between index files and lot files, or personal papers,
                    so-called, or post drafts. Wherever the story led us, we went. Now this is the
                    extreme position. But I thought you would like to know how it worked out.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The reason this is such a problem is that the post files particularly
                    are so enormous and the lot files too—some ll00 cases of them, 20,000 feet—and
                    if they are systematically searched it does extend a great deal the time
                    required for a compilation of these volumes. And we don’t have the same sort of
                    adequate leads to them as we do in the lot files.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It is a long job.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>But some of you individual staff members get up and explain—give your view and
                    your experience on this—Slany, and Stauffer and Fine and the others.</p>
                <p>MR. SLANY: In the case of the post files I suspect that the staff members are
                    tending in the war years and post war years to place a rather increasing use
                    upon them and reliance upon them, because of the difficulties that have arisen
                    in using the central decimal files, the increasing frequency with which
                    important documents are missing in the files, have been borrowed from the files,
                    have been returned to the operating desk for their use, and never again returned
                    to the central files. We found that often the post files, which are in many
                    cases bound and indexed according to the Foreign Service decimal system, serve
                    as a kind of backstop, and in many cases can facilitate a more swift appraisal
                    of the material, since you have the post record of the kind of telegrams and
                    dispatches that they received, the kind of notes that they exchanged with the
                    governments to which they were accredited. In some cases the post files are on
                    some specific issues, they have a complete record, whereas the decimal files for
                    one reason or another have gaps, missing documents for one reason or another. So
                    there is that particular use of the post files.</p>
                <p>Many of the staff members when considering the compilation of a particular
                    country accumulate these post files among their papers as a guide, as a source
                    of the original document, the original note that happened to be handed to our
                    representative to be correct readings, but also to find in the file a complete
                    rundown of the papers that may have been used, which may have become scattered
                    by the indexer when the papers arrived here in the Department.</p>
                <p>There are incidents—Herb Fine can elaborate on that—when the post files have been
                    the prime source of information. I am thinking on the China volumes that you
                    might recognize the use of the Marshall papers.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Do you want to say anything, Herb?</p>
                <p>MR. FINE: Well, I think I subscribe to everything that Mr. Slany has said. I
                    think the last point he mentioned was on these Marshall mission files, where the
                    Department index files had virtually nothing to do with Marshall’s mission in
                    China at all. Fortunately, we were able to get hold of a lot file which
                    contained all of the original papers that the Marshall mission gathered itself,
                    and they were used tremendously in the compilation of those volumes, or there
                    would have been no story at all on this whole mission.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: On what mission did you say?</p>
                <p>MR. FINE: The George Marshall mission to China, ’45 and ’46. I think it is a fair
                    statement to make— that there would have been no compilation of our story worth
                    anything if these files had not come to our attention.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Miss Bourne is here, Mr. Chairman. She is in charge over there in
                    Records Management, and I think we ought to hear from her.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: I was very much interested to hear what they had to say about these
                    post files, because I have been convinced that not enough use has been made
                    about the files since they have been here. When we discussed the Robert Murphy
                    files, we brought in from Vichy and Algiers Robert Murphy’s files since
                    1951.</p>
                <p>It seems to me in many of these cases we may pick up some of these files. In this
                    case it might be in the War Department post files, where they might not be here
                    in the files of the Department of State itself. I think we certainly are
                    bringing in a great deal of material on our international reorganization
                    material. These combined boards—the Department of State, the U. S. Government,
                    State Governments, have only copies of some of these things, and you know well
                    our storage problems on some of these things. I think the lot files are
                    extremely valuable.</p>
                <p>You, of course, know what we have been doing this past year to get some of this
                    material where it belongs in the central files. I think a lot of this goes back
                    to the way the Department’s records are kept. That is, we have a different
                    system here in the Department’s central files than we are using in our Foreign
                    Service posts. As Mr. Slany has indicated, you have a much more concentrated
                    collection of information on any country or area in your post files than you
                    will ever be able to pull together even with the indexes to the central files,
                    and for that reason we have continued to bring in material, although I might say
                    we have been criticized because we are bringing in material which should be
                    duplicated in the Department.</p>
                <p>I don’t know whether they would be interested to know, but as you know we are
                    working— I have a recommendation going up the line for a uniform file system for
                    the Department and the Foreign Service. I think that this is really the only
                    answer to most of the problems that you people have today. When we have such a
                    system, even these offices will be keeping their records (if we can get the plan
                    approved) by the same system as the central files in the Department, and also in
                    the Foreign Service. Then, certainly, there should be more duplication. You
                    wouldn’t have to bring as many records back. But they would be organized in a
                    way that you people need to use them. That would apply to all. Our report is
                    just at the printers now, and we hope we are going to get the inspectors to
                    recommend it and move ahead with this project. Whether there is money to do it
                    or not is something else again.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: How would you implement it in the offices?</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: The system has to be mandatory at the highest level of the
                    Department obviously.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Who is going to see to it that it is mandatory? This whole lot
                    system has grown up by accidents and lack of manpower and initiative.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: It grew up largely during the war years because you had such a
                    tremendous decentralization of the Department as it grew and people were
                    scattered in different buildings, and they began keeping their own records—that
                    plus the fact that you even have this decentralization in the post. And partly
                    because the systems may not be adequate, and you have a lot of untrained
                    secretaries, and the offices have been keeping their own collections because
                    they can’t get the kind of service they want from the central files or the
                    secretaries. So, again I think it goes back to a decent file system and trained
                    personnel, and once we have that why you people should be able to move ahead a
                    lot faster.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: That’s all on the record, is it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You are trying to get these lot files indexed, and put in the central
                    index files.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: That is correct. We have large quantities of files here that we know
                    contain probably 75% to 80% duplication of documents that are in the central
                    files of the Department already. And this past year we did work with Mr. Noble
                    to set up a working group to try and clear certain types of these lots for what
                    we call screening so that we could go through and remove documents that should
                    have been sent to the central files, and notes have been written to get them
                    back where they really belong, and get them indexed so they would be available
                    and eliminating much of the useless material that is in these lots, so that
                    would actually reduce the amount of time the FO people really need to do their
                    research.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Are these lot files physically scattered around in many places?</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: No. They are in the record service center. We have had a building
                    two miles distance and we are in the process of liquidating that and moving what
                    we can down here into this building. Unfortunately, our basement space in this
                    building is not available. That, in itself, should expedite some of the
                    research—when we get everything we need into one building for the first time in
                    years.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: If we had an extra half hour we would go up there and show you that
                    vast collection of these boxes.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: I think it would discourage them completely. To show you some of the
                    problems: we haven’t even had elevator service in that building since early in
                    August—it broke down, so we have had to carry the files down from the third
                    floor. Most of these lot files are on the third floor. And since the building is
                    to be torn down, nobody I am sure intends to fix the elevator. It is a terrific
                    problem.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I have heard some of the researchers say that some of these lot files
                    are peculiarly valuable because they are organized on a particular subject.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: That’s right. It is true. Many briefing books— We found an excellent
                    sample a few Saturdays ago, where a complete story of one of these South
                    American conferences had been put together in a book, and it would be a shame to
                    tear that thing apart. It did have some original papers which normally would be
                    in the central files, but a lot of the other stuff would be completely torn
                    apart under the central file procedure. But we left it, and identified on our
                    central control document so we would know where it could be found.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Does anybody else want to comment on this problem?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That shows you we have a problem.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It certainly does.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: The question was raised, I think by Mr. Goodrich, of the post-war
                    planning papers. This is a vast lot. Perhaps you would say the largest single
                    lot outside of the central files.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: I am not sure which one you are referring to, but on the collection
                    of Foreign Ministers files we have been working more than a year now. We started
                    the project I don’t know how many years ago—trying to pull together the council
                    of Foreign Ministers material, which is some of the most valuable material we
                    have. Now we have more than 200 feet. We have pulled this material from posts
                    from lot files, and everybody that we talked to thought they had a complete set.
                    Nobody has a complete set. In fact, we still don’t have an absolutely complete
                    set. But it certainly is growing, and I think certainly will be one of the most
                    valuable collections we have. Of course, we are only going to have one copy, and
                    it is such a valuable thing we won’t be able to let people borrow things out of
                    it. They will have to use it there to preserve the integrity of the file, but it
                    is certainly useful.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: The problem that you raised before was planning papers, post-war
                    planning papers—Dumbarton Oaks, Bretton Woods, PICAO and ICAO and all the rest.
                    This is a separate lot file all its own. Those papers have never been put into
                    the index files of the Department. They are separate, and there are some
                    advantages in that. But these two questions tie together here on the utilization
                    of lot material, and whether planning papers, which never entered into action,
                    should be reflected in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>; and, if so, to
                    what extent. There was a whole outfit where you always worked with the
                    geographer during boundaries, and boundaries and alternates, “A” through “Z”
                    none of which ever saw any action.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Any other comment by any of the staff here, or any member of the
                    committee on this subject. [Silence] If there is not, I think we might turn to
                    the next point that is raised by Mr. Noble’s memorandum.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We appreciate very much the work that Miss Bourne and her staff are
                    doing on that.</p>
                <p>MISS BOURNE: We are just sorry we can’t do it a little faster for you.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If you look at the memorandum you will find at the bottom of page 6
                    the heading “C. Background Papers” and it goes over to pages 7 and 8.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I suggest, Mr. Chairman, we might leave that instead until tomorrow
                    morning, because we want you to read this afternoon certain excerpts or portions
                    here which will put you in a better position to discuss the question
                    intelligently.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: All right. Then we would come to “II. Foreign Policy Papers in
                    Other Agencies.” We have had a little discussion of that. What would your
                    suggestion be with regards to that, Bernard? Do you want commentary?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I would just suggest that Mrs. Cassidy, who has spent a good deal of
                    time up there and works on them, might make a brief statement on the way it
                    works and the problem.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Mrs. Cassidy.</p>
                <p>MRS. CASSIDY: Excuse me.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: On the “Presidential Papers.”</p>
                <p>MRS. CASSIDY: I found a great many papers up there which are in our own files.
                    But from our own files I found leads to certain papers which were not to be
                    found here, but papers which the President made his notations on there and gave
                    to officials of other Governmental Agencies. I found compilations of papers on
                    certain subjects there that were a great convenience too. And the difficulty of
                    course is that there is no central index to the papers, and it is necessary to
                    go through many, many boxes in order to find what you want.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: But you found many papers to which there were no leads in the
                    Department?</p>
                <p>MRS. CASSIDY: Yes, some papers about which I knew nothing. And I made notes of
                    some papers which of course meant it was most valuable to go up there after
                    exhausting research here of our own files; otherwise, it would be almost
                    hopeless to go through a great mass of material and to keep a coordinated
                    picture in your mind of what you were searching for, and what is essential to
                    fill in the papers which you already found here to complete the story.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: “Up there”—you mean Hyde Park?</p>
                <p>MRS. CASSIDY: Yes, at Hyde Park. We haven’t had any experience on the Truman
                    Library as yet.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: On page 10, I really am shocked by the paragraph about whether the
                    Government Agencies have access prior to individuals. I certainly hope the
                    Bureau of Public Affairs will fight, fight, fight.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t quite get there what you are saying, Bernard. W[h]at is the
                    problem there?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is the Truman Library, where the position taken—as we interpret a
                    letter from the Director of the Library, Phil Brooks—is that we are on the same
                    basis as private citizens, and that if these papers are restricted they are
                    restricted to us as well as they are to private citizens.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, I am on the Board of the Truman Library.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Wonderful!</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That, I will look into.</p>
                <p>MR. FINE: Mr. Brooks is under the same boss that the Hyde Park Library is, and
                    why does Hyde Park tackle us differently?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We are investigating that matter right now, and we are having
                    conversations with the Archives on the subject, and I don’t know whether the
                    Archives feel they can interpret. It is a matter partly, I suppose, of
                    interpreting President Truman’s—what’s the word for that?—the instrument by
                    which he turned this over to the Government. Of course, he could have turned all
                    of them or none of them over to the Government. If he says this particular group
                    of papers is restricted, why what does that mean? Does it mean, as far as he is
                    concerned, that it is restricted to Government personnel as well as to others?
                    He has a perfect right to say that no one should see them, including the
                    Government—that’s the fact.</p>
                <p>So it comes down, I suppose, to a question really of interpreting what Truman
                    meant in that transfer of his papers to the Government. He has kept out a fairly
                    large group of papers, which Dick Dougall and I had a look at back in 1956 in
                    connection with the Potsdam papers. But he is still keeping those out, as I
                    understand it, from the Library. And apparently, aside from that, there are some
                    papers which are in the Library, but which are still restricted.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Does Phil’s interpretation come from talking with Mr. Truman at
                    least?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Mr. Truman still keeps his own interpretation; Mr. Roosevelt
                    doesn’t.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: According to Herbert Feis he was to see them. And Truman was told by
                    Phil Brooks that he couldn’t see them, and Truman had to apologize to Feis and
                    say he couldn’t see them.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I might say that in our regular annual volumes we have asked
                    for—I would not guarantee these files—let us say roughly about 30 documents from
                    the Truman Library, and we have received one document I believe it was—or was it
                    two?—I think it is one.</p>
                <p>MR. SLANY: One.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: And the reply was simply that the others were not available.
                    Presumably, they could not be located. Some of these were documents we got leads
                    to in Truman’s memoires. They were top-level correspondence with Stalin; I think
                    some with Churchill, which definitely one should have every reason to think
                    would be in the Truman Library.</p>
                <p>MR. DOUGALL: They are still probably in Mr. Truman’s hands. Certainly, if we
                    hadn’t had access to his papers before this Library setup was done we wouldn’t
                    have Potsdam in page proof now.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You have had no trouble with Kahn on the Roosevelt papers?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: No, we haven’t had any trouble with him.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Are you on that one, too?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: No.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We discussed that with him and he says that, frankly, we see
                    everything except the very personal things.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, to say you can’t find things, it is pretty hard to
                    answer that remark, again.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Sounds like Near Eastern archives.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Mr. Parks is going up to a meeting of the Southern Historical at
                    Tulsa, I believe, and he is going to stop by there to make a more thorough
                    examination of the “key” position as it were, if that’s the right word.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, that is what you had in mind, that Dick mentions. Isn’t it,
                    really?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That’s correct.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would be glad to have any other expressions of opinion. It seems
                    to me that it is very fortunate in the compilation. But perhaps the more people
                    that talk about it the better it would be.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We commend it to your attention as a member of the commission.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Does it meet annually?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. The date has not been fixed for 1961, as yet. And I don’t know
                    whether it will be the right time for me or not, if I go to Salzburg, but it
                    probably will.</p>
                <p>Well, now, let’s go on, if there is nothing more to be said on that. I think it
                    is good. You have something on the “Defense papers”? We have really discussed
                    that a little bit. Do you want some more comment on that?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think we have pretty well exhausted it. I take it you want us to use
                    them as far as we “reasonably can”, whatever that means—within the realm of, I
                    would say, our concern and our responsibility, rather than just responsibility
                    as Ralph says.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, the next point that is raised there—we are looking at
                    pages 12 and 13—we have the very important question I think of the National
                    Security Council. Now what is your experience on the National Security Council,
                    or have you reached the point where it—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We haven’t exhausted our inquiries there. Several years ago we had
                    occasion to get to talk it over with the Secretary with reference to a few
                    papers, and they were very, very cagey about this. And quite recently a member
                    of the staff was over, and we mentioned this to him and he looked rather shocked
                    and thought if this matter was suggested over there it would cause quite some
                    raising of eyebrows and so forth, but he thought it might be well to mention it
                    now because after a year or so they might have become accustomed to the idea. It
                    is our hope that at least their final decisions of the NSC may be made
                    available. I can’t for a moment believe that we would have access to the
                    recommendations, say, of the Defense to the NSC, or the recommendations perhaps
                    of the Department—I don’t know—particularly of Defense. But if we could get at—
                    What I think we ought to aim at at least is the final decision, or the final
                    recommendation, whatever you call it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That won’t become relevant for a little while. I mean this is
                    something to work at.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That’s right. I think it ought to be worked at.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Is it known what the NSC actually records? Does it record actually
                    much more than what is said?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They have, of course, these papers that come in from the various
                    agencies, particularly State, Defense, and Treasury. They have those, and then
                    they have debates and— What is the other subsidiary group that works with
                    them?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: OCB.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: OCB.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: I wonder how much of that is made a record.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Certainly, it is recorded. No doubt about that, the discussion.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I think I know what you are driving at. A good deal of these
                    inter-agency differences of opinion are worked out in the staff before the paper
                    is laid before the National Security Council. There may be a minority view which
                    is still held, but the original papers that go on, which discuss the different
                    points of view, are not so published to begin with. But the staff itself works
                    it out—Gordon Gray works out most of the problems before it comes up. It is only
                    those that they can’t work out which have to come up there, at least I have
                    never seen the other papers—these papers that have been submitted to the
                    National Security Council.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Of course, another thing that is going to become terrifically
                    important is that all the papers on our United Nations involvement— What papers
                    should we expect ultimately to be included in, say, our instructions to the
                    people in New York? That is something we have got to work out with them, and it
                    is, of course, terribly important. That is something we haven’t done yet.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The Office of Strategic Services has large files.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is another point.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We are coming to that.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Do you want to come to it now?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think you ought to read that first. Tomorrow morning will be the big
                    show for that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, are there any other comments on these particular pages of
                    Bernard’s report? We have taken over what he says with regard to the National
                    Security Council.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I might say we are getting to the years in ’42 and so on when the
                    intelligence operations of the U. S. Government begin to play a large part in
                    foreign policy decisions. So we might face this as “a man that is with us from
                    now on.”</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t see here how we can avoid giving very, very substantial
                    modifications that have got to be made in the technique as the volume of papers
                    increases, if we are going to do the really important things, and without
                    allowing the secondary things to become more significant than they really
                    are.</p>
                <p>Well, do you want to go on to the editorial problems? On these, again, I think we
                    want to discuss them. I would be glad to have any opinions from members of your
                    staff with regard to them. You have put the point—the question up here with
                    regard to several matters that we are ready to discuss, I am sure, in our
                    private session.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There are differences of view in our own staff, and although I think
                    neither is an extreme view, I don’t think anybody—I know no one expects to put
                    everything on a chronological basis—that would be too absurd. And some feel
                    though that they are broken up into too many stories, and there should be a
                    certain consolidation, and I don’t know that anybody is opposed to that. I don’t
                    believe you are, are you Ralph, to a certain consolidation?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Well, each is ad hoc, whether a story should be broken up or not.
                    I am absolutely opposed to throwing everything into the hopper in chronological
                    order. That isn’t the way Department offices work. No working desk officer would
                    just have a chronological file of all the documents coming to him. He,
                    naturally, when he is workin[g] on it—he would arrange it by subjects. I think
                    in regard to this Volume I of ’42 that we reviewed— I could see, for example, we
                    have here an “Emergency Repatriation Program” and then we have here “Exchange of
                    Officials and Non-officials.” I haven’t reviewed that carefully to see whether
                    that should have been consolidated or not. But you could perhaps put those two
                    stories into one, and arrange it. But I think you would agree that almost all of
                    these stories published in this volume should be by subjects and not thrown in
                    together with the other material.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Isn’t it the case, Bernard, to answer the question involved here,
                    but substantially on page 15—I think that seems to me the reasonable way to go
                    at the problem. But I think in all of these cases where we can get the views of
                    those here, of course, it is highly desirable. I don’t want to curtail
                    discussion in any way.</p>
                <p>MR. LE0POLD: This is this paragraph about the chronological table.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I simply want to ask a question for information. For example, take
                    “General” here at the beginning of this volume. What is the process by which you
                    come to a decision that these are the particular topics that you wanted to list?
                    Do you first have a body of documentary material, and then try to organize it,
                    or do you look over the material and decide “these are the more important
                    subjects that are covered this year, and we are going to assemble documents
                    under these particular subjects.”</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Yes, we look over the material and decide what subjects should be
                    treated, and then we compile on those subjects.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Presumably, then, there are subjects that are not treated. I mean
                    your process of selection is carried to that extent.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Obviously, the purpose is to treat all major subjects of
                    diplomacy. If something is so minor in importance that we do not think it rates
                    publication, why we don’t put it in.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I raise that question because it seems to me as we look ahead that
                    this is going to be an increasingly difficult problem.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We want to talk about this at length. But it seems to me that a
                    high degree of selectivity has probably got to be aimed at over the long
                    pull.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I would think your reading of this volume would be a very good basis
                    for a judgment on your part on this particular question.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, I don’t— One hesitates to express dogmatic opinions where one
                    hasn’t thought very deeply about it. But I don’t myself feel on an off-hand
                    judgment that 180 pages on “Agreement with enemy countries on the exchange of
                    officials and non-officials” is valuable to that degree. Now it is a question on
                    which I have an open mind. But it seems to me that one wonders about that a
                    little bit.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: But have you in reading this volume felt that some of these items,
                    particularly in the second half— I think the first part is obviously more
                    according to subject; the second half is not necessarily so exclusively on that
                    basis.</p>
                <p>Now I thought possibly you might have reached some conclusions on this question
                    as to whether the chronology could have been applied on a somewhat wider basis
                    than it is.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I was raising a somewhat different question. On the point you
                    raise, I wouldn’t want to see you depart too much from the present practice. I
                    think it is desirable to have sub headings.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: My feeling is that I think in general the technique embodied is
                    right, technically speaking. What do you say about it—on this question of
                    chronology I mean?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Of course, I have the feeling that some of these subjects are pretty
                    much determined by what has gone before. You carry on the story from one year to
                    another. But I have always—and I think my memory is correct on this—raised this
                    matter about the Table of Contents at the beginning, and it was abandoned with
                    what— the 1932 volumes, or something like that.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: And I realize the number of pages that it consumes, and the work
                    that is involved, but I have always been taken for this [indicating
                    memorandum].</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We are getting along here pretty well going over this memorandum
                    today, but this may be more relevant. What are your chances for getting more
                    funds? How are we going to look at this when we make recommendations? We have to
                    think of it as a practical problem down at the other end of the avenue. Is the
                    general feeling of opinion that it is favorable to further expansion, or is it
                    negative, or where is it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Ed, would you like to comment on that?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, let’s be frank about this. Since both parties have gone on
                    record for an expanded information program, I think the chances of more funds
                    being allocated to the general area of public affairs are pretty good. Now how
                    much control we can exercise over that in getting it into this sort of thing is
                    another question. This is very hard to answer at this point. I think the feeling
                    is that we probably will get more funds in our particular area. But the question
                    is whether they will allow us to sink it into historical volumes, or give us
                    very specific directives. They are much more interested in other things, of
                    course.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is this man Rooney the man you have to deal with?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Yes, but I would prefer not to talk on that level. That’s
                    inevitable.</p>
                <p>[Discussion off the record.]</p>
                <p>But I do think I am talking here about the higher level with greater emphasis on
                    this whole field of information. It is true, whichever party wins the election,
                    the question is how much we can push to allocate it the way we think it is
                    sensibly allocated.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: How much to allocate for historical information as compared to
                    other things more current at home. You can’t tell.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I can’t tell that. But I think we will have more money.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Mr. Chairman, I would like to suggest that on the basis of this rather
                    careful survey that we are making, and your reading and experience during the
                    past few years, you will be able to make a report emphasizing the relevant
                    aspects of this which might be quite useful. Your reports have been useful in
                    the Department already. I think it is quite useful for them. Don’t you agree,
                    Ed, it might be useful? If you said, “Here are the problems which we are up
                    against ....” And, obviously, the staff we have now is quite incapable of
                    meeting any of these additional things that probably ought to be done. They are
                    already saying, “We are falling behind in our staff because of the papers inside
                    the Department, including the lot files and the post files.” There is some
                    feeling of frustration even on that score because of the additional length of
                    time with the means required.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: It seems to me in that connection that the thing we should
                    concentrate on and would be most useful to you people is to try to indicate over
                    a period of the next, well, 15 or 20 years—from 1940 on—just what we think
                    should be our policy with regard to the scope of coverage and that sort of
                    thing. I think it would be more useful for us to look ahead than to be concerned
                    with so many details.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You take all of those facts and they can be tremendously
                    important.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Dexter, just on something that Bernard said there. I know you don’t
                    want to come out with this, but is it possible that the type of report we make
                    this year should differ from what we have done before? I think when we get
                    together late Saturday morning, as it was last year or— We sort of look back and
                    say “What did we recommend last year, and should we continue the same?” I wonder
                    whether the whole format of our report—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It seems to me that the answer to that ought to be “Yes.” I think
                    we are going to face a very difficult problem here—the two aspects of it. It
                    seems to me we have got to recognize the increasing volume of work which means
                    more money. But we won’t get more money if we won’t put more attention on the
                    essentiality and relevance. Those two things go together. Of course, that is for
                    us to discuss. Perhaps this isn’t the time to talk about it.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: One thing that makes it more difficult is the approach on the Hill.
                    The reason for that has got to be explained.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You are going to have more clearance problems, aren’t you?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is the combination now of the clearance problem and the problem of
                    the Department and outside that causes this drop in output.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: [Inaudible] Mr. Chairman, it seems to me, obviously, that we can’t
                    emphasize things.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You can say we have studied these problems and we know that.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Exactly.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: We did last year, Bob, suggest that we did think increased personnel
                    was necessary.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: I know that, but you can’t say how much.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Nor did we really spell out in our public report last year; we did
                    in the private report. We didn’t spell out in the public report, on these
                    problems of clearance, so that somebody on the Hill would understand why Bernard
                    said your output has declined.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: It seems to me that in that connection we have got to give more
                    attention in our public report to the difficulties you are up against and give
                    expression to the interest which the scholars whom we represent have in the work
                    that you are doing, and having it done along certain lines. Because I think we
                    have got to do something more than just advise you. We have got to serve as a
                    channel for interesting other people in what is going on here and building up
                    pressures outside.</p>
                <p>Now this last year Clarence and myself were unable to get the public report
                    published in the <hi rend="italic">American Political Science Review</hi>
                    because it was too general and so on. I think we have got to have something very
                    specific and more detailed here that will interest our respective clientele and
                    stir them up a bit.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Rooney will question any increase in funds or for the Historical
                    Division unless you come up with a really new approach to this. That’s the only
                    way he will listen to it, and then he will argue you it down too. But his
                    tendency is to hold all the funds exactly as last year, and even, if possible,
                    to get them lower. He never looks at any new expansion or challenge. And you
                    have got an awful battle to get it through the Bureau of the Budget first.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You have to consider first the lay reaction to this as well as the
                    professional reaction to this, because you are dealing with Congressmen and
                    Senators as well as historians.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: One other thing: I think you have got to approach it also from the
                    point of view that you can’t really expect to get the papers out day after
                    tomorrow. That is to say, there has got to be a lag of apparently this present
                    length, I think. Because we recognize, as well as our friends in the policy desk
                    recognize, that there are problems which make it impossible to publish the
                    documents very soon after occurrence. But even at that lag, if we are going to
                    do our job, we have got to have additional resources.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. But there is a general consensus, isn’t it, that 20 years is
                    about right?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: To be very honest, the trend inside the Department in the
                    political offices is longer. The trend is longer. Our relations are getting so
                    ramified and so complicated that there is a very strong feeling—I am talking now
                    outside of the Secretary’s staff meeting as recently as yesterday—that the
                    period ought to be longer. It is too sensitive.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, we probably feel, by committee record, that some of this
                    business is a little absurd. On this China business—not that we seem to make any
                    dint on anybody—it seems to me as much as is known is known about General Chiang
                    Kai-shek and his way of doing business.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I wouldn’t disagree with you. And this was not the particular
                    point of issue in this discussion. I agree this is a special case, and it has
                    its own unhappy history.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: And the antibiotics are working against you here. Twenty years in
                    the early 19th century and the old crowd was all gone; now they are back in.</p>
                <p>MR. PERKINS: I might say it seems to me people don’t come up with any specific
                    cases to justify that point of view. A good illustration are the Yalta volumes.
                    Now they did get into more or less of a hassle and mess on the Yalta volumes.
                    The criticism made and the harm done, if there was any, was with regard to the
                    particular method and circumstances of the release. As far as the content of
                    that material is concerned, put out very much under what we are doing in our
                    annual volumes, as far as I know there has been no harm done because those
                    records have become public.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I haven’t heard of any revolutionary change in our foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: That would be certainly as sensitive a set of documents as you
                    probably could find.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: In the case of a volume of that kind and the fact that it deals
                    with such a wide historical interest—does it make it easier to get it out?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The demands in the political campaign of ’52, you see.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course, yes.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: While we are speaking about this lag and so on, what is the status
                    of these so-called current problems? There hasn’t been any since 1956, has
                    there?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: That is correct. The 1957 volume will be out in a very few weeks. The
                    1958 volume is on the way. Actually, that is a larger undertaking than we had
                    thought. It really has extraordinary coverage. It is extraordinarily
                    well-organized, as I think you will admit— “a most useful document” everybody
                    says that uses it. But it is still more than a one-man job.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I bet it is.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: What we have to expect is about a three-year lag on that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We are going to try to get it more close than that—a one-year lag.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is pretty good timing. The ’57 is out, you say. And the ’58
                    you say is in what stage?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Oh, it is practically compiled, and I don’t think it has gone to the
                    press.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: No clearance problems?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: No clearance problems.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: No clearance problems. It is already to publish. I quite agree that
                    is extraordinarily useful, but I am not sure that it has made the impact on the
                    professionals that it should have. I was put over the grill by the committee of
                    the American Historical Association because I represent them on this committee.
                    They said, “What is going on up there in your advisory committee?” This was the
                    Committee on the Historians of the Federal Government. They weren’t hostile. I
                    said, “Look, take this current volume.” Some people started scribbling down as
                    though they never heard of it before.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This isn’t history, is it?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: This is a wedding of disciplines.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We think it is.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: But I think at least in the historical profession it has—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I get occasional letters asking urgently to be sent copies.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It is surely available.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: And in our review of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series I make a point of calling attention to it right in the review, so people
                    are aware of it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You correct me if I am wrong. There is one other question here that
                    I think we ought to discuss in the memorandum. There are quite a number of small
                    matters, but I think they can be kept for our private session. I would like to
                    hear more on paragraph 1, page 16. I would like to get some opinions from the
                    members of the staff here, from which of you write editorial notes, on which you
                    use more extensively and so forth in situations. Would you like to comment on
                    that?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, this problem of volume is one which, as you know, has been one
                    of our most serious problems, and the difficulties combined with that add to
                    that. The military, of course, have been able to come out— now they are going to
                    celebrate the appearance of the 50th volume in that series. We have, as you see,
                    put out 200 volumes. But, obviously, if we could follow somewhat the methods of
                    the military historians in some documents, we could greatly save space. Instead
                    of putting in many documents, if we could put in a very objective summary of
                    them, we could avoid the delicate question of clearance, and still give the gist
                    of the thing in many cases, we could save space. I feel that is a fair statement
                    of the case.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I have a very good reaction to that. I don’t know how the members
                    of the committee feel. That’s that paragraph on page 16.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I point out here that we have used this to an extent already—very,
                    very slight extent, in relation to the 1933 volumes, or in the 1933 volumes. We
                    left out a whole section of the materials on that Chamizal case involving the
                    boundary between Texas and Mexico, and explained quite frankly as a matter of
                    fact—didn’t we Ralph?—what it was all about. And we managed to get clearance
                    from policy officers, and we are doing that somewhat in the Volume V of 1940.
                    That’s where we have to leave out. But I think we can go beyond that, and
                    actually summarize a number of papers, and save more space. But that’s something
                    that needs experimenting with, and needs discussion I think.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Is there on your staff any opposition to that technique? Is there
                    feeling of difficulty about it?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I haven’t heard any. Ralph, what do you say?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Well, of course, you can see we have two different situations we
                    are speaking about here. Now one is the kind of situation we have, for example,
                    actually at that time on clearance—they didn’t want to even mention such a
                    place. We obviously could not summarize the documents. All we did say was that
                    there were negotiations with regard to water boundaries, which we were operating
                    on, because the negotiations had not been completed.</p>
                <p>Another case in point is the documentation on the boundary dispute between Peru
                    and Ecuador where there actually was military action taken, and we had to, in
                    clearance, leave out a very sizeable chunk of documentation. Now all we said
                    about that was that military operations took place, and we are leaving this
                    out.</p>
                <p>MR. WILSON: Did the reader expect that he could read one day the full story?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: That would bring up a question of going back years past and
                    digging stuff up. I should think probably not. I should think probably some day
                    the papers will be open for research.</p>
                <p>Now the other case would be to save space on a matter which we did not think
                    justified printing a long set of documentation, where we put in a note that
                    would simply cover the substance and perhaps give some citations.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: And that you don’t find objectionable necessarily?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Now if we really feel that the documentation is not of sufficient
                    importance to really warrant giving a great deal of space to it—</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This would, I think, greatly relieve the clearance problem.
                    Because you have a whole series of documents on the subject, and new names get
                    injected, and that’s where the problems arise.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Some of these questions we have are on personalities who are still
                    alive and might be bothered.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Isn’t there a middle ground on that though. As I understood Ralph’s
                    answer it was that where you came to a subject that there was a lot of
                    documentation, which might or might not involve names, that you would just have
                    a summary of the problem without printing any documents.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Of course, that is done—</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Now some time earlier I thought I heard the suggestion that you
                    would exercise greater selectivity on some documents and summarize the rest.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: In the first case, under Canada, you see, we have a long list of
                    executive agreements with Canada, 1942, for which we would merely print a
                    bracketed note citing executive agreements and United States stands. And we do
                    not print any correspondence. Some people know that such agreements were made,
                    but in that case we did not think the correspondence justified. Either we did
                    not have correspondence on them—because it was the State Department, naturally,
                    that drew up these agreements—or we did not think they were sufficiently
                    important to warrant printing correspondence.</p>
                <p>Now the other case, as you say, we could cut down. Of course, there is a serious
                    danger of running into the criticism, if we do it for the purpose of getting
                    over the stuff we can’t clear, that you are putting in these bracketed notes to
                    cover up. You see, in your bracketed note you can’t say anything very specific
                    about the nature of the material that is being omitted.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Wasn’t your point of view originally, however, that we were doing
                    this to save space—not to get rid of material that you couldn’t clear?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Now in that case, Dexter brought up the subject, for example, of
                    the exchange of officials and non-officials. Well, there the Department got into
                    somewhat of an operational procedure, and to tell the story extensively we had
                    to use lots of documentation.</p>
                <p>Now it may be from the standpoint of historical prospective that was not
                    necessary. Maybe it would have been sufficient to put in the agreements for
                    exchange and a bracketed note telling the substance. It might have been used. I
                    suppose that’s the kind of thing you mean.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That’s the kind of thing, without being dogmatic about it.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I still have the feeling that Ralph wants all or nothing—that either
                    you print a large section or you print a bracketed note. And I am trying to see
                    whether there is some little ground for the interest of saving space only.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: In the interest of saving space we probably would not have too
                    much difficulty to draft a bracketed note. It would be pretty hard where the
                    reason we are leaving it out is a clearance problem. And in those cases I don’t
                    think our policy officers would appreciate it if we say we are leaving this out
                    because we can’t get it cleared.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do your clearance problems tend to be longer in time, as well as
                    more numerous?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: As we go along?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You mean longer in time?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I mean by that is the time it takes to get a thing cleared
                    increasing?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Would you agree that it has, Mr. Phillips?</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: Yes. I mean take this Peru-Ecuador thing. It is a very hot issue
                    now today.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Not in the paper, but behind the scenes at least.</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: The Ecuadorians have denounced, not officially but unofficially,
                    the protocol and the present President of Peru was the President of Peru when
                    they had this war, and the documentation contains a great many derogatory
                    remarks made about him by our people, and, as one of the guarantors, anything we
                    say about the protocol guaranteeing the treaty is going to be taken wrong one
                    place or the other.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Both places probably.</p>
                <p>MR. PHILLIPS: Both places.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, I think we have some idea of how the problem shapes up.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think we ought to hear from a few more of our staff.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: There is a third type of editorial note we have heard about too, a
                    third type. Most examples already in print are in the Yalta volume. We know
                    about a meeting or discussion that took place and we have no document on it. We
                    put in an editorial note giving citations to authoritative private publications
                    or other official publications in lieu of our own documents we don’t have.</p>
                <p>MR. CHURCHILL: There is one more variation about this and that is issued in the
                    footnote. To considerable degree, in the compilation on the Soviet Union, I have
                    used perhaps a considerable number of footnotes which I have used only as an
                    excerpt from some other document, so that I don’t have to print the whole thing,
                    but can take out the point that applies to one in a document that is being
                    printed. And that has been done I think rather more in the collections on the
                    Soviet Union to hold them down in space and to cut out a whole lot of other
                    information or comment which is not necessary. So that, on the whole, that has
                    resulted in a considerable reduction in space. It does not reduce the time
                    required, however, to put these things in readable form, and with perfectly
                    honest excision of the point that applies, without the rest of the document
                    being show, which often is quite long.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Perhaps some such procedure would take care of one of the other
                    problems in clearance. You know we always get this argument when Bernard and I
                    go to talk to these boys about this: that the printing of the full document with
                    all of the ambassadors’ and ministers’ comments on the personality of the man he
                    is dealing with and so on will inhibit in the future frank reporting, and if he
                    knows that this in 20 years or less is going to be printed, what he has said, he
                    won’t be as frank as he is or should be. And this is a hard one to meet. But if
                    we could take the best document that describes the issue, and then fill it in
                    with footnotes or so on, it seems to me we would get away from a great many of
                    our clearance problems.</p>
                <p>MR. CHURCHILL: A good many times the things that I can excerpt are something that
                    will be of that nature. But by not printing the whole of it and just quoting a
                    few essential words, you get the sum and substance of it.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Look what the Army has brought out in their history series. I think
                    it is a beautiful illustration of how the documentary series, although more
                    solid, is a combination of straitjacket and anchor. They have been able to
                    describe, without difficulty, in page after page the top political strategic
                    decisions of these war-time conferences. We are still plugging along trying to
                    get the actual document out on it. We have a citation often, because there was
                    something elsewhere in the documents of no real consequence, but they wrote up
                    the gist of it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think our responsibility there is that whether or not we agree
                    with all those cantankerous people the digest means that some grisly facts have
                    been concealed. But that’s where we come in our educational function I think to
                    make people see, with any brains at all, that you can’t publish everything all
                    the time.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: One case that I recall was a 1939 volume that we discussed, and we
                    agreed that in one document we could put a brief three, four, or five lines
                    stating what the general trend was, and stating that it was a case that you
                    obviously couldn’t put the whole thing in.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It doesn’t offend me at all. It offends some people that don’t
                    understand the problem.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: It makes Ralph and his staff a problem. They have got to exercise
                    more judgment in the beginning as to what they can do or not do.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I don’t think everybody will be as charitable as Dexter in their
                    opinions of us. I can conceive we might be held up as first-class scoundrels. We
                    have to avoid giving the impression that when we do that it is just not to cover
                    up.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That’s true. And this is our experience where we can be helpful to
                    you.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Of course, our critics outside have a wrong impression of the
                    reasons why we leave out material. In most cases they think that the State
                    Department is up to some deviltry, or the Administration is up to some deviltry
                    and we are trying to cover up for them, which is not the case.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Well, has the criticism, say, in the last four years or so, been of
                    this nature? I thought it was a question of emphasis and present mindedness.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Different kind of deviltry.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Sheer incompetence, that’s all.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I mean they have either got to have extracts or 40 years—this is
                    what it is going to amount to in the time level.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: This Potsdam episode, so to speak, brought out these sorts of
                    criticism.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is an election year atmosphere you are working in. We have
                    had more correspondence from Senator Fulbright this year than for a long
                    time.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Maybe this point has been made, but coming back to this chapter on
                    the exchange of official and non-officials I wonder whether or not there are a
                    lot of documents that can be summarized for adequate purposes for the record.
                    And I don’t think there would be any problem there of concealment. No one is
                    going to be accused.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The question of abridgment is a question. There has been some
                    relationship whether the question can be made into a hot question by some
                    misguided person. I think abridgment would be regarded tolerantly where no great
                    political issue or emotion was involved.</p>
                <p>You think that you want to stand— We seem to be rambling a bit, but I think we
                    have covered the points we wanted to discuss. You think the decision you made—
                    We can’t communicate the files to individuals outside of the Department until
                    the books have been published, is that right?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, I think it is an unfortunate decision made necessary by the
                    circumstances. Obviously, we can’t afford to give out material that will be used
                    in the press in a sensational story. But if we took greater precautions.
                    Probably we may be partly to blame in not having said these must not be printed
                    until this volume is out. We didn’t have a contract, so to speak.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You would have to take that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: We would have to take that. Don’t you think so?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: We were forced to this decision, that is, in the release of August
                    23. Incidentally, the Secretary was down in San Jose at the time and I wrote it
                    here and sent it to him, and he approved it down there. But this makes Mr.
                    Berding and me very happy because we never were happy with this previous access
                    to certain people. In this case it was very bad. And it gave us the opportunity
                    to put the lid back on, which we had been forced to take off.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Of course, I think the historians generally agree that Herbert Feis
                    has done a fine job in doing the books he has done, and unfortunately his book
                    came out considerably ahead of our volume.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You see, Mr. Berding and I can’t make the distinction and say,
                    “Mr. Feis is a historian and responsible. Scotty Reston is not, and Marquis
                    Childs is not, or Walter Lippmann is not.” We are not going to do this. Thank
                    you very much. But this doesn’t hold water, you see—that there is one special
                    group. So we have just closed the door, and we are very happy to leave it closed
                    if you will let us.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: One point you made [to Mr. Kretzmann] and I think you [The Chairman]
                    made—that this effects the reporting. We have had a precise illustration of
                    that, or at least the threat of that.</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: Just on the question of how our policy publication might effect
                    the reporting and say memoranda of conversation that actually was stated, I have
                    talked to one or two Foreign Service Officers and this particularly in the
                    American Republics Area, where you can’t really pin them down. They say that “In
                    our talks when we record a conversation we do have a tendency now—and the way
                    they told it to me was somewhat general in the area—we will not put in that
                    memorandum of conversation what we said. In other words, the memorandum of
                    conversation will be blank in so far as what our man said to the other official.
                    For this very reason: that sometime it will be published.” I said, “Well, you
                    have a veto over these documents when it comes to you. I mean I wouldn’t want to
                    be your successor when I get your record to carry along.”</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: This is an extreme case, and I would like to consider this an
                    empty threat. I have heard similar ones. I think the Foreign Service Officer who
                    does that is remiss in his primary duties, and should be so disciplined if he
                    does. I have heard these arguments. I have chosen to consider them as sort of
                    empty threats. They don’t like the publications, Dick, I think that’s true in
                    ARA. Frankly, that isn’t the only hazardous profession.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Bernard suggests that we adjourn at this point and go down and see
                    the board on the operations and the—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The last section here is on planning, as you know. I know you are very
                    much interested in that, and our staff has set up a board which shows how it can
                    function, and I think you ought to see it and have it explained to you. Would
                    you like to go down and see it?</p>
                <p>Then just another word. We will have to be on this floor at one o’clock, the
                    members of the committee, and after that we will go down to the files and see a
                    demonstration of the operations. And then you will have time for reading here
                    and we will have the things here for you as soon after two o’clock as possible.
                    Then, we thought you might like to see some of the new areas of the building It
                    is really quite interesting. That will be around five o’clock, if you can get
                    your homework done.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Are you leaving classified papers here? If you are, we will have
                    to take steps.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: How about that, Gus?</p>
                <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: We will take care of that.</p>
                <p>[Whereupon, at 12:30 p.m., the meeting was adjourned.]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="saturday-session">
                <head>Transcript of November 5 Session of the 1960 Meeting of the Advisory Committee
                    on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 5, 1960<lb/> 9:05 a.m. to 12:10 p.m.</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p rend="underline">Members of the Committee:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Dexter Perkins, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Dr. Clarence A. Berdahl</item>
                    <item>Dr. Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                    <item>Dr. Fred H. Harrington</item>
                    <item>Dr. Richard W. Leopold</item>
                    <item>Dr. Philip W. Thayer</item>
                    <item>Mr. Robert R. Wilson</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Representing the Department of State:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Edwin N. J. Kretzmann, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>G. Bernard Noble, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Velma J. Cassidy, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Rogers P. Churchill, P/HO</item>
                    <item>John T. Dreyfuss, RAR/P</item>
                    <item>William M. Franklin, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Milan W. Jerabek, EUR</item>
                    <item>Gustave A. Nuermberger, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Ernest Ralph Perkins, P/HO</item>
                    <item>Richard I. Phillips, ARA</item>
                    <item>Robert M. Phillips, WST</item>
                    <item>Richard A. Poole, WST</item>
                    <item>Newton O. Sappington, P/HO</item>
                </list>
                <p>Reported by:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>V. Voce</item>
                </list>
                <p>[The Committee was reconvened at 9:05 a.m., Mr. Dexter Perkins presiding.]</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we want to spend a considerable part of the time this
                    morning in Executive Session. On the agenda for discussion as the first item,
                    however, is the study of the question regarding Departmental papers and we might
                    take a little time on that.</p>
                <p rend="underline">8. Discussion of Questions Involved in Reading of Department
                    Papers</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think all of us have read some of the papers and some of us have
                    read most of them. I don’t think we have found ourselves in disagreement with
                    the Department very often and, as far as the Latin American papers you want to
                    pay particular attention to—and in almost every case I went along with Ralph
                    Perkins and his point of view—we were shocked at the position of the CIA with
                    regard to the documents. It seems to me it was very skillfully answered by
                    Ralph. A great deal of material was excluded which is perfectly well known. But
                    perhaps some of the rest of the members of the committee will want to say
                    something about the documentation which we examined yesterday afternoon. Do you
                    want to comment, Clarence?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: No, I don’t think I have any comment.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We found, as a matter of fact, we were so much in agreement with
                    the Department that the time we spent on it was not altogether satisfactory. If
                    you need it to buttress your point of view—</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It is helpful.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: But there is only one thing I would like to say with regard to the
                    material I examined and that is, as I say, I thought that Ralph’s points were
                    almost universally taken. I think we want to discuss in Executive Session a
                    summarization of documents, where there were some deletions and where we can’t
                    make an issue of it very easily. I have very little to say on that subject.
                    Perhaps some of the other members have more to say.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The only thing you haven’t mentioned was the additional material
                    that you had gleaned that could be inserted in the ’42 volume. It seemed to me,
                    as I read that over—and I know Leland Goodrich agreed—this was very useful
                    information.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would agree with that. Well, I think we will go into Executive
                    Session, unless there are comments from the staff or the committee.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: If that is the way you feel about it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: If you want us to say we do have the support of the Division, I
                    think that we can.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think in your report we ought to say something specifically about
                    those volumes, if you can because it would be helpful to us. Although I realize
                    operations probably hasn’t seemed as important to you as it does to us, it can
                    be helpful to us in bolstering our point of view and in making it clear just
                    what your views are.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Well, Bernard, in that connection, I was talking informally with
                    Dexter and a couple of the other members last night before and after dinner and
                    the thought occurred to me perhaps this year we could say everything we needed
                    to say that should be said in a public report, in other words, submit perhaps
                    this year only one report. Now, if we did that, then we would have to be very
                    general, wouldn’t we, about these specific items that we were examining
                    yesterday?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Again, we really don’t differ, that is the point. I went through
                    all of the Latin American material yesterday and I find, as I say, myself in
                    accord with the point of view of the Department. We can say that, of course.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Getting back to that point, how does this matter of submitting only
                    one report this year appeal to you?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I think, in view of the statement you just made, it might be the
                    reasonable thing to do. There are always things which I assume you might want to
                    say privately.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We can make a separate memorandum. The reason I said that is
                    apparently the political scientists felt last year that there was so little in
                    the public report that was worth reprinting that they didn’t reprint it, is that
                    right?</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: It seems to me the public reports were becoming innocuous.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I’d much prefer you put your great emphasis on that and if there is
                    anything incidental you want to say to us, why do so.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Of course last year we referred to the specific items in clearance
                    problems.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. You couldn’t do that in a public report.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we would have something to say in the public report about
                    clearance problems probably. I don’t think the question is understood, however.
                    I certainly don’t think the desk officers always understand what it is we are
                    objecting to, as was indicated by a number of the materials we went over
                    yesterday. I don’t want to foreclose discussion by any members of the staff in
                    the Division here but if there is nothing more to be said about that, we will go
                    into Executive Session.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Mr. Chairman, I was wondering if you want to have any comment at
                    all from the policy officers who are present here?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We have come to this conclusion going over the material. Maybe the
                    desk officers will want to say something more in reply to our hastening
                    conclusion.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Mr. Phillips, how about that?</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: All right. Do you have any particular special item you would
                    rather hear about among the three? There are only three, I believe, now that
                    cannot be settled between ourselves and the Historical Office— the Ecuador-Peru
                    boundary dispute, the U.S. and Chile Hemisphere defense, and the Reciprocal
                    Trade Agreement with Peru.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Brazil, was that it?</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: No. That is an area which has withdrawn.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t know who besides myself saw the Latin American materials
                    yesterday. Do you feel the material on Peru-Ecuador might not be published at
                    the present time?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: Yes.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: So do I. What was the other one?</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: The efforts to secure cooperation between the U. S. and Chile
                    on certain measures of hemispheric defense and the negotiations leading to the
                    signing of the Reciprocal Trade Agreement between the United States and
                    Peru.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think in the case of the Chile documents, this reads a lot in
                    detail. But I was not adverse to leaving matters stand the way they are.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: That is just the way I felt about it.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t think there were any serious questions at issue there.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You mean you agreed with them?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We agreed with the deletions.</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: There were a couple of objections that we withdrew so that
                    left us on page 7-JJC. We withdraw our objection with inclusion of Embassy
                    Telegram 478 and on page 17 we withdraw our objection of including the last
                    paragraph of the Departmental memorandum of conversation of November 6th.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Have you done that formally?</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: We deleted it from the memorandum and somehow or other when
                    the galley proof came back it had this notation on it indicating that we were
                    still on record as opposing the inclusion of these items, you see.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: So we had actually deleted them. That is, we had dropped our
                    objection to the inclusion of those two items. But I had just done it by
                    scratching it out on the memorandum.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I see. Do you have those items?</p>
                <p>MR. SAPPINGTON: We have the galleys, yes.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I was wondering what the state of the record was on that.</p>
                <p>MR. SAPPINGTON: I don’t believe we have your reply on that.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We agreed with the desk officers, as a matter of fact, on the
                    points involved there. Isn’t that correct?</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: That’s right, yes.</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: I misunderstood, I thought you agreed with the Historical
                    Officer.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: On the Peru-Ecuador thing, we thought it ought not to be published.
                    We didn’t really have time enough to do what we should have done.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: We were more fascinated by the other things.</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: On the Reciprocal Trade Agreement with Peru—</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we can take a look at them again if you want us to. If you
                    want us to give some more study to the Latin American documents, some of the
                    other members of the committee can take a look at them. We don’t take a position
                    at all. On the CIA documents we entirely disagree with the position of the
                    CIA.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Oh, yes, 100 percent.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: I think Mr. Phillips had one more Latin American matter.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What’s the other Latin American matter?</p>
                <p>MR. R. I. PHILLIPS: The Reciprocal Trade Agreement with Peru, negotiations
                    leading to the signing of the Reciprocal Trade Agreement with Peru.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t think I saw that one. I’m afraid we missed that one. We had
                    so many documents.</p>
                <p>MR. POOLE: They were minor deletions, one in its entirety and about three
                    sentences scattered throughout the document.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: we can look at that before we adjourn this afternoon.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Could we have a summary of it while they are here?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you want to discuss it now? Do you have that?</p>
                <p>MR. POOLE: I don’t know what the objections of the Historical Division are.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Just what is it? Have we discussed this with them?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Is this about establishing a tire factory and all that sort of
                    thing?</p>
                <p>MR. SAPPINGTON: Yes.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think I have that here and I looked at it and I didn’t see any
                    particular reason why it should be omitted. Maybe I missed a point.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: The objection was made by the policy people in the WST office.
                    There was 1942 clearance. At the time this came back we had a number of issues
                    up getting 1941 cleared with ARA. So we decided rather than to throw too many
                    issues into the discussion at once we would postpone this discussion and we have
                    not made any reply to ARA on this. So, since we have received your memorandum we
                    have not discussed this.</p>
                <p>MR. POOLE: I’d be happy to answer any questions, but I don’t know what they
                    are.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I think what my comment was is that we don’t know just what the
                    reasons were why it should be left out.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I don’t want to take too much time on a point of this scale this
                    morning.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I think this is something we can discuss with the policy
                    officers.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I wish you would. And if you want our help maybe we can take it up
                    again this afternoon.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: In that case, we better thank you gentlemen for coming.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I think we will go into Executive Session at this point.</p>
                <p>[Whereupon at 9:25 a.m. the Committee met in Executive Session but reconvened at
                    11:30 a.m., at which time Deputy Assistant Secretary John F. Steeves discussed
                    the reasons for FE’s objections to the release of Volume V, 1941, Far East, and
                    the 1943 volume on China.]</p>
                <p>[Mr. Steeves’ remarks are summarized as follows:]</p>
                <p>The Volume V on Thailand, 1941, was taken up first and the reasons for objections
                    to its release were, in brief, that the individuals involved still were such
                    that publication would be damaging to Thailand’s relations. The representatives
                    of Thailand and Cambodia were presently participating in a meeting in New York
                    City in an attempt to work out something, but if this volume were published it
                    might be damaging to that peaceful settlement they were trying to work out.</p>
                <p>With regard to the China series, the situation had not changed substantially and
                    the Department was still opposed to the release of these volumes at this
                    time.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What do the members of the committee want to question Mr. Steeves
                    on?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: In the Thai-Cambodia question, would this really be bringing out
                    material which is quite varied? Would it be a flashing revelation of something
                    unknown to the people who count in Cambodia?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I just don’t know. Those unsympathetic to coming together with the
                    Thais and reaching rapprochement would probably use it as further documentation
                    that they now do not know exists in our papers, but which they suspect, of
                    course, we just give them additional documentation and proof of what a lot of
                    them feel.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: So far as Pibul Songgram is concerned, what’s his position? How do you
                    estimate that? He is the one who is most importantly concerned.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: So far as Pibul Songgram’s part was concerned, I think even last
                    year we said that it was possible that papers with respect to him might not be
                    as much of a problem now as they were a couple of years ago, three years
                    ago.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Your remarks, I take it, relate not only to the future publication
                    but to the volume that is ready for release?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Yes. There is one of these volumes that is in question which has
                    been published and held.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: That is the 141 volume.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The ’41 and ’43 on China. May I refer to the statement made by Mr.
                    Parsons last year, who came down to talk to the group also. He said that we
                    ought to consider preparing all the volumes for publication together. One volume
                    on ’43 on China is being held up and case-bound and the other 13 are in various
                    stages of preparation. Some of the ’44’s are in page numbers and the others are
                    all in galleys except three volumes of ’49. Mr. Parsons suggestion was that we
                    might get them all ready for publication simultaneously. Now, that is a very
                    interesting idea. If we did that, it would imply that we could get in the
                    preparation of them and publication clearance would be given, so that obviously
                    we couldn’t put them in case-bound form without having them cleared first. The
                    question is whether we could have them cleared and get them all ready for
                    publication when they were all published. Would you mind commenting on that, as
                    to the possibility?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: It’s a new thought to me.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: John, before you do, I think we should mention another question
                    behind this is, of course, the special kind of series that was asked for by the
                    committee in ’53, one of the things which has been discussed here in this group
                    yesterday, whether that is a good idea still or whether perhaps we shouldn’t
                    just say let’s put the China volumes back in the regular series. But last year
                    we were talking in terms of publishing the China series, but just getting them
                    all ready and then hoping that the time will come when we can release the whole
                    batch. I think you need that background.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I didn’t know that Mr. Parsons commented on this last year, so my
                    opinion on it is very much of a kind of <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> one
                    that I add here right now. I think the only thing that I would say is that when
                    they are in ready form they are subject to greater pressure for release than
                    when they are not in ready form.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, it always stands out to the tabulation.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Congressional pressures and things of that nature, also leakages,
                    are much easier once they are in the volume form and finished.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: You may know that the first ten volumes of the 1941 Volume V were
                    actually sold by the Superintendent of Documents on the basis of requests for
                    them, the requests for the coming publication being known and advertised by
                    Volume IV, which was released. So the 10 volumes are in the public domain.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I know that.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: There is the other question to which Mr. Kretzmann referred.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Would you like to address yourself to that John? Do you think the
                    pressures for the China series which were generated in ’53 in the ’50 political
                    atmosphere are such that we have to go ahead with this special kind of series?
                    Or can we make an effort to simply ask the committee of Congress?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Again, without having the benefit of full discussion of it, my
                    comment I’m afraid is a rather <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> one, but I
                    wouldn’t see any more reason for doing a special Chinese series than I would in
                    doing a special Japan series or any other area.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You know this was bound up with the volumes on war-time
                    conferences which commitment we have fulfilled or are in the process of
                    fulfilling.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Considering the volume which is going through this building now on
                    Laos, we will have to have a Laos series sometime.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I hope not.</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: The thought was that if these were incorporated back with the annual
                    volumes when they were released they wouldn’t stick out so much as a sore
                    thumb.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I would think they wouldn’t stick out so and it would be better to
                    be incorporated in a regular series rather than a special series.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It’s something to take note of.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: When we go up for our appropriations we are going to have to
                    answer these questions: Where are your China series and how are you coming along
                    on it? Is this a time to make a pitch and say, “We looked at this and we have
                    decided it’s better to put them in the regular series”?</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Just what was the form of the Congressional action with regard to
                    the China series? Did they request the division to do this?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They requested the publication of the China series. The resolution was
                    stated not precisely, shall we say, as explicitly as the members interpreted it
                    to mean, because it spoke about war-time conferences and the volumes on China;
                    and then bringing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Board farther
                    down to date, we knew from private conversations with them and from the letters
                    that had been written to the Secretary what they meant. They meant that the
                    war-time conferences and the China series should be published separately. The
                    resolution itself didn’t mention them specifically but the letters which had
                    been written did mention them specifically, from Senator Knowland and other
                    Senators. So we had to interpret the resolution in terms of the discussions and
                    communications.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You get into this area of forwarding the intent of Congress.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: Wasn’t it an action of the Senate Appropriations Committee?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Oh, yes, that’s right.</p>
                <p>MR. BERDAHL: No House action whatever.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: The action of the Appropriations Committee of the Senate.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: What year was it, 1953, that this suggestion was made?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: It was the Spring of ’53.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: You were given money for that too, weren’t you?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: They increased it from the previous fiscal year to $112 thousand.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What would be the procedure if one was to publi8h the volume and
                    incorporate the China documents?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: When you speak of incorporating it, remember that this China series
                    already is separated into volumes for the most part and there are actually—Ralph
                    can correct me if I’m wrong—14 volumes and it would be difficult to incorporate
                    them other than giving them a number perhaps along with the others because there
                    are so many volumes. You have the material for the volumes and you can’t very
                    well incorporate other materials in that if you have a whole volume strictly on
                    China for, say, 1945, and three volumes for 1946, something like that.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: I think the chief trouble there would be also in the preface. You
                    see, the series has been announced and naturally in future years they get 1942
                    and 1943 which is already bound, so naturally the readers are going to look for
                    the later volume. So when we do publish these volumes we would have to
                    incorporate them into the annual volumes. We would have to have an explanation
                    in the preface that this is what has become of the China series—the China series
                    is discontinued.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: In terms of the printer and cost, has this operation gone on so far
                    that it would cause serious disruption and therefore cost in changing your mind
                    in going back and incorporating them in the regular series?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Not except the 1943 volume, which is already bound of course.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: That would have to be actually thrown away and printed up again?</p>
                <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Since the ’42 one is already out, you would have to leave two
                    deviations, wouldn’t you, Ralph?</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: Make it a series of two.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Well, ’42-43, you’re in round currency anyway. You just have to
                    say they will be coming out regularly. This is the answer we can’t make at this
                    point.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: The ’43 volume could be changed by typing in pages, which of
                    course raises some question. We did at one time type in 11 pages and pointed out
                    to the appropriate Committee of Congress that all these pages had been typed in
                    after the volume had been bound.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Well, I think there is no serious problem there. We can publish the
                    China volume in, say, ’43 when the other ’43 volumes are published and the ’44
                    could be given, say, “<hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Volume” on
                    so-and-so, sub-head “China”. It would be a separate volume, but there is no
                    great problem there. The question is whether it would be agreeable to have us
                    issue, say, the 1943 China volume when we issue and publish the other volumes of
                    ’43 and so on into ’49.</p>
                <p>MR. KRBTZMANN: John, can I argue on your side for a moment?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Sure, delighted to have you.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I can see a great problem coming up within this next year on these
                    China series and if they are bound and ready, although they don’t want to go
                    back that far, ’42 and ’43, the pressures for us to put out our official
                    documents about relations with China I think are going to grow immensely. Now,
                    if they find out that you have got your volumes more or less ready up through
                    ’49, I think the pressures to get these out and to the public domain is going to
                    become almost irresistible.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: From whom? Pressures from whom?</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Congress.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: From appropriations hearings they know that we have these volumes
                    ready.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I know.</p>
                <p>MR. THAYER: That is where this all started.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, are there any other questions to be addressed to Mr. Steeves
                    in any other commentary? [None] You have satisfied us for the time being.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Thank you.</p>
                <p>MR. HARRINGTON: We share with you the concern about the general point that we are
                    facing a period of increasing difficulty because of sensitivity, but of course
                    along with the increasing sensitivity for the diplomatic people there is the
                    greater importance to the public and to the scholar of this material. So somehow
                    or other the position of the scholar and the general public needs to be
                    recognized too.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I know it. There is a balance in there somewhere. I’m afraid I’m
                    just not competent to pass judgment on it, because you could interpret it so
                    strictly if you just decided to do away with the idea of ever publishing them,
                    they would stay a classified document.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I take it it’s a policy problem. If for any reason our China policy
                    should be modified, we should keep, let us say, or establish relations with the
                    Peiping Government, why then the problem no longer exists.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: We certainly would have to look at it from a different viewpoint. It
                    might be a problem from another angle then.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: What we find from time to time is, even in some extreme cases,
                    publication of things which have been objected to, have already been published
                    in a book of some kind or the facts which ought to be concealed have been
                    discussed frequently in literature on the subject. And we had a very interesting
                    example this year, during this session, of materials which we studied, most of
                    which were already well known in the public domain as far as data were
                    concerned. And this is one of the aspects of the problem that concerns us, of
                    course.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I know when I asked about this one time I was given what seemed to
                    me to be a pretty good answer to that one though, that although the facts are
                    out in other form, that it doesn’t have quite the impact nor the ring of
                    authenticity that it would have when it comes out under the seal of the
                    Department of State.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: Dexter, if I could change your word, you used a very unhappy word
                    to me, the question of concealment. To us it’s a question of official
                    confirmation in those cases where it has already been written by other writers,
                    but what causes us to hesitate is do we want to put official confirmation on
                    these facts? It’s not a matter of concealment, I might say, because we don’t
                    deny the authenticity or the truth of these.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Could I ask this question: Would the political impact of the
                    publication of these documents be less if they came out more or less routinely
                    year by year instead of this question of publication being continually held up?
                    We are now publishing the ’42 volume. The ’42 volume is out. When you get ’43,
                    the ’44 volumes are published as a matter of routine along with the other
                    volume. Would that lessen the political impact of publication?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Yes, I would say if you finally decided to face it and come out
                    anyway, then of course to come out routinely would be better than to make it
                    look as if it was a sudden decision to release and let it go.</p>
                <p>MR. R. PERKINS: That is the situation we have got into because of these volumes
                    being held up. It was the general practice when the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> were compiled when it was published it would be released.
                    Then they decided not to release it at this time. Now, when they do release it,
                    it’s going to raise the question, why are you releasing it at this particular
                    time? So it seems to me it’s very unfortunate that the timing of release should
                    be always considered from the immediate political angle.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think it was unfortunate largely because this publication of the
                    series was based on political grounds too.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: The same thing was true of the supplementary volumes of the
                    conferences.</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: This is a period that corresponds roughly with the time of the
                    publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> but the China
                    volumes is a different matter.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I must say there would be embarrassment in building it up with a view
                    to publishing them altogether because from year to year we would be accumulating
                    more volumes that were case-bound and we would have to account for our
                    activities here in some way to the Appropriations Committee of the House and
                    Senate and we would have to tell them, in other words, that we are accumulating
                    some volumes here that are case-bound, that is how we have been doing some of
                    our activities, and that would become increasingly embarrassing. The other
                    method would be far better, of course, if we could get them published from year
                    to year in a regular series.</p>
                <p>May I ask one other question? Do you anticipate any time in the reasonable near
                    future in which the 1941 volume might be released?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: You’ re asking me?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes. Do you have in mind any time in the near future when it might be
                    released?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: It could only be a pure guess on my part as to whether or not this
                    particular series of events surrounding two or three people’s names changes but
                    I would hope that the situation might be a little bit better next year. One
                    individual’s star has dimmed quite a bit, so whatever is said about him, if it
                    continues to go in that direction wouldn’t mean merely as much a year from now
                    as it does now, and it wouldn’t mean as much this year as it did last year,
                    except for these talks that are going on.</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: Prince Wan is so slightly involved.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Any other comment?</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Was the reference to the possible need for future British clearance
                    made with regard to the Thai documentation or the Chinese?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: Chinese.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Isn’t the British position abundantly known on that subject?</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: I would have to go back into the document because my notes that were
                    done on this do not make reference to the actual document. Last year I pulled
                    out the documents concerned and read them all before last year, but I haven’t
                    done that this year, the sections in question. So I’m not quite prepared to
                    answer that specifically. We could do a little research on that and find out for
                    you the actual documents involved in that question.</p>
                <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I thought if there was anything in there that bothered you we would
                    clear that up. Mr. Churchill has gone far out of his way about his annoyance at
                    the constant American dealings with Chiang in 1943-44, etc., etc. And Mr.
                    Churchill seems to be very authoritative. We wouldn’t have anything really to
                    add or subtract to those documents from what he has said. If that is the nature
                    of the difficulty, perhaps we could look it up and see.</p>
                <p>MR. STEEVES: That being true, the historians of 1980 will find it very
                    interesting to read some documents of more recent years as against those.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, what do you suggest now?</p>
                <p>MR. NOBLE: I thought I would like to make a suggestion. But, first a question.
                    Our agenda for this afternoon called for a report back by the committee on its
                    private session and I’d like first to ask what your pleasure is on that, as to
                    whether you would like to have some further discussion on it or whether, on the
                    basis of the discussion we have had you feel that you are ready to proceed with
                    the final preparation of the report. What’s the view of the committee with
                    regard to the deliberations this morning? Would you like to have us go over the
                    ground which we covered with you, Ed and Bill and Ralph?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think we have more matters to discuss. We have some more matters
                    to discuss first. Ed tells me he has some other things he wanted to say.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: I haven’t finished my thesis yet.</p>
                <p>THE CHAIRMAN: You mean other matters to discuss, matters that we have not
                    discussed?</p>
                <p>MR. GOODRICH: Ed says he hasn’t finished his thesis and he has a speech on
                    this.</p>
                <p>MR. KRETZMANN: No, no. [OFF THE RECORD]</p>
                <p>[Whereupon at 12:10 p.m. the Committee sat in Executive Session.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
