<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="complete">Clarence Berdahl Report on Consultantship in the Historical
               Office, August 1961</title>
            <title type="short">Berdahl Consultantship Report, 1961</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
             <date type="created" when="1961-08-31">August 31, 1961</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                  target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1961-08-31-berdahl-consultantship-report.pdf">PDF</ref>, 721 KB, 8pp.)</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the
               Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files, 1957-1990
               (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 1, 1961-Report.</hi></p>
         <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough,
                  Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of the Foreign Relations of the United States
                  Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref target="../chapter-8#fn8">Footnote 8</ref></p>
         <div type="document">
            <head>Report on Consultantship</head>
            <dateline>June 20-August 31, 1961</dateline>
            <p>Mr. Noble:</p>
            <p>I submit the following report on my consultantship in the Historical Office during
               this summer (June 20-August 31, 1961):</p>
            <p>1. <hi rend="underline">Purpose</hi>. According to the terms of my appointment, I was to
               examine the procedures followed and advise the Director “with regard to the adequacy
               of coverage of the sources used and the methods of research followed by the Office,”
               and to make “such proposals in connection therewith as may seem justified.”</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="underline">Method of Work</hi>. In order to become fully acquainted with
               the problems and procedures in respect to the compilation, editing, and publication
               of the volumes on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>, I
               was first given a thorough introduction to the various records, files of documents,
               indexes and other finding devices, and library collection and facilities within the
               State Department and available to the Historical Office staff.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I conferred with every member of the Foreign Relations staff, and with some
               others, about the problems and procedures involved in the compilation of these
               volumes. Although there were some differences of opinion with respect to the
               practical application of these matters to the immediate tasks, there was virtual
               agreement on the nature of the problems involved, and I secured from these experts in
               historical research a far better understanding of the problems and difficulties with
               which they are confronted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I reviewed some of the published Foreign Relations volumes, including
               Conference volumes; some page-proof (especially 1942. II. Europe), some galleys
               (especially 1943. II. Europe); some compilations in various stages of preparation for
               production (1945, Dumbarton Oaks; 1945, Austria; 1945 Near and Middle East); and the
               plan or tentative contents for volumes in the course of compilation (1945). All this
               was for the purpose of noticing the scope, the source (whether from the Central Files
               or other sources); possible gaps, variety and relative importance of subject or
               stories, extent of non-political or non-State Department material (e.g. economic and
               military questions; Presidential, War or Defense, Intelligence, etc., documents).</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I examined carefully a considerable number and variety of documentary
               collections--the Algiers Post Files (the so-called Murphy Files) for 1943 (12 boxes);
               the European Affairs Office or Lot Files for 1943 (6 boxes); some of the Dumbarton
               oaks and other pre-United Nations papers in the International Organization Lot Files
               (10 out of the 104 boxes of this material); papers relating to the Allied Control
               Council for Austria (9 folders); some of the European Affairs Lot Files relating to
               the Occupation of Germany (2 boxes, 80 folders, principally for 1945 and 1947, but
               with occasional papers for earlier years). I tried also, without actually reading
               many papers to become reasonably well acquainted with the Central Files, the Index
               Cards, and various aids and finding devices for facilitating the use of these
               files.</p>
            <p>Finally, I read a number of memoranda on various matters, including clearance
               problems; attended staff meetings; and discussed numerous questions with individual
               staff members, some brought to my attention by them and some raised by me out of my
               examination of these papers and compilations. As a result of these weeks of study and
               observation, the following comments are made on what seem to me to be the major
               problems in respect to the Foreign Relations series:</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="underline">Quantity of Documentation</hi>. There is nothing quite so clear
               as the vast and growing amount of documentation that must be examined by those who
               compile the Foreign Relations volumes. A measurement of the Index Cards to the
               Central Files alone, and exclusively by countries, shows, for the years 1940-1944,
               3190-1/4 inches of these cards for Latin America, 1467-1/4 inches of cards for
               Western Europe, 1351-1/4 for the British Commonwealth, Eastern Europe, and the Far
               East, 473-1/2 for the Near East and Africa, or a total of 6482-1/4 inches of these
               index cards covering a period of five years. Another measurement, based on the number
               of cards per inch, shows with reference only to the correspondence to and from
               London, 4,680 cards for 1934, 35,955 cards for 1944, 20,280 cards for 1949. Well over
               400,000 documents were added to the Department's subject files in each year from 1955
               to 1960. A single compiler in one year examined 3,603 index cards and 7,463 papers
               relating to three countries (Bulgaria, Japan, USSR). These statistics, incomplete and
               limited as they are, give some indication of the enormous task now involved in the
               compilation of these volumes. Nor is there any reason to doubt that the amount of
               documentation will continue to increase. There may be some decrease for certain
               areas, such as Latin America, with the return of more normal relationships, but this
               will certainly be offset by the continuing development of multilateral agencies and
               regional and global relationships.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="underline">Complexity of Documentation</hi>. Much more of a problem than
               the mere quantity is the increasing complexity of the documentation. The war and
               post-war events have brought about a situation in which the State Department, once
               exclusively responsible for foreign policy, is now only one of the agencies involved,
               others being particularly the Department of Defense, the Central Intelligence Agency,
               the U.S. Information Agency, the Treasury Department, and others. The State
               Department itself has been required to engage in activities of a much broader scope
               than before, its own documentation thus becoming more complex (involving economic and
               military, as well as political considerations), while the documentation of these
               agencies is also closely related to the actual foreign policy as determined and
               carried on.</p>
            <p>The emphasis on multilateral (regional and global) relationships has produced a mass
               of documentation quite different from and much more difficult to classify and arrange
               than that based largely on the simpler bilateral relationships. This change has also,
               of course, vastly increased the quantity as well. Thus, the documentation relating to
               the pre-United Nations period (Atlantic Charter, Dumbarton Oaks Conversations, the
               State Department preparatory work, etc.) is contained in 104 boxes and an Inventory
               of these records, prepared by Dorothy B. Thomas, of the Reference and Documents
               Section of the Bureau of International Organization, makes up a booklet of 35 pages;
               the Department's documentation of the United Nations itself for the years 1946-1949
               occupies 49 files drawers and deals with 112 different subjects; and another
               Inventory of the records of the various wartime conferences of Heads of State,
               Council of Foreign Ministers, and similar meetings, prepared by Alycedale Collins and
               Hilda Nash, of the Records Service Center, comprises a booklet of 132 pages listing
               the contents of 243 boxes.</p>
            <p>The documents relating to the Austrian Control Council, contained in nine larger
               folders, reveal the intermingling of political, military, and economic questions; in
               the Central Files there are at least 45 drawers of documents dealing entirely or
               largely with economic problems in Occupied Germany; in the Bonn Post Files there are
               182 boxes of documents relating exclusively to the control of I.G. Farben, involving
               economic, financial, accounting, and legal questions; while in the European Affairs
               Lot Files there are in only two boxes 80 folders containing documents relating to
               German Occupation problems, principally in 1945, that include Council of Foreign
               Ministers' directives, restitution of property, reparations, economic unity of
               Germany, Rhineland-Ruhr, the Saar Valley, railways, the Polish boundary, and many
               others, including, significantly, a memorandum on “State-War Relations in respect to
               the Control of Germany.” The intermingling of political, territorial, economic, and
               military considerations in our post-war foreign policy is thus clearly revealed, with
               the consequent complexity of documentation which the compilers and editors have to
               put into proper perspective to produce a coherent account.</p>
            <p>5. <hi rend="underline">Use of Post and Lot (Office) Files</hi>. There is some
               difference of opinion as to the use that should be made of these papers, which are
               not in the Central Files. They are available at irregular intervals, the Post Files
               not being available at all, I believe, until 1955; they are often very poorly
               classified and arranged; they are not indexed and therefore take considerable time.
               Sometimes their examination yields very little in addition to what is found in the
               indexed Central Files.</p>
            <p>I am, however, convinced from my own sampling of these files that they may be and
               often are the source of very important documentation that has somehow not been
               included in the Central Files, and it is my opinion that they ought to be used rather
               assiduously. For example, the Algiers Post Files for 1943, often referred to as the
               Murphy Files, contain in 12 boxes a number of documents that filled in the record
               found in the Central Files and illuminated the account of the Giraud-de Gaulle
               problem. The Bonn Post Files have 182 boxes of documents on the I.G. Farben problem
               alone; and the European Affairs Lot Files contain 80 large folders of documents
               relating to the economic aspects of German occupation. These are samples only, and
               for some other matters similar files would not doubt be less important. To some
               extent the individual compiler, who knows his subject, may sense whether or how
               thorough a search need be made of these records, but they should by all means be
               taken seriously into account.</p>
            <p>6. <hi rend="underline">Scope and Selectivity</hi>. The vast increase in the amount of
               documentation has required considerable emphasis on the need for selectivity. It is
               obviously impossible any longer to publish all the documents if the volumes are to be
               kept within reasonable compass and produced within a reasonable period. The emphasis
               on a greater degree of selectivity is therefore quite necessary and proper. However,
               the directive under which the Historical office operates should also be emphasized,
               namely, that these Foreign Relations volumes should include “all documents needed to
               give a comprehensive record of the major foreign policy decision within the range of
               the Department of State's responsibilities, together with appropriate materials
               concerning the facts which contributed to the formulations of policies;” and that
               this record should also, if possible, “show the alternatives presented to the
               Department before the decision was made.” It seems to me quite clear that the first
               and principal consideration in compiling and editing these volumes must be to produce
               a complete and accurate record. The size and number of volumes and the speed of
               production are important but secondary considerations.</p>
            <p>This means, in the first place, that all State Department documents relating to major
               foreign policy questions, including the Post and Lot Files, must be taken into
               account. In this connection, every compiler has to contend with the problem of
               occasional missing documents, which may have been misplaced in the files, drawn out
               and indefinitely retained by some officer, and even completely lost through lack of
               adequate records. It would seem highly desirable that improved methods be used for
               recording, copying, and maintaining the Central Files so as to avoid this problem and
               save the time involved in searching for missing documents.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the principle of a thorough and accurate record means now, in my opinion,
               that use must also be made of documents produced and controlled by Government
               agencies other than the State Department, especially of Presidential, Defense, and
               Intelligence papers. The use of such outside papers was contemplated in the directive
               noted above; it is essential in respect to the Conference volumes, occupation and
               other post-War policies; but it seems to me desirable in respect to most major
               matters in view of their broad and complex nature. It may be regrettable that the
               State Department is no longer the exclusively agency in determining our foreign
               policy, but that is the situation which must be reflected to the extent necessary in
               the Foreign Relations volumes.</p>
            <p>All of this means greater difficulty in compiling these volumes, for the vast amount
               of documentation requires also emphatic application of the principle of
               selectivity--that is, selecting the essential documents for textual publication,
               summarizing or annotating those of lesser importance, and eliminating those not
               essential to a meaningful and accurate record. It should be pointed out, however,
               that the staff has for some time clearly recognized the need of such selectivity,
               first in deciding what are “major foreign policy decisions” deserving of
               documentation at all, and, secondly, in the actual selection of documents for final
               publication; and this deliberate selection has been emphasized and increased in
               response to the suggestions of the Advisory Committee. For example, the documentation
               of Refugees (1945) was reduced by 40 per cent as the original selection went through
               microfilming into working documents and final review; in another case involving three
               countries, more than 7,000 documents originally examined were reduced to about 1,300
               for working purposes, and less than one half of these, or about 7 per cent of the
               original selection, were actually compiled; in still another case, relating to the
               Far East (1943), only about 5 per cent of the papers in the Central Files were taken
               out for working purposes and less than 2 per cent were used in the compilation.</p>
            <p>While these figures suggest careful and even drastic selection in some cases, they
               reveal nothing about the principles involved. Everyone agrees that some subjects are
               less important than other subjects, but it is difficult to list those subjects
               without qualification as to time and circumstance; there are times when certain
               countries are so unimportant that no documentation is necessary at all, but it is
               quite impossible to list these countries for all time. It would be my conclusion,
               after reviewing a number of papers and compilations, that such matters as individual
               claims, passport and visa problems, rights of business firms, disposition of
               archives, air transport privileges, tele-communication stations--in general, matters
               concerning private individuals and companies--might generally be omitted, or be
               treated with an editorial note; but there are circumstances that make some of these
               of considerable public importance and deserving of documentation. There is no way of
               avoiding the best judgment of the individual compiler in respect to selection.</p>
            <p>Another feature of this selective process is that no time is saved by selection
               (except as certain few subjects might be eliminated in advance), for in order to
               decide what documents to eliminate or to reduce to an editorial note or to annotate,
               the compiler must look at all the documents. Greater selectivity should reduce the
               number and size of the volumes, but can hardly reduce the time of the staff to a
               perceptible extent.</p>
            <p>7. <hi rend="underline">Conference Volumes</hi>. The compilation of separate Conference
               volumes has produced some problems, particularly because some were compiled and
               published ahead of the regular volumes for the years covered. That required
               background material in the Conference volumes, some of which might more properly have
               been included within the regular volumes, and raises the question whether to reprint
               documents in the regular volumes in order to get a connected account or to permit a
               hop-skip-and-jump account in the regular volumes and refer to the documents already
               printed in the Conference volumes. Problems such as these might have been avoided if
               both Conference and regular volumes had been compiled at the same time, but this was
               impossible under the circumstances. It is my view that the production of separate
               Conference volumes is in itself desirable in view of the special and multilateral
               nature of those proceedings, and I should like to encourage their continued
               production in that form; but I would hope that so far as possible, they be compiled
               at the same time as the regular volumes in order to coordinate the materials somewhat
               better.</p>
            <p>8. <hi rend="underline">Publication Progress: Time Lag</hi>. My own view with respect to
               the time lag in publication of Foreign Relations have changed somewhat as I have
               observed the problems involved. The fact that the volumes are now approximately
               twenty years behind currency is deplorable from every point of view, and I would urge
               that every effort be made to narrow that gap or at least to prevent it from becoming
               wider. The situation must be faced realistically, however, and I do not find any
               reason to suppose that this time-lag can even be maintained in the immediate future.
               It does seem to me much more important to emphasize the need for a comprehensive and
               accurate record, no matter what it may cost in respect to time of publication.
               Although one should encourage at all a wider time-lag, and there must be a point at
               which the line should be held, that point is probably not yet reached in any crisis
               sense. In fact, compilation, which is approximately 16 years behind currency, is
               still ahead of some important sources, such as the Truman papers. It seems to me more
               important to use those known sources, even if this means further delay in
               publication. Also, the problems of clearance should be eased somewhat as time goes
               on.</p>
            <p>9. <hi rend="underline">Clearance</hi>. The clearance problem continues to be one of the
               most difficult, requiring time and forcing delay beyond what is reasonable. The
               problem is difficult within the State Department, and becomes much more difficult as
               Defense documents and even Intelligence documents are or should be used in order to
               prepare an authentic record. My attention has been called to cases where clearance
               has been refused even though the documents themselves had been declassified. The
               increased time-lag should ease this problem somewhat, but the problem continues such
               that serious effort ought to be made to get a White House ruling to govern all
               agencies. It seems to me that with persons on the White House Staff who are familiar
               with scholarly research and sympathetic to the production of an honest record, the
               time may now be propitious for a thorough consideration of this problem. I would
               earnestly suggest that the appropriate officials of the Bureau and the Department be
               persuaded to approach Mr. Schlesinger on this matter.</p>
            <p>10. <hi rend="underline">Planning</hi>. The Advisory Committee has suggested the
               desirability of planning these Foreign Relations volumes for a period of years in
               advance of compilation. This presumably implies considering the number of volumes,
               the content of those volumes, relative emphasis on the various subjects, the
               arrangement of the subject-matter; and might involve some changes, perhaps even
               drastic changes, in form and content. I know that the staff has given a good deal of
               attention to this matter, and I am not prepared to make specific suggestion at this
               time. It does seem to me, however, that in view of the time-lag, it should be
               possible to survey the general situation over a period of five years in the light of
               present knowledge of events, make a preliminary study of the documentation involved,
               and out of that come to some general conclusions with respect to what should be
               produced and how best to deal with the problems. Of course no one assumes that such
               planning can necessarily be carried out exactly as planned; there must be opportunity
               for adaptation to circumstances.</p>
            <p>11. <hi rend="underline">Staff</hi>. The staff problem is the crucial one, as I see it;
               and by that I do not refer to its quality but to its number. I have the highest
               admiration for the scholarship, devotion to duty, and integrity of every member of
               the staff; it is a group which any University Department of History or Political
               Science should be proud to claim. But this staff is confronted with an impossible
               task, and must be substantially enlarged if these Foreign Relations volumes are to be
               produced as they should be. The proposal of the Advisory Committee for additional
               staff seems to me much too modest, and I would suggest at least six additional
               members are essential in order to maintain the present time-lag of twenty years. I
               see no other solution to the problem.</p>
            <p>In view of the increased importance of economic question, it would no doubt be
               desirable to have on the staff at least one person thoroughly trained in Economics or
               Economic History. This does not seem to me absolutely essential, for most broadly
               trained historians or political scientists should easily recognize the importance of
               economic problems and evaluate the documents relating to those questions. I would
               seem to me that persons with abroad training and experience in research, who could be
               shifted easily from one area to another as the need arises, are highly desirable,
               together with a number who may be area specialists. But I strongly urge that every
               effort be made to secure substantial additions to the staff.</p>
            <p>12. <hi rend="underline">Conclusions</hi>. There is little that need be added to the
               comments already made. I may, however, emphasize these points:</p>
            <p>(a) There should be no effort to interfere with the individual approach which each
               compiler must make to his own subject. It might, however, be desirable to have
               somewhat more direction, consultation, and coordination with respect to the entire
               task. This should serve to ensure the appropriate emphasis on the various
               subjects.</p>
            <p>(b) The general examination and use of papers outside the Central Files--Post and Lot
               Files within the State Department, the White House papers, and the papers of other
               agencies--should be encouraged, although the extent of use must, of course, vary
               according to the subject. I would suggest also that editorial notes and annotations
               referring to memoirs and first-hand accounts might well be used to fill in gaps in
               the regular volumes, as they have been used particularly in the Conference
               volumes.</p>
            <p>(c) I should very much like to see the chronological List of Papers, discontinued in
               1937, restored. This would make possible some further rearrangement of the
               documents.</p>
            <p>(d) Attention might well be given to the subject-matter arrangement. I personally
               prefer this arrangement to the completely chronological, but the classifications
               might well be broadened into fewer subjects.</p>
            <p>(e) Finally, I would reemphasize that the crucial problems are those of clearance and
               staff, and even an enlarged staff would be hampered if there is no solution to
               clearance.</p>
            <p>In conclusion, I must express my appreciation of the unfailing courtesy and genuine
               cooperation I received from every member of the staff during this assignment.</p>
            <p>Clarence A. Berdahl</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
