<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1962</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1962</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-02-10">February 10, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1962-11-02">November 2-3, 1962</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1962-11-02-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 1.3 MB, 15pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1962—Minutes. Limited Official
                Use.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1962 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 2-3, 1962</dateline>
                <p>The morning session on Friday, November 2, began at approximately 9:15 a.m.</p>
                <p>Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Clarence A. Berdahl</item>
                            <item>Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                            <item>Fred H. Harrington</item>
                            <item>Richard W. Leopold</item>
                            <item>Dexter Perkins</item>
                            <item>Philip W. Thayer</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Officers of the Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin</item>
                            <item>E. R. Perkins</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>E. Taylor Parks</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff:<list>
                            <item>Newton O. Sappington</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Almon R. Wright</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>George Kent</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>G. Bernard Noble, former Director of the Historical Office</item>
                </list>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM 1: Opening remarks:</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin welcomed the Committee with appropriate opening remarks.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM 2: Report on status of the series:</p>
                <p>Mr. E. R. Perkins stated that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had not
                    made rapid progress in 1962. An American Republics volumes for 1941 was still
                    beset by clearance difficulties. In one instance, we had even retrogressed, for
                    despite FE commitment on the release of 1944 China, voices of protest from
                    Taipei and second thoughts in FE had again resulted in shelving the series. Mr.
                    Perkins expressed great optimism on our forthcoming publication program. He
                    predicted that five volumes would be published during the remainder of the
                    fiscal year (American Republics, 1941, vol. VII, and 1942, vol. VI; General,
                    1943, vol. I; and Near East, 1942, vol. IV, and 1943, vol. IV) and that one
                    additional volume (American Republics, 1941, vol. VI) would possibly be
                    published. The compilations for 1944 soon be in galleys, opening the way to
                    undertake clearance activities. Manuscript for two volumes of 1945 was being
                    readied for transfer to PB.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted that two or three conference volumes would be in galleys by
                    the end of the fiscal year--one or possibly two volumes on the Washington and
                    Casablanca conferences (depending on the amount of material) and one on the
                    Quebec conferences.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM 3: Report on clearance problems:</p>
                <p>Mr. Sappington discussed the clearance problems facing the American Republics
                    area for 1941, the most protracted clearance problem (over 18 months) faced by
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> today. ARA, a year ago, had raised
                    the issue of clearing memoranda of conversation with foreign Governments but had
                    recently withdrawn from this position after opposition by HO. The chief obstacle
                    remaining was the dilatoriness of ARA in clearing the proclaimed list of
                    compilation (1941, vol. VI). Mr. Sappington was puzzled at the ARA position
                    inasmuch as only broad policies and principles were documented and the names of
                    individuals and companies were not cited. Mr. Thayer, who, as a State Department
                    officer, had been closely connected with the administration of proclaimed list
                    activities during the war, gave his opinion that ARA objections were
                    unwarranted.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then discussed clearance problems of the China series. He outlined
                    three possibilities regarding publication of the series--rapid release of the
                    entire series in the relatively near future, which Secretary Rusk opposed
                    because of the political implications; release of the volumes at the same time
                    as the regular annual volumes, which Mr. Franklin regarded as a waste of the
                    vast efforts put into their preparation; and a compromise arrangement of getting
                    out one year’s compilation each year, permitting release of the volumes from
                    1944 to 1949 in six years. The Committee agreed to support the last
                    alternative.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sappington discussed a further clearance problem with disturbing
                    implication--the failure of the Portuguese Government to take positive action on
                    three representations over a period of two years for permission to print. We
                    inquired whether we might publish certain Portuguese documents without the
                    consent of the Portuguese Government under these circumstances. Mr. Franklin
                    noted that in connection with the Cairo-Tehran volume, the Turkish Government
                    had not responded to clearance requests and that relevant documents had been
                    published, finally, after NEA approval. No reaction had been heard from the
                    Turkish Government. He also noted that one foreign government official had
                    indicated to American authorities that it might be better for the Department to
                    publish documents originating with foreign governments without asking
                    permission. Mr. Churchill observed that we had notified the Ethiopian Government
                    in 1960, after non-receipt of replies to clearance queries, that the Department
                    would print certain Ethiopian documents unless the Ethiopian Government replied
                    within a given time and that we had printed them when nothing was heard from
                    that Government. Mr. Franklin expressed his view that there should be no time
                    limit of foreign clearance but that we reserved the right to publish if there
                    was no substantive reply.</p>
                <p>Mr. Berdahl raised the question as to whether there should be a three-month time
                    limit on Department clearance. It was the sense of the Committee that this would
                    be most desirable. Mr. Franklin agreed with the concept but was willing to
                    accept up to a six-month limit as a fallback position. It was noted that several
                    years ago Deputy Under Secretary Robert D. Murphy had called for a month’s
                    deadline but this had not been enforced.</p>
                <p>Messrs. Goodrich and Leopold cited the President’s letter of September 6, 1961,
                    as an aid in stimulating more rapid clearance. During the discussion which
                    ensued, Mr. Franklin pointed out that the letter had not received the personal
                    approval of the Secretary. It was the sense of the Committee that the matter not
                    be raised with the Secretary when the Committee had lunch with him the following
                    day.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM 4: Report on review of volumes for 1945:</p>
                <p>Mr. E. R. Perkins noted that the end of compilation was in sight, with Eastern
                    Europe and Germany as the chief area farthest from completion. He stated that
                    pressures from above to reduce the number of annual volumes for 1945 to eight
                    had forced the staff to reevaluate compilations already bearing his approval,
                    with a view to cutting down or eliminating them. The Committee queried whether
                    it might profitably give its judgments on cutting down or eliminating
                    compilations along the lines of the 1946 priorities program. Mr. E. R. Perkins
                    gave his opinion that there would be insufficient time for this to be done
                    profitably.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Goodrich regarding the type of materials to be
                    used in the UNCIO compilation, Mr. E. R. Perkins stated that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> would not duplicate materials included in the
                    published record of the conference.</p>
                <p>There was a lengthy discussion of budgetary matters, centering particularly on
                    the problem of scheduling publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes. Mr. Noble gave an interesting budgetary history of
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, dating from the early 1950’s. Mr.
                    Franklin cautioned against raising directly budgetary problems with the
                    Secretary the next day, since if the Secretary went along with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> program, the budget official of the
                    Department would also go along. Mr. Harrington asserted that since the budgetary
                    stringency was in the Department, the budget problem should be discussed with
                    the Secretary.</p>
                <p>As a corollary, discussion ensued as the usefulness of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> program. Mr. Dexter Perkins noted that in speaking
                    to the Secretary, the Committee must show concretely the utility of the program
                    to the scholarly world.</p>
                <p>Mr. Harrington commented concerning the Department cutback of the number of 1945
                    volumes and suggested the possibility that the Department might decide to reduce
                    the series possibly to five volumes in the future. He stressed that such
                    administrative determinations might become a menace to the continuation of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> as a useful series. He urged the
                    Committee to press for ten volumes as a reasonable figure and get the backing of
                    the scholarly community for this effort.</p>
                <p>In connection with the personnel situation, Mr. Franklin stated that HO had
                    requested three additional <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> positions
                    and two Historical Studies positions but that these had been “washed out” in P.
                    Mr. Goodrich asked why HO was placed organizationally in P. Mr. Franklin replied
                    that for practical and other reasons, HO was more advantageously situated in P
                    than elsewhere in the Department and that publication problems had been
                    sympathetically treated by the Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM 5: Report on planning of volumes for 1946:</p>
                <p>Mr. Harrington commented that the concept of priorities was being introduced for
                    the first time for 1946 and commended this as an excellent approach. Mr. Dexter
                    Perkins and Mr. Leopold concurred.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason discussed the background and principles under which planning for 1946
                    had been accomplished by him, with the special assistance of Mr. Goodwin and the
                    general assistance of Mr. E. R. Perkins and the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff. He had reviewed a large number of the completed 1945
                    compilations, making estimates of the sort of material that might safely be cut
                    or eliminated. He had studied the Advisory Committee Minutes and Reports for
                    1961 and Mr. Berdahl’s report in the same year, and had had conferences with
                    each staff member. The staff had prepared for him listings of possible
                    compilations for 1946 and he had established a system of priorities for them.
                    Finally, he had had a further series of conferences with the staff regarding the
                    system of priorities and the organization of the material, so that the paper
                    finally turned out for the use of the Committee was in considerable measure a
                    consensus of the staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin emphasized that a question of the philosophy of history was involved
                    in planning of this sort. Should priorities be based on the importance attached
                    to issues by the Department at the time they were happening, or should
                    priorities of importance be based on the hindsight given to us by the passage of
                    time? He concluded that we would use primarily the latter approach but not be
                    oblivious to the former. Thus, for example, greater priority would be given to
                    the question of access to Berlin than to the question of Safehaven--although the
                    latter would not be ignored.</p>
                <p>After the point was raised by Mr. Goodrich, Mr. Franklin agreed that in the paper
                    on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> planning for 1946, the bracketed
                    note approach was reserved for subjects of third-priority interest. He stressed,
                    however, that bracketed notes might well be used also for subjects of higher
                    priority and to condense pertinent sections of major compilations and that brief
                    documentary treatment might even be given to third-priority subjects. Mr.
                    Berdahl noted that subjects that might be of special interest to international
                    lawyers had been relegated to third-priority status.</p>
                <p>Mr. E. R. Perkins stated that he and Mr. Gleason agreed to treat the Council of
                    Foreign Ministers meetings in 1945 and 1946 as distinct compilations rather than
                    to divide the various subjects discussed among the compilers of bilateral
                    subjects. On the other hand, problems discussed at the United Nations but whose
                    chief locus was elsewhere (e.g., the Iranian question) would be treated as part
                    of bilateral compilations.</p>
                <p>Another general decision on planning was that larger numbers of related subjects
                    would be grouped into a single compilation than heretofore, e.g., Mr. Reid’s
                    major compilation on Japan for 1946. This will result in fewer stories and fewer
                    documents overall.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany suggested that some type of narrative device might be introduced in
                    order to cope with the ever-increasing volume of documentation in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. One possibility would be for each
                    compilation of documents to be preceded by a brief narrative chronology of
                    documents relevant to the compilation, including those not printed. He observed
                    that the voluminous documentation of the essentially parallel development of
                    policy towards the various eastern European countries raised the question of
                    giving consideration to some sort of narrative treatment as a means of curbing
                    the size of future compilations for the area. Mr. Franklin stated that if the
                    administrative restriction on the number of volumes continued,<hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> might feel constrained to use this approach.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold asked how the subject of the formulation of Department policy would
                    be handled in the 1946 compilations. Mr. Harrington suggested that policy
                    planning should be documented, even though such planning did not eventuate in
                    policy. Mr. E. R. Perkins expressed strong opposition to this viewpoint. Mr.
                    Noble expressed concern over the ability of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to do justice to policy planning in the future because the
                    Policy Planning Staff and other parts of the Department had expressed strong
                    opposition to the inclusion of briefing papers in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. The point was also made that access to NSC papers might
                    prove difficult.</p>
                <p>Mr. Harrington expressed the view that the speed of publication was of great
                    importance to the historical profession and learned societies. He tied the
                    problem to that of access to the records of the Department by private
                    researchers, hoping that access to more current material would be afforded if
                    publication slowed down. Mr. Franklin stated that his policy was to try to get
                    the period of access moved along as each year of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> was published and that there was a vital correlation between
                    speed of publication and the liberalization of access rather than the reverse.
                    Mr. Parks explained how the procedures on access worked.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin asserted that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> for 1946
                    would be compiled in the field of first-priority subjects until stock could be
                    taken of space and time requirements; if these were favorable, second and
                    possibly third-priority subjects would then be considered.</p>
                <p>There was further discussion of the “philosophy of history” as it applied to the
                    problems of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. E. R. Perkins raised
                    the question as to how to treat such ad hoc problems as economic warfare,
                    removing the Nazis from Latin America, the proclaimed list, etc., if hindsight
                    on the continuing importance of subjects should be the governing consideration.
                    Mr. Goodrich noted that the problem would also present itself in reverse
                    fashion. As a case in point, he queried whether we would feel constrained to
                    examine every nook and cranny for documentation on the antecedents of Cuban
                    Communism in 1946 since the questions of Communism in Cuba is a major problem
                    today. He felt that Cuba in 1946 should have the pace warranted by its
                    importance as that time rather than its importance today. Mr. Harrington
                    disagreed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold commented favorably that HO carried out all requests made by the
                    Committee in 1961 except for the question as to whether the annual approach
                    should be abandoned. Mr. Franklin said that it seemed desirable to retain this
                    approach for various reasons, particularly because it gave a chronological
                    “push” for the regular clearance for each year’s volumes.</p>
                <p rend="center">AFTERNOON SESSION</p>
                <p>Assistant Secretary Manning greeted the Advisory Committee at 2:15 p.m. and
                    discussed the problems of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He stressed
                    the sense of history he himself felt and the admiration and envy he felt for the
                    profession of historian. He stated that as journalist and newspaper editor he
                    had noted that the written word was more effective when compressed and concluded
                    that 10 volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> were a reasonable
                    number in view of budgetary stringency.</p>
                <p>Mr. Harrington extended the appreciation of the Committee for the sympathetic
                    attitude of Mr. Manning toward the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    program and then outlined to the four basic problems facing the Historical
                    Office in the compilation and publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, problems which the Committee expected to raise with
                    the Secretary of State at luncheon the following day.</p>
                <p>1. Quantity of publication: Mr. Harrington emphasized the importance the
                    scholarly world attached to the continued full presentation of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>. He noted that without a rein on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>, as many as 20 volumes a year might be compiled in
                    the postwar period. He agreed with Mr. manning;s observations on the
                    effectiveness of compression in enhancing our product and realized as well that
                    budgetary considerations precluded a publication program of such extent. The
                    Committee had agreed, therefore, to the compression of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to a maximum of 10 volumes annually. He expressed the
                    Committee’s concern that should budgetary considerations be uppermost in the
                    minds of those who administered the Department, there might be an administrative
                    decision to cut the maximum number of volumes to a point that would impair the
                    usefulness of the series. Assurances might be sought that this would not be
                    allowed to happen.</p>
                <p>2. Personnel question: Mr. Harrington noted that in previous years the Congress
                    had been the stumbling block to adequate funds for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> program. He expressed the concern of the Committee that now
                    it was the Department that was reluctant to allocate adequate funds to maintain
                    the operation. Not only was the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff
                    not increasing in line with its wider responsibilities but was actually
                    shrinking. He expressed the Committee’s concern that young men were not being
                    recruited to assume future leadership of the program and that staff salaries
                    were insufficient to attract outstanding personnel to Government service in view
                    of the competition of higher salaries on college faculties.</p>
                <p>3. Publication gap: Mr. Harrington recalled that the increasing time-lag between
                    events covered and the publication of the documentation of these events was an
                    important issue in the minds of the Committee members. He noted the pride of
                    American scholars that the United States was far ahead of the rest of the world
                    in the publication of its diplomatic papers, and he stressed the advantage that
                    this afforded to the American scholarly community to able to write on a
                    scientific basis concerning international affairs of recent times. He expressed
                    concern, now that the United States was the paramount world power with all the
                    attendant political, financial and other obligations, that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> might fall farther behind currency because of the
                    sensitivity of the material and budgetary considerations.</p>
                <p>4. Clearance: Mr Harrington expressed the Committee’s concern over the clearance
                    problem but did not go into detail in this matter.</p>
                <p>In reply, Mr. Manning stated there had been a tendency in the Department and in
                    Congress to downgrade the importance of all Departmental activities not in the
                    main stream of policy and that this was a problem not only for <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> and the Historical Office but for the entire Bureau
                    of Public Affairs in connection with budgetary and other problems. But the
                    release of all types of information to the American people was of tremendous
                    importance. He felt that the attitude in the Department that P functions were
                    peripheral was breaking down and as P’s position was strengthened, the position
                    of HO would improve as well.</p>
                <p>Mr. Manning was especially pleased that Mr. Harrington had raised the question of
                    the recruitment of young people, which he also considered important. As regards
                    clearance, Mr. manning counseled that this operation was one that must be
                    diligently and tirelessly pursued and that such persistent tactics would win in
                    the end. As regards the time-lag, Mr. Manning felt that the Secretary was not
                    greatly disturbed about the twenty-year lag and would probably not favor a
                    decrease in the lag.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall drew attention to the fact that several times in recent years the
                    Historical Office had lost promising talent because it had been unable to
                    guarantee that, by the time security clearances were completed, the job slot
                    would not have been abolished. Mr. manning thought that the situation in this
                    regard would be more encouraging in the future.</p>
                <p>Mr. Perkins stressed the deleterious effect on morale of the staff caused by the
                    slowness of clearance and publishing procedures and the failure of the
                    Department to effectuate President Kennedy’s September 1961 letter.</p>
                <p>The Committee then went into executive session.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Saturday Morning, November 3, 1962, 9:00
                        a.m.</hi></p>
                <p>Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Dexter Perkins (Chairman)</item>
                            <item>Clarence A. Berdahl</item>
                            <item>Leland M. Goodrich</item>
                            <item>Fred H. Harrington</item>
                            <item>Richard W. Leopold</item>
                            <item>Philip W. Thayer</item>
                            <item>Robert R. Wilson</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin</item>
                            <item>G. M. R. Dougall</item>
                            <item>E. R. Perkins</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Dexter Perkins opened the meeting by asking what points the Committee should
                    take up at luncheon with Secretary of State Rusk, particularly since Mr. Rusk
                    was understood not to favor bringing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes any closer to currency than at present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that during yesterday’s discussions he came to feel that one
                    fact dominated our present predicament, namely, the lack of any agreed
                    publication schedule. Such a schedule, approved by the Department as a matter of
                    standing policy, would serve as a target for the Historical office and the
                    Division of Publications and would afford leverage in dealing with budget
                    officers and in getting clearance for our galleys. We would have a regular
                    established position with the normal presumption that the Department would
                    provide the personnel and funds to carry out our assigned tasks according to a
                    predetermined program, one not subject to slowdowns whenever the budget got
                    tight. Without a definite schedule we have no strong defense against periodic
                    cuts, and our experience has been that we rarely could regain lost ground. With
                    a fixed timetable we could go to the administrators and budget people and point
                    to the measurable needs and actual deadlines. Also, a regular schedule would
                    protect us in the future from special series, which have caused us so many
                    problems in recent years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Churchill commented that getting a 20-year commitment would not of itself
                    solve our problems of staff and clearances, but there was general agreement that
                    such a commitment would make our budget presentation much more effective, for we
                    should not then be regarded as an operation that could be slowed down whenever
                    funds were short. We particularly must have some momentum in order to attract
                    new recruits of the caliber we seek.</p>
                <p>Members of the Committee discussed what the proper interval should be: 20, 25, or
                    30 year, for example, or even the 15 years mentioned in President Kennedy’s
                    letter of September 1961. It was hard to be dogmatic on this, since it was a
                    matter of balancing needs of national security and national enlightenment, both
                    of which are important. Mr. Harrington pointed out that if the Committee
                    recommended 20 years, this in itself represented a great concession on the part
                    of the scholarly world, and one which should be recognized by the Department of
                    State, which had invited the Committee’s views on this matter. The learned
                    societies were trying to be reasonable, and they hoped that the Department
                    appreciated this. There was a major public interest in the question, one going
                    beyond the immediate convenience of the Department, which must recognize its
                    obligations in the matter. Mr. Ralph Perkins, pointing to the advantages of
                    early publication both for the usefulness of the series and for the morale of
                    the staff, expressed the view that more use should be made of President
                    Kennedy’s letter of September 1961, and there was considerable discussion as to
                    how this could best be done. Mr. Goodrich thought it was particularly important
                    to arouse Secretary Rusk’s interest, both as a scholar and a practitioner in
                    diplomacy and international relations, in the solid merits and practical utility
                    of the series and to persuade him to lay it down as his own policy that the
                    series should be afforded the priorities and resources it needed to maintain the
                    very fine tradition it has long enjoyed but which is now endangered. Without the
                    full weight of the Secretary’s authority behind the series, it could hardly be
                    expected to fulfill its historic function in a way acceptable to the scholarly
                    world, as represented by this Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold agreed that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was a customary
                    and traditional activity of the Department of State, of great value to the
                    scholarly world, and Mr. Gleason added that it was valuable not only to the
                    professors but also to their students, to whom the benefits were directly
                    communicated. Mr. Harrington commented that most Americans did not know enough
                    about these things and that it was up to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to supply much of the basic information. Mr. Goodrich and Mr.
                    Wilson said that these volumes were the logical place to begin research on most
                    questions of U.S. foreign policy and that it was important to give them proper
                    backing. Mr. Ralph Perkins noted that in the early years the volumes came out
                    soon after the events; he felt that the longer interval detracted from the
                    usefulness. Morale had never been higher than during the editing of the China
                    volumes, which were expected to appear promptly. Mr. Leopold agreed that a sense
                    of timeliness and urgency made a great difference, but he thought that in
                    addition to the delays another drawback was that there were too many volumes now
                    per year for convenient use by desk officers and foreign service officers. One
                    of the merits of the tighter selection would be to make the volumes more useful
                    through elimination of much marginal material.</p>
                <p>Summing up this phase of the discussion, the Chairman said that the Committee
                    should take up with Secretary Rusk the question of setting a definite interval
                    between events and publication, and that it should explore the possibility of
                    getting the Secretary’s agreement in principle to have the Department provide
                    the resources needed to do the job properly and steadily. The Committee need not
                    necessarily press for any particular interval, such as 20 years, but they ought
                    to try to get the principle accepted.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ralph Perkins then raised the question mentioned in the previous day’s
                    meeting as to how much attention should be given to technical subjects, such as
                    suppression of opium traffic, whaling conventions, and the like. Mr. Leopold
                    said that the Committee had considered this matter in its closed meeting
                    yesterday and that there had been some sentiment for holding this material down
                    to a reasonable limit. Mr. Goodrich added that the Committee did not wish to go
                    into particulars, for these were matters of judgment on the part of the editors,
                    and it was not asking for automatic exclusion of certain topics that sounded
                    unpromising on the face of it, but they did hope that excessive detail could be
                    avoided. Bracketed notes and similar editorial devices should be used freely
                    when there were good standard sources to cite to, and the editors should show
                    some “restraint” on minor matters. As had been said the previous day,
                    compression actually improved many stories. While the Committee had ideas on the
                    relative importance of various matters, it was really up to the editors to
                    decide what to cut. The priorities system used for 1946 seemed to offer a very
                    good solution, and Mr. Berdahl asked if it could be applied to 1945. Mr.
                    Churchill gave an illustration that this was already being done; when the
                    editors found that a particular Soviet story was rated as second priority in
                    1946, they had gone back to shorten the related story for 1945. Mr. Berdahl
                    thought that this sort of review should be very helpful.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ralph Perkins then brought up the question, which went back in part to last
                    year’s discussions, about consolidating certain subjects which apply to many
                    countries. He asked if scholars were interested more in countries or in topics?
                    Should we stress coffee or Brazil? Mr. Goodrich thought there was a growing
                    emphasis on the multilateral at the expense of the bilateral but that the
                    Committee could not be very helpful on this point. Mr. Harrington felt that the
                    plan reflected the growing trend toward interdisciplinary scholarship, but he
                    noted that some scholars were still interested in countries as such.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then noted that our discussions in preparing the plan for 1946 had
                    brought to light an interesting contrast, between the approach of stressing
                    “foreign relations” and that of stressing “foreign policy”. Both were desirable
                    but under pressure of space the former might have to be where the cutting would
                    be done. Mr. Ralph Perkins pointed out that foreign policy is not made in a
                    vacuum but develops in particular cases, and that the series customarily has
                    shown the factual situations which have led to the policy decisions. Under the
                    pressure to compress our documentation we naturally have to give priority to
                    papers which describe the fully-formulated policy, but we try to give enough of
                    the story to explain the actual circumstances giving rise to a particular
                    policy. Mr. Gleason agreed that the facts are interesting and important, and
                    only questioned how many we can include and still stay within the bounds imposed
                    on us. There was some discussion of the documents on the Eastern European
                    countries in 1945 as a knotty editorial question: When policy is roughly the
                    same but conditions vary from country to country, how to allocate space? It was
                    agreed that this was a challenge to the editors, and the Advisory Committee did
                    not think they could be helpful in detail on questions of this sort. Mr.
                    Harrington said there was no real controversy here, for the 1946 plan solved the
                    problem by assigning priorities which took all factors into account. The plan
                    had given a new and much-needed dimension to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Mr. Goodrich added that it was impossible to please everyone
                    in this regard. The main thing was to make decisions on the basis of our best
                    judgment, and the Committee would support us.</p>
                <p>After a short break, the Committee went into a closed session.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
