<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1964</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1964</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-08">April 8, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1964-11-06">November 6-7, 1964</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1964-11-06-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 815 KB, 19pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1964—Minutes. Limited Official
                Use.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1964 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 6-7, 1964</dateline>
                <p>The morning session on Friday, November 6, began at approximately 9:30 a.m.</p>
                <p>Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Richard W. Leopold, Chairman</item>
                            <item>William W. Bishop, Jr.</item>
                            <item>Robert H. Ferrell</item>
                            <item>Philip E. Mosely<note n="*" place="end" xml:id="fn1">These new
                                    members of the Committee were sworn in by Angier Biddle Duke,
                                    Chief of Protocol, in ceremonies in the West Diplomatic
                                    Reception Room, at 9:15 a.m. (AGENDA ITEM l)</note></item>
                            <item>Robert E. Osgood</item>
                            <item>Robert B. Stewart*</item>
                            <item>Robert R. Wilson</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>E. Taylor Parks</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Peter V. Curl</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>George O. Kent</item>
                            <item>Richard S. Patterson</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Newton O. Sappington</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>Almon R. Wright</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Francis T. Murphy, Executive Director</item>
                            <item>Eleanor G. Jacobson</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Publication and Reproduction Services Division:<list>
                            <item>Jerome H. Perlmutter, Chief</item>
                            <item>Peter A. Smith</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 2: Opening remarks</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin welcomed the members of the Committee and announced that Mr. Leopold
                    had been chosen as Chairman. He noted that the Historical Office was much the
                    same as at this time last year--the same 39 authorized positions, some 37 souls
                    to fill them and two seemingly perpetual vacancies. He also stated that for the
                    first time in several years, the Committee would take a look at some items
                    deleted from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> because of clearance
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 3: Report on status of the series and publication
                    plans</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl distributed two charts describing the status of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>. He stated that all volumes for 1942 and earlier had
                    been published except for the volume dealing with the three Washington
                    Conferences and Casablanca, 1941-1943. Manuscript on the Third Washington
                    Conference was being reviewed in HO and the remainder was in the hands of the
                    technical editors in PB. It was expected that this volume would be released late
                    in 1965. The volume on the two Quebec Conferences had not progressed because the
                    historians assigned to them had been detailed to work of higher priority. Mr.
                    Franklin noted that a greater length of time was needed to compile these volumes
                    in contrast to the annual volumes because of the greater detail they embodied.
                    He felt that a complete documentation was required for the conferences in order
                    to avoid charges of suppressing the record. He corroborated Mr. Aandahl’s
                    estimate that the Washington and Casablanca conferences volume would be released
                    late in 1965 unless touchy clearance problems arose. He did not anticipate that
                    any would arise. He was not as optimistic, in this respect, concerning the
                    Quebec conferences because of treatment of sensitive subjects, such as the
                    Morgenthau Plan. He noted that the Historical Office for many years had
                    possessed the basic documentation for the wartime conferences and had responded
                    to numerous inquiries on the conferences on the strength of this documentation.
                    It had been discovered, however, that much more research was required in
                    Department files and in the papers of other agencies in order to prepare the
                    complete record of the conferences.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl observed that all regular volumes for 1943 had been published except
                    for volumes V and VI. These two volumes were being indexed and would probably be
                    released about March 1965. He noted that the volumes for 1944 were well along
                    toward clearance and would probably be released in 1965 except for the American
                    Republics (vol. VI) which would likely appear the following year. Mr. Gleason
                    cautioned that vol. IV on Europe might also be delayed because of clearance
                    difficulties raised by Defense. He finally concluded that Defense was not
                    unfavorable to publication <hi rend="underline">per se</hi> but certainly was
                    not disposed to speedy clearance. The staff was now coping with a four-page,
                    single-spaced Defense memorandum on vol. IV which in large measure requested us
                    to obtain British clearance of State documents which quoted or summarized
                    Combined Chiefs of Staff papers. HO had previously decided not to seek such
                    clearance. Defense had taken an excessively long time in answering our clearance
                    query. Part of the slowness was due to the bureaucratic organization of Defense
                    with the necessity of its obtaining JCS, Army, Navy and Air Force concurrence in
                    the formulation of Defense views. We ultimately got from Defense what we were
                    after but the time factor was most difficult. This was in contrast to Treasury,
                    Interior and other Governmental units which gave us few if any clearance
                    problems and were rapid in their response.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl concluded his discussion of the 1944 volumes with a statement that HO
                    had made a decision to number the China volumes beginning with that year to
                    facilitate cross-referencing. In reply to Mr. Wilson’s question whether complete
                    coverage would be given to the 1944 Civil Aviation Conference at Chicago, Mr.
                    Aandahl answered in the affirmative, taking into account published material.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl then reviewed the status of the 1945 volumes. Five of the eight
                    regular volumes were in various stages of clearance and he anticipated that all
                    the 1945 volumes would be published in 1966, except the American Republics
                    volume which he hoped would be released in 1967. As for 1946, he stated that
                    nearly all of these volumes would be compiled by the end of 1964.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop inquired whether the San Francisco Conference compilation would
                    include the reprinting of papers already published. Mrs. Cassidy replied that
                    there was no duplication of printed material but there was extensive
                    cross-referencing to such materials. She noted that the chief stress in the
                    compilation was on American Delegation papers and correspondence, previously
                    unpublished.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Wilson as to why there were two China volumes
                    for 1946, Mr. Gleason stated that two volumes had been required because of the
                    detailed treatment given to the Marshall Mission. He had recently undertaken a
                    special review of these volumes to see whether the two volumes could be reduced
                    to one. He had decided against doing so because of the importance of the Mission
                    and the high level of the material used. He noted that the record might have
                    been compressed if there had been summary telegrams to use. Regrettably, there
                    were no such adequate summaries. Mr, Franklin underscored the ever-increasing
                    need to condense <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> through the
                    utilization of summary documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell inquired whether there might be a return in the foreseeable future to
                    the practice of allowing scholars to have access to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> galleys prior to publication. Mr. Franklin stated that such
                    access had never been a general policy of HO. In a few exceptional cases, such
                    access had been granted. The question of equity was involved. Moreover, galleys
                    were now classified materials, which complicated giving access to scholars, who
                    normally did not have Department clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Parks gave a brief summary of the recent history of access. He observed that
                    from about 1950 to about 1960, several scholars had been given access,
                    informally, to cleared galleys where such access would bring their material one
                    year closer to currency. New considerations, however, came into play thereafter.
                    Mr. Feis’ request for access differed from previous ones in that the scope of
                    his entire volume paralleled that of the Potsdam papers. The situation grew
                    serious, when because of the decision to include additional important materials
                    and HO’s dependence on GPO schedules, the Potsdam volumes were not released
                    until after Mr. Feis had already published his volume. The situation was further
                    worsened when two journalists who had been given access to the Potsdam papers
                    before their release wrote sensational articles on the decision to drop the
                    atomic bomb. These articles, which seriously distorted the Potsdam records, had
                    a further unfortunate result for the Department inasmuch as they also appeared
                    before publication of the Potsdam volumes. These experiences made necessary the
                    termination of the practice of granting access to unpublished galleys.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 4: Report on the conference volumes:</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted that this item had been sufficiently covered under previous
                    agenda item. He added comments on the standards of inclusion. Coverage was
                    extremely intensive based on the necessity of including materials on a virtual
                    hour-by-hour basis to avoid any suspicion of censoring the record. He regretted
                    that such treatment had delayed preparation of the conference volumes but he
                    trusted that the Committee would approve the special intensity of treatment.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 5: Report on the annual volumes for 1946:</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason stated that the major compiling problem was the enormous
                    proliferation of documentation in the Department’s files. He expressed the
                    conviction that, had we continued to compile on the same basis as before, the
                    number of volumes would have increased to the point of impairing the value of
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to scholars and other users. A plan
                    was therefore devised for 1946 which for the first time established a series of
                    priorities to ensure that major policies or negotiations were treated first and
                    that marginal problems were cut back drastically or eliminated. As a result, we
                    have been successful in holding the regular annual volumes for 1946 to seven or
                    eight, in addition to the two China volumes already in galleys. Where figures
                    were available, the number of manuscript pages was considerably less than the
                    original estimates made in the plan. The process of weeding out low-priority
                    subjects and documents had at times proved painful but had enhanced the value of
                    the series by malting the volumes more manageable and readable. The quality of
                    the volumes had stood up well but scholars would have to do more work than
                    before as a result of some of the short cuts we had adopted. He mentioned some
                    of the time-saving practices that had been instituted by the technical editors
                    and touched on similar practices contemplated for use in our 1947 work, such as
                    simplification of headings. He noted that except for the two General Section
                    volumes dealing primarily with the UN and the Council of Foreign Ministers,
                    compilation for 1946 would be completed by the end of 1964.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 6: Efforts to expedite output:</p>
                <p>a) Budget estimates and problems: Mr. Gleason noted that Mr. Franklin had already
                    mentioned this matter and that we should hear more of it later in the
                    morning.</p>
                <p>b) Editorial procedures: Mr. Gleason cited a number of changes in editorial
                    procedures involving various short cuts by the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff and the technical editors. He concluded that the short
                    cuts had resulted in expediting output without compromising our traditional high
                    standards.</p>
                <p>c) Clearances and deletions: Mr. Gleason stated the record on these matters had
                    improved over the last year. Except for a perennial problem such as the
                    Peru-Ecuador boundary dispute, clearance difficulties had forced us to delete
                    only occasional documents or phrases which he felt did not impair the integrity
                    of the record. Such deletions did not bulk large in content and were usually
                    more colorful than essential. In cases where we felt that requested deletions
                    would impair the record, we put up a vigorous resistance with generally
                    satisfactory results. He indicated that later in the day he would make available
                    to the Committee various galleys showing typical deletions on which we had been
                    obliged to yield, or on which we had won.</p>
                <p>d) Reaction to volume II, 1943: Mr. Gleason noted that clearance difficulties
                    were sometimes accentuated by reviews of our volumes in the press. He cited, as
                    a case in point, press reaction to 1943, volume II. The French press was most
                    critical of the volume as insulting to General de Gaulle. The press of the world
                    also dealt extensively with the attitude of the Vatican toward Nazi persecution
                    of the Jews at a time when a play on the same subject had raised temperatures.
                    Such controversies made the geographic desks more averse to sanctioning
                    publication of sensitive papers, even in cases where a great deal of knowledge
                    of the matters covered had been long in the public domain. Our chief approach
                    was to convince the geographic desks that we were not hopelessly embarrassing
                    the conduct of current diplomatic negotiations by untimely publication.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 7: Special report on UN compilation for 1946:</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason stated that Mr. Goodwin would explain later our plans for dealing
                    with United States policy with respect to this question for 1946 and subsequent
                    years.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 8: Priorities for 1947 compilations:</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason stated that we had not prepared a plan of priorities for 1947 like
                    that for 1946 because of the pressure of time. The researchers had prepared
                    first priority items only. A hard look would be taken at other subjects as they
                    emerged from a closer study of the files.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold asked the Committee for comments on Mr. Gleason’s presentation. Mr.
                    Stewart raised a question on the method of presenting and justifying budgetary
                    requests to the Congress. Mr. Franklin explained that Mr. Murphy would make an
                    appearance shortly to speak on the questions of budgets and Congressional
                    presentation. He noted that Congressman Rooney, head of the House Subcommittee
                    on the State Department budget, accepted <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> as a proper function and understood that the series was aimed
                    at the image-forming elite.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then discussed the budget. Printing and binding money, he said, was
                    the only item specifically set forth in our budget. Last year, HO received a
                    printing and binding budget of $18,500, an insufficient sum when it cost about
                    $15,000 to print and bind a single volume of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Expenditures for printing and binding a given volume were
                    not made in one fell swoop but at different stages. We were able to squeak by,
                    first, because the GPO was willing to accept a down payment of $3,500 per volume
                    instead of the customary $7,000 and then only because Mr. Murphy was able to
                    provide further funds. As a result, $58,500 was actually spent on printing and
                    binding last year. This year the printing and binding budget was $22,500,
                    although, as Mr. Dougall noted, HO had requested $123,000. Mr. Franklin
                    expressed the views that $60,000 was a minimum figure and that if we were to
                    make the twenty-year goal a reality, $120,000 would be needed. In reply to a
                    question by Mr. Ferrell on the size of a press run of a volume, Mr. Franklin
                    stated that approximately 4000 copies were an average run. Some 700-800 copies
                    were distributed to various depositories and 350-400 were distributed by the
                    Department. The GPO retained the remainder for sale to the public. Mr. Dougall
                    commented that the Superintendent of Documents was free to print as many copies
                    he felt able to sell. Thus the Yalta volume had a much higher run than
                    average.</p>
                <p>Mr. Perlmutter and Mr. Smith joined the group at about 10:50 a.m. and a
                    discussion of technical editing problems followed. Mr. Perlmutter expressed his
                    belief in the necessity of recruiting younger personnel in PB so that the
                    expertise of the existing staff would be blended with the vigor of younger
                    employees. He mentioned, short cuts in editing made by his staff without
                    impairing the quality of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He noted that
                    the Department was using the budgetary concept of the working capital fund under
                    which his office drew on funds charged to HO for services performed and used
                    these funds to pay the salaries of his staff and to pay outsiders for contract
                    work on indexes. The first job of the newly-arrived Mr. Smith was to recruit
                    promising free-lance workers trained in the subject matter of the volumes to
                    index them more speedily than before. Mr. Smith stated that a volume has been
                    contracted out for indexing purposes to a candidate for an MA in History at
                    George Washington University at a rate of $1.15 per page, conditional upon PB
                    doing the name entries. He hoped that continuity would be provided in such
                    contract work to ensure the most efficient operation. Mr. Franklin emphasized
                    that the Committee would wish the quality of the indexes maintained, especially
                    their analytical features.</p>
                <p>Mr. Murphy, accompanied by Miss Jacobson, arrived at 11 a.m. He stressed the
                    facts that money spent by the Department was taxpayers’ money and that it was
                    important to be aware that money saved by economies was the money of all of us.
                    He emphasized that HO had never lacked money to publish volumes and was
                    confident that this would continue to be the case. It had to be realized that
                    HO’s expenditures were large, amounting to $500,000, primarily for salaries and
                    $58,000 for printing and binding. HO accounted for 27% of the Bureau’s total
                    expenditures. The Bureau had 150 positions and HO’s 39 employees made it the
                    largest office in the Bureau and one which received great attention from the top
                    officers of the Bureau. It was not possible to give HO all it desired any more
                    than it was possible to do so for any other office. What must be done was to
                    find the most desirable plateau. At the same time, he was not optimistic about
                    future additions to our budget because he anticipated continued stress by the
                    administration on economy and efficiency of operation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Murphy then gave statistics illustrating the Bureau’s budgetary problems. In
                    1958, the Bureau had spent $1,200,000 for salaries of 156 persons and had
                    expended an additional $266,000 for non-salary items. For fiscal year 1965, the
                    Bureau anticipated spending $1,650,000 for salaries of 150 persons and $533,000
                    for non-salary items. The steady upward trend of expenditures required great
                    efforts to hold costs down and to use our resources prudently. He concluded by
                    stating that five volumes had been published last year, one of the largest in
                    the recent history of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stated that the Advisory Committee favored a twenty-year gap and
                    that Secretary Rusk had given a nod of approval in this direction. We could not
                    hold to that goal with five volumes a year and eight volumes must be aimed for
                    if we were to remain within hailing distance of that goal. Mr. Leopold added
                    that the Advisory Committee was being pressed by scholarly organizations about
                    the slow pace of publishing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Murphy observed that he read the scholarly journals in order to glean
                    information that might be useful in his presentation of HO money requests in
                    Department budget discussions. He then continued with a description of the
                    budgetary cycle. Usually in September, the Bureau put together a draft budget.
                    These figures were honed over by groups under the direct chairmanship of the
                    Secretary and the Under Secretary. A final product delineating what the
                    Department would like to have was then submitted to the Bureau of the Budget.
                    Final decisions were made in the Executive Office of the President and notice
                    given to the Department of the budget to be submitted to the Hill. The
                    Department had then to review its operations and fit itself into the proposed
                    budget. In the Congressional examination of the proposed budget, two figures
                    were of special import: the Base Figure, the money currently being spent for a
                    given program, and the Increase, the amount above the Base Figure being
                    requested for that program. Normally, Congress accepted the Base Figure and
                    looked closely at the Increase. In the absence of Congressional authorization of
                    funds, the Department must “feed on itself” to meet the costs of new programs.
                    Thus when the Department found it necessary to expand its program on Africa and
                    during other emergencies, it was compelled to draw funds from other operations.
                    Mr. Franklin interjected that the Base Figure for printing and binding <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had been $40,000 to $50,000 but that
                    last year the amount had been cut to $18,500, a development he deplored. Mr.
                    Murphy said that printing and binding funds had been made available, however,
                    regardless of the leanness of the Base Figure. He noted that when such funds
                    were needed above the Base Figure, the Bureau had gone to the Department’s
                    budgetary officers and gotten more. Thus the $18,500 had risen to an actual
                    expenditure of $58,000 by the end of the year. This year, the Base Figure was
                    $22,500. The Bureau understood this was insufficient and expected to be able to
                    provide at least as much as last year but this addition could not be
                    guaranteed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked why the twenty-year goal was slipping away, if we had always
                    gotten sufficient printing and binding money. He wondered whether this was due
                    to the need for additional personnel. Mr, Franklin replied that despite efforts
                    by HO and PB to speed up procedures and use short cuts, there was simply an
                    inadequate number of professional people on the staff. Mr. Murphy pointed out
                    that the Bureau was operating under a strict personnel ceiling and had not
                    requested any additions for the last two years because of directives from the
                    President and the Bureau of the Budget. He predicted that the Bureau would not
                    make any requests for increases this year and in the foreseeable future. Mr.
                    Franklin estimated that there was little more that we could do by way of
                    improving procedures to hold the twenty-year line with the existing staff; the
                    goal was slipping from sight.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop noted that the twenty-year goal could certainly not be maintained
                    unless productivity and/or staff were increased, in view of the enormous bulk of
                    documentation in the post-war years. Mr. Leopold noted that the Advisory
                    Committee had accepted the twenty-year goal with reluctance, some of the
                    Committee members having pressed for a fifteen-year lag.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold wondered how planning of the series was affected by the need to go
                    hat in hand for additional printing and binding money. Mr. Franklin pointed to
                    Mr. Aandahl’s charts and said the availability of funds might make them
                    conjectural. He expressed the opinion that if the Base Figure were increased to
                    pay for six and then seven volumes per year, there would be an incentive to the
                    staff toward greater productivity.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart once more alluded to the fact that the printing and binding money was
                    not the primary problem. He asked whether the Committee wished to concentrate on
                    the major problem of personnel ceiling. Mr. Leopold quickly rejoined that such
                    ceiling was a fact of life. He asked Mr. Murphy whether the Committee could help
                    on the budgetary problem. Mr. Morphy said the Committee had done a fine job and
                    asked it to continue its pressure. He was not sanguine, however, that anything
                    could be done because of the rigidity of personnel ceilings.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin observed that a continuing program like the publication of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was hurt more by long unfilled
                    vacancies than an office where work loads could be managed. Mr. Murphy stated no
                    relief was possible soon. On orders from the Bureau of the Budget, he said, 4%
                    of the 150 jobs in the Bureau of Public Affairs could not be filled. He
                    expressed concern lest the Bureau of the Budget raise this percentage. He
                    acknowledged that HO had two long-term vacancies. He noted that vacancies
                    existed elsewhere in the Bureau also and that HO had fared as well as any in
                    filling vacancies. In fact, he added, the only two vacancies beyond the 4% job
                    loss rate recently filled had been filled in HO.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood inquired whether the Advisory Committee1s reports had been used in
                    budgetary presentations to the Congress. Mr. Murphy replied that the reports
                    were not used on the Hill but were used in the Department’s budgetary
                    discussions. Mr. Bishop asked whether the reports could be improved in
                    presentation to be of greater help to Mr. Murphy. He answered in the negative,
                    stating they were well done and could not be improved from his point of
                    view.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart inquired as to the specific justification of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> program given to Congressman Rooney at budget
                    hearings. Mr. Murphy stated, and Mr. Franklin agreed, that the program did not
                    require annual justification at these hearings as the program was solidly
                    established and its value accepted by the Congressman.</p>
                <p>Mr. Murphy noted that Mr. Manning in the last few years had addressed himself to
                    the question of the value of the program in testimony on the Hill and that
                    during the ’40’s, Francis Russell and the then Director of the Historical
                    Office, E. Wilder Spaulding, had also done so. He suggested that Mr. Franklin
                    make excerpts of their testimony available to the Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely inquired whether it would be possible to request a Base Figure
                    appropriation of $50,000 for printing and binding and Mr. Murphy replied in the
                    negative. Mr. Wilson asked whether the Bureau stressed the need to maintain
                    quality in asking for more funds. Mr. Murphy replied that he always stressed
                    quality as well as the question of the time lag.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold thanked Mr. Murphy for his candid presentation and assured him that
                    the Committee would “keep at it”. Mr. Murphy and Miss Jacobson left just before
                    noon.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smith concluded his presentation regarding PB’s efforts to utilize outside
                    skills and resources to help maintain the twenty-year goal. He stated that
                    clearance delays were the main factor in slowing down publication. In response
                    to a query from Mr. Franklin, he admitted that PB would be in a grave difficulty
                    if a large number of volumes were suddenly cleared but pledged PB’s efforts to
                    cope with such a contingency should it occur. Mr. Franklin saw the need to add
                    one person to the PB staff, if the twenty-year line was to be held. He thanked
                    Mr. Smith for his presentation and the latter left at 12:05 p.m.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart returned to the question of justifying the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> program. He stressed the strategic role of Mr. Murphy in the
                    quest for further funds and that the reiteration to him of the twenty-year goal
                    might not be sufficient. He thought that the statements by Russell et al should
                    be set forth in a cogent paper to Mr. Murphy, because Mr. Murphy’s degree of
                    conviction was all-important.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stated that it could no longer be said that the series was of much
                    current-reference value. He recalled that a canvass had been made of Congressmen
                    some time ago to check on their utilization of the volumes. It was discovered
                    that they respected the intellectual qualities of the volumes but that they did
                    not make use of them because of their remoteness from currency.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely, in expressing his justification of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, asserted that democracy operates at its best when a
                    free society knows itself. A major function of the series was to serve as a tool
                    to enable our society to know itself. The fact that the actual documents were
                    presented provided the series with a unique opportunity for achieving this end.
                    Since there was a continuity of basic factors and political judgments, these
                    volumes provided a base of information which a democracy could use in adapting
                    to new problems. In addition, these volumes, by making the record public,
                    ensured against excessive secrecy and spared our democracy from the myths of
                    foreign policy with which European powers found themselves saddled. Furthermore,
                    these volumes helped prepare and train those young people who would some day be
                    in positions of power and responsibility in this country, He also noted that we
                    were helping shape the scholarship of foreigners who now have <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> although they are denied any comparable publication
                    based on the files of their own Foreign Offices and are denied access to those
                    files as well.</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin suggested that the reports of the Senate Appropriations Sub-Committee
                    dealing with the budget of the State Department during the 1950’s under the
                    chairmanship of then Senator Johnson might reveal some interesting comments on
                    the value of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>The morning session of the Committee adjourned at 12:15 p.m. The Committee,
                    accompanied by Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs Greenfield, Mr.
                    Franklin and Mr. Gleason, had lunch with Under Secretary of State Harriman. The
                    Committee reassembled at 2:30 p.m., and Mr. Franklin announced that the
                    Committee had heard encouraging words from on high. In particular, Mr. Harriman
                    and Mr. Greenfield had encouraged the Committee to take its campaign on behalf
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> directly to the appropriate
                    committees on the Hill.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason supplemented his earlier remarks on the 1947 compilations, now in
                    progress. He noted again that less effort had been put into planning for 1947 as
                    opposed to 1946 because of unwillingness to devote time to such a project when
                    all efforts were being devoted to speeding up compilation. He observed that the
                    experience of the staff with the 1946 plan made easier their determination of
                    first priority stories for 1947. A skeleton plan listing first-priority subjects
                    only had been prepared and was available for examination by the Committee. In
                    the meantime, he read a representative listing of first priority titles.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then asked Mr. Goodwin to address himself to the handling of the
                    United Nations aspects of compilation. Mr. Goodwin observed that “everything was
                    new” in connection with the UN, principles and procedures having to be devised
                    for the first time. He then outlined the most important decisions made in the
                    development of these principles and procedures. The initial decision, embodied
                    in the 1946 plan, established two levels of compilation, a general United
                    Nations level embracing procedural and organizational questions and substantive
                    UN questions. An example of the latter type was the question of furnishing
                    military contingents to the UN. Compilations centering on these questions were
                    to be treated in the UN compilation. The second level was concerned with area or
                    regional problems which during their course involved the UN, e.g., the Iranian
                    appeal. Problems of this kind were assigned to the appropriate geographic or
                    area compilation.</p>
                <p>A second decision involved the creation of terms of reference for compiling on
                    the general UN level. Four concepts gradually had emerged:</p>
                <p>1. Primary emphasis was to be placed on the United Nations <hi rend="underline"
                        >proper</hi> rather than on the United Nations <hi rend="underline"
                        >system</hi>, thereby largely excluding the specialized agencies.</p>
                <p>2. Preponderant weight was to be given to political and security issues as the
                    area in which the United States was engaged in “major foreign policy
                    decisions”.</p>
                <p>3. Within the political and security field, emphasis was to be placed on those
                    issues in which the United States determined that the “universal” or global
                    approach was more effective than bilateral, regional, or other multilateral
                    channels and utilized the machinery of the UN for the implementation of a
                    particular United States policy. Examples of these issues were general security
                    matters, trusteeship and the development of law in international relations.</p>
                <p>4. The UN as a political institution and United States policies relating thereto
                    warranted careful treatment in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    Examples of pertinent issues were United States involvement in constitutional,
                    organizational and political matters directly affecting the structure of the UN
                    itself and the balance of political power there.</p>
                <p>A third decision related to the establishment of procedures for compiling those
                    sections of bilateral subjects in which there was a UN presence. Initial
                    responsibility has been placed on the area specialist. The UN specialist has
                    been charged with contributing to and ensuring that the UN aspects of the
                    compilation have been adequately treated.</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin made mention of the earlier decision to focus on political and
                    security issues as the area in which the United States was engaged in “major
                    foreign policy decisions”. He raised the question as what this expression meant
                    in terms of United States involvement with the UN. He then set forth the formula
                    to be used, in the following terms: “The term ‘major foreign policy decisions’
                    will be construed to mean those policy decisions and diplomatic actions that
                    utilized the machinery of the United Nations at any given moment as the most
                    effective medium for the expression of a particular United States policy; or
                    that, in response to the United Nations policies of another state or states,
                    resulted in the assumption of a strong leadership position by the United States
                    at the United Nations: or that involved the United States significantly in
                    United Nations political and constitutional issues; such actions standing in an
                    immediate relationship to a vital United States interest and being of
                    consequence in the diplomatic history of that interest.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin then set forth the organization developed for 1946 compilations
                    involving the UN. The General volume would deal with the general policy of the
                    United States toward the UN, voting in the Security Council, admission of new
                    members, the trusteeship system, general security matters and United States
                    interest in the furtherance of the rule of law. The European and British
                    Commonwealth volume would treat such problems as refugees, war crimes and the
                    Southwest Africa question. The Near East volume would document the actions of
                    the Security Council involving Iran, Greece, and Syria and Lebanon. The Far East
                    volume would deal with Siam and Indonesia.</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin concluded his remarks by describing some of the compilation
                    procedures that had been developed for stories involving UN subjects: the
                    establishment of forms and styles for headings and for footnote citations to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Official Records</hi> of the several UN organs; the
                    setting up of priorities as between UN and other official sources for purposes
                    of citation; and the establishment of differing compilation objectives and
                    procedures (the broadening of the volume of documentation, the extent of the use
                    made of the verbatim record and the utilization of footnotes and bracketed notes
                    to expand and clarify the record) for subjects of prime significance to the
                    United States, e.g., the Iranian question, as opposed to subjects of lesser
                    importance, e.g., the Spanish question.</p>
                <p>The Committee adjourned at 3:30 p.m. for coffee with the Secretary of State in
                    the Monroe Room. The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff members were
                    excused from further participation in the Committee’s discussions.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Saturday Session, November 7, 1964, 9
                        a.m.</hi></p>
                <p>Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Richard W. Leopold, Chairman</item>
                            <item>William W. Bishop, Jr.</item>
                            <item>Robert H. Ferrell</item>
                            <item>Philip E. Mosely</item>
                            <item>Robert E. Osgood</item>
                            <item>Robert R. Wilson</item>
                            <item>(Mr. Stewart was attending another meeting elsewhere in the
                                Department)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Leopold opened the meeting by asking whether the Committee’s report should
                    take approximately the same form as in previous years. Mr. Franklin thought that
                    it should and pointed out that brevity increased its chances of being read in
                    the Department and printed by the learned journals. Mr. Leopold thought the
                    report should cover the status of the series, prospects for holding the 20-year
                    line, clearance, access to files by unofficial researchers, personnel, and
                    budget. Mr. Franklin remarked that this was crisp and clear and that he had no
                    special recommendations. The Committee might wish to note that this year it had
                    reviewed the question of deletions and had seen various examples, and they might
                    wish to comment on this. Mr. Franklin also mentioned the open hint from Mr.
                    Harriman and Mr. Greenfield that the Committee might be well advised to approach
                    appropriate members of Congress directly in the interest of the series; this
                    should not go into the written report, of course.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that he expected to have the minutes sent out by the end of the
                    following week.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson asked if there had been any problem in getting the Committee’s report
                    of last year printed. Mr. Leopold said only the historians had lagged on this;
                    the international law and political science journals had published the report in
                    full and sooner. He also asked about the Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulletin</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi>, and Mr. Franklin
                    said he would see what coverage could be arranged. Mr. Leopold then asked if
                    there were any other aspect of the work of the Historical Office on which the
                    Committee could usefully comment, and Mr. Franklin replied that the Office was
                    pushing hard on the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> volumes, which were
                    mentioned in last year’s report, and that in addition to the regular staff
                    headed by Messrs. Parks and Curl various specialists from Mr. Dougall’s
                    Historical Studies Division were also being used. The volumes for 1961 and 1962
                    should be published in 1965, and the manuscript for 1963 and 1964 should be well
                    advanced.</p>
                <p>At this point the members of the Historical Office withdrew, and the Committee
                    discussed the contents of its report, to be prepared subsequently.</p>
                <p>At 10:20 a.m. the full meeting reconvened.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold said that the Committee was strongly in favor of the proposed “alumni
                    association” of its former members and felt that they should be kept informed of
                    current work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold then said that the Committee wished to discuss with the Historical
                    Office two things: the nature of its report, and the nature of the Committee
                    itself.</p>
                <p>The report would follow last year’s pattern, but would be shorter and follow a
                    somewhat different order. It would again make a play on personnel and budget and
                    would mention the efforts of the Division of Publishing and Reproduction
                    Services to solve the problem of indexing. For the benefit of the associations
                    represented in the Committee the report would briefly summarize the situation
                    with regard to access to Department of State files by unofficial researchers.
                    Mr. Ferrell commented that tying such access to the appearance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes meant that many people would
                    wish to push the publication of these volumes.</p>
                <p>Noting that there was no clear line setting off the closed, restricted, and open
                    periods, Mr. Franklin suggested that interested persons write to the Historical
                    Office for specific information on their particular projects. Much depended on
                    which volumes had been published as of any given time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold then said that the Committee’s report would probably comment on the
                    clearance problem, indicating that there had been some improvement but that
                    there was still a long way to go. The problem seemed less pressing than in some
                    previous years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that since he would circulate copies of the report to the
                    public affairs officers in the various bureaus it might be good to put in a
                    friendly word on their efforts to expedite clearance.</p>
                <p>Referring to the problems of selecting documents and of deletions required by the
                    various bureaus, Mr. Leopold said that the report would state that the Committee
                    had considered the matter and that the Historical Office seemed to be acting
                    wisely and in accordance with the high standards that have characterized the
                    series. Mr. Franklin commented that when deletions were involved we did not
                    always think these standards were so high, but that we sometimes had little
                    choice.</p>
                <p>There would be no mention of the Truman Papers, Mr. Leopold continued, but there
                    would be a word on the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series. As
                    previously noted, the main emphasis in the report would be on the status of the
                    series, personnel, and budget, and account would be taken of the points raised
                    on Friday by Mr. Murphy. The proposal for an intern program would not be
                    mentioned in the report, but would be handled in letters to Messrs. Harrington
                    and Berdahl.</p>
                <p>The report would say something about recruitment and future staff needs, Mr.
                    Leopold went on, and an attempt would be made to provide an arresting first
                    paragraph.</p>
                <p>Turning to the other main subject to be discussed at this time with the
                    Historical Office, Mr. Leopold then spoke of the structure of the Committee
                    itself. As for terms of office, there had been informal but by no means
                    unanimous agreement on 4 years instead of the present 3. As for selection of a
                    new chairman, the most dignified way seemed to be for the retiring chairman to
                    write in late September or in October to the other members to ask their
                    preference for the following year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin thought that the 4-year term would, be acceptable to the
                    administrators of the Department, and Mr. Dougall noted that the proposed change
                    would affect the terms of the continuing members of the Committee. Mr. Franklin
                    pointed out that (so as to avoid possible conflict of interest) the official
                    chairman must be an officer of the Department, but that the selection of the
                    group’s spokesman was an internal matter for the Committee to decide.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson asked what would happen if a member were out of the country or
                    otherwise unavailable. There was no quorum rule, but Mr. Franklin said that in
                    order to meet this contingency he had each year kept the outgoing members
                    officially eligible until their successors were sworn in. In case of need
                    clearance could be reactivated on a previous member from one of the three
                    learned societies represented on the Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Leopold noted that the Committee had authorized him to thank Mr. Harriman and
                    other officers for their hospitality.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell said that he wished to express appreciation to Mr. Gleason for the
                    way he had taken on his new job, and Mr. Leopold said that he was greatly
                    impressed by what Mr. Gleason and his staff were doing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason responded that it was a terrific boost to the morale of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division to have the Committee make its
                    appearance annually to give serious and sympathetic consideration to the work
                    being done.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wilson as a retiring member expressed his personal appreciation for the
                    opportunity to serve this important enterprise of the Department of State. He
                    had found it enjoyable, interesting, and enlightening,</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin replied that the Committee had tremendous value in raising the
                    prestige and stature of the whole operation, for the annual meetings enabled the
                    Office to bring out many things. The Committee’s presence was impressive to the
                    Secretary of State and other officers, and it led them to focus once a year on
                    the work going steadily forward. The Committee provided a favorable and
                    persuasive backdrop which greatly strengthened the efforts of the Historical
                    Office.</p>
                <p>Apropos of a remark made to the group by Mr. Rusk on Friday, Mr. Wilson asked how
                    were the six telegrams a day requiring the Secretary’s attention selected? Mr.
                    Franklin described the Secretary’s staff meeting, and said that unfortunately
                    the Historical Office was not present, so that problems within its area of
                    competence trickled down to us instead of coming directly, as for example a
                    recent inquiry on the Oder-Neisse line. Mr. Dougall said that he had discussed
                    possible remedies with Mr. Greenfield.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, Mr. Leopold expressed the Committee’s gratitude to Mr. Franklin
                    and his staff, and said that this was the best working committee he had served
                    on in Government. It really “dug in” and was not all window dressing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin again expressed the Department’s thanks to the Committee, and noted
                    with appreciation the remarkably high attendance rate through the years.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
