<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1965</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1965</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-08">April 8, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1965-11-05">November 5-6, 1965</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1965-11-05-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 1.6 MB, 23pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1965—Minutes. Limited Official
                Use.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn52">Footnote 52</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1965 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 5-6, 1965</dateline>
                <p>The morning session on Friday, November 5, began at 9:15 a.m. in Room 1105, New
                    State.</p>
                <p>Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Philip E. Mosely, Chairman</item>
                            <item>Robert H. Ferrell</item>
                            <item>Stanley D. Metzger</item>
                            <item>Robert E. Osgood</item>
                            <item>Robert B. Stewart</item>
                            <item>Robert R. Wilson</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>E. Taylor Parks</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>George O. Kent</item>
                            <item>Marvin W. Kranz</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John J. Reed</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 1: Opening Remarks:</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin welcomed the Committee and especially its new member, Mr. Metzger.
                    He expressed regret that Messrs. William W. Bishop, Jr., and J. E. Wallace
                    Sterling were unable to be present and thanked Mr. Wilson for substituting for
                    Mr. Bishop.</p>
                <p>Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs James L. Greenfield joined the
                    group at 9:20. He welcomed the Committee and suggested that it might wish to
                    recess its meeting at 10:30 to attend the Secretary’s press conference. He noted
                    that the earmarking of large sums of money for printing and binding <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was a fact worth noticing and he gave
                    credit for this development to Mr. Crockett (with whom the Committee had a
                    luncheon engagement) and to Congressman Rooney. Mr. Greenfield noted that the
                    large sum earmarked for printing and binding was a good precedent and he hoped
                    it would continue.</p>
                <p>Mr. Greenfield observed, as far as the Bureau of Public Affairs (P) was
                    concerned, that “they” lobbed grenades into our trenches and all through the
                    year P was busy throwing the grenades out. As a result, by the time a year came
                    to an end, it seemed, regretfully, as if P might not have a great deal of
                    permanent value to show for its activity. The <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series was the chief product of lasting and constructive
                    value that came out of the Bureau. The series had attained an even greater
                    importance to the Department and the academic community because of increased
                    interest in and argumentation about foreign affairs. It was a complete and
                    honest review of what the Department of State had done and it contributed toward
                    the credibility of P and the Department. He concluded by thanking the Committee
                    for its contributions to the success of the series.</p>
                <p>After Mr. Greenfield’s departure Mr. Franklin reviewed changes in the Historical
                    Office since the last meeting, including the elevation of Mr. Dougall to the
                    position of Deputy Director and of Mr. Costrell to that of Chief of the
                    Historical Studies Division. He noted also changes in two of the three <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> branches, Mr. Aandahl taking the place
                    of the retired Owen Sappington as Chief of the Western Branch and Mr. Goodwin
                    taking Mr. Aandahl’s former position as Chief of the General Branch, with Mr.
                    Churchill remaining as Chief of the Eastern Branch. In addition to losing the
                    services of Mr. Sappington, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had been
                    hurt by the transfer of Mr. Glennon to duties as editor of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> series. To counterbalance these departures, <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had acquired the services of Marvin
                    Kranz and John J. Reed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stressed the drive to get the <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> series up to date. The 1961 volume had already been released.
                    With part-time assistance from the Historical Studies Division, it was hoped to
                    publish the volumes for 1962 and 1963 within the next twelve months and those
                    for 1964 and 1965 within the twelve months thereafter. As a result, the series
                    would soon be within one year of currency and would be held at that point.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 2: Report on Status of Series and Publication
                    Plans:</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl distributed a chart describing the status of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. He noted that the moving of the volumes
                    through the pipelines toward publication was a grim business but that we had
                    made progress. All the galleys for the Washington and Casablanca Conferences,
                    1941-1943, had been sent to Defense for clearance. The dialogue with Defense
                    usually took about one year but their criticisms and observations had often
                    helped to improve the volumes.</p>
                <p>Volumes III and V for 1944 had been released during the past year; four
                    additional volumes had been cleared and had been sent to the Publishing and
                    Reproduction Services Division (PBR) for putting into page proof and indexing.
                    The China volume provided a special problem, as usual, but of the others for
                    1944 only the one on the American Republics had been unduly delayed. Clearance
                    activities in the Bureau of Inter-American Affairs (ARA) had ceased with the
                    crisis in the Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>Volumes I and II for 1945 been cleared and were ready for paging. The remaining
                    volumes were in clearance or at PBR. Mr. Aandahl noted that the British
                    Government acted speedily on clearance requests, usually within a month or
                    so.</p>
                <p>All the 1946 volumes have taken shape but in larger numbers than estimated last
                    year, primarily because the Paris Peace Conference material required two
                    volumes. The material for 1947 was well advanced but could not be organized into
                    specific volumes as yet.</p>
                <p>At 9:40, the Committee adjourned for ten minutes to have photographs taken in the
                    lobby of the Diplomatic Entrance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart then raised the question as to how British clearance jibed with the
                    policy of the British Government regarding publication of its own papers. Mr.
                    Gleason observed that British complaints regarding clearance were few and were
                    based primarily on the volume of the material presented for clearance, not on
                    its sensitivity. The number of documents sent to London for clearance had soared
                    because Defense insisted that we send not only British documents but even those
                    American documents that reflected activities of the Combined Chiefs of Staff. He
                    said he would be very happy if clearance problems within the Department were as
                    easy of solution as those with the British. He then noted that there was a great
                    deal of sentiment in Britain to advance access to British documents to a period
                    of 35-40 years from currency. He noted the complaint of British scholars that
                    they were obliged to use American publications rather than their own because the
                    former were closer to currency.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart then queried whether a reduction of the British time lag for access
                    would be of value to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Franklin
                    stated that any shortening of the British 50-year rule would be helpful to us.
                    Secretary Rusk has implied that we could not hope to reduce our 20-year lag when
                    all other nations were so far behind us, inquiring “aren’t we way ahead of the
                    others?”. Mr. Metzger asked whether Clive Parry, who is doing a job for the
                    British along the lines of Hackworth and Whiteman, was getting access to more
                    recent documentation. When Mr. Dougall stated that Mr. Parry would presumably
                    have access to such documentation, as did compilers of other British official
                    and semi-official publications, Mr. Metzger observed that these examples might
                    be cited as an answer to queries of the Rusk type. Mr. Franklin stated that
                    there was strong sentiment for Parliament to set the limits on access to British
                    documents by law rather than to allow the British Foreign Office to set
                    them.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 3: Report on Wartime Conference Volumes:</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin reported that the galleys for the volume on the three Washington
                    Conferences and the Casablanca Conference had been sent to Defense for
                    clearance. We were getting priority from Defense but there would also be many
                    wearying months within the Department. At one time we had made progress toward a
                    three-month clearance rule but we had retrogressed. Mr. Ferrell expressed
                    special interest in speedy publication of the documentation on the Casablanca
                    Conference. Mr. Franklin stated that he hoped the high public interest in this
                    volume would stimulate faster action. The basic problem was that clearing
                    galleys was added to the other duties of Desk officers; that was why it took so
                    long. Mr. Ferrell said that it seemed that Desk officers placed galleys in their
                    file cabinet and left them untouched for long periods of time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger inquired whether we had experiences in which the Desks had prevented
                    publication because of high sensitivity of material which HO itself had not
                    spotted as critical. Mr. Franklin acknowledged that this had sometimes happened,
                    and Mr. Gleason stated that an example of this sort of thing would be shown to
                    the Committee later. On the other hand Mr. Franklin felt that publication of a
                    sensitive passage often might produce merely a ripple in the press for a couple
                    of days which would then pass away. He concluded that we defined the areas of
                    real sensitivity in a much smaller compass than did the geographic Desks.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart raised the question of expediting the clearance process. He
                    speculated whether <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> branch chiefs might
                    not volunteer to review compilations with Desk officers and to point out the
                    sensitive portions. These would have the effect, at least, of getting galleys
                    out of file cabinets and reducing the amount of material the Desk officers would
                    have to look at with a critical eye. In the ensuing discussion it was brought
                    out that we had sometimes marked sensitive passages, although Mr. Perkins (Mr.
                    Gleason’s predecessor) had opposed this practice. It was his attitude that it
                    was the business of the Desks to find the sensitive areas and not for us to
                    supply them with data which they might use against us. Mr. Franklin stated that
                    he had taken the opposite point of view at first, particularly in connection
                    with clearing the Yalta volume where he had marked the sensitive passages. On
                    the return of the galleys, Mr. Franklin observed that the Desks had requested
                    deletion of all the marked items as well as many others they regarded as too
                    sensitive for publication. Mr. Gleason noted that the experiment, especially in
                    connection with Defense, had not attained its objectives and that we no longer
                    marked sensitive passages. Mr. Churchill stated this procedure had failed and
                    had resulted merely in more work for the staff.</p>
                <p>In connection with clearance by Defense, Mr. Franklin stated that there was a
                    tendency to attribute our difficulties to Mr. Winnacker, the Historian of the
                    Office of the Secretary of Defense. In justice to Mr. Winnacker it had to be
                    said that he parceled out our galleys to the various services and that he had a
                    hard time with them. He and the historians of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Army,
                    and Navy have often been helpful in supplying identifications and completing
                    information given in our documents. We have sometimes been in accord with their
                    suggestions and felt our volumes were better products as a result. So some of
                    the time spent in review by Defense was useful to us.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Wilson, Mr. Franklin said that as a result of
                    the Committee’s lively interest, we had been able to pry certain volumes (1943,
                    China, and 1941, vol. V, Far East) out of the deep-freeze of the Bureau of Ear
                    Eastern Affairs (FE). Mr. Churchill added that FE had promised to consider
                    sympathetically the release of “China 1944”.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then returned to a discussion of the proposed volume on the Quebec
                    Conferences of 1943 and 1944. Mr. Dougall was working on the first Quebec
                    Conference. The work on the second conference was in abeyance, awaiting the
                    completion, before long, of Mr. Kogan’s work on the Berlin problem. Mr. Franklin
                    noted that we have had the basic documentation on these conferences for a decade
                    and a half and that the compilations were substantially complete. Filling in the
                    final gaps, however, always required an extraordinary amount of time, which we
                    felt was necessary for the conference volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall then discussed some of the difficult problems facing the compilers of
                    the Quebec Conferences. The Conferences were peripatetic, moving between Quebec,
                    Washington, and Hyde Park. A difficult problem was the question of inclusion of
                    material in between these stages. There were also many special collections of
                    papers that required searching because of the large number of persons present.
                    Then too, the number of high-level politico-military subjects discussed at these
                    Conferences was high.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall observed that for the First Quebec Conference there would be a
                    section on arrangements but that the only substantive subject that would need to
                    be treated in the pre-conference chapter was atomic energy. The remaining
                    subjects would be treated more sparingly since they were treated in detail in
                    the annual volumes.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 10:15 for coffee, after which the Committee and the
                    staff attended Secretary Rusk’s press conference. The meeting reconvened at
                    11:20.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin returned to a discussion of the conference volumes. He stated that
                    the slowness and difficulty of compiling such volumes were due to the high
                    saturation of military matters as well as other problems dealt with outside of
                    State Department channels, particularly by the President. Because the Yalta and
                    Potsdam volumes were prepared well in advance of the rest of the series, there
                    was not adequate background in the annual volumes to cite to in the conference
                    volumes. Atomic energy discussions, for example, had been held on the
                    Presidential level, and many of the basic papers were not in the Department’s
                    records.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall pointed out that very few memoranda and minutes of conversations
                    exist for Roosevelt-Churchill conversations in the White House and at Hyde Park.
                    Thus the compilers must piece together items gleaned from a host of memoirs and
                    diverse sources.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 4: Report on Annual Volumes for 1947:</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason prefaced his remarks by looking back at our experience with the
                    volumes for 1946. Last year he had expressed to the Committee his hopes to
                    restrict the number of 1946 volumes to eight, in addition to the China volumes,
                    and the size of each volume to 1,000 pages. Neither of these hopes seemed likely
                    to be realized. We now estimated that three or four volumes could be required to
                    give comprehensive coverage to such of our multilateral policies as the United
                    Nations, foreign economic policy, atomic energy, disarmament, the two sessions
                    of the Council of Foreign Ministers and the Paris Peace Conference. Five other
                    volumes would be required for the traditional area divisions. Two volumes on
                    China would make a total of 11 volumes. The great expansion had been concerned
                    with various aspects of our multilateral diplomacy in the post-war world, which
                    would be covered in our General volumes.</p>
                <p>Last year, Mr. Goodwin had reported to the Committee on our plans for coping with
                    the massive problem of documenting United States participation in United Nations
                    affairs. As a result of his work, this documentation had been kept within
                    reasonable limits by establishing an austere frame of reference and by
                    refraining from printing documents already available in U.N. official records.
                    This approach has necessitated unusually heavy annotation to guide the reader
                    through the maze of the official U.N. records. Even so, we anticipated that a
                    volume of 1400 pages would emerge from Mr. Goodwin’s work for 1946.</p>
                <p>The difficulties of the U.N. compilations we were well aware of last year. We
                    were less aware of the magnitude of the documentation on the CFM meetings and on
                    the Paris Peace Conference. The latter, which was being prepared by a very
                    valuable new member of the staff, Mr. Petersen, would probably run to two
                    good-sized volumes. Unhappily, there existed for the Peace Treaties no easily
                    available official documentation such as appeared in the U.N. record. This had
                    necessitated extensive reprinting of documents actually in print, and ponderous
                    annotation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then moved to consideration of the volumes for 1947. He reported Mr.
                    Goodwin’s estimate that the documentation for the General Branch would he
                    restricted to two volumes, one of some 1100 pages dealing with the United
                    Nations and other general subjects and one of about 1300 pages covering the two
                    sessions of the Council of Foreign Ministers. He cautioned the Committee to
                    regard these predictions with more than usual scepticism because of past
                    experience and because little compilation was actually under way.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then made the following projections: The American Republics volume
                    should be completed by April 1966 in about 1100 pages; the British Commonwealth
                    and Western Europe should be completed by the late fall of 1966 in at least 1100
                    pages; the Near East and Africa volume should be completed by late spring of
                    1966 in under 1000 pages; the Far East should be completed by March 1966 in
                    slightly over 1000 pages.</p>
                <p>The uneven rate of progress in compiling the 1947 volumes was a reflection of
                    insufficient personnel complicated by retirements and staff changes. Mr. Gleason
                    expected to cope with this problem by greater staff flexibility, i.e., by
                    reassigning personnel to fields other than their specialities and by deferring
                    work on 1948 until 1947 was completed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely inquired whether it was necessary to reprint published documents
                    relating to the Paris Peace Conference in our 1946 compilation. He was advised
                    that the volume of Selected Documents compiled by Mrs. Cassidy and released by
                    the Department in 1947 was out of print. The four-volume collection released by
                    the French Government was also out of print. These publications were released in
                    relatively small printings and neither seems to be generally available, even in
                    libraries of large universities. Mr. Mosely suggested the possibility of
                    reprinting the Cassidy volume through photo-offset reproduction to reduce the
                    number of documents to be published in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    Mr. Franklin felt this was not feasible because the Cassidy volume was
                    originally printed by photo-offset method and would not lend itself readily to
                    further reproduction. Mr. Gleason said the problem had been wrestled with for
                    months and that he was impressed with the advantages of covering fully the Paris
                    Peace Conference in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then pointed out that there might be particular clearance
                    difficulties with the Council of Foreign Ministers compilation, particularly
                    since the French had been nearly as difficult as the Soviets at the London
                    meeting. Mr. Gleason noted, parenthetically, one ray of sunshine regarding the
                    French -- that the Office of Western European Affairs (WE) no longer believed
                    that the setting forth in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of our views
                    on De Gaulle would seriously affect our relations with France.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell inquired why there was only one China volume for 1947, since 1947 was
                    an implementing year and 1946 a policy year. Mr. Gleason explained that we had
                    had two China volumes for 1946 because of our exceedingly intensive treatment of
                    the Marshall Mission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart requested information about the “ban” on publishing the China
                    volumes. Mr. Franklin stated that HO had at first given strong priority to these
                    volumes and they had been prepared far ahead of the other volumes in the series.
                    After the first volume in the series -- that for 1942 -- had been released,
                    Secretary Dulles and Assistant Secretary Robertson of the Bureau of Far Eastern
                    Affairs (FE) had put a ban on releasing any other China volumes until further
                    notice. The Committee, with assistance from Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., had helped
                    us to get the 1943 volume released. The Committee had since advocated orderly
                    publication of the China volumes and, after discussions with Secretary Rusk, it
                    has been agreed to bring them out in such fashion, no volumes to be released
                    ahead of other annual volumes for the same year nor any to be held back unduly.
                    The 1944 China volume had recently been sent to FE for approval to release along
                    with the other 1944 volumes. If this could be done, it would be made as obvious
                    as possible that the volume was being issued automatically as a part of a
                    historical series and not as an <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> political
                    weapon.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin observed that the intention of the original Congressional sponsors
                    of the China series had been to show who had “sold out” China. The 1942 and 1943
                    volumes had not borne out their expectations and had contained much criticism of
                    the Chiang Kai-shek regime. Thus the Government of the Republic of China had
                    joined the group which opposed the release of further volumes. In our press
                    release issued for 1944, volume V, we had included an incautious sentence
                    stating that documentation on American policy toward China would appear in a
                    subsequent volume in the series. The very next day the Chinese Embassy sent an
                    officer to FE to find out when the next “bombshell” against his Government would
                    be dropped. FE had informed him that the volume was not coming out immediately
                    but would be published as part of a historical series at an appropriate future
                    date.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell inquired whether reducing the number of volumes published would
                    enable us to reduce our time lag to 20 years. Some HO members stated that it
                    would take more time to compile <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in
                    fewer volumes. Mr. Ferrell then suggested that if this were so perhaps we should
                        <hi rend="underline">increase</hi> the number of volumes per year to attain
                    the 20-year line. It was pointed out that this would increase the time spent in
                    technical editing by PBR, already a prime bottleneck in the pipeline.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell queried whether a lowering of the standards used in compiling <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would permit us to attain our 20-year
                    goal. Mr. Gleason stated that this suggestion would not be helpful toward that
                    end. A lowering of standards entailed less selectivity end therefore a larger
                    number of volumes, and this in turn would make the series less usable and
                    useful. He suggested that falling further behind currency might make clearance
                    easier. He observed that there were many in the Department who would be willing
                    to abolish <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> or to let it fall 50 years
                    behind. Few were sympathetic to a 20-year gap or to publication within the
                    lifetime of the persons covered. Antibiotics, he noted, were making for greater
                    longevity. If it become apparent that we were not going to get relief in the way
                    of additional personnel and if the series fell further and further behind, to
                    say 25 years, it might be possible, Mr. Gleason speculated, to strike a bargain
                    with Department officials for a genuine agreement to clear within three
                    months.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger asked if the problem of clearance was the sole problem slowing down
                    publication of the series. If not, he saw no reason to strike such a bargain. He
                    would continue to press for more personnel. To the extent that clearance was a
                    major problem, he thought that top-level representatives from each area should
                    come to HO and read the galleys and take appropriate action. In this way the
                    process might be completed within one week. Had this been attempted?</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stated that everything had been attempted. He cited as an example
                    that his predecessor, Mr. Noble, had attended a staff meeting in ARA some 10
                    years ago and as a result a high-level officer in ARA had been designated to
                    take care of our problems with that Bureau. All bureaus divided their work among
                    their Desk officers and ARA gave its Desk men greater responsibility than most
                    bureaus. ARA therefore had no one at a high level competent to pass on clearance
                    and insisted that only its Desk men were acquainted with such details as whether
                    Mr. X were still the power behind the junta, were an important editor, etc. Thus
                    the arrangement made by Mr. Noble had not succeeded in speeding clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall noted that enough was being cleared under existing conditions to fill
                    the pipelines at PBR and that if the clearance problem disappeared, PBR would be
                    unable to handle the extra volume of material. In other words, clearance was not
                    the heart of the problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin recalled that years ago he had felt that if we would let our 15-year
                    lag slip to 20 years, the clearance problem would be simplified. Time had showed
                    that the clearance problem had not become easier even with a lag of more than 20
                    years. Mr. Metzger thought that even falling back to a 30-year lag would not
                    help the clearance problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted, as an item of incidental interest, that Professor Mario
                    Toscano, Historical Adviser in the Italian Foreign Office and editor of the
                    Italian diplomatic papers, did not have to clear his work in the Foreign
                    Office.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason emphasized the bottlenecks other than clearance -- compiling and
                    technical editing. He noted that even should the first bottleneck disappear, the
                    technical-editing bottleneck would clog the pipelines. Mr. Ferrell suggested
                    reducing the number of volumes to meet this problem. Mr. Gleason replied that we
                    have already became extremely selective and that we cannot reduce further the
                    number of volumes and still have a worthwhile product. He also noted with dismay
                    that in compiling for the years after 1947 we would have to take into account
                    the fact that the National Security Council and other government agencies
                    participated increasingly in the formulation of United States foreign policy.
                    The State Department, after that year, would merely be the first among peers in
                    the realm of foreign policy.</p>
                <p>Mr. Costrell suggested the possibility of an approach to the planning and
                    management staff to reduce our clearance problems. He observed that Mr.
                    Crockett, in sponsoring studies by that staff, had complained that there were
                    too many initials on State Department papers. Mr. Franklin observed that he had
                    mentioned Mr. Crockett’s idea at a P staff meeting in this very connection, but
                    no one had thought that it could seriously be used to expedite clearance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He did not feel that the management
                    staff in the Department could give us an exemption from the area people. The
                    core of the difficulty was that overlapping of responsibilities in the
                    Department could not be eliminated and that <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> was a prime example of such overlap. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> could not be divorced from current operations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Churchill noted that in almost all instances we heard from the clearance
                    people for the first time by memorandum after they had reviewed the galleys and
                    that preliminary discussions with them were unusual. He noted an example of such
                    discussion with GTI on Iranian questions, and he suggested that more of this
                    informal consultation would be desirable.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell inquired whether there had been any major adverse reaction in the
                    last 10 years to our published volumes, except for China. Mr. Gleason noted that
                    the French press had reacted adversely to our accounts of remarks by President
                    Roosevelt and Prime Minister Churchill on De Gaulle and that our Ambassador at
                    Paris had been disturbed enough by the press accounts to cable the Department.
                    The press contended that these documents had been issued in June 1964 as revenge
                    because De Gaulle did not attend the D-day anniversary ceremonies in Normandy.
                    We talked to WE about it and nothing more had been heard about the matter. Mr.
                    Gleason also noted critical reaction in the Greek press to our account (in a
                    document of Prime Minister Churchill) that Papandreou was unable to make up his
                    mind. The press had regarded the release of our volume last summer as American
                    intervention in the then acute political Greek crisis. The matter had blown over
                    quickly when it was pointed out that the accusation against Papandreou had been
                    published years ago in Churchill’s memoirs.</p>
                <p> Mr. Franklin pointed out that the French press agency, which had a large
                    clientele in Latin America, had published an account of a recent American
                    Republics volume, giving it an anti-American slant (which gets so much play
                    below the border). Since the volume had not yet reached Colombia, our Ambassador
                    there sent a frantic cable inquiring about the new “White Paper” issued by the
                    Department. When our volumes arrived at Bogotá, it became clear that the press
                    agency had twisted the story, but some damage had been done. Nothing could
                    prevent this kind of distortion now and then.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell raised the question whether we should abolish press releases for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Mr. Gleason observed that
                    these releases had purposely been made so bland as to say virtually nothing. Mr.
                    Metzger suggested the opposite approach -- to prepare perhaps a three-page
                    release which would give something in detail to the reporters that they could
                    use in preparing their stories. Mr. Franklin stated that newspapers treat a
                    released volume as “hard news” rather than as a subject for a book review.
                    Consequently the press stories often did not mention the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series but just talked about “documents”. Maybe it
                    would be better to give up the press releases. Mr. Metzger felt that we ought
                    either to abolish the press releases or make them meaningful.</p>
                <p>The morning session adjourned at 12:20, to enable the Committee to get ready for
                    luncheon at 1 o’clock with Mr. Crockett at the Blair House.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 7: Problems Relating to Technical Editing:</p>
                <p>The afternoon session began at 3:05, with Messrs. Metzger and Wilson absent. Mr.
                    Franklin introduced Peter Smith, supervisor of the editing staff of PBR, who
                    discussed the problems of speed and staff. Mr. Smith noted that in some cases
                    the work might be speeded up by borrowing staff from other sections of PBR or by
                    contracting out certain jobs, such as indexing. Upon being asked whether PBR
                    could edit five volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> a year, he
                    answered in the affirmative. He cautioned, however, that with the present staff
                    and little or no prospect for an increase, he believed that five volumes
                    represented maximum production. There was some discussion on the question of
                    inter-Bureau transfers of funds with Mr. Smith commenting that so far this had
                    been no problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smith then described the kinds of work being done by PBR. Mr. Franklin added
                    that the technical editors did more than just catch typographical and mechanical
                    errors; they knew something of the substance of the volumes, and they asked
                    helpful and penetrating questions and significantly improved the product. Mr,
                    Stewart expressed his belief that HO and PBR had to be considered a combined
                    operation. There was some question as to whether the standards of PBR might be
                    lowered a bit in an effort to speed production. Mr. Franklin stated that he and
                    Mr. Jerome Perlmutter, Chief of PBR, had already agreed on several short-cuts
                    which in fact might let a few errors slip through. Risks were involved, however,
                    and he felt strongly that any further dilution of standards had to be held to
                    the barest minimum. The real need was for more personnel, not lower
                    standards.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood inquired how many persons would be required to handle eight volumes a
                    year instead of the four volumes now being handled. Mr. Smith thought that eight
                    more persons would actually be needed, but that by some contracting out the
                    number might be reduced.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smith said that Miss Elizabeth Vary, Chief of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Editing Branch of PBR, was trying to train more people as
                    final reviewers. Since these experienced employees catch a host of errors, we
                    might risk some additional short-cuts in the earlier stages of editing if we
                    could count on top-notch final review. A number of the more experienced final
                    reviewers would be retiring over the next several years, and this would pose a
                    serious problem.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Ferrell, Mr. Smith observed that his staff
                    spent the greatest amount of its time in proofreading, both oral and silent.
                    Indexing was then discussed. Mr. Smith indicated that an index for a 1000-page
                    volume cost about $1500. It was pointed out that indexes to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> were complicated to prepare since they covered
                    analytic concepts rather than merely proper names and key words. Inclusion of
                    proper names was restricted to persons substantially involved in the events
                    described.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell inquired whether time might be saved by a simpler method of making up
                    a typeface dummy sheet. Mr. Smith replied that this step had been taken two
                    years ago when GPO was given a generalized dummy to serve as a model for all <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He noted several short-cuts
                    and money-saving devices introduced by Mr. Perlmutter.</p>
                <p> Mr. Smith was asked whether his editors had ever completed more than five
                    volumes in a year, and he answered that it had been done only rarely in the
                    past. He concluded his remarks with an expression of confidence that his staff
                    would turn out volumes as rapidly as HO provided copy.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 5: Efforts to Expedite Output:</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason remarked that most of the items concerning Item 5 had been covered
                    but that he wished to devote special attention to clearance problems. He noted
                    that of all the Desk areas, ARA had been the hardest to please, requesting us to
                    remove substantial amounts of material and in same instances, like the
                    Ecuador-Peru boundary dispute, to delete entire stories.</p>
                <p>These calls for deletion were not always frivolous or unreasonable. He gave as an
                    example a compilation on the question of United States bases in Iceland. The
                    Icelandic Government refused permission to print certain of its documents. It
                    also expressed the view that no documentation whatsoever should be printed
                    regarding the base negotiations as that would be embarrassing to the Government
                    and would impair relations with the United States. The American Ambassador
                    reviewed the compilations and agreed that publication of the material would
                    embarrass the Icelandic Government and perhaps cause it to fall, with the added
                    possibility that the United States would lose the bases. The Bureau of European
                    Affairs (EUR) agreed with the Ambassador. Mr. Gleason said that he had made an
                    attempt to select documents that might make possible the printing of some
                    compilation on the subject which would not cause difficulty. This proved
                    impossible and we had substituted a short editorial note for the documentary
                    collection.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason asserted that the base story illustrated the dilemma confronting us.
                    Our charter warns us “to avoid publication of matters which would tend to impede
                    current diplomatic negotiations or other business”. On the other hand, we were
                    obliged to insure that “nothing shall be omitted for the purpose of concealing
                    or glossing over what might be regarded by some as a defect of policy.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood asked whether it would help HO to differentiate between valid and
                    frivolous deletion requests if the Advisory Committee issued a policy statement
                    for consideration by the Secretary of State. Mr. Franklin replied that this
                    might help by emphasizing the positive value of the series. The trouble was that
                    only HO was convinced of the positive value of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>; every one else just looked on it as a possible source of
                    trouble for him and his “clients”.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin asked Mr. Gleason whether there had been difficulties with other
                    base stories. The answer was that while there had been little objection thus
                    far, he anticipated future trouble as our bases became world-wide. Mr. Goodwin
                    noted that the decision had been made some years ago to handle compilations on
                    this subject on a bilateral rather than a global basis in order to reduce the
                    sensational aspect of the subject. Mr. Gleason concluded that the Icelandic
                    story pointed up the need for review of our work by Desk officers, for HO had
                    not anticipated any adverse reaction to the story.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 6: Special Report on Problems Relating to the
                    Compilations on the Council of Foreign Ministers and the Paris Peace Conference
                    of 1946</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany discussed some of the problems relating to the CFM meetings and the
                    Paris Peace Conference of 1946. He stressed the difficulty of selection, noting
                    the huge volume of materials. A decision had been made to focus directly on
                    documentation at the CFM and to exclude indirectly connected materials bearing,
                    for example, on other negotiations conducted in Paris or New York; these would
                    instead be documented in bilateral compilations. Because of the possibility of
                    having too much material even with such a restriction, it was decided to present
                    a complete account of all CFM meetings in which the Secretary of State
                    participated and in which major documents were discussed, as well as meetings
                    of the Secretary with other delegations. It was anticipated that all major
                    documents would be printed and that the volume would contain an elaborate
                    editorial apparatus dealing with materials that could not be printed because of
                    space limitations. In these ways, we hoped to present a comprehensive record of
                    maximum value to the reader.</p>
                <p>The problems encountered in producing the compilation on the Paris Peace
                    Conference were similar. We again encountered a huge mass of documentation in
                    the form of documents of the meetings, minutes, daily summaries, resolutions,
                    amendments, etc. In this case, however, much of the material was already in the
                    public domain. The French Government had published a four-volume work but it was
                    generally unavailable. The Department’s publication (No. 2868) was not widely
                    distributed and was not in most university libraries. We faced therefore the
                    problem of the extent to which we should reproduce this documentation in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. We had decided that we had to
                    duplicate a considerable portion of this documentation and to bring out a
                    comprehensive story in two volumes. Thus we would be using the American
                    Delegation’s daily journal, key amendments, certain verbatim records and other
                    conference documents, all extensively annotated, together with heretofore
                    classified papers on the negotiations of the U.S. Delegation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin observed that the earlier State Department publication had been
                    poorly reproduced and in a small press run. He thought we had learned the lesson
                    that a work of this sort should be published in permanent form with full
                    distribution in order to enable <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to cite
                    to it in the future.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then commented on the problems presented to us by the Austrian State
                    Treaty, being worked on by Mr. Kent. The negotiation of the treaty involved
                    almost 10 years of protracted and repetitious talks and produced a vast
                    documentation. Mr. Gleason noted that extensive annotation would boil down such
                    a story considerably. On the other hand, he noted that printing the documents
                    would have the value of showing continuing Soviet obstructionism. This, however,
                    needed not to be done time and time again. Mr. Franklin agreed that the
                    narrative form would be a method of cutting down repetition. Mr. Goodwin noted
                    that much was being done along these lines in connection with U.N.
                    compilations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell wondered if it were too late to consider the revision downward of the
                    number of volumes devoted to the CFM and the Peace Conference. Mr. Aandahl noted
                    that despite the bulk of the volumes, our compilations were only a summary or
                    skeletal outline of what had taken place. Mr. Ferrell nevertheless questioned,
                    in view of Soviet obstructionism and the lack of concrete results, whether these
                    subjects were worth three of the eleven volumes for l946. Mr. Mosely stated that
                    some things were accomplished at the 1946 meetings. Mr. Franklin suggested that
                    the Secretary of State thought these meetings were of extreme importance judging
                    by the amount of time he had devoted to them. Mr, Ferrell agreed but continued
                    to maintain that the meetings w«re not of earthshaking significance. By 1946
                    Hungary, Rumania, Bulgaria and Finland were, to all intents and purposes,
                    already behind the Iron Curtain and whatever happened in connection with them at
                    the Paris Peace Conference was relatively unimportant, American efforts having
                    been to no avail.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely argued that American efforts in fashioning the peace treaties with the
                    satellites, while perhaps not of immediate significance in shaping events in
                    Eastern Europe, in the long run had confirmed United States interest in
                    maintaining the independence of these countries and had gradually aided them in
                    freeing themselves from the complete control of the Soviet Union. It was also
                    pointed out that Italy had been a major element at the meetings.</p>
                <p>There fallowed a discussion of the philosophy of inclusion and exclusion as to
                    the kind of balance that had to be struck between the value of a story in its
                    time and its value today. Mr. Franklin noted that in the Yalta volume the
                    activities of Alger Hiss, because of his later notoriety, were documented more
                    extensively than they would have been otherwise. Mr. Gleason cited as another
                    example Cuba, where we would pay strong attention to Communist activities, not
                    seemingly important at the time, because of the later emergence of Castro. On
                    the other hand, Mr. Aandahl pointed out that certain wartime economic programs
                    (Safehaven, Proclaimed List and the like) had generated vast amounts of
                    documentation but that because of diminished interest in such matters we were
                    giving them relatively brief coverage in the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell then asked about prospects for the volumes for 1947. Mr. Gleason felt
                    that our plans were too indefinite to make a firm prediction, but pledged his
                    best efforts to keep down the number of volumes and yet fulfill the injunctions
                    of our charter.</p>
                <p>There was general discussion as to the comparative value of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series, which Mr. Ferrell noted was the most
                    detailed of any published by any Government in the world. No other series came
                    even close to ours in inclusiveness. Mr. Dougall noted that the series has had
                    increasing value in that since 1940 American foreign relations had been global
                    in scope so that our volumes were as useful for European or Far Eastern as for
                    American diplomatic history. Mr. Franklin advanced the idea of the theoretical
                    possibility of changing our publication policy and of printing spot documents
                    without continuity. This would result in cutting the number of volumes for a
                    year but it would destroy the look-behind-the-scenes our present volumes
                    gave.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell, in expressing appreciation for what had already been done by HO,
                    hoped it would move vigorously to hold the 20-year line. It was clear that there
                    was slippage, and that it was getting increasingly difficult to get out a year
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in a year. This, however, was what
                    must be done to hold the line.</p>
                <p>At 5 p.m., the Committee went into private session in order to consider in detail
                    the documents regarding the 1945 compilation on Iceland which had been gathered
                    by Mr. Gleason.</p>
                <p rend="center">*****</p>
                <p>The Saturday morning session began at 9 a.m., with Messrs. Mosely, Ferrell,
                    Osgood, Stewart, Franklin, Dougall, Gleason and Aandahl present.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 5: Deletions:</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart opened the discussion by recapitulating his views on the deletion of
                    the story on Iceland for 1945, galleys for which the Committee members had read
                    on Friday afternoon. He felt that the Historical Office and the Committee were
                    up against a stone wall when both the Government of Iceland and our own
                    political officers (Ambassador Penfield and EUR) were opposed to publication.
                    From a practical point of view Mr. Stewart questioned whether there would be any
                    chance of winning a fight on this subject. Also there did not seem to be much
                    advantage in delaying the volume, since the problem was not likely to go
                    away.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that he would be willing if necessary to fight the Department of
                    Defense on the general question of covering overseas bases, but not the
                    responsible political officers in a particular case such as Iceland, where a
                    pretty powerful case had been presented.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood asked if bases would become a chronic problem for clearance. Would
                    there be similar risk in other cases of endangering a friendly government, or
                    was Iceland a unique case? Mr. Gleason thought that this situation was
                    practically unique, but that the specific circumstances in Iceland would
                    presumably continue for many years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart thought that this case called for a very close decision, and he asked
                    whether Ambassador Penfield had been outraged by the undue pressure applied in
                    1945 by the United States against Iceland or was more concerned at the
                    implications of publishing the record now. Mr. Gleason said that the Ambassador
                    felt that the story could be used against the United States now.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood noted that while there is usually no demonstrable cause and effect
                    relationship between publication of a given document or set of documents and
                    possible trouble in another country, in the present case there seemed to be a
                    real connection. As a matter of principle we should be free to publish the basic
                    documents of American foreign policy despite occasional embarrassments and
                    awkward situations unless there was a clear probability of bad consequences.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin commented that it was hard for the Historical Office to know in
                    advance which documents or subjects were sensitive. We had not expected so sharp
                    a reaction from the Icelandic Government or our own officials. There were likely
                    to be similar sticky situations regarding other bases; if we gave in on all of
                    them, the total amount of substantive deletion would be serious.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood felt that we could not agree not to tread on any toes. Mr. Franklin
                    said that if the situation becomes too difficult we might have to state that we
                    were omitting base negotiations in general and call them a Defense matter
                    outside the scope of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason pointed out that it should always be remembered that in most base
                    questions American motives were good and that the bases were intended to support
                    policies that could themselves be defended, even though the negotiations
                    themselves were sometimes indelicate.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood then asked if anything could be gained by reopening with EUR the
                    Iceland question. Mr. Franklin thought it was too soon now, and that little
                    could be done until there had been a change of officers somewhere. Mr. Gleason
                    believed that Secretary Rusk would support EUR if the matter came to him now,
                    and Mr. Osgood commented that if we published the story and all the dire
                    predictions proved to be correct, we would really be “in the soup”. Mr. Franklin
                    observed that so far we had not actually pressed any cases to dire results, so
                    that the question had not really come up in acute form. Mr. Gleason added that
                    in general EUR has been most cooperative. Mr. Franklin feared that this might
                    change somewhat, for the series had now reached the end of the period of many
                    memoirs, which have always helped to ease clearance problems within EUR°s
                    jurisdiction. Much has been published on European questions through the end of
                    World War II, but relatively little on other regions. Churchill and De Gaulle
                    had eased our way in Europe.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that he always wanted to know how complete a publication was
                    and what sources had been available to the author. He liked to see a clear
                    indication of what was, or was not, covered. In this connection, the reader was
                    entitled to know exactly what was to be found in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Mr. Gleason described the bracketed note substituted for the
                    story on Iceland, indicating that it was just enough to show the reader that the
                    subject had come up.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood asked if it would help if the Committee took note of the growing
                    clearance problem and stated positively that material should not be deleted
                    merely because it was embarrassing and stepped on toes. Would it not be
                    desirable to state in broad terms the principle involved and then indicate
                    certain legitimate exceptions?</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason reminded the Committee that many deletions were proposed on trivial
                    grounds, and he would like the Committee to ask reviewing officers to bear in
                    mind the real advantages of forthright publication even at the expense of
                    temporary embarrassments on awkward passages. Such a statement would be most
                    helpful to the Historical Office in handling clearance within the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin agreed that we could use some ringing words on the positive side.
                    After all, the American people had a right to know how we got the Iceland base
                    -- that is why we have the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series --
                    but that point rarely gets stated positively. The Desk officers see the narrow
                    problem of some troublesome document affecting their immediate area of
                    responsibility, and to counter this we need a principle showing the positive
                    value of the historical undertaking.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood thought that the permissible exceptions should be stated rather
                    clearly so as to strengthen the affirmative principle.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that he would try to handle the Icelandic story for 1946 in “low
                    key” and see what EUR would do. Mr. Franklin noted that it was difficult to
                    predict what the reaction would be in the Department and in the foreign press.
                    Some minor things were picked up immediately and others were never noticed. As a
                    rule the foreign press in Washington was quite alert to materials relating to
                    their respective countries; one could never count on their missing an item that
                    would make headlines back home.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that there was no question that the present Icelandic officials
                    were fully informed of the original base negotiations. It was the official
                    documentation that was touchy, not the general outline as presented in
                    Neuchterlein’s book. The subject had been covered rather fully in the Icelandic
                    newspapers. Mr. Mosely pointed out that often one or another paper had the true
                    story of a secret event, but no one knew at the time which speculative press
                    story was correct.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked what were the alternatives for now and what were the possible
                    consequences for the future. Mr. Franklin answered that we could publish in
                    full, publish in part, print in full but delay the volume, or limit our coverage
                    to a bracketed note, indicating the file numbers of relevant documents, even
                    though these would be put in blue envelopes so that they would not be
                    automatically available to unofficial researchers when the files entered the
                    restricted period. (Mr. Franklin then described the procedures for granting
                    unofficial researchers access to various categories of Department records.)</p>
                <p>After Mr. Franklin explained that we could more safely leave out third-party
                    quarrels (such as the Peru-Ecuador boundary dispute) than matters of direct
                    United States involvement (such as the base in Iceland), Mr. Stewart asked him
                    to say what the Committee could do to help in this regard.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin thought that the Committee could express serious concern about cases
                    such as Iceland, admitting that it could understand the peculiar circumstances
                    of this case, but hoping that this would prove to be most exceptional. It might
                    be appropriate this year to have a confidential report for circulation within
                    the Department, in addition to the regular public report. Mr. Gleason suggested
                    a slight amendment; it would be most useful to express concern at the danger of
                    wholesale deletions and then cite Iceland as a current example. Those
                    responsible should be asked to weigh the long-term advantages of a candid
                    account against the temporary embarrassment of a little adverse publicity.
                    Iceland, Mr. Franklin pointed out, was a particularly good example, because the
                    withholding of clearance was by no means captious, as in so many other
                    instances, and the episode posed a serious problem not only for the Government
                    but also for the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely warned that in referring to deletions the Committee must be cautious
                    in its language, for it was quite possible that a Congressional Committee might
                    ask the members exactly what they had in mind.</p>
                <p>Referring again to a possible general statement by the Committee, Mr. Franklin
                    said that ringing words would help the higher officers in a geographical bureau
                    to overcome the objection of Desk officers. The higher officers were generally
                    willing to admit the strength of the arguments of the Historical Office, but
                    were reluctant to overrule the Desks, which have day-to-day responsibility for
                    relations with a given country. An affirmative statement of the overall value of
                    the series would be most helpful.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question by Mr. Osgood, Mr. Franklin said that he did not think it
                    would be helpful to arouse the interest of members of Congress in the problem of
                    deletions. Politics might be injected into the issue. Mr. Aandahl said that the
                    issue was muddied by the fact that the overwhelming number of omissions were to
                    save space rather than to maintain security or to avoid giving needless offense.
                    This would be hard to explain to non-professional persons. Mr. Franklin pointed
                    out that the basic regulation (written in 1924 when the series was only 10 or 12
                    years behind currency) called for two contradictory things: all basic documents
                    were to be printed, but nothing was to be printed that might interfere with
                    current negotiations.</p>
                <p rend="underline">The Hays Bill and HO Personnel:</p>
                <p>In response to a question from the Committee, Mr. Franklin said that it would be
                    premature for the Committee to make any comments on the possible effect of the
                    Hays Bill on the personnel and workings of the Historical Office. The Committee
                    could write to Mr. Crockett if the need should arise. Mr. Stewart thought that
                    Mr. Crockett had seemed to be reassuring on this during the luncheon at Blair
                    House yesterday, but Mr. Osgood was not sure exactly what he had in mind with
                    regard to maintaining a professional register.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely summed up the sense of the Committee on this point: it wanted to be
                    sure that proper professional standards were maintained with regard to
                    recruitment, retirement, promotion, and other factors. In this regard. Mr.
                    Franklin noted that two uniquely valuable members of the staff, E. Taylor Parks
                    and Richard S. Patterson, would retire within a few weeks. Both were quite
                    irreplaceable, each having a rare combination of special knowledge and superior
                    judgment in certain fields of our work. The question of replacements was made
                    even more complicated by the uncertainties of the situation. We did not know
                    what to tell job candidates about their status. At the moment they would
                    apparently come in as Foreign Service Reserve officers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood referred to Mr. Crockett’s reply of September 9 to Mr. Leopold’s
                    letter about the need for printing funds and staff. When Mr. Crockett had
                    referred favorably to the “second stage” need for additional staff, Mr. Osgood
                    felt that he had in mind the idea that he had expressed at the Blair House of
                    using graduate students as temporary internes. The Committee were all agreed
                    that the real need was for trained full-time staff, and that internes would not
                    do.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely said that as Chairman he had spoken quite vigorously and privately to
                    Mr. Crockett yesterday before lunch, thanking him for the letter to Mr. Leopold
                    but urging that more needed to be done in filling vacancies and giving
                    administrative support.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely also said that graduate students would clearly not be of much help to
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, and that the senior interne
                    program (with which he had been working with the Ford Foundation) was intended
                    not for historical and intelligence work but for the fields of policy and law.
                    It was agreed that it might be desirable for Mr. Mosely to write a private
                    letter to Mr. Crockett to explain why this idea would not meet the needs of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then said that the Committee could do something that no one in the
                    Department dared do: it could ask for more people. But the Committee should know
                    that the Department’s view was that there should be no increase in staff. It was
                    obvious that the Historical Office and the Publishing and Reproduction Services
                    Division, which is part of the Office of Operations, both needed additional
                    personnel in order to maintain the schedule to which we were nominally
                    committed. It was relatively easy to get money for contracts, machines, and
                    special programs. The hardest thing was to get approval for another body.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason suggested that the Committee’s public report might refer to the
                    present ferment in university communities as an added reason for publishing on
                    time a candid record of American foreign relations. Mr. Greenfield had referred
                    to this in his remarks on Friday morning.</p>
                <p>The possibility of a session on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> at a
                    meeting of one of the historical associations was discussed. Mr. Ferrell said
                    that he thought it would be easy to arrange a session for the meetings a year or
                    so from now, and he invited suggestions on possible topics. He also mentioned
                    that it would be useful for representatives of the Historical Office to visit
                    the various universities. Mr. Franklin pointed out that we had very little
                    travel money but that the Bureau was pretty good about paying for trips in
                    response to specific invitations.</p>
                <p>At this point the Committee went into closed session.</p>
                <p rend="center">*****</p>
                <p rend="underline">Closing Remarks</p>
                <p>When the members of the Historical Office rejoined the Committee members some
                    twenty minutes later, Mr. Mosely expressed appreciation for the work of the HO
                    staff and hope that the series could be brought closer to the 20-year line. Mr.
                    Franklin expressed his thanks for the work of the Committee and said that he
                    would do a little research on the number of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> historians over the years compared to the amount of material
                    to be studied, the number of posts, etc. Such a chart might help to show the
                    need for more staff. The Historical Office had recently been able to get
                    replacements and promotions, within the existing table of organization, but it
                    was under great pressure to recruit at the bottom. It was asked to take M.A.’s
                    when it needed Ph.D.’s, and the latter were hard to find anyway. Mr. Franklin
                    asked the Committee members to recommend qualified people to him and let him see
                    what could be done about meeting academic salaries. Unless he had good
                    candidates he could not hold out for Ph.D.’s. Mr. Stewart wondered whether that
                    meant that all HO positions needed Ph.D.’s. Mr. Franklin replied that of course
                    we would recruit some staff with lesser qualifications but that we needed to
                    catch good Ph.D.’s whenever possible so that we would have historians of broad
                    competence to carry on the work in the future.</p>
                <p>The meeting broke up about 11:30 a.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
