<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1966</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1966</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-08">April 8, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1966-11-04">November 4, 1966</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1966-11-04-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 1.8 MB, 28pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1966—Minutes. Limited Official
                Use.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1966 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 4, 1966</dateline>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">PARTICIPANTS</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>William W. Bishop, Jr., Chairman, Professor of Law, University of
                                Michigan Law School</item>
                            <item>Robert H. Ferrell, Professor of History, Indiana University</item>
                            <item>Philip E. Mosely, Director, European Institute, Columbia
                                University</item>
                            <item>Robert E. Osgood, Director, Washington Center of Foreign Policy
                                Research, School of Advanced International Studies, The Johns
                                Hopkins University</item>
                            <item>J. E. Wallace Sterling, President, Stanford University</item>
                            <item>Robert B. Stewart, Professor of International Law and
                                Organization, Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts
                                University</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Marvin W. Kranz</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>Almon Wright</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Richard I. Phillips, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Public Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Publishing and Reproduction Services Division:<list>
                            <item>Jerome H. Perlmutter, Chief</item>
                            <item>Peter A. Smith</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Bureau of European Affairs (EUR):<list>
                            <item>Milan W. Jerabek</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>Bureau of East Asian and Pacific Affairs (EA):<list>
                            <item>Oscar V. Armstrong</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>The morning session began at approximately 9:30.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 1: Opening remarks</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin announced that the new Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                    Affairs, Dixon Donnelley, was unable to attend the meeting of the Committee and
                    that Deputy Assistant Secretary Phillips would welcome the members. He stated
                    that not all of HO’s hopes and plans had been realized but that we would have
                    been much worse off without “Dick” Phillips.</p>
                <p>Mr. Phillips conveyed the Assistant Secretary’s regrets at not being able to be
                    present. He expressed his appreciation of the time and effort given by the
                    Committee to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He welcomed
                    its advice and pointed out that its sage counsel had been followed almost
                    consistently by the Department, with one major exception - its plea for
                    increased staff. Its advice, in this connection, had not been followed, not
                    because the advice was not sound nor because the Bureau was not in agreement,
                    but because of budgetary stringency.</p>
                <p>Mr. Phillips noted that the idea of restricting the number of volumes compiled to
                    that which could actually be published, about six a year, entailed greater
                    selectivity and less comprehensiveness. This approach, at the same time, fitted
                    the realities of the budgetary situation and therefore merited consideration by
                    the Committee. Mr. Phillips then departed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin called on Mr. Mosely, who proposed Mr. Bishop as Chairman. After
                    this was agreed to, Mr. Bishop took the chair and stated that he was pleased to
                    be with the Committee after having missed the meeting the year before. He
                    expressed the hope that the Committee would contribute to the furtherance of the
                    series through its report and by making personal contacts.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin announced that Stanley D. Metzger of Georgetown University was not
                    present as a participating member of the Committee because of teaching
                    activities in Ceylon and that Mr. Ferrell, delayed by a snowstorm, would put in
                    an appearance shortly after 11 a.m. He noted also the two changes in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff during the past year, the
                    transfer of George O. Kent to the Library of Congress and the reappointment of
                    an old friend, David H. Stauffer, after service with the Peace Corps.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 2: Report on status of series and publication
                    plans</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl handed a chart to each of the Committee members showing the 12 stages
                    of the various compilations through 1948, from manuscript in preparation to
                    actual release, and giving target dates for anticipated publication. He noted
                    that the animal volumes had caught up with the China volumes as far as
                    publication was concerned, so that we were not in such disarray as before; that
                    all 1947 volumes were close to completion of compilation; that the 1948 volumes
                    were organized in name only - although several were in process - except for the
                    China volumes, which were already in galleys. He also commented on the
                    bottlenecks in the clearance pipelines.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin detailed for the Committee the organizational structure of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division in its three branches. He
                    pointed out that the notable stage on Mr. Aandahl1s chart was No. 7, i.e.,
                    completion of clearance, at which point the basic HO work on a volume was
                    completed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin announced that at 3:30 the Public Affairs Officers of EA and EUR
                    would discuss clearance problems with the Committee. He noted that Mr. Armstrong
                    of EA was receptive to our needs but that action was still needed. He mentioned
                    that release of the 1944 Chine volume was being held up this time pending the
                    vote of the General Assembly regarding the admission of Communist China to the
                    United Nations. He suggested that the Committee “lean on” the PAO from EA to
                    ensure early release of the volume.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl stated that advance paperback copies of 1944, volume I were now
                    ready. This volume contained documents on the European Advisory Commission and
                    various other general subjects, and it should be published within the next few
                    weeks. He then distributed a second chart, showing an ever widening interval
                    between events and publication if we continued to release volumes at the present
                    rate of about four per year. On this basis, the manuscript for the Latin
                    American volume for 1947, which was sent to PBR for copy editing three weeks
                    ago, would not be released until 1975, 28 years after the events covered.
                    Similarly, it would require nearly three years just to publish the 11 volumes
                    for 1946, and this would further increase the spread for all future years. Mr.
                    Bishop inquired whether the target date of 1971 for publication of the 1946
                    Paris Peace Conference documentation, as set forth in the Aandahl chart, meant
                    that the two volumes would take five additional years to release, even though
                    compilation was completed. Mr. Franklin replied that he expected Messrs.
                    Perlmutter and Smith at 11:30 to give the Committee insight into the technical
                    editing problem. We had been pressing PBR to expedite production, but that
                    office had been handicapped by inability to obtain replacements. Some indexing
                    had been contracted out, but this practice had been far from an unqualified
                    success. It was hoped that with further contracting out of indexes, with greater
                    safeguards, we would be able to release up to five volumes this year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then raised the question of the relative rates of progress by the
                    staff in compiling and the actual release of printed volumes. Mr. Gleason stated
                    that compiling was a speedier process than publication.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop asked, looking at the chart once more, whether there would be five
                    years more of time lag for volumes III, IV, V, and VI for 1946. Mr. Gleason
                    noted that PBR could process about four volumes a year. Mr. Franklin commented
                    that PBR was unable to replace any retirees and was therefore farming out work
                    on indexes, hoping thereby to process five volumes annually.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop asked at what stage clearance took place. Mr. Gleason informed him
                    that clearance took place after printing of the galleys. The galleys for any
                    given volume were sent to the one or more bureaus concerned with the substance
                    of the documents. There was normally no further clearance after the page-proof
                    stage but rather the processes of editing, indexing, and binding.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stated that the suggestion of clearing manuscript instead of galleys
                    to save time would not work satisfactorily. The making of sufficient copies
                    would be very expensive and the material would be very bulky and difficult to
                    read. The result would be to lengthen the present clearance time of about one
                    year. He noted that, except for the China volumes, once the galleys were
                    cleared, that was final and there was no further submission to the desks at the
                    page-proof stage. The sole problem at the latter stage centered around the time
                    of release, lest publication of a volume be interpreted <hi rend="underline">per
                        se</hi> as an act of foreign policy. Deletion of documents from page proof
                    was rare, fortunately, as this would bring the credibility of the series into
                    question. PBR was efficient at catching errors. Its standards were high and very
                    few errors had ever gotten into print.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart inquired whether Miss Vary’s staff had any function dealing with the
                    substance of compilations. Mr. Franklin replied that PBR did not deal with
                    substance but that its technical editing was of a very high order. Those
                    sharp-eyed ladies caught inconsistencies which might be a thousand pages apart
                    in a volume or even in different volumes. Mr. Bishop asked about the length of
                    time required for release of a typical volume after compilation of the
                    manuscript. Mr. Gleason answered that average clearance took about 18 months. To
                    this should be added the long time expended in getting to the page-proof stage,
                    indexing and binding. He noted that although he had been Editor of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> for several years, he had yet to see
                    published any of the volumes he had edited. He observed that the manuscript for
                    1944, volume I, one of the better ones, for time taken, had been sent to PBR in
                    fiscal year 1963; the master galleys had been received on December 1, 1964; the
                    cleared galleys had been sent to PBR in May 1965, and the volume was only now
                    about to be released.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop queried how much delay was accounted for by clearance, how much by PBR
                    editing and indexing, and how much by the Government Printing Office. Mr.
                    Franklin underscored the distinction between the work of clearing by the desks
                    and the work of PBR in processing the volumes. In the bureaus, our work often
                    lay untouched for long periods of time presumably at the bottom of file
                    cabinets; the problem was to get a desk man to devote time to it. In PBR, our
                    work did not lie buried. The time spent there was used to improve our product.
                    In the one, however, it was a question of getting to the job; in PBR it was a
                    problem of insufficient manpower. Some had suggested that PBR be combined with
                    HO, as indeed it once was. The manpower shortage, however, would remain a
                    problem regardless of where PBR was domiciled. Mr. Franklin noted,
                    parenthetically, that PBR had not been as successful in securing replacements as
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division. </p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop asked if there would still be long delay, even if clearance were
                    speeded. After Mr. Franklin’s affirmative reply, Mr. Bishop inferred the need
                    for more personnel in both PBR and in the staff of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 3: Report on wartime conference volumes</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall reported that two wartime conference volumes were still to be
                    released. One, dealing with the three Washington Conferences and the Casablanca
                    Conference, covered the period December 1941 to the middle of 1943 and had been
                    in galleys for many months. Mr. Dougall mentioned three clearance problems that
                    were giving us difficulties. A problem involving the Australian Government might
                    well be brought to a head soon. The problem with EA centered around an old
                    difficulty - not so much the question of substance as the matter of getting that
                    bureau to review the galleys. The third problem was the most difficult because
                    it involved a question of substance - the problem of the occupation of the
                    Azores under certain contingencies by the United States and the United Kingdom.
                    The Portuguese desk had exhibited deep sensitivity on the matter and HO had been
                    turned down flatly on one occasion. Our Embassy at Lisbon had also expressed
                    grave disquiet, and the views of our new Ambassador there, Tapley Bennett, were
                    being sounded out. Mr. Franklin was not sanguine that the Ambassador would “rock
                    the boat”. He pointed out that a memorandum by Mr. Gleason had demolished the
                    argument against publication. It showed that knowledge of Allied efforts to gain
                    bases in the Azores was already in the public domain, placed there by
                    authoritative memoirs, by the Potsdam and Cairo-Tehran volumes, and by
                    Portuguese historians. Thus there was no possibility that Salazar would be
                    surprised by new revelations. Mr. Dougall thought it ironic that the later
                    events in the story were already public knowledge while we were being asked to
                    withhold the earlier portions of the record on the grounds that publication
                    would adversely affect our current relations with Portugal. He regarded the
                    Anglo-American plan as an important element in our wartime diplomacy, which must
                    be documented, and said that we were now fighting the battle for clearance
                    through Assistant Secretary Donnelley. A further problem was that the desks
                    shied away from clearing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> because the
                    publication was official but cleared the work of private scholars more freely
                    since they felt no responsibility for them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted that one of the effects of our clearance difficulties was the
                    growing gap between the year of the printed record and the present time. <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was falling back to a gap of 30 years.
                    The British, on the other hand, were hoping to move from a lag of 50 years to
                    one of 30 years in the opening of their records.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason suggested that we encounter greater difficulties in the matter of
                    clearance with our own officials than with foreign governments. Mr. Sterling
                    inquired whether our difficulties were related to current problems. Mr. Gleason
                    answered in the affirmative. Yet he confessed his inability to discern why our
                    uneasy relations with Portugal caused by our current attitude on Angola and
                    Mozambique would be worsened by publishing documentation on other matters that
                    took place over 20 years ago.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall concluded his discussion of the Washington-Casablanca conference
                    volume by stating that the attitude of the Assistant Secretary for European
                    Affairs was all-important. If he were understanding and sympathetic to printing
                    the record, the problem would be solved quickly. Otherwise, we might still
                    appeal to the Secretary of State, something we would do only if we thought we
                    would win.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall then discussed the volume documenting the Quebec Conferences of 1943
                    and 1944, which was not nearly so far along as the one for the
                    Washington-Casablanca Conferences. We had largely collected the documents and
                    done much annotation for First Quebec, but we were trying to get additional
                    documents from Defense, Hyde Park and elsewhere. Second Quebec was not being
                    worked on because its compiler, Mr. Kogan, was engrossed with his new duties as
                    Chief of the Research Guidance and Review Division.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin explained that the open and closed periods of the State Department
                    files presented no difficulty to Mr. Kogan. Rather it was the restricted period,
                    geared to the release of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, which
                    provided the bulk of his work. One effect of the slowing down of publication of
                    the series was to narrow the restricted period and thus reduce the potential
                    volume of work for Mr. Kogan’s office. Mr. Franklin was optimistic, therefore,
                    that Mr. Kogan would get back to Second Quebec as the pressure of his current
                    duties lessened.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop summarized the situation regarding the two remaining conference
                    volumes, stating that they were the furthest behind currency. Clearance
                    problems, he noted, were a challenge to the former; as for the second,
                    compilation of manuscript was the problem.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 4: Report on annual volumes for 1947</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason stated his report would constitute “minor variations on a melancholy
                    theme by Gleason”. His Division had set three major objectives for 1947
                    compilations: (1) to cover the major themes for the year in six or seven
                    volumes, exclusive of the China volume; (2) to limit the size of the volumes to
                    about 1,000 printed pages; and (3) to compile the manuscript in the space of one
                    year. These objectives reflected the view, he thought shared by the Committee,
                    that since no additional staff was likely, our only hope of staying even in
                    sight of the 20-year line was to limit the number of volumes by being more
                    selective in our choice of subjects. The attempt to achieve these objectives
                    meant the disappearance of certain favorite themes of the past for which we
                    could expect criticism. It had also meant a more rigorous definition of the
                    major American policies to be covered as well as a more austere treatment of
                    them, an economy he did not think would be universally applauded. On the other
                    hand, we could point to the advantage to scholars in obtaining access to the
                    files immediately after publication. This emphasized the desirability of trying
                    to keep within sight of the 20-year gap.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that we had not achieved our objectives but had come close
                    enough to warrant optimism that further progress may be attained in another
                    year. The bulk of the work on 1947 had been done and completion of the remainder
                    was anticipated by the end of the winter. If we decided on six volumes, several
                    would exceed the desired thousand-page limit, but except for the China volume,
                    which was already in galleys, by not very significant margins. If the
                    seven-volume plan seemed more desirable, most would fall within this limit. The
                    China volume, because of the exceptional circumstances of its compilation, would
                    approximate 1300 pages.</p>
                <p>In view of the fact that the 1946 volumes totaled nine, not including two China
                    volumes, Mr. Gleason felt that we were making progress toward attainment of the
                    first two objectives. As to the third objective of compiling a year in a year,
                    progress was much less notable. No single volume had been compiled within the
                    space of a year, although two might be described as near misses. He was not
                    sanguine that this objective could be achieved in the future without additional
                    personnel unless the character of the series were drastically altered. Paper in
                    the files would continue to proliferate by geometric progression and our efforts
                    to reduce the number and size of the volumes by greater selectivity would be
                    increasingly time-consuming.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason reminded the Committee that even if the staff succeeded in achieving
                    the three objectives, there was no likelihood that we alone could close the
                    20-year gap or even keep it from falling further behind the 22-year gap it has
                    reached. This unfortunate situation derived from the lack of sufficient
                    personnel in PBR and, unless some means were found to speed its technical
                    editing and indexing, six or seven volumes could not be published is one year,
                    even though compiled.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop commented that according to Mr. Aandahl’s chart, the 1947 volumes
                    would not be published for 6 to 7 years. Mr. Gleason agreed. In reply to a
                    question from Mr. Stewart, Mr. Gleason stated that we were sending manuscript to
                    PBR as rapidly as possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin commented on one aspect of the PBR bottleneck - the question of
                    indexing. PBR had come up with the idea of contracting out the preparation of
                    indexes. Its experience in this field had been unfortunate. The work had not
                    been satisfactory and had to be redone by PBR. Normally an index prepared in PBR
                    took one experienced person at least three months full time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin reported for the General Branch. He noted that if he stuck narrowly
                    to the agenda, he would have little to say as his branch was immersed in 1946
                    and had not gotten deeply into 1947. Yet the situation was favorable, possibly
                    because it had been so unfavorable before. He stressed two reasons for the
                    previously unfavorable situation: (1) new types of compilations had produced
                    unfamiliar substantive and procedural problems with respect to the United
                    Nations; and (2) problems had inevitably been created by the advent of new
                    personnel. Actually, there had been a complete turnover in the Branch’s
                    personnel since 1962. Admittedly, the Branch had been in a wilderness, but with
                    the staff approaching a level of optimum performance, it was now coming out into
                    the open.</p>
                <p>The problem of the UN had been brought under control, both as to what was going
                    to be done and how it was going to be done. Much of the planning brought to the
                    attention of the Committee two years ago had by now become reality and was being
                    tested in a second round with the UN in 1947. He emphasized that the General
                    Branch handled United States policy on constitutional and organizational
                    problems involved at the UN. These, basically, were projections of issues of
                    Dumbarton Oaks and San Francisco. Regional and substantive issues at the United
                    Nations were being handled by area compilers. He was pleased to report that many
                    of the critical UN issues for 1946 diminished in scope and intensity in 1947 and
                    even disappeared. He predicted that in no future year would the UN documentation
                    printed be as bulky or present such acute problems as that for 1946. Mr. Goodwin
                    noted that he was personally responsible for this part of his Branch’s work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen compiled the record in a second area of multilateral and conference
                    diplomacy for which the General Branch had responsibility, and in which the UN
                    factor continued to loom large. He referred to that whole segment of United
                    States foreign relations that might be described loosely as “disarmament and
                    related matters”. The whole vast subject of international control of atomic
                    energy and regulation of conventional armaments fell within this field, as well
                    as so-called collective security subjects. Also within this area, the Branch
                    covered the interminable Soviet attempts at the UN to get the armed forces of
                    the West out of foreign countries and foreign bases. It also had a whole new
                    field of politico-military subjects, separate from the armaments and atomic
                    energy subject, yet closely related. This field, described as “national security
                    policy”, would include such items as “think pieces” ground out by the State
                    Department, the State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee and the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff, reflecting the new partnership between the political and military
                    elements in the Executive Branch in the formulation of United States foreign
                    policy. Other subjects to be covered here could be the United States development
                    of atomic energy, that is, questions relating to accessibility to raw materials,
                    the relationship of the United Kingdom to the United States, etc.</p>
                <p>The third major area of multilateral and conference diplomacy related
                    preponderantly to economic foreign policy. Mr. Kranz was handling these
                    compilations, which included such large-scale subjects as the efforts by the
                    United States to bring about the establishment of an International Trade
                    Organization and GATT. A complex 1946 story done by Mr. Kranz on the foreign
                    financial and loan program of the United States in the 18-month period following
                    the end of the war had led him into the Western Branch jurisdiction and the
                    General Branch has undertaken to compile the record of the diplomacy of the
                    Marshall Plan. It is also doing a story relating to the British financial crisis
                    of 1947 and its impact upon the multilateral financial diplomacy of the late
                    1940’s, with specific reference to the implementation of the Anglo-American
                    Financial Agreement of 1945. Mr. Goodwin stated that we were thus tackling this
                    complex of issues relating to international commercial and financial policy and
                    diplomacy as a more or less unified subject although jurisdictionally the
                    individual components fell between two of our Branches.</p>
                <p>As to the volumes themselves, volume I for 1946 would be a fat 1600 printed
                    pages; volume I for 1947 had just been started and was projected at about 1200
                    pages, to be completed by April 1967, except possibly in the field of economic
                    foreign policy. Little could be said about volume I for 1948. A very rough,
                    tentative projection had been made calling for its completion by the end of 1967
                    in a slightly smaller volume than that for 1947.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop inquired whether we would be documenting at length the activities of
                    the specialized agencies such as the International Bank, the International Labor
                    Organization, and the International Monetary Fund. Mr. Goodwin stated we would
                    try to avoid getting bogged down in this field unless United States policy were
                    deeply involved. In reply to a further question from Mr. Bishop about the
                    Chicago Civil Aviation Conference of 1944, Mr. Aandahl stated that the
                    compilation on that Conference had been a very lengthy one but that it had been
                    cut back drastically lately, its technical matter, particularly, being
                    excised.</p>
                <p>The meeting resumed after a short intermission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl spoke of the activities of the Western Branch, which took in Western
                    Europe and Latin America. He noted that Latin America was traditionally the area
                    fastest compiled and the slowest cleared, and that compilation for Western
                    Europe was being retarded by a shortage of personnel. He reported that the Latin
                    American volume for 1947, compiled by Mr. Wright and Mrs. Cassidy, had recently
                    been sent to PBR, the first of any of the 1947 volumes to be turned over to the
                    technical editors. He concluded by saying that we were bound to have staffing
                    complications when the 12 historians of the Division have had to deal with the
                    40 volumes now in process, covering the years 1944 through 1948 as well as the
                    two earlier Conference volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell arrived at 11:10.</p>
                <p>Mr. Churchill then reviewed the work of the Eastern Branch. He advised that he
                    and Mr. Slany had completed the 1947 compilations for the Soviet Union and
                    Eastern Europe and that Mr. Reid had completed the compilations for the same
                    year on the Far East. The Near East was well along, awaiting primarily Mr.
                    Fine’s compilation on the Truman Doctrine, which he estimated would be completed
                    by the end of this winter.</p>
                <p>As for 1948, Mr. Churchill informed the Committee that except for the Near East,
                    compilation was well under way. He predicted completion of the Soviet Union and
                    Eastern Europe by September 1967 and the Far East possibly by the end of 1967.
                    The Near East volume was not expected to be completed until the end of the
                    summer of 1968.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 5: Efforts to expedite output (editorial
                    procedures):</p>
                <p>Messrs. Perlmutter and Smith joined the Committee at 11:15 to discuss efforts to
                    expedite output through editorial procedures. Mr. Franklin referred to the
                    second chart produced by Mr. Aandahl (agenda item 2) and stated that it
                    illustrated painfully the time lag between completion of compilation and
                    publication. He observed that the longer portion of the time interval was
                    accounted for by clearance; the PBR record was much better and its efforts were
                    devoted continually to improving our product. Yet it was barely able to keep
                    pace with the manuscript sent over by HO.</p>
                <p>Mr. Perlmutter announced himself as the bearer of good tidings regarding the
                    editorial picture. PBR had turned the corner in production and would turn out
                    five volumes in fiscal year 1967: volumes I, II, and VII for 1944 and I and II
                    for 1945. It would thus bring out all volumes thus far cleared. He felt the
                    prospects were excellent for bringing out volumes III, IV, and V for 1945 after
                    June 30, 1967. Thereafter, he predicted, PBR would keep up with all cleared
                    material. He lauded the splendid cooperation he had had from Mr. Franklin.</p>
                <p>He then discussed the steps he had taken to accelerate progress on publication.
                    The first had been to identify efficient outside indexers to take up the slack
                    in that area. Then he announced that he was exploring the possibility of making
                    arrangements with the Columbia University Press, which had edited the Alexander
                    Hamilton Papers, to assume responsibility for processing one <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volume, beginning next February. He stated lastly
                    that the productivity of the PBR staff was increasing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Perlmutter said that he had sent a questionnaire to some 150 publishers and
                    indexers, hoping to recruit outside help thereby. He had no hope for increasing
                    the PBR staff because of budgetary restrictions, but he did not feel this an
                    unmitigated evil because the slack would be taken up by outsiders. He concluded
                    by restating his optimism for the next year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked Mr. Perlmutter whether private enterprise in the field of
                    technical editing would do the job more cheaply and efficiently than PBR. Mr.
                    Perlmutter asserted that certain phases of the work would be done more cheaply
                    and efficiently on the outside. Several veterans on his staff were being paid
                    “top-dollar” wages that would not be matched outside. In any event, resort to
                    outside contracting was made necessary by the lack of sufficient regular
                    staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin expressed concern that outsiders might dilute the qualitative job
                    done by PBR and that it had to be proved that they would not do so. Mr. Smith
                    replied that the work in PBR was of top quality but was expensive. He felt that
                    if the outside work required a minimum of review by PBR, the system would be
                    faster and more efficient. In response to questions from Messrs. Bishop and
                    Sterling, he noted his intention to contract out for proofreading. Time limits,
                    he said, would be set in the contract with Columbia University Press.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop inquired whether there had been any difficulty with the work performed
                    by outside indexers. Mr. Smith replied that one volume had been contracted out
                    successfully. Mr. Bishop asked if Mr. Smith thought it necessary for outside
                    editors to have familiarity with the content of the material. Mr. Smith said
                    that it depended on the individual as to how well it would be done. He remarked
                    also that it would be uneconomical to contract out a single volume to an outside
                    indexer. Actually that indexer was acquiring training for subsequent work. He
                    regarded the Columbia University Press as a pilot project which would be
                    carefully reviewed by PBR. He hoped that the results would be such as to warrant
                    extension of the plan.</p>
                <p>After questions by Mr. Bishop, Mr. Smith commented on the security aspects of the
                    pilot project. He cited the understanding with the Office of Security (SY)
                    regarding handling manuscript material as confidential. Outside editors would
                    have to be cleared by SY and their facilities for storage would require official
                    approval. Many outside contractors were already cleared for handling classified
                    material of the Department and the security aspects provided no major
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall inquired whether PBR could increase its pace from the five volumes
                    promised for fiscal year 1967 to six volumes the following year. Mr. Perlmutter
                    asserted that every volume cleared in 1967 and 1968 would be published. Mr.
                    Smith felt that chances were good for six volumes to appear in 1968. Mr. Bishop
                    took note of the likelihood that PBR would cease to be a bottleneck if the steps
                    contemplated by Mr. Perlmutter were successful. Mr. Perlmutter stated he had
                    every confidence in the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked if the time forecast in Chart No. 2 for producing published
                    volumes could now be shortened. Mr. Perlmutter said he believed so on the ground
                    that our growing outside help would supplement a basically static in-house
                    capability.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin stated that last year, he and Mr. Perlmutter had had several
                    conferences regarding shortcuts in technical editing and they had agreed to cut
                    corners, some of a potentially dangerous character. HO had relieved PBR of
                    checking footnote citations, taking responsibility for their accuracy in what
                    could best be described as a calculated risk. Mr. Gleason stated that he was
                    attempting to cut down on the number, length, and elaborateness of footnotes,
                    retaining those that clarified the documents to which they were appended and
                    eliminating those merely of general help to the reader. Mr. Bishop testified to
                    the soundness of this approach, pointing out that our first duty was to bring
                    out published volumes. </p>
                <p>Messrs. Perlmutter and Smith left the meeting at 11:45.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 5: Efforts to expedite output (clearance):</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason stated that in the past year there had been no appreciable change for
                    the better or worse and that the situation remained, therefore, thoroughly
                    discouraging. Within the Department, the best performance was clearance of a
                    volume in 10 months; the worst, in 22 months, and then only a “threatening
                    letter” had produced action. The average clearance time was approximately a year
                    and a half, as against our goal of clearance in three months.</p>
                <p>In may cases, the galleys simply lay at the bottom of a file cabinet, untouched
                    for long periods of time. When the bureaus finally did take action, they often
                    requested us to delete a few documents for what often appeared to us to be
                    frivolous reasons. We could only conclude that the delay resulted from
                    procrastination and inexperience.</p>
                <p>In the case of Argentina, clearance was turned over to an FSO-5 who seemingly
                    felt that he would keep out of difficulty by finding problems. What was required
                    for this work was a mature, high level officer with continuity of experience and
                    willingness to assume direct responsibility. A person of this caliber would have
                    known that the Department’s Blue Book on Argentina long ago had said everything
                    of substance that we proposed to print. The FSO-5 was apparently unfamiliar with
                    the Blue Book.</p>
                <p>Occasionally, there was a genuine problem of sensitivity, such as the case of
                    Iceland, where there had been a realistic fear that the Government would fall if
                    we published the compilation on American bases there. In this case, we had
                    deleted the story. More typical were the dubious objections, such as those
                    encompassed in the Argentine desk’s view that printing documents on Perón would
                    make cold our present tepid relations with Argentina. Overlooked was the fact
                    that the current Argentine Government was most anti-Perón and our relations with
                    it were not likely to be injured by <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop asked if HO might send the Blue Book or similar work along with the
                    galleys to assist clearing officers. Mr. Gleason stated that it had not been our
                    practice to send supporting material with the galleys. Mr. Franklin asserted
                    that in times past, however, we had marked with clips the passages HO thought
                    might be regarded as sensitive by the clearing desks. Our idea in so doing was
                    that the desks would concentrate their efforts on these matters and pass
                    routinely and rapidly over the reminder. The results had been most unfortunate.
                    The desks had requested deletion of the clipped items and then had requested
                    further deletions from other portions of the galleys which we had felt were not
                    sensitive. Mr. Franklin suggested that the long delays in clearance would be a
                    fitting subject to bring up with Under Secretary Rostow during the Committee’s
                    luncheon with him. As a new man, he might be appalled that it took almost two
                    years to clear a volume.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin suggested that what was needed was to get one or two men in each
                    bureau, at the level of a Deputy Assistant Secretary or a Special Assistant to
                    the Assistant Secretary, to do the clearing work. We have thus far been unable
                    to get such high-level people with sufficient time to do this chore. Yet
                    maturity, background and a firm conviction that the series was useful were
                    necessary requirements for clearing officials.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason deplored the fact that the desks did not think in terms of the value
                    of a given volume but rather of the impact of page X; this negative attitude was
                    most disturbing. Mr. Franklin noted that Mr. Rusk had made an address a few
                    years ago at the University of Wisconsin and that we had been able to work into
                    it a sympathetic word for Mr. Harrington and the Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood inquired whether guidelines were provided to reviewing officers by HO.
                    Mr. Franklin replied that a “Notice to Reviewing Officers” suggested that they
                    make no requests for deletions unless publication of a document or passage would
                    constitute a “clear and present danger” to our current international
                    relationships, requested that review be completed in three months, etc. The
                    notice stressed that the reviewers should “think big”, but it seems to have made
                    no impression.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling inquired how much time was actually spent on clearance once the
                    reviewing officer got around to it and whether there was one person in each
                    bureau to “bird dog” the operation. Mr. Franklin stated that each bureau had a
                    Public Affairs Officer (PAO) and that two of them would meet with the Committee
                    in the afternoon. Mr. Gleason noted that the PAO’s played the “bird-dogging”
                    role but not very effectively.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop expressed great interest in HO’s efforts at obtaining a clearance time
                    limit. Mr. Franklin stated that three years ago Mr. Manning had introduced a
                    memorandum at a meeting of the Assistant Secretaries in which he had set a time
                    limit of three months for clearance. The Assistant Secretaries had agreed to the
                    time limit. Regrettably, HO had not enforced this limit because of its potential
                    wastefulness. A bureau not giving direct clearance during the galley stage might
                    make numerous requests for deletions in the page proof stage. In any event, we
                    did not dare to take a strong stand on the matter without backing at the highest
                    levels.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then turned to other aspects of the clearance question. He stated
                    that compared with the difficulties we faced in the Department, those with other
                    agencies and foreign governments were pale. The British Foreign Office patiently
                    cleared large numbers of documents with only a rare refusal. Even the Quai
                    d’Orsay had not discovered in refusal of permission to print French documents
                    another way to irritate the United States. Defense was certainly slower than we
                    wished in clearing political military documentation, but there was little point
                    in increasing pressure on them when our own bureaus moved even more slowly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then announced the impending retirement of Almon Wright from our
                    Latin American field. He paid generous tribute to Mr. Wright’s contributions to
                    the series and stated how great a loss his retirement would be to us. He spoke
                    of the difficulty of replacing him; in fact, we were not even sure of being able
                    to get a new employee to fill his slot.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop then inquired whether Assistant Secretary Donnelley shared Mr.
                    Manning’s convictions on the clearance operation. Mr. Franklin was not sure
                    because of the paucity of his contacts with Mr. Donnelley, all of which,
                    however, had been very helpful. Mr. Bishop suggested that since there had been
                    so much turnover in the ranks of the Assistant Secretaries in the Department, it
                    might be useful to submit a new memorandum on three-month clearance to be signed
                    by Mr. Donnelley. Mr. Franklin agreed, proposing to incorporate examples of our
                    worst experiences.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart raised the question of clearance with Eastern European countries. Mr.
                    Gleason said that in the past we had published documents from those Communist
                    states without clearance from the Governments involved. Recently, the Office of
                    Eastern European Affairs had suggested that we regard Yugoslavia as a “friendly
                    government” and submit its documents for clearance. Mr. Gleason stated that he
                    was horrified at the suggestion, for United States relations with Yugoslavia in
                    1946 and 1947 were as bad as almost any, and he had prevailed on EE to hold off
                    on its suggestion at least until the 1948 papers. He anticipated great
                    difficulty in clearance simply because Yugoslavia was a Communist state and he
                    felt it likely that the Yugoslavs would not be interested in clearing documents
                    anyway. Mr. Gleason also mentioned the case in which our Embassy in Nicaragua
                    had recommended that certain Nicaraguan documents not be submitted for
                    clearance. Needless to say we had hastened to concur.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop asked whether Mr. Gleason shared the optimism expressed and radiated
                    by Mr. Perlmutter. Mr. Gleason said he was quite skeptical and had reservations
                    about the quality of work by outsiders. Mr. Mosely referred to some of his
                    dealings with Columbia University Press in which he had found them very slow. In
                    fact, he had withdrawn from the Press certain studies on the Soviet Union and
                    sent them elsewhere for editing and printing.</p>
                <p>The Committee adjourned at 12:15 for luncheon (AGENDA ITEM 7) with Under
                    Secretary Rostow.</p>
                <p rend="center">*****</p>
                <p>The afternoon session began at 2:30.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop announced the Committee’s intention to complete its work the same
                    afternoon, obviating any need for a Saturday session.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 6: Problems of technical editing:</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop requested the Committee to turn its attention to the technical editing
                    reforms proposed by the PBR officers. Mr. Stewart felt it was the consensus of
                    the members that the Perlmutter-Smith report had been overly optimistic and that
                    the program of contracting out a portion of PBR’s work was not likely by itself
                    to result in the elimination of the bottleneck posed by technical editing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mosely left the meeting at this point.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin expressed the view that the proposed PBR measures were being
                    undertaken because it was easier for government agencies to obtain funds for
                    external contract activities than to hire additional government employees. He
                    said that the quality of outside editing procedures remained to be assessed. In
                    response to a question from Mr. Bishop, Mr. Franklin thought that a report on
                    the success of these procedures could be made at the Committee meeting next
                    November, and that the agenda for that meeting could include an item for
                    assessing their effectiveness. He felt, tentatively, that the contracting-out
                    system might be of some help since it was impossible for PBR to hire new
                    personnel. He also took occasion to review the great difficulties encountered so
                    far in contracting out <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> indexes,
                    pointing out that considerable time was often expended by PBR personnel in
                    bringing the indexes prepared by outsiders up to acceptable standards. Mr.
                    Bishop, similarly, related the difficulties encountered by the <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Journal of International Law</hi> in letting a contract for
                    outside indexing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl expressed doubt that outside contracting was going to be of decisive
                    help since the work to be contracted for was in the early stages of technical
                    editing, whereas the real bottleneck existed in the area of final editing. Mr.
                    Dougall expressed skepticism that the contracting out of technical editing would
                    progress far enough by next November to permit the Committee to evaluate its
                    merits.</p>
                <p>Mr. Churchill observed that editing by out-of-town contractors would make
                    impossible the current regular consultation by PBR with the personnel in HO who
                    had prepared the manuscript.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling emphasized the seriousness of the fact that two of the three senior
                    technical editors were approaching retirement age and that, in view of current
                    and prospective job freezes, the Department had a real problem in being able to
                    hire replacements.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop wondered whether the Committee should urge the grooming of
                    replacements for the senior editors in addition to approving the proposed
                    contracting out of technical editing, for the latter in any case would not be
                    the sole solution of the editing problem. He requested that Mr. Franklin have a
                    memorandum prepared for the Committee, reviewing the organization and numerical
                    strength of PBR personnel and setting forth the approximate dates of anticipated
                    retirement.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell gave his opinion that the technical editors, who were turning out for
                    publication only five volumes a year, were being much too thorough in their
                    work. He recalled that the 25-member staff of the Indiana University Press
                    prepared over 50 volumes a year for publication, and that not only technical
                    editing but promotional and other activities were included. He reiterated his
                    shock at learning that the 11 technical editors turned out but five volumes
                    annually and speculated that perhaps a too-leisurely work pace contributed to
                    this record.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin spoke out in defense of PBR, stating that it was dangerous to hack
                    away at the standards used. He averred his complete satisfaction with the
                    thoroughness, dedication, accuracy and skill of the PBR staff, but admitted it
                    might exhibit a degree of over-conscientiousness and over-attention to detail.
                    He reminded the Committee that in the past few years, by agreement between HO
                    and PBR, various short cuts in editorial practices had been introduced. He also
                    noted that technical editing of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> did not
                    involve straight narrative texts such as produced by university presses. A
                    sample of raw, difficult manuscript was shown to the Committee as typical of the
                    kind that PBR works on. The volumes, moreover, were much larger than those
                    generally produced by university presses.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smyth noted, by way of comparison, that the technical editing of the German
                    Foreign Office documents in Washington by PBR was at a substantially higher
                    level of accuracy and speed than for those volumes edited in London. Mr. Aandahl
                    noted that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes included
                    extensive cross-referencing of intricate inter-relationships which required
                    considerable time and effort by PBR.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell expressed his desire for a 15-year time lag for <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> and subsequently said that a 20-year limit should be
                    our target, even at the expanse of less meticulous preparation of the volumes.
                    Mr. Franklin pointed out the dangers of appreciably lowering editorial
                    standards. One could not be certain whether errors which might then creep in
                    were major or minor ones. He cited the possibility of unfavorable reviews and
                    comments by users.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell gave his opinion that there were relatively few scholarly reviews of
                    the series. Generally, the reviewers restricted themselves to “sizing up” the
                    volumes and there was little likelihood that they would detect the occasional
                    typographical errors that might result from relaxation of editorial standards.
                    In any case, expedited publication would result in earlier opening of the State
                    Department archives--Mr. Ferrell stressed the great importance he attached to
                    this--so that scholars would be able to detect and correct any errors. Mr.
                    Franklin reiterated his fear that lowered editorial standards might result in
                    major errors, thereby compromising the series in the eyes of its users.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Cassidy recalled that the 1946 Paris Peace Conference volume, which she
                    compiled and fully prepared for publication in about three months in 1947,
                    received one unfavorable review for poor editorial practices that are eliminated
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> by the painstaking and
                    time-consuming PBR processes. Because the aim of the Department was to release
                    her special publication as speedily and cheaply as possible, the original
                    Conference papers, most of which were poorly mimeographed and full of errors,
                    were reproduced by the photo-offset process, without correction of errors,
                    without annotation, without benefit of technical editing, and without an index.
                    The above-mentioned critic complained, also, of the limited documentation in the
                    single volume, and various individuals here and abroad sent written requests to
                    the Department for additional material and information. Mr. Franklin added what
                    he termed a sorrowful postscript--that the compilation on the Peace Conference
                    had had to be redone, this time in a manner consonant with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> standards. Mr. Bishop noted that the only real
                    problem with the Cassidy volume was that it was released in too short supply.
                    Many potential reviewers were unable to obtain copies. If the volume had been
                    issued in sufficient numbers, the critical review would likely have been
                    outweighed by more favorable ones.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling summarized the situation posed to the Committee by the proposed PBR
                    reforms: (l) it would be necessary for the Committee to examine the quality of
                    the editorial work accomplished under private contract; (2) as a tool to aid in
                    evaluating the efficiency of editorial practices within PBR, the Committee
                    should be provided with a memorandum giving a detailed picture of the practices
                    and procedures of that office.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart made a strong plea for retention of cross-referencing devices
                    currently employed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> as they were of
                    tremendous value to scholars. Mr, Franklin said that cross-references within the
                    series would be retained; but other types of annotation would have to be
                    curtailed in order to save time. These included such items as elimination of
                    references to printed sources for treaties, statutes, and the like.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood stated that Mr. Ferrell’s basic point concerning the desirability of
                    hewing to the 20-year line and its relationship to the question of access to the
                    files by scholars, even at the expense of lowering somewhat the quality of the
                    volumes, should be represented in the report of the Committee. He also expressed
                    his concern that Under Secretary Rostow was not thoroughly familiar with the
                    situation. (Mr. Rostow, during luncheon with the Committee, had expressed his
                    desire to retain the qualitative standards of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, and had said that if this involved a further slipping away
                    from the 20-year line, it was a price he was willing to pay.)</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell, who had been engaging in arithmetic computations, asserted that
                    given an annual production of five volumes, each of the technical editors was
                    turning out an average of two pages a day, a shockingly low figure. He
                    reiterated the necessity for speeding technical editing by reducing qualitative
                    standards. He then suggested elimination of the index in order to maintain the
                    20-year line.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling thought it would be very useful for the Committee to have detailed
                    information on the actual range of activities of the PBR staff, the number of
                    volumes each editor worked on, etc. Mr. Bishop was also of the opinion that the
                    Committee needed additional knowledge of PBR’s operations and procedures and
                    called for a detailed memorandum on the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin recalled that in 1962, when he and Mr. Perlmutter had recently
                    assumed their present duties, both had been impatient with the slowness of the
                    technical editing process. They had investigated the problem thoroughly and had
                    agreed to cut out certain of the operations. They had both deemed it unwise to
                    cut out further steps for fear of grievously lowering standards.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin took issue with Mr. Ferrell’s statistics about the daily work-rate
                    per PBR editor, noting that they failed to take into account, for example the
                    time-consuming job of preparing indexes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell recalled that he and his wife had completed the index for his recent
                    book on Secretary Marshall in two days. The process of indexing <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> should be speeded up enormously.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smyth suggested that the rate of producing <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> be compared with that of other major diplomatic documentary
                    series such as those of the British, French, and Italians. He felt certain that
                    the rate of producing the American volumes would be found to compare most
                    favorably with those of the others. He spoke additionally of the high quality of
                    our product. Mr. Ferrell agreed that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series was the best of its kind published and the closest to
                    currency as well. He insisted, however, on the importance of maintaining the
                    20-year line. Mr. Franklin noted that an appreciable lowering of standards might
                    make <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> look poor in comparison with
                    similar publications of other nations.</p>
                <p>In response to a request by Mr. Bishop, Mr. Franklin promised to supply the
                    Committee with a descriptive list of PBR processes recently prepared at his
                    request by PBR. Mr. Bishop concluded the discussion of technical editing by
                    requesting that a PBR senior editor appear before the Committee at its next
                    meeting.</p>
                <p rend="underline">AGENDA ITEM 8: Discussion with Public Affairs Officers on
                    clearance problems:</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop inquired whether Committee members cared to make any observations on
                    clearance before the Public Affairs Officers arrived at 3:30. Mr. Stewart
                    observed that the present system of using PAO’s as the liaison agents to clear
                    galleys had resulted in great delay. He speculated whether the Committee should
                    request the views of the PAO’s as to whether the process would be more
                    expeditious if they should turn over their clearance role to Deputy Assistant
                    Secretaries, who had greater prestige and knowledge. Mr. Franklin went a step
                    further and suggested that the PAO’s be asked whether the Deputies could assume
                    the entire clearance responsibility, rather than have our material parceled out
                    to the various country desks.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl suggested referral to the Bureaus, initially, of only a table of
                    contents with a request that clearance be given immediately to compilations
                    whose title promised no difficulty, and that only galleys specifically requested
                    by the Bureaus because of their sensitivity be sent.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop queried whether the PAO’s were really “sold” on the desirability of
                    rapid clearance. Mr. Ferrell deplored the widespread indifference to the series
                    apparent in the Department. He said the basic question was how such an attitude
                    could be corrected. Mr. Bishop emphasized the need for an educational campaign
                    to convince Department officers, both at the highest level and the lowest, of
                    the importance of the series. It was not enough to educate one group of officers
                    any more than it sufficed to educate one group of students at a university. Such
                    a campaign should be a continuing one and the Committee should maintain a
                    continuing responsibility in this field.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin assured the Committee of HO’s appreciation of the work already done
                    by the Committee along these lines. He recalled that articles by Dick Leopold
                    and others had made quite a “splash”. In response to a question from Mr. Osgood,
                    Mr. Franklin agreed that the Committee’s efforts to have pro-<hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> material placed in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Congressional Record</hi> had been useful but that benefits had been
                    minimal.</p>
                <p>Mr. Goodwin cited Joseph M. Jones’ <hi rend="italic">The Fifteen Weeks</hi>
                    (1955) as authority for the existence of a “deep and yawning chasm that existed
                    between the operational and informational areas of the Department”. Mr. Gleason
                    observed that much of the clearance difficulty was caused because the geographic
                    desks were badly overworked and understaffed and were subject to rapid and
                    continuing turnover.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jerabek, PAO for the Bureau of European Affairs, joined the meeting at 3:30.
                    Mr Franklin introduced him to the Committee as a veteran PAO who had expended
                    great efforts and time on the clearance problem and that HO was much further
                    ahead because he had filled his role well. Mr. Bishop summarized for Mr. Jerabek
                    the efforts to be taken by PBR to speed editing of the series and asked in the
                    name of the Committee whether he, Mr. Jerabek, could suggest measures to speed
                    clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jerabek reviewed the past and present status of EUR clearance. He noted that
                    clearance of wartime volumes had presented no special problems and had moved
                    along well. Difficulties began to crop up with the ending of the war. Procedural
                    difficulties in EUR had also resulted in clearance delays. He recalled two
                    specific clearance problems, in connection with Tito in mid-1945 and with de
                    Gaulle; but once these had been settled, clearance had moved swiftly. The major
                    problem in recent years had been the Azores. In connection with the ease of
                    difficulty of clearance, he gave his theory that where relations with a foreign
                    government were hopelessly bad or exceptionally good, clearance presented few
                    problems at the geographic desk level; but that where relations were in between
                    these extremes, clearance was more difficult.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Ferrell, on actual clearance procedures in
                    EUR, Mr. Jerabek stated that he reviewed all the galleys and decided which of
                    them required no further review. He sent to the desks only those galleys which
                    required further scrutiny.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop inquired if some improvement in the clearance procedure might be
                    realized by shifting the first overall galley clearance from the PAO’s to the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary level. Mr. Jerabek stated that this procedure had not
                    been tried in EUR, but he was most dubious that the Deputies would be able to
                    devote the necessary time to clearance. They would doubtless refer the galleys
                    to desk officers for examination in much the same way the PAO’s now did.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling asked if it were true, as the Committee understood, that galleys
                    often lay unexamined for months in file cabinets of desk officers. Mr. Jerabek
                    conceded that this was often the case. Not only were desk officers extremely
                    pressed for time but they usually had higher priority work. Because of these
                    pressures, desk officers found that the only way to review the galleys was to
                    come to the Department on weekends. Mr. Sterling inquired whether a reluctance
                    to make decisions was a factor in delay. Mr. Jerabek said that this was probably
                    true in some cases.</p>
                <p>At this point, Mr. Armstrong, PAO for the Bureau of East Asian and Pacific
                    Affairs (EA), arrived and was introduced to the Committee. It was noted that he
                    was newly arrived at his job, having come from USIA about two months ago. Mr.
                    Franklin explained to him the functions of the Committee in examining the
                    operations and problems of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                    He said that while clearance had been singled out for attention at this point,
                    the practices of HO and PBR were also under scrutiny. He pointed out that
                    clearance delays involving the Defense Department and foreign governments were
                    generally much less severe than those involving the geographic bureaus.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop referred to Mr. Manning’s memorandum of 1963 which specified that
                    clearance was to be completed in three months. He noted for the PAO’s that the
                    Manning memorandum had been concurred in at the time by the Assistant
                    Secretaries in charge of the bureaus and asked whether reissuing the memorandum
                    at this time would serve to expedite clearance. Mr. Jerabek informed the
                    Committee that he reminds his desk officers of the necessity of working on the
                    galleys after three months. He felt uncertain whether a reissue of the Manning
                    memorandum would provide a sufficient prod to accomplish HO’s purposes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling suggested that the PAO’s obtain clear authority to fix clearance
                    deadlines, but there was no discussion of this point.</p>
                <p>Mr. Osgood asked whether publication of diplomatic documents had interfered with
                    or adversely affected the conduct of diplomacy. In his own experience, he said,
                    he remembered virtually no documents that had had such impact. He observed that
                    the burden of proof as to whether publication of documents would upset current
                    negotiations should be placed on the desks, not on HO. Mr. Armstrong told the
                    Committee that Department officers were not opposed to publication of the series
                    and that delay in clearance was not the result of a negative attitude. Rather it
                    was simply a question of having time to get around to the work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall wondered how adverse would be the effect of publishing the 1944 China
                    volume in comparison with the impact of the President’s decision not to visit
                    Taiwan on his recent Asian trip. Mr. Armstrong expressed his hope that EA would
                    approve publication of that volume so that it could be released with the other
                    1944 volumes. Mr. Franklin informed him that the rest of the 1944 volumes would
                    be in print shortly, so that EA would have to hurry to attain that goal and
                    prevent the China volume from looking conspicuous by coming out long after the
                    remainder of the volumes for that year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell explained to the PAO’s two major reasons why historians were anxious
                    to speed publication of the series. The first was that access to the
                    Department’s files was geared to publication of the series; the second was that
                    by publishing a comprehensive record speedily, the United States would influence
                    all written history. He cited the very speedy publication of pre-1914 diplomatic
                    correspondence by the German Republic soon after the ending of World War I and
                    stated that the history of the origins of that war was written on the basis of
                    the German documents since they were the first and for long the only official
                    documents published.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin recalled that when the series was sliding from 15 years behind
                    currency to 20 years, everyone had felt that the longer lapse would facilitate
                    clearance. Clearly this had not happened.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Armstrong about the seriousness of the delays
                    in clearance, Mr. Gleason asserted that currently the time required for
                    clearance varied from 10 months to 22 months, despite the three months that the
                    bureaus had agreed to “in principle”.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling described as unacceptable the fact that <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> material was simply put aside and cleared only after great
                    delay. He noted that he had been a university president for 18 years and knew
                    well that there were not enough hours in a day. Yet if clearance were
                    accomplished in 22 months, why couldn’t the process be accomplished much
                    earlier. “If it can be done on Tuesday, why can’t it be done on Monday?,” he
                    asked. He expressed his utter inability to understand the interminable delay and
                    characterized it as irresponsible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Armstrong stated that the pressures on clearance officers in their regular
                    assignments kept mounting and they were simply unable to undertake clearance
                    until the pressures relaxed somewhat. He observed, in answer to a question from
                    Mr. Bishop, that PAO’s did not need greater power in as much as they already had
                    authority to clear galleys if they saw fit to do so.</p>
                <p>At one point, Mr. Armstrong stated that only recently he had discovered in a file
                    cabinet certain galleys to be cleared in EA. Mr. Churchill asked him if these
                    galleys were those for 1945, volume VI, which had been sent to his predecessor
                    on August 30, 1965. After the laughter had subsided, Mr. Armstrong replied that
                    they probably were the ones Mr. Churchill had referred to. Mr. Franklin
                    suggested that perhaps clearance would be expedited by pre-dating our
                    transmittal memoranda.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason pointed to the dangers in assigning clearance tasks to young,
                    inexperienced, low-level FSO’s, who were reluctant to risk clearing material for
                    publication. Would it not be preferable, he asked, to assign clearance to
                    mature, experienced, high-level officers who would be able to clear galleys with
                    confidence and dispatch?</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin recalled that at the time of the Manning memorandum, it had been
                    recognized that some weeks would be too full for officers to work on clearance
                    but that three months was a realistic time limit. He felt that it might be
                    worthwhile to renew the three-month rule; the PAO’s agreed it would be worth
                    trying.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop stressed that not only did delay in clearance hold up publication of a
                    historical series but that it was also detrimental to the morale of the HO staff
                    who, after striving to cut down the time expended on compilation, saw the
                    product of their labors lie idle in the clearance stage.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop again asked Messrs. Jerabek and Armstrong for suggestions on speeding
                    clearance. Their sole suggestion was to have the galleys downgraded. Mr.
                    Franklin promised to see what could be done about downgrading the galleys to
                    Limited Official Use. At this point he showed the PAO’s Mr. Aandahl’s projection
                    indicating that if publication continued at the present rate for the next four
                    years, the series would soon drop behind an additional six years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bishop expressed the Committee’s appreciation to Messrs. Jerabek and
                    Armstrong for participating in the meeting, and they departed. The Committee
                    discussed their contributions to solving the clearance problem.</p>
                <p>At this point, the HO staff withdrew and the Committee went into private
                    session.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
