<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1967</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1967</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-21">April 21, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1967-11-03">November 3, 1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1967-11-03-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 403 KB, 15pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1967—Minutes. Limited Official
                Use.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn53">Footnote 53</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1967 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 3, 1967</dateline>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">PARTICIPANTS</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Hardy Cross Dillard, Dean of the School of Law, University of
                                Virginia (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>W. Stull Holt, Professor of History, University of Washington
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Stanley D. Metzger, Professor of Law, The Georgetown University
                                Law School (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Philip E. Mosely (absent), Director, European Institute, Columbia
                                University (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Elmer Plischke, Professor of Government and Politics, University
                                of Maryland (American Political Science Association)</item>
                            <item>J. E. Wallace Sterling, President of Stanford University (American
                                Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Robert B. Stewart (chairman), Professor of International Law and
                                Organization, Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University
                                (American Political Science Association)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Richard I. Phillips, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Public Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>Marvin W. Kranz</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Publishing and Reproduction Services Division:<list>
                            <item>Jerome H. Perlmutter, Chief</item>
                            <item>Peter A. Smith</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">1. Opening Remarks</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin opened the meeting at 9:35 a.m. by welcoming the Committee and
                    pointing out that the entire staff looked forward to its coming each year as a
                    source of ideas and inspiration. He then introduced Mr. Richard I. Phillips,
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, who greeted the
                    Committee on behalf of Assistant Secretary Dixon Donnelley, who could not be
                    present. Mr. Phillips expressed the gratitude of the Department of State and the
                    Bureau of Public Affairs for the time and effort contributed by members of the
                    Committee in helping with the problems and challenges facing the Historical
                    Office. In addition to the work on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, the
                    Historical Office was regularly called upon to meet a wide variety of current
                    demands by the Department, and the Bureau of Public Affairs derived great
                    benefits from the excellent standards of performance that it had maintained.
                    Secretary Rusk and other high officials frequently asked P/HO to provide
                    information or analysis on all sorts of questions. Looking at the 22 or 23 year
                    gap that now prevails between events and the publication of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>, Mr. Phillips then speculated on the problems that
                    the editors and the Committee would face in 1990 when they tried to compress
                    into a few volumes the complicated events of 1967. As a form of recognition for
                    the valued advice and services of the Committee, Mr. Phillips concluded his
                    remarks by suggesting that the members be named in the preface of each volume.
                    Repeating his thanks to the Committee, Mr. Phillips then withdrew, stating that
                    he would see the members again at luncheon.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin (as ex officio chairman) then brought up the question of selecting a
                    chairman for the group. Every sort of procedure had been employed over the
                    years, but this year he ventured to point out that there was only one senior
                    member present, namely Mr. Stewart. Mr. Stewart offered a counter-proposal, but
                    he was chosen Chairman by acclamation.</p>
                <p rend="underline">2. Reports on Status of the Series and Publication Plans</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl distributed copies of a progress chart, “Status of Volumes, November
                    1967” (annexed to these minutes), which showed that after some lean years
                    several volumes were coming out this fall and winter. He pointed out that some
                    recent volumes had been very large, so that there had not been much decline in
                    actual output of pages as compared to earlier years. He gave a short account of
                    the clearance process in the Departments of State and Defense and other agencies
                    and foreign governments to the extent that they are involved. Mr. Franklin noted
                    that business with the Department of Defense was increasing because the series
                    was regularly concerned with interconnections of foreign policy and military
                    strategy in the postwar world. In response to questions by Mr. Dillard and Mr.
                    Stewart, Mr. Gleason pointed out that the Defense historians (Mr. Winnacker of
                    the Office of the Secretary of Defense, and the historians of the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff and the Office of the Chief of Military History) often made useful
                    suggestions for improving the text. In addition, they were more systematic about
                    the process of clearance than many offices in the State Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger said that he was struck by the inordinate delay shown on the chart
                    between completion of manuscript and the beginning of clearance. Mr. Franklin
                    said that most of this time was spent in technical editing and preparation of
                    galley proof, and that Messrs. Perlmutter and Smith of the Publishing and
                    Reproduction Services Division (PBR) would be present at 11 o’clock to discuss
                    this aspect of the work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason referred to the large number of volumes scheduled to appear in the
                    current fiscal year (the last one for 1944 and the first five for 1945). Some
                    years ago Secretary Rusk had approved the principle that the series should be
                    maintained at twenty years from currency. Under present conditions there was no
                    hope of attaining this goal, but through more detailed advance planning, more
                    rigorous selection of documents, and various editorial devices we at least were
                    able to keep from slipping further behind the 20-year line. Mr. Gleason then
                    stated that we were trying to do three things: (a) reduce the number of annual
                    volumes to six or seven, (b) keep the volumes under 1,000 pages, and (c) compile
                    a year in a year. We were making good progress on the first two. There are eight
                    volumes for 1947 compared to twelve for 1945 (including conferences) and eleven
                    for 1946, and we had considerably reduced the average number of pages. The third
                    objective, to compile a year in a year, seemed unlikely of achievement because
                    of staff shortages. We did not have enough historians to review and edit the
                    mass of documentation for a given year and also attend to our other duties.</p>
                <p>The bottleneck in technical editing, Mr. Gleason continued, seems susceptible of
                    improvement. Some indexing work and technical editing had been contracted out to
                    World Publishing Company in Cleveland, and this has eased the pressure on PBR’s
                    own staff, which had not been able to process the various volumes fast enough.
                    We are not yet sure, he said, that World can maintain the high standards of the
                    series, but if they can do an acceptable job on some of the tasks, PBR should be
                    able to keep the whole process moving on schedule and still maintain the
                    necessary level of quality.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt questioned Mr. Gleason’s statement that progress was being made when the
                    series was continuing to fall farther and farther behind, as shown in the time
                    lag from the 1945 to the 1947 volumes. Mr. Gleason said that the series was
                    still falling behind but at a slower rate, and Mr. Stewart commented that so
                    long as it was impossible to compile a year in a year, falling further behind
                    was inevitable. Mr. Franklin added that if we actually did a year in a year he
                    would find it much easier to apply pressure to other offices to speed up
                    clearance and technical work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked if this meant that the need for additional historians was the
                    number one problem. Mr. Franklin said that over the years the Committee has
                    several times recommended an increase of five or six historians, but this was
                    never taken seriously. Perhaps the appointment of even two more would enable us
                    to compile a year in a year. We had tried to be very realistic.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling asked if this were a budget problem or a recruiting problem. Mr.
                    Franklin answered that it was a matter of budget and “job slots”. Contracting
                    out was fashionable and money was available for it, but there were no funds to
                    hire new people to work in the Department. Messrs. Stewart and Sterling then
                    asked what the Committee could do to help. Mr. Franklin summarized previous
                    actions by the Committee and said that things would no doubt have been worse
                    without these concrete indications that the scholarly world and the foreign
                    affairs community were actively interested in the series, but little practical
                    assistance had been forthcoming. The Department of State is always involved in
                    some kind of international crisis, and priorities are necessarily given to
                    emergency task forces rather than to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    and other non-priority, continuing operations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason felt that what was really needed was an awareness among senior
                    officers in the Department that there would be some practical advantage in
                    having the 1945-1947 documents available now to show the origins of the Cold
                    War. A new revisionism is growing up, but desk officers seldom appreciate the
                    great value of a candid presentation of American foreign policy. Mr. Stewart
                    asked if it would not be possible, given the tumultuous state of American public
                    opinion on international questions, to ask for temporary measures to get these
                    volumes out now in time to provide a sound factual basis for decision. Mr.
                    Stewart thought that the Committee might wish to draw up some recommendation to
                    this effect.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin mentioned that the Committee would be having lunch with Under
                    Secretary Katzenbach, who might be interested in these thoughts. His
                    predecessor, Mr. George Ball, had shown a lively sense of history and had sent
                    us a variety of urgent inquiries, many of which could be answered rapidly only
                    because the material had been compiled for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Messrs. Churchill and Goodwin then described the current work of the Eastern and
                    General Branches, calling particular attention to the vast amount of
                    documentation available and the difficulty of compressing it into a few
                    1,000-page volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dillard asked about the delay in publishing the China volumes. Mr. Franklin
                    explained that they were originally compiled in the 1950’s on a special speed-up
                    basis, but that after publication of the first one, for 1942, Secretary Dulles
                    had ordered the publication stopped. Secretary Rusk has agreed to the principle
                    that the China volumes should be published with other volumes for the same year,
                    and that is what we have done for the China volumes for 1943 and 1944. We hope
                    to do the same for the 1945 volume.</p>
                <p rend="underline">3. Report on Wartime Conference Volumes</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin explained that objections by the Bureau of European Affairs (EUR) to
                    publishing certain documents on the Azores had led us to transfer the records of
                    the Third Washington Conference of May 1943 to the next volume. In addition to
                    the volumes on Cairo-Tehran (1943), Malta-Yalta (1945), and Potsdam (1945),
                    already published, the series will include: “The Conferences at Washington,
                    1941-1942, and Casablanca, 1943” (now cleared for paging), “The Conferences at
                    Washington and Quebec, 1943”, and “The Conference at Quebec, 1944.” Mr. Dougall
                    pointed out that he was now completing work on the first Quebec conference, but
                    that it too contained material on the Azores. So this Trident-Quadrant volume
                    may have to be held in galley for a while. Messrs. Stewart and Metzger expressed
                    surprise that the Azores question could still cause trouble, and Messrs.
                    Franklin and Gleason pointed out the steps that P/HO had taken to convince EUR
                    and Embassy Lisbon that the main lines of the story had already been widely
                    publicized. EUR held, however, that this was not the same as printing the
                    documents in our own official publication.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report on Problems of Technical Editing</p>
                <p>Messrs. Perlmutter and Smith of PBR arrived at 11 o’clock to discuss problems of
                    copy editing, preparation and correction of proofs, and indexing. Mr. Perlmutter
                    said that he was pleased to report that nine volumes would be published during
                    the current fiscal year. Much of the editorial work was being contracted out to
                    World Publishing Company of Cleveland, which had established a special unit of
                    four or five people to work exclusively on <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. World had sent some of its executives to Washington to talk
                    to Messrs. Franklin and Gleason, and P/HO had been very helpful in working out
                    arrangements and explaining what needed to be done. Mr. Perlmutter felt that the
                    picture was the brightest he had seen since becoming Chief of PBR.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt noted that last year’s minutes showed that Mr. Perlmutter had said five
                    volumes would be published in fiscal year 1967, but only three had come out. Mr.
                    Smith explained that the two late volumes had been delayed by indexing problems
                    of private indexers other than World Publishing Company. World, on the other
                    hand, had now prepared three indexes on time and in reasonably good shape, and
                    he thought they were building up good experience for future indexes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt asked if work were still being done by PBR directly, and Mr. Perlmutter
                    replied that it was doing more than half of the technical editing for the
                    series. Mr. Dillard asked what kinds of decisions the technical editors had to
                    make, and Mr. Smith explained that these all related to style, typography,
                    consistency, etc., whereas the historians retained full responsibility for the
                    contents and general accuracy of the volumes. Mr. Perlmutter added that he
                    thought there was a considerable financial saving to the Department in
                    contracting out. Mr. Metzger asked why this was so. Mr. Perlmutter said that
                    under the established accounting procedure PBR had a fixed charge of $6.75 per
                    hour for its services, whereas World Publishing Company had a much lower rate,
                    about $4.00. Mr. Metzger asked how this could be, when World was earning a
                    profit. He wondered if contracting out really saved the taxpayer’s money or if
                    this was only “playing with figures”. Mr. Perlmutter estimated that there was an
                    actual saving of about 40 per cent.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling stated that what Mr. Perlmutter was saying was that the United
                    States Government should get out of the editing and publishing business. Mr.
                    Franklin pointed out that the technical editors at PBR were in fact highly
                    skilled, and it was not yet established that World could match the quality of
                    their work. Mr. Dougall added that senior historians had had to spend much time
                    reviewing and correcting the indexes produced so far by World, and this was
                    certainly a hidden cost.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted that the Department did not have at present any choice between
                    hiring additional editors or contracting work out. That was not the issue, for
                    PBR did not have enough staff to handle the entire job, and they were not
                    allowed to recruit additional editors and indexers. So some of the work would
                    have to be contracted out, as matters now stood. Mr. Stewart said that there
                    clearly was a difference of opinion on matters of quality and cost. Mr.
                    Perlmutter stated that he was a great champion of maintaining the integrity and
                    standards of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> but that he was also aware
                    that many of the most skilled editors at PBR were approaching retirement. Mr.
                    Franklin suggested that some replacements would certainly be necessary, but Mr.
                    Perlmutter replied that the present outlook was that no new editors would be
                    hired. When one retired, the “job slot” was taken away. Mr. Holt called
                    attention to the two-year lag between clearance and publication, and Messrs.
                    Perlmutter and Smith agreed that this was too long. They were trying to speed up
                    the various stages, and had worked out a better schedule with the Government
                    Printing Office (GPO). Mr. Metzger said that he was not prepared to accept <hi
                        rend="underline">a priori</hi> the idea that contracting was best, which
                    seemed to be a “theological” attitude of PBR. Mr. Smith replied that under
                    present limitations and circumstances PBR felt that there were pragmatic
                    advantages to contracting out, given the present staff and workload. Mr. Metzger
                    said he “decried” the idea of not hiring replacements to do a job that he felt
                    properly belonged in the Government.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart then asked if there was any way of reducing the two-year interval
                    between clearance and publication. Mr. Dillard thought that this was much too
                    long. Messrs. Perlmutter and Smith agreed, and they withdrew after saying that
                    they thought that six to nine months could be saved, and that they were looking
                    for new manuscript.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason said that he was glad that the state of euphoria at the beginning of
                    the discussion had been dispelled. Noting Mr. Perlmutter’s remark that his
                    people at PBR were slow, Mr. Franklin said they were slow because they were
                    accurate. Mr. Dougall added that the reason Mr. Perlmutter’s staff is relatively
                    expensive is that he has not recruited any junior members lately.</p>
                <p>Summing up, Mr. Stewart said that he sensed a feeling of frustration in the
                    meeting as to exactly what the Committee could recommend about technical
                    editing.</p>
                <p>[The question of technical editing came up again briefly in the afternoon
                    session. In connection with editorial procedures Messrs. Franklin and Gleason
                    described various steps taken by P/HO to improve the condition of the manuscript
                    and to eliminate the need for various tasks previously done by PBR. Despite the
                    increased use of photocopies there were still many problems of legibility,
                    marking for the printer, etc., and we needed competent technical editors as much
                    as ever. Referring to the staffing problems described by Mr. Perlmutter, Mr.
                    Holt then asked why the technical editors should not be transferred to P/HO,
                    which was obviously interested in their work and dependent on it. Mr. Franklin
                    said that until 1946 they had been part of the Division of Research and
                    Publication, P/HO’s predecessor, but that as part of a general reorganization
                    the editing function was one of the central services transferred to the Bureau
                    of Administration. Their return to P/HO would probably offer no particular
                    benefit except that we would put up a stiffer fight to obtain suitable
                    replacements for the editors who retire.]</p>
                <p rend="underline">4A. Problems of Access to Department of State Records</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart said that the Agenda did not refer to problems of access to records
                    but that he thought the Committee should take note of the recent news item about
                    a book by Mr. Arthur Morse on the question of Jewish refugees in World War II.
                    He wondered if the Historical Office had been under excessive pressure to make
                    the records available, and whether this episode had any bearing on the proposal
                    by the Ford Foundation to undertake a major project on the diplomatic history of
                    the postwar years. [This discussion was interrupted when Messrs. Perlmutter and
                    Smith came to discuss Agenda Item 4.]</p>
                <p>In response to Mr. Stewart’s question about the Morse book, Mr. Franklin
                    described the access policies of the Department, which are administered by the
                    Division headed by Mr. Kogan. At present the open period extends to 1937, the
                    restricted period to 1944, and the closed period from 1945. Mr. Morse received
                    no special access but he received the benefit of our decision to treat the
                    records of the War Refugee Board (and several other wartime agencies) as
                    “restricted” all the way through to the end of the war rather than to keep the
                    last two years closed. Recalling that Dr. Stewart had posed his question in
                    connection with the proposed Ford Foundation project, Mr. Dougall stated that
                    Mr. Morse had worked only in the restricted period, whereas the group that had
                    Foundation backing was interested in the closed period.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger asked why there should be a restricted period at all, in view of the
                    difficulty of administering it. Mr. Franklin agreed and said that it was
                    gradually being phased out. The open period keeps to thirty years of currency,
                    while <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> gradually slips backward toward
                    that point, thus squeezing out the restricted period. Mr. Kogan had come up with
                    an even more radical plan, namely, to try to get the files opened for the entire
                    war period as soon as all <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes were
                    published for 1945. The open period would then be held there until 1975, when it
                    would again begin advancing a year at a time. Mr. Franklin thought that this
                    plan had a fair chance of being accepted by the policy bureaus, if we pushed it
                    vigorously. Since these bureaus had to review a lot of notes in the restricted
                    period, they also had some real interest in having the files either open or
                    closed.</p>
                <p>The meeting recessed at 12:20 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="underline">6. Efforts to Expedite Output</p>
                <p rend="underline">a. Clearance</p>
                <p>During the morning session Mr. Dillard had asked whether recommendations by desk
                    officers and others for deletion were made in writing, whether reasons were
                    given, and who had the final decision in the matter. Mr. Franklin had replied
                    that objections were in writing, that reasons were usually provided and could be
                    asked for if needed, and that cases of disagreement could theoretically be
                    carried to the Secretary but in practice rarely went above the Deputy Under
                    Secretary for Political Affairs. Mr. Dillard then asked if any material
                    published in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had ever actually caused
                    the Department real embarrassment. Mr. Franklin said that he did not know of any
                    cases that were serious. There had been various minor flurries, almost always on
                    material not expected to be troublesome. We had some difficulties because of the
                    large number of elderly statesmen still in power, but many of these were more
                    frank and realistic than their younger colleagues.</p>
                <p>When the subject of clearance came up again in the afternoon session, Mr. Gleason
                    summarized the current situation as “mixed”. The three-month deadline for return
                    of galleys was seldom met, but on the other hand we had fewer cases of long
                    delays of a year or more. With faster returns we were getting more requests for
                    deletions, many of which showed a lack of awareness of what has gone before. The
                    job of reviewing our galleys was usually assigned to very junior officers, who
                    were hypercautious. With much effort we had been able to refute a great many
                    objections and persuade the desks to withdraw them, but this was a very
                    inefficient and laborious process. One promising development was the suggestion
                    by Mr. Francis T. Murphy, Executive Director of the Bureau of Public Affairs,
                    that senior officers awaiting reassignment be asked to undertake the clearance
                    of galleys. The long-delayed documents on Palestine for 1945 had been cleared in
                    this manner. Mr. Metzger suggested using retired Foreign Service Officers in the
                    same way, but Mr. Franklin thought there might be security problems.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gleason then noted that despite forebodings in some quarters the China volume
                    for 1944 had caused not a ripple in the United States and only a small reaction
                    in Taipei. Mr. Franklin added that we now publish the volumes without issuing a
                    press release but instead include a routine announcement in Mr. McCloskey’s noon
                    briefing. This helps to dispel the suspicion that the Department is publishing
                    the volume for some special purpose. Mr. Plischke asked if there would be any
                    advantage in releasing the volumes at regular intervals, perhaps quarterly. Mr.
                    Franklin agreed that the automatic feature would be helpful but said that there
                    would be difficult problems of scheduling and storage.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dillard asked if definite guidelines had been sent to the bureaus responsible
                    for clearance, and Mr. Franklin explained that a sheet with such guidelines
                    accompanied each set of galleys sent out for clearance. The present one bore Mr.
                    Franklin’s signature, but he felt that it might now be time to revise the
                    document and have it signed by a higher officer. Mr. Stewart asked that a copy
                    of the guidelines be included in these minutes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Plischke, noting that under present arrangements the desks were delegating
                    clearance to junior officers, asked if there were not some way to assign more of
                    the responsibility to P/HO. Could not the historians assume the primary
                    responsibility? They would naturally consult the desks in doubtful cases, but
                    surely the historians were better informed than the desks on “the state of the
                    question” except in very current matters.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart asked if P/HO would be willing to accept this responsibility. Mr.
                    Gleason replied perhaps, but that he wondered if the Department would be willing
                    to grant it. Mr. Stewart thought it might be worth trying, and Mr. Plischke
                    asked if there were anything the Committee could do to help. Mr. Gleason pointed
                    out that the great stumbling block was that P/HO was not fully informed on
                    current operations and negotiations, as in the recent cases involving Iceland
                    and Portugal. In view of this Mr. Stewart asked if there were anyone except the
                    desks who could handle clearance. Mr. Gleason replied that no one at a higher
                    level could find time to deal with clearance on a regular basis.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by Mr. Plischke, Mr. Gleason said that in general only
                    about five per cent of the material had any trouble getting cleared. This five
                    per cent caused much of the delay in the total product. Mr. Plischke then
                    suggested that only this small amount be sent to the bureaus for clearance. Mr.
                    Dillard said that P/HO should have primary responsibility for clearance and
                    simply send to the desks whatever it felt might conceivably impair current
                    negotiations. Mr. Metzger said that P/HO should be given a chance to operate
                    with primary responsibility for clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that this could only be done if the Department were willing to
                    accept the fact that publication of some items would occasionally “rattle the
                    china” for a day or two, and not only with China volumes. Replying to questions
                    by Messrs. Sterling and Plischke, he pointed out that P/HO has the authority to
                    delete passages that might give “needless offense” to individuals or
                    nationalities. He pointed out that we were in good company, since the latest
                    documentary volume published by the Vatican had indicated the omission of some
                    personal references.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt asked if anything could be done to enforce the three-month limit on
                    clearances, and Mr. Gleason said that this would have to be mostly by
                    persuasion. Mr. Stewart said that the Committee would study the note that
                    accompanies galleys sent out for clearance and would offer some suggestions. Mr.
                    Metzger thought the three months could be reduced to six weeks, since in any
                    event the normal human reaction was to wait until two or three days before the
                    deadline. Mr. Plischke asked if formal responsibility for clearance lay with
                    P/HO or with the desks; Mr. Franklin replied that it lay with the desks (which
                    have the formal authority to declassify papers within their purview). The
                    trouble was that the desks did not regard the task as urgent, and unfortunately
                    there had been much blurring in the Department of the distinction (once
                    carefully observed) between the “urgent” and the “important.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart summed up this phase of the discussion by saying it would be
                    desirable to get Under Secretary Katzenbach or some other high official to sign
                    a clearance directive calling for prompt action and defining quite strictly what
                    sorts of deletions were permissible. He thought it would be desirable to find
                    ways of mobilizing senior officers to handle clearance, and he asked if there
                    were anything further that the Committee could do to reduce the delays
                    occasioned by the clearance process. Mr. Plischke asked if the Committee should
                    recommend that responsibility for clearance be turned over to the Historical
                    Office, and Mr. Gleason replied that he would be reluctant to accept it unless
                    some way were found to ensure that we did not unwittingly interfere with current
                    negotiations. Mr. Stewart said that the Committee would study the matter further
                    after it received the minutes of the meeting. He felt it was important to
                    emphasize the positive value of publishing these volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">b. Editorial Procedures</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart noted the enormous proliferation of papers in the wartime years and
                    after. This made the historian’s task infinitely greater. Mr. Franklin added
                    that the problem was intensified by the Department’s “ox-cart” filing system,
                    and could only be solved by electronic storage and retrieval. Mr. Stewart asked
                    that a survey be made to show how tremendously the documentation had increased
                    since the war. Mr. Franklin agreed that this could be done.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling raised the question discussed at the morning session of making a
                    special effort to expedite publication of documents on the origins and early
                    years of the Cold War. Mr. Stewart thought that the Committee should do
                    something about this. He felt that the Chairman should draft and circulate among
                    the members a letter to the appropriate officer presenting the strong case for
                    accelerated publication of these important and timely papers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dillard pointed out that when he was a law student in the 1920’s the gap
                    between events and publication was about nine years. Now it had reached
                    twenty-three, and that was too much. He asked if P/HO had received enough
                    support for budget and manpower from the Committee. What practical measures
                    could the Committee take to help speed up this schedule?</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling commented that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had
                    obviously been given a low priority for many years, and the results were not
                    satisfactory. As a university president he knew that all projects had to compete
                    for funds, and clearly you could not do everything at the same time. On the
                    other hand, a careful administrator knew that various activities had to take
                    turns. One year the law school got the money, and maybe next year the library or
                    the physics department. The whole operation had to be kept in balance. It seemed
                    to him that it was the turn of the Historical Office to get the necessary
                    support.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt noted that for years the American Historical Association and other
                    learned societies had been passing resolutions pointing to the real needs of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and calling for additional public
                    support. Had these done any good? Mr. Dougall expressed the view that without
                    these resolutions the situation would have been worse.</p>
                <p>Mr. Metzger asked about the possible use of Foundation funds to provide interns,
                    and there was general discussion of the legal and recruiting problems involved.
                    The idea was once more being explored, but it was agreed that an intern was no
                    adequate substitute for a fully-trained permanent member of the staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sterling expressed a feeling of helplessness that he had felt before as a
                    member of advisory committees. He did not have precise knowledge of the
                    budgetary and appropriations situation. It always came down to the crunch with
                    the dollar sign on it. He felt that the Committee was at a disadvantage because
                    it did not know the exact financial situation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holt then asked if crash programs interfered with the regular output of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Franklin explained that most of
                    the work done for the White House, the Secretary, and other high officials
                    (referred to by Mr. Phillips in his opening remarks) was done by the Historical
                    Studies Division, headed by Mr. Costrell. As a rule the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> staff was not called on for this work. Mr. Stewart
                    thought that a summary chart of the Historical Office organization and duties
                    might assist the Committee in its attempt to draft recommendations for
                    additional staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall cautioned that the Department did not wish to ask for any more “job
                    slots”. The Department would expect instead that additional jobs for the
                    Historical Office would be found elsewhere in the Bureau of Public Affairs. The
                    Bureau in turn would ask that additional jobs for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> be taken out of the Historical Studies Division.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dillard cited programs of the Defense Department to allow various specialists
                    to meet their military obligations by working in their particular fields; could
                    we find some historians in this way? Mr. Plischke thought the same thing might
                    apply to young Foreign Service Officers before going overseas.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart brought up the earlier suggestion by Mr. Phillips that the names of
                    the members of the Committee be listed in the preface of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Mr. Franklin noted that this practice had
                    been followed in the military-history volumes and in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Documents on German Foreign Policy</hi>. After some discussion the
                    Committee agreed that it would be difficult to know which names to print in the
                    front of any given volume, in view of the changing membership. They were willing
                    to consider the matter further, if P/HO felt that it would help the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stewart expressed the Committee’s appreciation for the lively and interesting
                    session with the members of the Historical Office. It was agreed that the
                    Committee would adjourn to attend a briefing by Secretary Rusk and would then
                    return for a private meeting. The meeting adjourned at 4:10 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
