<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1968</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1968</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-21">April 21, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1968-11-01">November 1, 1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1968-11-01-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 394 KB, 15pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1968—Minutes. Limited Official Use. Page 2
                    of the minutes is missing from the record copy. Attached charts are not
                    posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn55">Footnote 55</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Record of the 1968 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 1, 1968</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Inis L. Claude, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs,
                                University of Virginia (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Hardy C. Dillard, Dean of the School of Law, University of
                                Virginia (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>W. Stull Holt, Professor of History, University of Washington
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Ernest R. May, Professor of History, Harvard University (American
                                Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Stanley D. Metzger (Chairman), Chairman, United States Tariff
                                Commission and Professor of Law, Georgetown University (American
                                Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Elmer Plischke, Professor of Government and Politics, University
                                of Maryland (American Political Science Association)</item>
                            <item>J. E. Wallace Sterling (Absent), Chancellor of Stanford University
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Paul L. Ward (substituting for Dr. Sterling), Executive Secretary,
                                American Historical Association</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Dixon Donnelley, Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>Velma H. Cassidy</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Marvin W. Kranz</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Publishing and Reproduction Services Division, Office of Operations:<list>
                            <item>Peter A. Smith, Chief, Editorial Services Branch</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Page 2 is missing from the record copy.</hi>]</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> expressed the grave concern felt by historians
                    at the slowness of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> publication
                    program. The further the series fell behind currency, the more slowly were files
                    of the Department opened for access to the scholars. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Holt</hi> raised the question whether restrictions on access to files by
                    “outside” researchers were based on substantive grounds or on procedural delays
                    in the publication process. He thought that the latter should not be allowed to
                    determine the time of access. Why could not access be granted in accordance with
                    the original intent of the 20-year rule, regardless of the lag in the editing
                    and publishing of the volumes?</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> also suggested that if clearance could take
                    place at the manuscript stage rather than the galley, the declassified documents
                    could thereby be made available to outside researchers much earlier. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that much declassification of
                    documents could be effected even sooner than 20 years if the necessary manpower
                    were available. But in the absence of such resources, it was only with the
                    printing and circulation of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> galleys
                    that top-level papers could be brought up for declassification by policy
                    officers in an organized and wholesale fashion. The whole process could be
                    speeded up if <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> published the documents
                    in raw facsimile, but this was impracticable because of the large number that
                    would be illegible or incomprehensible without editorial treatment. As it was,
                    the Department’s policy officers were so busy with their regular work that they
                    could hardly find time to clear printed galleys that were clear and compact. It
                    would be hopeless to attempt any earlier clearance of facsimiles in any large
                    quantities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> asked if technical innovations in compiling
                    procedures might not significantly save time in preparing <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> and
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied that computerized document
                    retrieval had no possible application soon to the work of the series. One
                    technological improvement had been utilized, however. The use of microfilm
                    blowups in place of typed manuscript had considerably increased the speed and
                    accuracy of compiling and editing of the volumes. In connection with the
                    discussion of microfilming, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> observed the
                    possible usefulness to scholars of routing indications on documents and asked if
                    these might be somehow recorded in texts printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> replied that routing
                    indicators of real consequence on source texts are frequently noted in
                    annotations in the volumes. He pointed out that the exact routing of a document
                    was often unknown.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> wondered whether it might be possible to
                    publish certain volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> more rapidly
                    than others. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied by pointing out the
                    serious consequences of issuing volumes very far out of chronology.</p>
                <p>THE COLD WAR AND <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN RELATIONS</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> pointed out the timely relevance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to the current debate on international
                    relations, particularly in light of the revisionist trends in the study of the
                    Cold War, and their impact on college students. He noted that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume for 1945 that he had recently
                    read made it brilliantly clear who started the Cold War.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> agreed. He indicated his concern about the
                    growing criticism by alienated younger scholars to the effect that the United
                    States was just as bad as Russia. Certainly history had a fundamental role to
                    play in this situation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> said that he had hoped very much last year
                    that this argument could help to speed up the series. It had indeed been
                    mentioned in the Committee’s report, but the Department had not responded with
                    any real assistance. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> felt that this had
                    not been emphasized enough, and that the Department of State had shown a very
                    short-sighted attitude in this regard. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> asked
                    if a resolution of the American Historical Association would help. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> said he would hope so, but that the “New
                    Left” would always feel that we had left the meat out of our volumes, if they
                    read them at all.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> said that our concern should be not so much
                    with the “New Left” itself as with the other scholars who while awaiting the
                    record, have tended to acquiesce in their views. The Department of State should
                    provide the official record as a basis for better understanding of the
                    situation. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> said that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> was an opinion-molder, and the Department needed to
                    see this. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> agreed, pointing out that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> showed the actual choices and
                    alternative policies open to the United States in response to immediate
                    situations; this put the whole thing on a plane of reality. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Dillard</hi> thought that Secretary Rusk might have made too much of
                    the analogy to Munich, but that one needed a feel for documents to put world
                    developments into some kind of perspective. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Metzger</hi> added that the postwar German and Polish stories were quite
                    crucial to an understanding of the Cold War. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> said that the records show how we leaned over backwards in 1945
                    to make every possible concession to the Soviets to demonstrate our good faith
                    in seeking peaceful solutions in Europe. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi>
                    thought that it would be very helpful if we could compile and publish “a year in
                    a year” as an earnest of the Department’s intention to further this kind of
                    debate on the early years of the Cold War. It was very important that our
                    position was not reaching the public. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi>
                    noted the relevancy of our stories on Czechoslovakia in 1945 and 1948 to the
                    recent crisis in that country. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> said that
                    our 1948 volume would have an enormous impact if it were out now. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that this was an excellent example
                    of the benefits of the 20-year rule, if only we could make it stick.
                    Unfortunately the top officers of the Department had not so far seen it that
                    way.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> noted that target dates also affected our
                    own morale and output. The long delay between completion of a manuscript and
                    final publication could be quite disheartening. The whole assembly line for
                    these volumes would move faster if HO actually had a firm schedule and could do
                    a year in a year. Short of that, everything sagged all along the line.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM II: PROBLEMS OF EDITING</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Smith</hi> reviewed the work of the Publishing and
                    Reproduction Services Division. He was particularly pleased to report to the
                    Committee that 9322 pages of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had been
                    published in fiscal year 1968, a record output. He advised the Committee that a
                    new outside contractor, Crowell Collier Educational Corporation, a subsidiary of
                    Crowell Collier Macmillan, Inc., was replacing the World Publishing Company as
                    technical editor of the series. He admitted a severe contraction of the
                    Department’s “in-house” capability, but he asserted it would suffice to maintain
                    quality control. In this regard, he laid great stress on silent reading by
                    senior editors. He explained that scheduling was of the essence in dealing with
                    outside contractors, and he noted that the four volumes of 1946 languishing in
                    clearance were injuring his schedule. He said also that if the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> staff would compile a year in a year, such
                    scheduling would be facilitated. He pledged that technical editing would keep up
                    with HO compiling. His aim, through outside contracting, was to have a volume of
                    manuscript readied for galleys in 45 working days and an index in one month,
                    both far shorter than had previously been the case.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> commented that <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Smith’s</hi> picture was far too optimistic. He cited the example of the
                    Washington-Casablanca volume which had been grossly mishandled and delayed by
                    the Government Printing Office. He explained that although outside contractors
                    might finish an index in a month or two, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff had spent much time reviewing and correcting their
                    work. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Smith</hi> admitted that this was true but he
                    felt that the picture was improving.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> raised the question of annual contracts vs.
                    multiyear contracts, pointing out that some of the risk involved in contract
                    editing with private firms might be eliminated or reduced if these firms were
                    obliged to undertake a contract covering several years. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Smith</hi> explained that PBR was not authorized to make contracts exceeding
                    one year, but <hi rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> urged that the Department
                    should obtain such authorization.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Slany</hi> urged the Committee to consider accepting a
                    more simplified index for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in place of
                    the detailed analytical index which had been traditional with the series and
                    which required four to six months to prepare. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> noted that other major publications of official documents
                    seemed to get by with very poor and thin indexes. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Ward</hi> stressed the value of the good <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> indexes, and it was the consensus of the Committee that there
                    should be no lowering of the standards. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi>
                    noted that one of the recent indexes, despite its length and quality, did not
                    carry all significant entries under important names, such as John McCloy.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM III: CLEARANCE DIFFICULTIES AND PROSPECTS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> told the Committee that there had been a
                    slight trend in the direction of more rapid Departmental clearance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. In the cases of some volumes,
                    clearance had been completed in less than six months. There remained, however,
                    those annoying cases at the other extreme; a 1945 volume had been in the
                    clearance process for 23 months. Some of the more rapid Departmental clearances
                    must be attributed to a new procedure inaugurated during the past year. With the
                    help of the Executive Director of the Bureau, it had been possible to have
                    several upper-grade Foreign Service Officers who were temporarily available
                    assigned the task of assisting the policy bureaus in reviewing <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> galleys. These Foreign Service Officers had
                    performed their tasks most expeditiously, and <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> hoped that more such officers would be available in the future.
                    Clearance of galleys in the Department of Defense remained slow -- averaging
                    over a year in time. In answer to a question, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> explained that the galleys were reviewed by all the military
                    services, but that the major clearance hurdle was the Historical Division of the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff, a small and heavily burdened group. But their review was
                    meticulous and often provided additional information. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> felt that the few suggested improvements failed to outweigh the
                    long delay in clearance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> protested that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series was after all a responsibility of the Department of
                    State, and it was the Department’s policies and negotiations which formed the
                    core of the documentation in the volumes. Perfection in nuance by other agencies
                    ought to be resisted when it involved long delay in publication.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> at this point offered two suggestions to
                    speed internal clearance: (1) To extend from the current three months to six
                    months the amount of time desk officers would be allowed to clear a volume; if
                    there was no reaction from the desks by that time, <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> would proceed with publication after making such deletions as
                    appeared necessary. (2) Clearance at the desks should only be handled by
                    officers of Class III and higher. These are the experienced officers, with a
                    broader view of the subject, who would not raise the inconsequential objections
                    frequently now made by lower ranking officers with less experience and
                    authority.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> opined that clearance difficulties would
                    mount in the years ahead, for the following reasons: (1) We had made successful
                    use of the flood of good wartime memoirs to rebut objections, but the number of
                    good memoirs was much lower for the postwar period; (2) Many emergent postwar
                    problems, such as the acquisition of overseas military bases, were still very
                    much alive today; (3) We were “fighting the antibiotics” in that many persons of
                    prominence in the immediate postwar years were still in the political limelight;
                    (4) The United States in the postwar years was in the center of the diplomatic
                    history of the world; responsibilities and commitments made for clearance
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> thought that the real need was to get the
                    documents published as an aid to our political posture, and he thought that
                    there had been too much parochial thinking on the part of clearance officers in
                    the Department. Somehow the notion must get to them that these papers
                    represented a positive contribution and were important in their own right. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> observed that we must use the
                    countervailing force of the public interest in getting the documents out. In
                    many cases <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was but reinforcing known
                    material rather than offering new data, but this was a valuable and defensible
                    contribution too. <hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> added that ninety percent of
                    the real information about the postwar world had already appeared in the news
                    papers, and that there was not much real revelation in the documents. The prime
                    value of the series was systematic documentation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> thought that the 25-year gap might be reduced
                    by narrowing the coverage of the series, and he particularly objected to the
                    long delay in publishing volumes after they had been cleared. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> pointed out that we had already done much
                    to tighten the selections in the volumes for 1947 and 1948. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Ward</hi> said that he was much encouraged, for he felt that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would have a much greater impact if it
                    were more selective. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> proposed raising the
                    level of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> documentation and restricting
                    the record largely to the ultimate policies and decisions and the immediate
                    factors leading thereto. Lower-level documentation would be omitted. In this way
                    it might be possible to concentrate the annual record into three or four
                    volumes. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Metzger</hi> stressed that American
                    motivations and the assessment thereof were the really important factors to be
                    documented.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> felt that no substantial improvement in
                    the clearance matter could be engineered at the working level and that real
                    gains could come only through strong support from the top officers of the
                    Department. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> said that this was a familiar
                    syndrome both in government and in the foundations; there was a certain apathy
                    about historical and scholarly projects, and we had somehow to strike a positive
                    note and convince the policy-makers that this was not some purely antiquarian
                    operation.</p>
                <p>At 12:10 p.m. the Committee adjourned for lunch with the Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>Afternoon Session</p>
                <p>When the Committee resumed its session after lunch Dr. Franklin served as Acting
                    Chairman, since Dr. Metzger had had to leave for a hearing involving the Tariff
                    Commission.</p>
                <p>THE PROBLEM OF PARAPHRASING</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    described to the Committee the problem that had arisen regarding cryptography.
                    The Department of Defense had insisted that certain telegraphic messages,
                    beginning in February 1946, had to be paraphrased, since otherwise there was the
                    possibility that other, classified messages sent in the same codes on the same
                    day might be decyphered by any foreign power that had taped and retained all
                    such encrypted texts.</p>
                <p>The position of the Department of Defense has had the effect of halting the
                    processing of four <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for 1946
                    already otherwise cleared and ready for conversion from galley to page proof.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Aandahl</hi> estimated that as many as 1000 pages
                    of material in the 1946 sequence of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    would have to be paraphrased in order to conform to the injunction. The fact
                    that most of the messages in question were in substance State Department
                    telegrams rather than military cables had no bearing on the matter. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Slany</hi> noted that the problem appeared to diminish
                    for the period after October 1946, since few telegrams after that date, either
                    State Department or military, bore any injunction requiring paraphrasing. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that the Historical Office had
                    sought to obtain a waiver of the paraphrase requirement on these telegrams. The
                    National Security Agency was inclined to grant the waiver on the ground that the
                    risk of decyphering the still-classified texts was minimal, but the Defense
                    Intelligence Agency and the Central Intelligence Agency insisted that we observe
                    the paraphrasing requirement. Their decision was based on the fact that in a
                    sampling of 63 messages they had discovered one reference to a covert
                    source.</p>
                <p>The Committee asked what it might do to support the Historical Office in this
                    problem. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed that none of us could
                    argue the cryptographic angle of the matter, but that the Committee could help
                    by expressing its strong preference for the publication of true texts rather
                    than paraphrases in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. In this connection
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> pointed to the sometimes significant
                    differences between the English-language texts of Roosevelt-Stalin
                    correspondence published by Soviet authorities and those published in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. The difference arose from the fact
                    that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> printed Roosevelt messages as
                    cabled to Moscow. The Soviet publication presents those messages as delivered to
                    Stalin in paraphrase.</p>
                <p>In answer to inquiries from the Committee, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    indicated that he would appeal the decision through higher officers. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> noted that it would help if we only had to
                    paraphrase the opening and closing sentences. The complete paraphrasing of all
                    of the messages involved would require the full time of one historian for
                    several months. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> urged the Historical Office
                    to confirm that the protected system was no longer significantly used after 1946
                    in order to strengthen the argument that very little pertinent data in still
                    classified messages would be affected even theoretically.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM V: <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN RELATIONS</hi> AND ACCESS TO THE
                    FILES</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that he had put this subject on the
                    agenda because access was tied to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and
                    he knew that the Committee was concerned with this whole situation. For this
                    reason he had asked Dr. Kogan to attend.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> briefly summarized the Department’s policy
                    regarding access to official records. Documents 30 years and older are in the
                    “open” period, which is advanced automatically each year. At present the “open”
                    period extends through 1938. Documents in this period are maintained at the
                    National Archives in Washington and can be consulted by anyone -- even citizens
                    of foreign countries. This category does not, however, include papers involving
                    such matters as personnel, security investigations, intelligence reports, and
                    visa and passport applications. Nor does it include those papers denied
                    clearance for publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> by the
                    Department, other government agencies, or foreign governments. The interval
                    between the “open” period and the last year covered by <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is the “restricted” period, at present 1938 through 1944 and
                    into 1945 for those subjects documented in the volumes of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> for 1945 that are already published. Records for
                    this “restricted” period are available to qualified researchers upon approval of
                    their application and subject to the review of their notes. Non-American
                    citizens are not allowed access to documents in the “restricted” period because
                    of the classification problem. Topics for research in the “restricted” period
                    must be approved by the appropriate policy offices of the Department. Topics for
                    research are rarely disallowed. The Department’s Central Files for the period
                    through 1944 are in the National Archives Building or in the Federal Records
                    Center at Suitland, Maryland, and servicing of those records is conducted by the
                    National Archives under the general control of the Department. Notes by
                    researchers working the “restricted” period are reviewed by the Historical
                    Office, in consultation with Department policy officers on possibly sensitive
                    questions.</p>
                <p>Department Central File documents for the period 1945 and later continue to be
                    housed in the Department of State Building, and this poses a problem. Requests
                    for documents of 1945 must be serviced by the Records Services Division under
                    the general supervision of the Historical Office. Facilities for private
                    researchers are very limited, and they are located in the midst of the
                    Department’s current records operation, thus posing a security problem. Only
                    part-time assistance from RS personnel is available. All these circumstances
                    combine to make access to the post-1944 records more awkward and time-consuming
                    than for earlier years. This situation is compounded by the growing number of
                    so-called “lot files”.</p>
                <p>LOT FILES</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> briefly described the “lot files” of the
                    Department. Until the period of the Second World War, the system of document
                    management within the Department assured that all documents of record were
                    eventually included in the indexed Central Files. Under the impact of the war,
                    this system had broken down; records retired from various offices and bureaus
                    were kept together and labeled as a “lot” from that particular administrative
                    area. The individual papers were not indexed and put into the Central Files, but
                    were left in the original boxes where they still are today. This “system” was no
                    system at all; it maintained a generally meaningless “archival provenance” which
                    was of no help to the historian, who would have to go through these boxes paper
                    by paper to find the “nuggets”.</p>
                <p>The practice of accumulating unindexed “lot files” proliferated and goes on to
                    the present day without sign of abatement. There are now thousands of separate
                    “lot files”, stored in the Department or in the Federal Records Center at
                    Suitland. The limited manpower available to the Division of the Records Services
                    could only perform a most limited program of screening these messy files for
                    duplicative and useless papers.</p>
                <p>In answer to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed that the National Archives has
                    refused to accept or service these files because of the absence of indexes and
                    the unscreened nature of these aggregations of paper. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Kranz</hi> emphasized the incredibly chaotic state of the “lot files” and
                    the fact that some very unlikely collections had yielded important
                    documentation. Therefore they could not be ignored by any scholar. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> recalled that “lot files” had first been
                    used extensively in the Yalta volume, where they are indicated by special
                    headnotes rather than index numbers. In the Department’s central files there had
                    been but a handful of documents on the Yalta Conference, and the great bulk of
                    Conference papers had to be ferreted out of other “lot files”. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> observed that he had found certain Italian
                    surrender documents in an unlikely “lot file” after a sleuthing operation that
                    began with the Central Files and led through various other “lot files”.</p>
                <p>In response to an inquiry from the Committee, it was pointed out that files of
                    overseas missions were periodically retired to Washington, and they too were
                    maintained at the Federal Records Center at Suitland. These post files were also
                    a type of “lot file”, and they were important sources for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>ACCESS TO THE FILES (Continued)</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> observed that the use of “lot files” by
                    private researchers involved time-consuming complexities not encountered in the
                    use of the indexed Central Files. Lacking indexes or adequate finding aids, the
                    “lot files” must usually be subjected to a careful paper-by-paper examination.
                    Dr. Kogan explained that part of the enduring value of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> lay in its trailblazing through these “lot files”,
                    identifying those of particular value and use to outside scholars. The files are
                    usually not internally organized on a chronological basis and often contain many
                    papers originating with foreign governments, and other U. S. government agencies
                    -- papers that cannot be made available to researchers. This means that more
                    trust has to be put in the researcher to take notes only on what he is cleared
                    for, by subject and chronology. There is no adequate research area for work on
                    “lot files” either in the Department or in the Federal Records Center.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> pointed out that his ever increasing
                    responsibilities were complicated by the steady growth in the number of persons
                    requesting access to the Department’s records. In order to render effective
                    assistance to “outside” scholars it will be necessary to limit the categories of
                    persons admitted. Some years ago it had been decided not to admit undergraduates
                    to the files; now the question was whether we could continue to admit M.A.
                    candidates, most of whom were certainly not very mature scholars. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> asked how many persons annually applied
                    for access to the files. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> supplied some
                    tentative figures with respect to the number of people applying and the
                    proportion of advanced scholars as compared to graduate students and other users
                    of records such as writers and journalists. He emphasized that without checking
                    the files of the Historical Office he could only give estimates. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> indicated that the Committee would be
                    provided with detailed information later on. [In recent years the number of
                    persons applying for access to records was in the neighborhood of 450 each
                    year.]</p>
                <p>Dr. Kogan concluded that the difficulties involved in administering the
                    Department’s access program for the post-1944 period might necessitate some
                    limitations on who might be admitted. Access might have to be limited to mature
                    and responsible scholars. In practice this would mean that access would be
                    restricted to Ph.D. candidates or other researchers exhibiting maturity and
                    responsibility. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> said that he had received
                    angry comments from Professors Philip Crowl (Nebraska) and Walter Johnson
                    (Hawaii) about the Department’s refusal to let Johnson have access to the
                    “Stevenson Papers”. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied that Prof.
                    Johnson was told that he could obtain access to the records in the restricted
                    period on exactly the same basis as all other scholars; he wanted to make it
                    clear that there had been no discrimination against Dr. Johnson. On the other
                    hand it was worth recalling that Dr. Johnson had been the lucky recipient of
                    treasure-troves of official papers in the private possession of Stettinius and
                    Grew. What Johnson wanted was for the Department to let him “back up a truck”
                    (as he had said at Dallas) and remove “Stevenson’s Papers” which Adlai would
                    have done if he had lived. But times had changed since the passage of the
                    Federal Records Act of 1950, which had resulted from the wholesale removals of
                    official papers by Morgenthau and Stettinius. In fact Dr. Johnson has (from
                    Adlai’s son) all the papers that were truly Stevenson’s; what he calls
                    “Stevenson Papers” in the Department ate the official papers of the Department
                    reflecting the activities of Adlai Stevenson. It was really not too difficult to
                    distinguish private from official papers, and with regard to the latter he saw
                    no reason why an exception to the rules should be made for Professor
                    Johnson.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> expressed the view that Walter Johnson’s
                    remark at Dallas (about “backing up a truck and removing your papers”) had been
                    intended as a description of what actually happened, not an endorsement of the
                    practice. Dr. Franklin said that this practice had been diminishing since the
                    Federal Records Act and with more modern security controls. He mentioned that
                    Secretary Rusk had been shocked to learn of the wholesale removals by Stettinius
                    and that the Secretary had declared that his papers would remain in the
                    Department “where they belonged”.</p>
                <p>Dr. May observed that many government officials are able to leave the government
                    with their official files intact through the expedient of donating such papers
                    to a Presidential library, which takes care of the security angle. Various
                    members of the Committee noted that the control over such papers remained in
                    official hands, through the Archivist. It was noted also that the Presidents
                    themselves can (and do) retain any of their own papers that they may not wish to
                    turn over to their Libraries. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out
                    that Secretary Dulles had had no difficulty in distinguishing between his
                    private and official papers; he had clearly specified that the microfilms of his
                    official papers at Princeton should be controlled by the Department’s
                    regulations on access.</p>
                <p>CLEARANCE AND ACCESS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> summarized the many delays in the preparation
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He pointed out that there
                    was a period averaging two years in length per volume after clearances had been
                    secured for galleys and the final release of volumes. He proposed that access be
                    granted to the material as soon as it was cleared. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        May</hi> supported this proposal. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    pointed out that unfortunately the Historical Office could never be sure of when
                    a volume would be released; some had been stopped or altered in various ways at
                    the last minute. It would be a serious risk for the Historical Office to admit
                    anyone to the files before the volumes were actually published. It was noted
                    that the release of the special <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    sub-series dealing with China had been interrupted by order of Secretary Dulles
                    after several volumes had been published. Reference was also made to other
                    examples through the years. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out
                    that publication of the volumes put the documents in the public domain and
                    constituted an open announcement of areas now open for access; did the Committee
                    want to abandon this equitable system in favor of one that would give an
                    advantage to the scholars who happened to ask for something at the right
                    moment?</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> suggested that scholars could be given access
                    to the files for which galley clearances had been obtained, but their notes
                    would be withheld until the date of release of the pertinent <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. In answer to a question as to how the
                    academic community would know about the status of clearances, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> suggested that a notification could be issued
                    semi-annually by the Historical Office indicating those portions of the files
                    newly added to the “restricted period” as a result of galley clearance. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> pointed out the administrative difficulties
                    of dealing with such an irregular system. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi>
                    emphasized that clearance granted at the galley stage was only preliminary and
                    that formal clearance occurred only at the actual time of release of volumes.
                    The real “green light” came at that final moment when the imminent publication
                    of a volume was announced and no dissenting voice was raised in the Department.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> asked if it would be appropriate for the
                    Committee to recommend that the Historical Office seek formal authorization to
                    publish materials at the time of galley clearance, thus changing preliminary
                    clearance into final clearance and allowing the advance of the “restricted
                    period”. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> agreed that the Committee could
                    make such a recommendation, but he suggested that the Committee should indicate
                    that its first preference would be to accelerate clearance, publication, and
                    access rather than to change the current access rules.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> saw little prospect for any acceleration in
                    the clearance of documents. He regarded the delays, often as long as two years,
                    as “indefensible”. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> regarded the clearance
                    difficulties as the direct result of “blatant bureaucratic inertia” of the worst
                    sort. He thought the Committee should recommend that a time limit of three or
                    perhaps six months should be set for clearance after which time the Historical
                    Office would feel free to assume there were no objections to publication and the
                    preparation of the volumes could proceed. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    reminded the Committee that he had prepared a statement along these lines that
                    was sent to Department officers along with galleys for clearance. This notice,
                    at the Assistant Secretary level, stressed a three-month deadline on clearance,
                    but the Historical Office had never dared to enforce it. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Gleason</hi> proposed that clearing officers be given a six-month
                    deadline, after which the volume would proceed to publication. In answer to a
                    question from the Committee, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> said that
                    suggestions for deletions were never made by the Historical Office to clearing
                    officers. Such a procedure would merely invite deletions -- whether necessary or
                    not.</p>
                <p>PROPOSED STAFF INCREASE</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Ward</hi> referred to previous recommendations for staff
                    increases and asked if the addition of two historians to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> staff would be sufficient to accelerate the
                    publishing program significantly. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said
                    that we would have to see. The addition of even two good historians could make
                    quite a difference in everyone’s morale. The Committee had initially recommended
                    six additional positions, but this was unrealistic in view of the budgetary
                    situation in recent years. Former Assistant Secretary Manning had actually asked
                    for three additional historians, but this request had not gotten past the budget
                    office in the Department. In answer to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Dillard</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that additional
                    personnel at the compiling stage was the most important item of all. A faster
                    rate of compilation would set in train a faster flow throughout all steps in the
                    preparations of volumes. A faster preparation of manuscripts would generate
                    persuasive pressure for speedier editing, indexing, clearing, and publishing. If
                    the Historical Office could actually compile a year in a year then the whole
                    assembly line would suddenly acquire a goal and a schedule.</p>
                <p>COVERAGE FOR 1947-1948</p>
                <p>At the end of the meeting, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> asked members of
                    the Committee to examine the tables of contents of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes for 1947-1948 (copies of which had been given to the
                    Committee) and to indicate whether they were in agreement with the coverage
                    proposed for those years.</p>
                <p rend="center">*****</p>
                <p>The open meeting ended at about 5 p.m. and the Committee continued in private
                    session for another half hour.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
