<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1969</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1969</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-04-21">April 21, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1969-11-07">November 7, 1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1969-11-07-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 448 KB, 17pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1969—Minutes. Limited Official Use.
                    Attachments 2-4 are present, but not posted.</hi></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="minutes">
                <head>Record of the 1969 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 7, 1969</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Inis L. Claude, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs,
                                University of Virginia (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>David R. Deener, Provost and Dean of the Graduate School, Tulane
                                University (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Hardy C. Dillard, Professor of Law, University of Virginia
                                (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>W. Stull Holt, Professor of History, University of Washington
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Ernest R. May, Dean of Harvard College (American Historical
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Elmer Plischke, Professor of Government and Politics, University
                                of Maryland (American Political Science Association)</item>
                            <item>Paul A. Varg, Dean of the College of Arts and Letters, Michigan
                                State University (American Historical Association)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Richard I. Phillips, Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Public Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Opening Session - 9:15 am. - 12:15 p.m.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM I: OPENING REMARKS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Acting Assistant Secretary Phillips</hi> presented brief
                    welcoming remarks, expressing the appreciation of the Department for the work of
                    the Committee.</p>
                <p>Following the departure of Mr. Phillips, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    explained that Secretary Rogers had gone with the President to Key Biscayne and
                    so would be unavailable for luncheon with the Committee. However, the Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs, U. Alexis Johnson, would be joining
                    the Committee for luncheon at 12:30 p.m.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM II: ELECTION OF CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>By acclamation, the Advisory Committee selected Dr. Elmer Plischke to serve as
                    its Chairman.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM III: STATUS OF THE SERIES AND PUBLICATION</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> presented a report on the current position
                    of the Series [see Attachment 1].</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that during the past year, two
                    additional job slots had been obtained for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Division, one from the Bureau and one from elsewhere in the
                    Historical Office. This had necessitated the curtailment of <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Foreign Policy: Current Documents</hi>. The good effect of the two
                    additional jobs, however, had been offset this year by retirements from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> described the difficulties involved in
                    recruiting personnel for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> on the open
                    market. The efforts of the Department to reduce the size of the Foreign Service
                    abroad was resulting in attempts to place surplus Foreign Service officers in
                    domestic vacancies, such as those in the Historical Office. The Department was
                    reluctant to admit that it had no FSOs qualified for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> positions. Actually the lack of graduate training in history
                    of most FSOs placed limitations upon the extent to which they could contribute,
                    although certain FSOs had performed outstandingly on a short-term basis in the
                    Historical Studies Division of the Office.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> asked how the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series could assure satisfactory coverage of materials in
                    view of the continuing growth of existing documentation and the stated objective
                    of reducing both the number of volumes and the size of each volume in
                    forthcoming years. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> stated that he did not
                    believe that reduction of the amount of documentation published would result in
                    the omission of important papers. Cuts were being made at the expense of
                    marginal material. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> then expressed
                    apprehension regarding a policy of limiting the number and size of volumes in
                    advance of determining what subjects would have to be treated. He feared that if
                    seven 1000-page volumes became the fixed limit, it might prove difficult to
                    expand coverage should the subject matter demand it. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> gave assurances that if more volumes were needed to cover
                    topics adequately, they would be forthcoming as required.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>, in response to a question, observed that
                    there had been no problem since the early 1950’s in obtaining adequate funds for
                    printing and binding. The problem lay in getting more staff for compilation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> reviewed the personnel situation and asked
                    whether it would be appropriate for the Committee’s report to urge that the
                    Historical Office he allowed to fill vacant slots. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> stated that the Committee could properly make such a
                    recommendation, with emphasis on the fact that the candidates must be
                    qualified.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> wondered if job slots “were truly ordained
                    by God”, or if they could not be altered on the basis of demonstrated need and
                    sound arguments. He also raised the possibility of hiring qualified Ph.D.
                    candidates on a part-time basis. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> noted
                    that the Historical Office had recently interviewed several well-qualified
                    candidates for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> positions but that HO
                    had not been able even to initiate the six-month security clearance
                    procedure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> emphasized that the Committee must seek to
                    convince the Department that the Historical Office must have outside recruiting
                    authority. He asked if Government salaries were competitive. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied that they were, at least at the
                    GS-11 level where HO sought to recruit young Ph.Ds. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> cited the added inducement of civil service fringe
                    benefits.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> wondered if the Committee might not make the
                    point that the need to publish <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> promptly
                    was such that it must take precedence over the Department’s desire to use the
                    Historical Office as a place of assignment for surplus Foreign Service officers.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> added that the recent emergence of the
                    revisionist interpretation of the cold war presented an additional reason for
                    providing the public with <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> documentation
                    as soon as possible. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> thought that the
                    Committee should bear down hard on the necessity for recruiting top people with
                    a career interest in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He cited the
                    critical importance of each job slot in view of the small size of the staff. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> inquired as to the exact pay scale. [The
                    Committee was subsequently informed that the starting salary of a GS-11 is now
                    $11,233].</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> stated that it was important that
                    vacancies be filled rapidly. He asked how long it took the Department to fill HO
                    vacancies from within the FSO structure. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi>
                    replied that HO had submitted a request two months ago, but there had been no
                    action to date.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> turned to discussion of the acceptance of
                    the relevance of history within the Department and in society as a whole. He
                    sensed from his own experience in dealing with foundations that a profoundly
                    anti-historical and future-minded spirit was abroad in the land. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> expressed agreement, citing the
                    Department’s pragmatic attitude toward history. History was seldom recognized as
                    vital unless the Senate Foreign Relations Committee requested background on a
                    specific topic such as Vietnam or Laos. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    pointed out that the Historical Studies Division of the Office was engaged in
                    responding to such requests on a full-time basis, but this did not help <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> asked if it might be possible to obtain
                    additional researchers for Historical Studies and then transfer them to <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> work. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Dougall</hi> stated that at present it was no easier to procure additional
                    staff for Historical Studies than for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> observed that neither outsiders nor the
                    Department itself fully appreciated the value of historical research within the
                    Department on recent issues. He thought that it would be helpful if the period
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compilation, if not publication,
                    could be moved forward so that the Department would have documentary studies
                    upon which to draw when confronted with questions of urgent, immediate interest.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> mentioned the British Foreign Office
                    procedure of preparing such documentary collections for internal use.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> noted with dismay that even if the current
                    publication schedule were maintained, the series would be 25 years behind
                    currency before the 1946 volumes were all out. <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> seemed to be acquiescing in a 25-year lag. He urged that the
                    report of the Committee include a recommendation that the gap be reduced to 15
                    years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> thought that “acquiesce” wasn’t the right
                    word. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was fighting the problem day in
                    and day out. He also felt that the advocacy of a 15-year lag was tactically
                    unwise since it was sufficiently divorced from reality to be disregarded. He
                    believed it would be sounder tactics for the Committee to deplore the slip from
                    the authorized 20-year line.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> reminded the Committee of the statement
                    drafted by Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and issued by President Kennedy calling for
                    a l5-year publication lag. Rather than promoting easier clearance, this
                    statement only served to terrify Department officers. It was never carried into
                    effect.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> reiterated his belief that the proposal for a
                    15-year target would have beneficial shock value. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> pointed out that we were actually in danger of losing the
                    25-year line. An alternative strategy for “shocking” the Department consisted of
                    pointing out that a 3O-year lag would soon be reached unless clearance
                    procedures were speeded up. Since the records were opened to all researchers
                    after 30 years, this prospect had very serious implications for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> contended that the Committee should deplore
                    the slippage to the 25-year line. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> said that
                    the Committee could speak of both the 15 and 3O-year factors. He was convinced
                    that the ideal of the 15-year lag should at least be mentioned in the
                    Committee’s report.</p>
                <p>[The Committee recessed briefly for coffee.]</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> presented the suggestion that the Historical
                    Office regularly prepare a prospectus for circulation in the scholarly community
                    which would outline the contents of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes scheduled for imminent publication. He suggested that this type of
                    announcement would whet the appetite of outside scholars and might help to build
                    up pressure for earlier publication of the volumes. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Dillard</hi> agreed with Dr. Deener’s suggestion, mentioning the problems
                    faced by the reviewers of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in
                    attempting to define the most significant material therein.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out that until recently the
                    issuance of each volume had been accompanied by a press release summarizing the
                    contents. But because newsmen exploited this procedure to speculate on reasons
                    for publication at a particular time, tying the release to a current foreign
                    policy situation, the practice had been discontinued. Currently, the release of
                    each volume was simply announced at a regular noon briefing of newsmen conducted
                    by Mr. McCloskey, the Department’s spokesman. In general, the Historical Office
                    desired less rather than more press coverage since sensational or distorted news
                    items increased our subsequent clearance difficulties. On the other hand, book
                    reviews were always more than welcome. In answer to a question from Dr. Dillard,
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that 700 to 800 copies of
                    each <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume were given to depository
                    libraries and several hundred copies were bought and distributed by the
                    Department.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> noted that Dean Acheson’s recently published
                    book [<hi rend="italic">Present at the Creation: My Years in the State
                        Department</hi> (New York: Norton, 1969)] contained frequent references to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He wondered if this could
                    be turned to advantage.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> explained that his earlier proposal was not
                    related to press releases. What he had in mind was some sort of prospectus which
                    could possibly stir additional interest in the academic community. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> Division could not undertake the long-range planning
                    necessary to implement such a proposal. The current one-year plans consumed many
                    man-hours. Manpower was not available to develop any more elaborate plans or
                    prospectuses. <hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> suggested that HO prepare an
                    annual release to the journals of the three organizations represented on the
                    Committee, summarizing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    published during the year and outlining plans for future publication.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> summarized the discussion by stating that
                    the Committee suggested that HO build up support for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> by using scholarly publications to inform the academic
                    community of current developments. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> added
                    the suggestion that one-page summaries of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes be sent to the learned societies as a method of
                    “spreading the gospel.” Dr. Franklin expressed regret concerning the lack of
                    publicity given to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes by the
                    Superintendent of Documents. Much more advertising should be done by G.P.O.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> expressed dismay at the length of time between
                    the completion of clearance and actual publication. He asked if any progress had
                    been made in expediting the final stages of production. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> stated that there had not been notable progress. However,
                    Crowell-Collier was now working diligently and reasonably effectively on galley
                    proof. Indeed, they were maintaining pressure on the Historical Office to keep
                    them supplied with a steady flow of manuscript. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> added that the inordinate amount of time involved in the final
                    phases of publication was largely a factor of the excessive number of volumes
                    for 1945 (12) and 1946 (11). The reduction of the number of volumes for each
                    year would reduce the lead time. He was aiming at a lead time of three years
                    from compilation to publication. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> noted
                    that post-clearance operations, particularly indexing, had already been speeded
                    up somewhat. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that technical
                    editing was now largely contracted out by the Publishing and Reproduction
                    Services Division since funds were more readily available for this purpose than
                    for maintaining a staff. Personnel for technical editing had been reduced from
                    twelve to two in recent years. As a result, quality had fallen off a bit, but
                    speed had been increased.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> delivered a report on the status of the
                    wartime conference volumes. He reviewed the decision to separate documentation
                    on the Third Washington Conference (<hi rend="underline">Trident</hi>), 1943,
                    from that on the earlier Washington Conferences and the Casablanca Conference
                    because of clearance difficulties on a continuing problem involving a military
                    base. It was now contemplated that <hi rend="underline">Trident</hi> and the
                    First Quebec Conference, 1943, would be combined in a volume which would be
                    ready for final processing when EUR clearance was given. Meanwhile, compilation
                    on the Second Quebec Conference, 1944, was nearing completion, and galley proof
                    would be ordered shortly. The British Foreign Office had been helpful in
                    providing certain papers missing from United States files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reviewed the clearance problem on <hi
                        rend="underline">Trident</hi>, emphasizing that it was difficult for him to
                    advocate a 15-year line when we were still having clearance problems for the
                    year 1943. He pointed out that the matter of bases promised to be an endemic
                    problem. Iceland, for instance, had already caused clearance trouble, and there
                    would doubtless be others.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> stated that he saw no rational principle to
                    explain the great disparity between the length of clearance delays. The Paris
                    Peace Conference volumes of 1946 were cleared in four months, while Latin
                    American volumes had taken 22 months. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi>
                    pointed out that the Bureau of Inter-American Affairs traditionally presented
                    especially difficult clearance problems.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM IV: CLEARANCE DIFFICULTIES</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> reported that there had been measurable
                    improvement in both the speed with which the geographic offices of the
                    Department had cleared our galleys and in the reduction of the number of
                    deletions requested. Few offices, however, actually completed the clearance
                    process in the required three months and one office had kept a set of galley
                    proof for 18 months. Clearance was still assigned to junior officers within the
                    geographic offices, which continued to make requests for absurd modifications.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> noted that there had been relatively
                    few requests for wholesale deletions. We were unable to print anything on
                    relations with Iceland and had to delete entirely one compilation on U.S. policy
                    in the Far East. Nevertheless, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> won the
                    overwhelming majority of these clearance battles one way or another, or it went
                    down fighting.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> asked who on the desks dealt with clearance.
                    Couldn’t the problem be attacked by getting more responsible officers to do the
                    job? <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> replied that in some cases HO had
                    very good personal relationships with clearance officers. The clearance by the
                    Bureau of East Asian and Pacific Affairs of the 1946 volumes on China with the
                    deletion of only one sentence was greatly facilitated by such a situation. He
                    suggested that what was really needed was a declaration by the Secretary of
                    State that if clearance procedures were not completed within six months, HO
                    would be free to go ahead with publication. The current three-month rule was not
                    being enforced. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> asked whether the
                    Committee had not in the past asked for a three-month ultimatum. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that the Historical Office
                    itself, some years ago, had initiated the three-month rule which had been
                    approved by the Assistant Secretaries and had been incorporated into the
                    memorandum which accompanies galleys sent for clearance [see Attachment 4]. The
                    Assistant Secretaries, however, had not consented to the enforcement of this
                    deadline when it came into conflict with current policy considerations. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi>, in answer to a Committee query, stated
                    that efforts to implement the three-month rule risked the possibility of bound
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes being held up at the last
                    moment by desks which had never granted clearance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> asked about clearance by the Department of
                    Defense. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> reported that Defense clearance
                    was slow due to the fact that an extremely small staff at DOD was assigned to
                    the task.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> inquired regarding the possible contribution
                    of available Foreign Service officers toward meeting the clearance problem. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> indicated that some high-level FSOs had
                    rendered outstanding service in obtaining the speedy clearance of volumes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> asked whether the publication of material
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had ever had serious repercussions.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> could not recall any real crisis
                    having arisen, but there had been occasionally unfavorable reactions here and
                    abroad. For example, the Chinese Government had regularly expressed its chagrin
                    at the unflattering references to Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek in the China
                    volumes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> expressed interest regarding the clearance of
                    CIA and other intelligence material. He asked whether intelligence documentation
                    was being used in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Gleason</hi> explained that this problem arose sharply with respect to
                    the use of National Security Council documents. The <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Division was still awaiting some form of guidance from the
                    NSC Staff on the use of these papers, including the question as to whether such
                    documents might be identified by number and date. He felt this was a ludicrous
                    argument and that clearance should be based on substance, not on the externals
                    of identification. With respect to intelligence materials as such, he indicated
                    that such papers were used only when their direct relationship to policy
                    preparation could be established.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from the Committee, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> briefly reviewed the application of the 3O-year rule to the
                    opening of the files. Seven categories of papers, one being intelligence
                    material, were not open for research even after 30 years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> noted the relevance of clearance to
                    attempts to shorten the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> lead time. He
                    wondered if efforts to reduce the gap might not result in the exclusion of
                    material which might be cleared with the passage of additional time.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> then expressed concern regarding the
                    elimination of material on the grounds that it caused “needless offense” to
                    individuals. He thought it was possible to argue that a public figure would know
                    that he was going to be criticized, that he was in the kitchen because he could
                    stand the heat. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> and <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Gleason</hi> stated that this rule was really not much of a problem.
                    Such cases were quickly won or lost. Generally, it was the substance of policy
                    rather than personal references which created severe clearance difficulties.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out that in the post-war period
                    many policy issues carried a continuing sensitivity. It would be possible to
                    publish a great deal within fifteen years of the present if certain sensitive
                    areas were avoided. He presumed, however, that the Committee would object to
                    such an approach to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, even though it had
                    been followed in the past. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> voiced the
                    assumption that the Committee would not accept the omission of material on
                    overseas bases, for instance. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> inquired
                    whether the Historical Office needed the help of the Committee on this matter.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> replied that the Committee’s support
                    at a later date might be helpful. A high-level Conference with the Department Of
                    Defense to revise the present understanding might prove necessary.</p>
                <p>[The Committee recessed for lunch with Under Secretary U. Alexis Johnson]</p>
                <p>Afternoon Session - 2:15 p.m. - 4:00 p.m.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> suggested that the Committee take a stand
                    on the policy of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series that only
                    coverage of minor matters was subject to deletion and that publication of
                    volumes was postponed when necessary pending clearance of material on all major
                    policy issues. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> stated that each case must be
                    considered on its individual merits. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                    Franklin</hi>alluded to the wartime-conference volumes, recalling that HO had
                    insisted that all minutes and other high-level documentation on important issues
                    be included, even if it meant delaying the volumes. Was this approved by the
                    Committee?</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> raised the possibility of publishing delayed
                    supplements consisting of papers on subjects which could not be covered earlier
                    because of clearance difficulties. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> stated
                    that such a procedure had never been seriously considered; it might make it
                    easier for policy officers to insist on deletions. Returning to the question of
                    military bases, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> asked whether the release
                    of volumes might not proceed with the exception of this particularly sensitive
                    category of material which might be published subsequently. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Deener</hi> inquired whether material on Iceland, for instance, if
                    omitted now could be included in a later volume.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> observed that documents deleted at the
                    request of clearance officers were returned to the files and placed in blue
                    envelopes, under special non-access security. Groups of documents eliminated for
                    reasons of clearance were replaced in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    by editorial notes which indicated the nature of the omitted material and
                    possibly relevant file numbers. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> added
                    that the documents contained in the specially marked envelopes were not normally
                    available to researchers immediately after the files were opened on a restricted
                    basis. However, this material would be reviewed from time to time with a view
                    toward making it available to scholars. “Blue envelope” material would become
                    available after 30 years, in any case. There was not generally any way of
                    working into a subsequent volume of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> expressed apprehension concerning the
                    precedent established by the omission of the entire record of the Iceland
                    question. He feared that clearance officers might hold out in the future with
                    the hope that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would print only an
                    editorial note.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> distributed copies of the memorandum which
                    accompanies galley proof sent to clearing officers [Attachment 4]. In response
                    to a question from Dr. Plischke, he reiterated that the three-month limitation
                    on clearance had not been enforced. He felt that clearance would speed up if the
                    Secretary really wanted to stop the slippage in the series.</p>
                <p>AGENDA ITEM VI: PROBLEMS OF ACCESS</p>
                <p>In answer to a question <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> noted that the
                    files for 1945 were still stored in New State. The granting of access to this
                    material raised special problems of security and space for the Department. This
                    situation would continue until the entire 1945-1949 block of files was
                    transferred to the National Archives.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> (Chief of the Research Guidance and Review
                    Division of HO) summarized the current policy of the Department on access. The
                    Open Period now extended through the end of 1941. Scholars, including foreign
                    scholars, might examine this material at the National Archives, reproduce
                    copies, and conduct research without any control by the Department of State. The
                    Restricted Period now extended from 1942 through 1945, the most recent year
                    covered by <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Certain “lot”
                    files, consisting of material which has not been integrated into the central
                    (decimal) files of the Department, have also been made available to scholars.
                    Notable among the latter is Lot 60 D 224, which contains documentation on policy
                    with respect to the establishment of the United Nations and other aspects of
                    Departmental planning for the postwar period. While access is also granted to
                    other lot files mentioned in the pages of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, many lots cannot be opened because of their size,
                    disorganized condition, and the physical inability of the Department to carry
                    out appropriate screening. Furthermore, many lots are located at the Federal
                    Records Center at Suitland, Maryland, twelve miles from Washington. The
                    remoteness of the FRC makes it nearly impossible for the Historical Office to
                    administer lots located there. The FRC is not itself currently equipped to deal
                    with controlled access to such lots.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> presented a brief description of these lot
                    files and described the appalling administrative problems which they created. In
                    response to a question from the Committee, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi>
                    explained that Post files were different from the office lots, were often larger
                    and hence even more difficult to administer and screen. Post records, however,
                    did not generally contain papers that could not be found in the Department’s
                    central files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> asked at what point the central files were
                    turned over to the Archives. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> and <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> explained that the central files were
                    transferred in five-year blocks. When the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff had completed its work on the 1949 records, the entire
                    block of material for the period 1945-1949 would be shipped to the Archives. In
                    response to a query from Dr. Holt, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> agreed
                    that the Committee might set forth its views on the lot file problem.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> asked whether there were facilities for
                    researchers at the Federal Records Center. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi>
                    indicated that facilities did exist, but that thus far only the records of the
                    Office of War Information and the Foreign Economic Administration had been
                    opened for access. Most Department of State files at the FRC are without finding
                    aids and cannot be administered there at the present time.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> spoke of the incredulity of the outside
                    scholarly world as to the necessity of waiting to gain access to the files until
                    after <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes were actually released.
                    He repeated the question often put to him: why couldn’t access be granted once
                    the volumes had been cleared? Why did scholars have to wait during the period of
                    mechanical printing and binding? He suggested that it was believed in some
                    quarters that the Historical Office insisted on this delay in order to gain for
                    itself kudos for first publication.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> noted that documents were sometimes still
                    used by the staff after clearance for verification purposes. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> stated that it was perfectly
                    understandable that the Department did not grant access in advance of its own
                    documentary publication. Publication was the only proper way to make them
                    available. It would be impractical for the Historical Office to attempt to keep
                    the academic community abreast of clearance operations within the Government.
                    Moreover, the volumes were not regarded as actually cleared until they were
                    released to the public. In the past, some volumes which had been cleared had
                    been held up at the last moment at the insistence of geographic desks. What the
                    Historical Office sought was simply an equitable system under which everyone
                    would enjoy equal access -- not a situation in which a few well informed
                    individuals could gain an advantage over others. Furthermore, he continued, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series could not be permitted to be
                    swamped by administrative problems accruing from private scholars seeking
                    pre-publication access.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. May</hi> asked if it might be possible to permit
                    scholars to read cleared galleys. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> reviewed
                    instances when this practice had been allowed. He mentioned the case of Herbert
                    Feis who had rushed into print with material on atomic energy in the periodical
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi>. Knebel and Bailey, allowed to use
                    galley proof in preparation of a work on atomic energy [Fletcher Knebel and
                    Charles W. Bailey II, <hi rend="italic">No High Ground</hi> (New York, 1960)],
                    had published Potsdam papers on eastern Europe in a sensational “exclusive” in
                    the Des Moines <hi rend="italic">Register</hi>. Feis, in misusing the Potsdam
                    galleys, had wound up with the wrong document number citations (because new
                    materials were later added) and had missed some very important late material on
                    the Polish boundaries which is still unknown to many scholars because they rely
                    on Feis instead of reading the documents. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    assured the Committee that this sort of situation would not be permitted to
                    arise again.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> also reviewed the case of the Yalta
                    galleys which in 1955 had been prematurely released to James Reston of the <hi
                        rend="italic">New York Times</hi> by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Public Affairs. The Historical Office, unprepared for this eventuality, had been
                    compelled to search hurriedly for dog-eared galleys for other newsmen. The
                    Advisory Committee, created soon afterward partially as a result of the episode,
                    had vindicated the Historical Office regarding its role in the incident.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed that the Committee might
                    rightfully express its concern over the time lag between the clearance of
                    galleys and the release of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> still felt that there were strong arguments
                    for allowing access immediately after clearance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> asked if there were areas of the post-1945
                    files not of concern to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> which might be
                    opened to scholars. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> did not think that
                    such material would be of much interest. He stated that individual, identifiable
                    papers might be obtained through the procedures of the Freedom of Information
                    Act, but <hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> pointed out that declassification
                    of documents under this procedure was slow and costly. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        May</hi> asked about automatic downgrading. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> replied that due to lack of personnel, no one in the
                    Department was actively involved in that process. Our automatic declassification
                    was the 30-year rule for opening files to scholars.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> inquired as to whether the papers prepared
                    by the Historical Studies Division would be declassified and whether they would
                    be used in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He also asked whether the
                    Department was less disposed to issue publications than had formerly been the
                    case, mentioning the international conference pamphlets, which no longer
                    appeared. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out that the projects
                    completed by Historical Studies were not in themselves appropriate for inclusion
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. However, the original documents
                    upon which these studies were based might well be included. He though that in
                    general there had been a decline in the Department’s interest in publication
                    since the Dulles era when the Secretary’s own attitude had greatly encouraged
                        <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> publications.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> suggested that the Committee might
                    consider the question of Departmental historical source material in general. He
                    had in mind the unfortunate curtailment of the <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> series. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> indicated that
                    the loss of two more positions had compelled the Historical office to eliminate
                    its lowest priority operation. One of the two historians on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> had been assigned to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> expressed the hope
                    that it would be possible to resume publication in the future. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> contended that the impact of the Committee’s
                    recommendations might be diluted should the effort be made to discuss
                    publications other than <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>In reply to a query from the Committee, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi>
                    recalled that ten or twelve years ago the Historical Office had embarked upon a
                    pilot project of compiling collections of documents on subjects of the very
                    recent past in an effort to determine the utility of such a procedure to the
                    Department. The program evoked no response, perhaps due to the fact that the
                    topics selected were not of immediate interest to policy officers. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Dillard</hi> asked it the Office of the Legal Adviser
                    ever drew upon the resources of the Historical Office. He was assured by Dr.
                    Franklin and Dr. Dougall that L and HO had a close working relationship. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> went on to explain that few projects were
                    initiated by the Historical Studies Division. Generally, HO responded to
                    requests -- “felt needs” in the jargon of the Department.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question from Dr. Dillard, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi>
                    stated that there were no photographs in the annual <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes presently in preparation; some maps, however, were
                    being included. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> noted that the volumes of
                    the wartime-conference series contained both photographs and maps.</p>
                <p>Following an expression of appreciation by <hi rend="underline">Chairman
                        Plischke</hi> on behalf of the Committee for the continuing efforts of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff, the open meeting concluded.
                    The Committee continued in private session for an additional hour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="attachment">
                <p>Attachment 1</p>
                <p rend="center">Report by Dr. S. Everett Gleason, Chief of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> Division, on the Status of the Series and
                    Publication Prospects</p>
                <p>The charts that Mr. Aandahl has distributed [Attachments 2 and 3] should provide
                    the Committee with detailed information on the current status of the series and
                    prospects for the next couple of years. I will draw some deductions.</p>
                <p>In some respects we can congratulate ourselves on achievements since the last
                    meeting of the Committee. For the benefit of our new members let me remind you
                    that one of our goals since I became Editor of the series has been to reduce the
                    number of annual volumes to a reasonable figure. In this we have had some
                    success. The series for 1946 required 11 volumes. For 1947 we have reason to
                    believe that the material can be covered in 8 volumes, and 1948 not more than
                    that figure.</p>
                <p>It has also been an objective of the Division to reduce the size of each volume
                    to manageable handling as well as to reduce the number annual volumes. Here our
                    success can be measured but it is rather less than spectacular. Of the 1946
                    volumes only four out of the eleven were within range of our objective of
                    approximately 1,000 pages per volume.</p>
                <p>We shall do rather better for 1947. According to present estimates only two of
                    eight projected volumes should exceed 1200 pages.</p>
                <p>The Committee will realize, I trust, that the most obvious reason for not
                    achieving complete success in reducing the number of pages in each volume, is
                    that we have as the same time decreased the number of annual volumes for these
                    years.</p>
                <p>Turning now to the question of current and future prospects for publication. At
                    first sight the picture looks very gratifying. In Fiscal 1968 six volumes in the
                    annual series were published. In Fiscal 1969 the total dropped to three, one of
                    which was a conference volume. In the present Fiscal year, 1970, nine volumes
                    should appear. Four have already been published, two are in press. Depending on
                    the uncertain capabilities of the technical editors, we hope that Fiscal 1971
                    will see nine more volumes published. All this is very gratifying considering
                    that it has been accomplished with diminished rather than increased staff over
                    the fiscal years in question.</p>
                <p>I should however, be a good deal less than candid, if I were to convey to you an
                    impression that our current output in the years after FY 1971 will continue at
                    anything like this pace. On the contrary, unless our circumstances change
                    rapidly and for the better the prospects are nothing less than dismal. Since the
                    last meeting of the Committee we have lost by retirement or resignation no less
                    than three regular staff members. Mr. Reid and Mrs. Cassidy retired. Mr. Kranz
                    resigned. We were able to get Mr. Reid back on a contract basis which can,
                    however, be terminated at any time either by Mr. Reid himself or by the
                    Department. In addition there is every likelihood that we shall lose another
                    staff member by resignation next January.</p>
                <p>To compound our sorrows, I’m obliged to point out that the situation of our
                    technical editors is even worse than our own. There are now just two people in
                    PBR regularly assigned to work on our volumes. Only a couple of years ago there
                    were six such competent people. Manifestly these two persons can’t hope to edit
                    our manuscript at anything approaching the volume of publication we have
                    achieved in the last two fiscal years.</p>
                <p>To sum up on status and prospects. Unless we can get replacements for personnel
                    we are losing, and unless PBR can do likewise, I think it is accurate to say
                    that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series will face an actual
                    crisis, and any prospect of publishing our volumes 25 years after the event is
                    remote. Meanwhile we are informed that the freeze on hiring additional personnel
                    in the State Department is deeper and more solid than at any time since the
                    early 1950s.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
