<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1970</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1970</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-05">May 5, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1970-11-06">November 6, 1970</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1970-11-06-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 429 KB, 19pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1970—Minutes. Limited Official Use.
                    Drafted by William Slany. Attachment 1 is present, but not posted.</hi></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="minutes">
                <head>Record of the 1970 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 6, 1970</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Inis L. Claude, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs,
                                University of Virginia (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>David R. Deener, Provost and Dean of the Graduate School, Tulane
                                University (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Hardy C. Dillard [In Europe], Professor of Law, University of
                                Virginia (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>W. Stull Holt, Professor of History, University of Washington
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Ernest R. May, Dean of Harvard College (American Historical
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Elmer Plischke, Professor of Government and Politics, University
                                of Maryland (American Political Science Association)</item>
                            <item>Paul A. Varg, Professor of History, Michigan State University
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Stephen M. Schwebel<note n="1">Substitute for Dr. Dillard, now
                                    serving on the World Court.</note>, Executive Director and Vice
                                President, The American Society of International Law</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Michael Collins, Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>John G. Reid</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>Howard M. Smyth</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Opening Session - 9:15 am. - 12:15 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">OPENING REMARKS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> welcomed the Committee and announced that
                    Assistant Secretary of State Collins would participate in the Committee’s
                    session later in the morning. He also noted that the Committee, whose current
                    membership was unchanged from that of 1969, would next year lose the services of
                    Drs. Dillard, Holt, and Plischke.</p>
                <p>Before proceeding with the scheduled agenda of the Committee, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reported on an exchange that he had had
                    with Professor Howard Zinn, Professor of Government at Boston University and one
                    of the leading “New Left” historians, during a session of the Society of
                    American Archivists in Washington on September 30. Prof. Zinn had criticized the
                    Advisory Committee for not insisting that all documents should be published
                    before they were more than a year or two old. Dr. Franklin had felt obliged to
                    respond in defense of the Department and the Advisory Committee, indicating that
                    the Department was ahead of all other foreign offices in its publication and
                    access programs, and that the Committee was neither tame nor captive. Dr.
                    Franklin confessed that he had made practically no impression on Zinn, who was
                    personally not unpleasant but utterly unrealistic in his demands.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM I: SELECTION OF CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>Dr. Claude nominated Dr. Varg to serve as Chairman. When Dr. May moved that the
                    nominations be closed, there was unanimous agreement.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM II: STATUS OF THE SERIES AND PUBLICATION PROSPECTS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Aandahl</hi> distributed to the Committee copies of the
                    latest chart summarizing the status of annual volumes for 1946-1949 and the two
                    remaining wartime conference volumes [see Attachment l].</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> presented a report on the current position
                    of the series [see Attachment 2].</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM III: CLEARANCE AND TECHNICAL EDITING</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> advised the Committee that clearance and
                    technical editing remained the two principal obstacles to speedier publication
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Personnel in the
                    Publishing and Reproduction Division of the Department of State responsible for
                    the technical editing of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had been
                    reduced to 2 1/2 editors -- the lowest number in many years. Last week the
                    number had been raised to 3 1/2. Most of the technical editing and all of the
                    indexing for the series was carried out under contract outside the Department of
                    State. The contracted technical editing had proved so far to be reasonably
                    satisfactory, but the indexing had been poor and had resulted in much delay.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> reported that clearance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> within the Department of State was no
                    more difficult than heretofore, and the time involved ranged from three to
                    thirteen months. The principal clearance problems were with the Defense
                    Department and the National Security Council. Defense Department clearance had
                    never been easy, but until recently the requests had been based upon often
                    reasonable arguments of national security. In the past year significant requests
                    for deletions from the Defense Department had been based not on national
                    security but had appeared to stem from the desire of the military to show a “low
                    profile”. The deletions were of the sort which would endanger the credibility
                    and authority of the series. Even more serious was the inability of the
                    Historical Office to obtain permission from the National Security Council for
                    the publication of documents originated by that body. Failure to obtain NSC
                    clearance had resulted in the holding up of Volume III of 1947 since December
                    1968. The absence of NSC clearance threatened the very life of the series in as
                    much as the Council was the ultimate arbiter in practically every major problem
                    in U.S. foreign policy in the late 1940’s.</p>
                <p>A discussion of Dr. Gleason’s report followed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> expressed a cautious optimism regarding
                    the acceleration of the compilation of later volumes of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>, but he expressed apprehension that clearance delays
                    might more than offset gains in the rate of compilation. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Plischke</hi> asked if the slippage of the publication of the series
                    beyond the 20-year line was continuing, if at a declining rate. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> responded by stating that in his
                    discussions with other officers of the Department of State he would insist upon
                    25 years as the absolute limit in the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> was not optimistic that
                    the slippage could be held to 25 years and inquired how the Committee could be
                    of assistance. He observed that the Department officers appeared not to be
                    observing the requirement to complete the clearance within three months, and he
                    proposed that a six-months rule would be reasonable and should be adopted and
                    enforced. In response to <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt’s</hi> question as to
                    which level of Department office could best expedite observance of some definite
                    limitation on clearance time, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> suggested
                    that the Assistant Secretaries of State might be able to demand fulfillment by
                    country directors.</p>
                <p>The discussion turned to the personnel problems of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> recalled that
                    the staff had been increased by four positions in the past decade. Two of these
                    had been transferred from the German Documents Project and one from the Current
                    Documents Project (regarding whose demise Dr. Franklin expressed regret). The
                    fourth job had come from a vacancy elsewhere in the Bureau. The two most recent
                    additions to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff were introduced
                    to the Committee: <hi rend="underline">Evans Gerakas</hi> who had formerly been
                    with the Current Documents Project, and <hi rend="underline">Dr. David
                        Mabon</hi> who had come to the Department from the California State College
                    at Hayward. Two Foreign Service officers with graduate training had been
                    recruited to fill upcoming vacancies. Assistant Secretary of State Collins, who
                    had taken a lively interest in the work of the Historical Office, has approved
                    the Office’s request for two new positions. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi>
                    asked about the special studies activities in the Historical Office, and <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> indicated that the present reduced staff
                    was barely able to keep up with current assignments. As an example of personnel
                    stringencies within the Historical Office, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> observed that Dr. Kogan no longer had any staff to assist him
                    in administering the access program.</p>
                <p>The Committee returned to the Defense Department clearance problem and asked what
                    it might do in the matter. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> felt that any
                    strong Advisory Committee initiative with respect to Defense clearance delays
                    would be inappropriate and would not be well received by officials in Defense.
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> pointed out that the chart summarizing
                    the status of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes [attachment 1]
                    appeared to indicate that the Defense Department cleared galleys more rapidly
                    than the State Department. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> observed that
                    Defense cleared galleys rapidly in matters not deeply involved with national
                    security but was slow where such issues appeared to be involved. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> again deplored the fact that recent
                    Defense Department requests for deletions did not appear to be based on
                    questions of national security. He pointed to the Pacific trusteeship islands as
                    an example. The attitude of the Joint Chiefs of Staff towards these islands in
                    the late 1940’s was a matter of public knowledge. Nevertheless the Defense
                    Department now objected to the publication of the official records on the
                    subject. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> recalled that in the past the
                    Defense Department had sometimes refused to approve the publication in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of Joint Chiefs of Staff views which
                    had appeared in the memoirs of President Truman and Prime Minister
                    Churchill.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schwebel</hi> alluded to the reluctance of the Defense
                    Department to permit the use of the terms “military attaché” and “naval attaché”
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He warned that the proposed resort
                    to editorial circumlocutions to avoid these terms would only lead readers to the
                    erroneous conclusion that the series was concealing references to covert
                    intelligence operatives rather than to the well-known and traditional
                    information-gathering activities of Embassy attaches. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> remarked that the argument had already been raised with
                    Defense.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> expressed the view that any effort to
                    speed up Defense clearance would have to emanate from the Under Secretary of
                    State level. It was pointed out that Under Secretary Irwin had previously served
                    as Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Affairs and might be able to
                    take some action in the Defense clearance problem. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Varg</hi> stated that the Advisory Committee ought to try to raise the
                    matter during their luncheon with Under Secretary Irwin.</p>
                <p>In response to a query from <hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi>
                    reviewed the issues involved in securing downgrading of National Security
                    Council documents and the steps so far taken in the matter. The Defense
                    Department was adhering closely to the letter of the regulations in insisting
                    that NSC documents could only be declassified by the NSC. The NSC had apparently
                    never considered the possibility of declassification, and it was proving
                    difficult to obtain prompt and favorable action.</p>
                <p>[The Committee recessed briefly for coffee.]</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> observed that the focus of the
                    declassification problem appeared to be moving away from delay and toward
                    outright refusal to permit publication of documents. He advocated the
                    establishment of some procedural apparatus -- possibly a neutral appeals board
                    -- which could review and reverse negative clearance decisions and mitigate the
                    authority of clearance officers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi> felt that the question of clearance with other
                    agencies was not really a procedural matter but a policy question which the
                    Department of State alone could not resolve. He suggested that there was need
                    for an executive order which would remove the prohibition to the publication of
                    documents of a given age. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Schwebel</hi> doubted that
                    the matter of clearance of documents outside the Department of State could be
                    handled by any automatic procedure. Any appeals board would be limited by not
                    being a policy-making body. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> suggested that
                    Congress might pass a law opening all records in the National Archives after 20
                    years in place of the current 30-year rule. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi>
                    suggested the desirability of bringing together top State and NSC officials at
                    luncheons for the discussion of clearance problems, and <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Claude</hi> offered the possibility that such meetings could be expanded to
                    include Defense officials.</p>
                <p>In responding to the various ideas put forward on the clearance problem, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed that the traditional method for
                    appealing denials of clearance was to push such controversies to higher levels
                    in the Department and in the government, including the President. He recalled
                    that the publication of the records of the Big Four meetings at the 1919 Paris
                    Peace Conference had been considered by Hull, Roosevelt, and Churchill for a
                    final (if reluctant) decision. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> doubted
                    that any clearance appeals board would have either the responsibility or the
                    power necessary to operate effectively, and he saw no reason to believe that
                    Congress would legislate the full opening of Defense and NSC files after 20
                    years. Any legislation, such as the current Freedom of Information law, would
                    necessarily be so phrased as to exclude all those areas of important and
                    sensitive policy documentation to which the scholars sought access. He was not
                    sanguine that the NSC and the Central Intelligence Agency would be willing to
                    adhere to even a 30-year rule on disclosure.</p>
                <p>In answer to a query <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that the
                    agreement with the Department of Defense provided that the latter would supply
                    for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> only those documents that
                    represented the advice and recommendations of the Defense Department to the
                    Secretary of State and the President.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> agreed that the use of top-level papers
                    was a reasonable formula for inter-agency relations, and he wondered about its
                    application to the problem of NSC documents. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Dougall</hi> pointed out that there was no problem of acquiring NSC
                    documents, in contrast to Defense files, in as much as the State Department was
                    a repository of NSC documents. The question was one of clearance. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> observed that many NSC documents were
                    similar to or identical with Department of State Policy Planning Staff papers.
                    The NSC could not object to the publication of such Policy Planning Staff papers
                    as such but it had refused to approve the declassification of these same papers
                    as NSC numbered documents.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> inquired if the Committee’s report should call
                    for more inter-agency agreements as a basis for clearance. At the suggestion of
                        <hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> further discussion of this issue was
                    held over for the private meeting of the Committee.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi> asked if the Historical Office had considered
                    the possibility of preparing a current, classified version of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> for internal Department use. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Franklin</hi> replied that work of this sort was in effect being done
                    by the Historical Studies Division of the Historical Office. There was not
                    sufficient staff, however, to carry forward the work on any large scale. To do
                    so would require the assignment of members of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff and would thus further slow down the publication of the
                    series.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion of the application of modern technological innovations
                    to the task of speeding the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that he and
                    other members of the staff had taken courses dealing with the application of
                    computerized data retrieval systems to foreign-policy problems. He described
                    briefly the Department-wide computerized data system currently under
                    development, but he noted that this system would only cover current
                    documentation from a certain date onwards; it would be of no assistance for
                    research in the pre-computer period.</p>
                <p>[Assistant Secretary of State Collins entered the meeting at 11 a.m. and was
                    introduced to the members of the Advisory Committee.]</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> stated that historians were dismayed at the
                    slippage in the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    Professional groups wanted something done to reverse the trend. It had been
                    suggested that the introduction of the photo-offset process method of
                    reproducing original documents from the files of the Department would save a
                    portion of the time spent in the technical editing of the letterpress volumes
                    and greatly accelerate the publication of the series. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Varg</hi> was interested in the suggestion. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> expressed preference for the present editing-printing process
                    and felt that the real need of the series was for more staff. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that the photo-offset process
                    had been investigated some time ago. Although it might speed up the series a
                    bit, compilation and clearance would remain the principal time-consuming phases
                    of publication. He reminded the Committee that photo-offset would necessitate
                    additional annotation to explain typographical errors, stamps, endorsements,
                    garbled phrases, etc., and that legibility of the finished product would be
                    poor. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> added that offset would in fact
                    increase clearance time, in so far as clearance officers would either refuse to
                    read the often illegible copy or would read it more slowly.</p>
                <p>At <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg’s</hi> request, <hi rend="underline">Dean
                        May</hi> reported on the historians’ views on the delay in publishing <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi>,
                    who with <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> was a member of the Ad Hoc Committee
                    of the American Historical Association and the Organization of American
                    Historians on access to the files, stated that historians and students were
                    worried because the delayed volumes were those covering the controversial “cold
                    war” period. Concern over the delay in publication was coupled with concern
                    regarding earlier access to the files of the Department of State. Photo-offset
                    was one of the ideas suggested by the historians. Another possibility was a
                    further reduction in the number of volumes published for each year. Yet another
                    suggestion was that temporary workers be brought into the Department from the
                    academic field to aid in the selection of documents for the series. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> emphasized that the Ad Hoc Committee was
                    particularly concerned about the access problem.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> would want the firm backing of the Advisory Committee if
                    further reductions were to be made in the scope and size of the series. Many
                    historians assumed that the number of annual volumes would actually increase to
                    cover the important materials of the “cold war” period. When <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> asked what advantage would result from
                    restricting the series to four volumes per year, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> replied that such a reduction would neither speed compilation
                    nor would it permit adequate coverage of major topics. He feared that major
                    topics would be excluded from such an abbreviated series, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> would cease to function as a guide to important
                    subjects and files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi> expressed the opinion that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> was valuable to students doing initial research or
                    engaged in senior theses, but serious graduate students necessarily had to
                    resort to the primary materials in the files. Historians would be much happier
                    with a selective <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, suitable for
                    course work, together with microfilm depositories around the country of State
                    Department files. Such regional microfilm files might be related to the
                    Presidential libraries.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schwebel</hi> preferred a complete series rather than a
                    selective one. He mentioned the problem of foreign scholars who were unable to
                    work in the files of the Department, and he stated that the United States had an
                    obligation to publish a complete record, particularly in view of its past record
                    of openness. He also mentioned his regret as an international lawyer that the
                    volume of documentation on international law topics had already been reduced in
                    recent volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Claude</hi> stated that given a choice between a comprehensive series
                    published after 25 years or a minimal one published after 20 years, he would
                    choose the latter, and he thought most political scientists would agree. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> observed that if reducing the number of
                    volumes would not result in earlier publication, he would prefer to see the more
                    comprehensive series continue. What was really needed, he observed, was more
                    people both to expedite the publication of the series and to provide earlier
                    access to the files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Assistant Secretary of State Collins</hi> stated that the
                    Public Affairs Bureau was actively working toward the goal of increased staff. A
                    request for two additional persons for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff had been approved by the Department. He warned that the
                    request, which represented two-thirds of the Bureau’s total staff increase
                    request, might have difficulty when reviewed by the Budget Bureau.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> reported that the Society for Historians of
                    American Foreign Relations had applied to several foundations for grants to
                    support internships in the Department of State. Plans envisaged two-year
                    internships for young scholars at the doctorate level. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Holt</hi> reported further that financial support had not yet been obtained,
                    partly because the foundations felt that funds should be available from the
                    Department for normal staffing. He felt that the academic community would
                    benefit greatly if there were more younger historians who had first-hand
                    experience in the functioning of the Department.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> felt it would be necessary to be cautious
                    in taking up the intern plan. The work in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> required a long apprenticeship. It might be advisable to
                    begin the program on a trial basis with one or two carefully chosen young
                    scholars. <hi rend="underline">Assistant Secretary Collins</hi> mentioned to the
                    Committee the current program for White House Fellows as possibly providing
                    ideas for handling the proposed intern program. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> mentioned the possibility that interns under a program of the
                    National Historical Publications Commission might be assigned to the Department
                    of State for training -- although most of these interns were specializing in a
                    much earlier period of American history.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> stated that there was a view held by many
                    people, but with which he did not agree, that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series should be abandoned if it falls more than 30 years
                    beyond currency and that it should be replaced by a number of regional microfilm
                    centers of State Department materials.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> asked if it would be possible to give access
                    to the files for years for which <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> were
                    not released or in some way defining the restricted access period in a fixed
                    relationship to the 30-year limit rather than to the release of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. In reply, <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Franklin</hi> reviewed the general problem of document
                    declassification. He pointed out that the State Department did not have a
                    declassification team. The publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> was of critical importance in the downgrading and
                    declassification of blocks and years of files. In preparing documentation for
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, the staff in effect was operating
                    as a declassification team. The publication in the series of documentation on a
                    particular subject generally permitted Department officers to decide that other
                    materials on the same subject could be declassified. Without the prior
                    publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, access to the files in
                    the restricted period and favorable review by desk officers of notes on such
                    materials would be incomparably more difficult. In addition, there would be a
                    multiplication of the number of case-by-case determinations of grants of access
                    and review of notes with a consequent inevitable delay in time.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> pointed out that he and perhaps other
                    members of the Committee had seen in draft an article by James MacGregor Burns
                    proposing that all documents six years and older be made available to the
                    public. [The Burns article appeared subsequently in <hi rend="italic">The New
                        York Times Book Review</hi>, November 8, 1970.] <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Schwebel</hi> felt that advocacy of such a short closed period was
                    irresponsible. It was also important to remember that such a proposal would lead
                    to complications with many foreign governments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> stated that several initiatives for
                    Congressional action on earlier access to the files were to be anticipated. A
                    20-year rule was being mentioned. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    predicted that none of these proposals would effect the automatic
                    declassification of precisely those types of high-level and/or multilateral
                    documentation that caused the real trouble, such as NSC, JCS or NATO
                    documentation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> asked whether the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes for 1947-1948 constituted a bottleneck for the
                    series, and <hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> expressed the anxiety that the
                    series was steadily slipping further from currency despite efforts of the staff
                    to speed up publication. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reiterated his
                    guarded optimism concerning the improving prospects for speedier publication of
                    the series. The reduction in the number of volumes per year would slowly result
                    in faster coverage per year. The benefits of the reduction would become more
                    evident as the series completed publication of the large number of volumes
                    covering 1945 and 1946. The number of volumes published in the last three or
                    four years exceeded the number published in the preceding three or four
                    years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>, replying to a question from <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi>, explained that the files for 1945 had
                    been opened as the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for that
                    year were published, area by area. The practice had not been very satisfactory
                    either for the scholars or for the Department. Hence the decision had been made
                    not to open up the year 1946 for access until all the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes for that year had been published.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> asked about the likely consequence to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series of an Advisory Committee
                    recommendation in support of a 20-year access rule unrelated to the publication
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He felt that the public access
                    program should not suffer merely because the Department of State was unable to
                    provide the staff adequate to keep the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series up to 20 years. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> stressed the range
                    of practical difficulties which would result from an access program that was not
                    directly related to the publication of the series. These difficulties included
                    the probable necessity of detailing members of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff to service the larger number of researchers entering
                    the uncompiled portion of the files and the need for full security clearance of
                    scholars rather than the more simplified name check employed at present. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> commented that a fixed 20-year access rule
                    appeared likely simply to shift the clearance problem from the series to
                    individual scholars.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schwebel</hi> observed that some officials who had left
                    government service had not followed the rules of access, had taken documents,
                    and had published books on the basis of such papers. He suggested that
                    Congressional action was necessary to prevent such a practice. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reviewed the current regulations
                    governing the control and removal of official documents by retired officials. He
                    pointed out that the microfilm materials constituting the Dulles Papers were
                    under the same restrictions as the original materials retained by the Department
                    of State. Former Presidents could take away all papers in the White House, but
                    they had no authority to declassify them. Existing laws and regulations did not
                    really cover this problem.</p>
                <p>In closing the morning session, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> observed that
                    a 20-year access rule was excellent in principle. The problem remained how to
                    implement the rule.</p>
                <p>[The Committee recessed for lunch with Under Secretary of State John N. Irwin
                    II.]</p>
                <p>Afternoon Session - 2:45 p.m. - 3:30 p.m.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> opened the afternoon session. He observed that
                    the agenda appeared to have been well covered in the morning, and he asked for
                    any additional questions or comments on the items already discussed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Slany</hi> reminded the Committee of another aspect of
                    the relationship between the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> and the access policy. Scholars should be under no illusion
                    that the grant of access would offer quick and direct discovery of the most
                    important foreign-policy records on a given subject. The records of the
                    Department were in a state of archival chaos. Some of the most important
                    documentation was in unindexed lot files. Although they enjoy the advantage of
                    wide-ranging official authority in carrying out their work, members of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff have the greatest difficulty
                    groping through the documentary maze. The often unhappy experience of scholars
                    who have or are now working in the files of the Department demonstrates the
                    hazards and difficulties. The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    alone would provide the authoritative guide to the vital records of the
                    Department.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> commented upon the principal problems
                    emerging from the access program. After five years of experience in reviewing
                    the notes and manuscripts of outside scholars who have been granted access to
                    the files, he was convinced that little had been added by this research to the
                    official record already published in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. He stressed his conviction that the series had very
                    extensive coverage on all the major foreign-policy questions of the post-war
                    period. Referring to Dean May’s earlier assessment of the value of the series to
                    scholars and students, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> emphasized his
                    confidence that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was important to the
                    experienced scholar as well as to the beginning researchers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi> replied that he had not intended to deprecate
                    the series but merely to indicate that historians would find it necessary to go
                    beyond the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes and into the
                    unpublished records for the full story on any subject.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> reminded the Committee that
                    student-scholars given access to the files often lacked the training and ability
                    to use the raw files of the Department. There were many aspects to the documents
                    that could be misunderstood by untrained students. It was the years of training
                    and experience in the handling of Department documents which permitted the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff to prepare an accurate and
                    authoritative printed record. The problems of using raw documents were matters
                    of serious concern in connection with the proposals for interns and photo-offset
                    publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Holt</hi> asked if the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff could prepare more complete finding aids to the
                    Department’s files to assist private researchers. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> explained that the Records Management Division of the
                    Department, the logical source for such guides, lacked the personnel to do
                    anything more extensive along this line. He pointed out that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> performed precisely the function of a detailed
                    finding aid to the files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> commented that during its luncheon with Under
                    Secretary Irwin, the Advisory Committee took the opportunity to point out the
                    great contribution which the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    made to historical knowledge. He added that the Committee in its annual meetings
                    dealt mostly with the problems and difficulties of the series, but it should be
                    said that the Committee had a high regard for the high scholarly quality of the
                    series and for the skill of the staff which compiled it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> reiterated the essential role of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series as a finding aid to the files of
                    the Department -- particularly the lot files. Administrative and security
                    problems made it difficult for private researchers to exploit these files
                    usefully. The proliferation of multilateral documents and papers of other
                    government agencies in the files for the post-war period presented another
                    obstacle to the access program. He was convinced that the mounting problems in
                    servicing and exploiting the files combined with the diminution in the size of
                    his staff made necessary some serious restriction on the categories of
                    researchers who could be granted access.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out some additional hazards and
                    difficulties in use of lot files by private researchers. Because of the
                    varieties of proscribed materials included in such files, it was necessary that
                    they be screened before release to researchers. Dr. Kogan consulted with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff on questions of access and the
                    screening of files. He warned that the chaotic state of the lot files raised the
                    spectre of inadvertent omission of important materials by <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> and even by outside scholars who might later raise
                    cries of discrimination if subsequent research disclosed documents not
                    previously identified.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dean May</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reviewed the current status of the
                    1945-1949 block of Department indexed files which were being transferred to the
                    custody of National Archives. He pointed out the great difficulty in
                    administering and servicing files dispersed in various records centers
                    throughout the Washington area.</p>
                <p>Responding to questions from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> briefly reviewed aspects of the work of his
                    staff. In the first 10 months of 1970 there were applications for access from 48
                    Ph.D. candidates, 4 Masters candidates, 36 researchers for books, and 5
                    researchers for articles. In addition he had responded to a variety of requests
                    for the declassification of papers from other agencies. His responsibility
                    extended to the review of notes taken by researchers on the foreign-policy
                    aspects of documents in the Division of Modern Military Records of the National
                    Archives. He also had responsibility for the records of certain wartime agencies
                    such as the Office of War Information and the War Refugee Board, which were in
                    the custody of the Department of State.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> conceded that too many student-researchers
                    were wasting their time in the files. He inquired whether the Committee could
                    help in some way to prepare researchers for their work in the files. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> stressed that the basic prerequisite was for
                    researchers to study <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> thoroughly before
                    beginning their examination of the raw files. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> expressed anxiety that too many untrained students were
                    seeking access to the files. In view of the limitations of time and personnel,
                    it might be necessary to be more restrictive in granting access to the files
                    beginning with 1946.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Smyth</hi> observed that the British historian D. C.
                    Watt had been instrumental in the action of his government in establishing a
                    30-year rule for access to documents. Watt had made much of the fact that
                    British scholars were obliged to use <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in
                    order to discover the story of British foreign policy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> noted that the British action would help
                    to keep <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> ahead of the 30-year rule. He
                    said that it was very helpful for the United States and the United Kingdom to
                    maintain the same pace in granting access to the files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> circulated copies of a detailed and
                    favorable article by Geoffrey Warner in <hi rend="italic">International
                        Affairs</hi>, July 1970, reviewing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes for 1945 covering the origins of the “cold war”.</p>
                <p>After expressions of appreciation to the members of the staff, the open meeting
                    concluded. The Committee continued in private session.</p>
                <p>Attachments:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Status of Volumes, October 1970.</item>
                    <item>2. Report to the Advisory Committee, Fourteenth Annual Meeting, November
                        6, 1970.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="attachment">
                <p rend="center">Attachment 2</p>
                <p rend="center">Report by Dr. S. Everett Gleason, Chief, <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Division, to the Advisory Committee Fourteenth Annual
                    Meeting, November 6, 1970</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="underline">Status of the Series and Publication Prospects</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl’s charts which have been given to you summarize in brief form the
                    present status of the volumes in the Series for the years 1946, 1947, 1948, and
                    1949.</p>
                <p>I will confine my remarks to emphasizing the significance of these figures as
                    they relate to the problems the Series is currently facing.</p>
                <p>Perhaps of most concern to the Committee and certainly to the Historical Office
                    is the matter of the time lag, and our hopes of not falling further behind the
                    agreed objective of publishing our volumes twenty years after the events they
                    document.</p>
                <p>The picture here is not reassuring. Of the eleven volumes for 1946 four remain
                    unpublished as of this time. Volume I, General: The United Nations has been in
                    clearance since April 1969. No difficulty was encountered within the Department,
                    but Defense has raised a number of critical objections which we are still
                    negotiating - primarily documentation relating to bases, military assistance and
                    the Pacific strategic trusteeship. Until these issues are settled the galleys
                    for this volume can’t go to pages.</p>
                <p>The remaining three volumes, two large ones dealing with China, and the third
                    with the Far East exclusive of China, are now in pages and await only indexing
                    which will have been accomplished by the end of this year or early in 1971. Thus
                    in 1970 the 1946 Series lags 24 years plus behind the event.</p>
                <p>None of the volumes for 1947 or 1948 have been published, although, as you have
                    noticed, several are in pages or awaiting indexing. There seems little hope,
                    therefore, of doing more than holding the line at 24, and a greater likelihood,
                    because of clearance and technical editing bottlenecks, we shall slip to 25
                    years or more.</p>
                <p>In our efforts to reduce the number of volumes in each annual series, and the
                    number of pages in each volume we are making some progress, though we are still
                    short of the goals we had set. As opposed to the eleven volumes in the 1946
                    series, we will cover 1947 in eight volumes. We had hoped to cover 1948
                    similarly in eight, but have been forced to go to nine which is the likely
                    number for 1949 even though the charts show a tentative number of eight.</p>
                <p>Regrettably in our efforts to reduce the number of volumes for each year, we have
                    failed in a number of instances in 1947 and 1948 to keep the individual volumes
                    down to the range of about a thousand pages. I’m inclined to apologize for this
                    failing. In certain instances it simply proved impossible to discharge our
                    responsibility to document the major problems of U.S. foreign policy while at
                    the same time achieving our objective of reducing the number and size of the
                    volumes for recent years. You can well imagine which problems we met, in this
                    respect, in such compilations as the Marshall Plan, Western European Union,
                    NATO, the Arab-Zionist controversy, and Aid to Greece and Turkey. Large as these
                    compilations have perforce turned out to be, some of my staff, I am sure, feel
                    that in my attempts to cut out fat, a lot of muscle has had to go too.</p>
                <p>In terms of the number of volumes published in recent fiscal years, we have at
                    least improved remarkably over the low point of 3 volumes in FY 1969. In Fiscal
                    1970 we published 8 volumes. In the present fiscal year we are quite sure we
                    shall publish 7 volumes. For FY 1972 we have scheduled 7 volumes; the same for
                    FY 1973.</p>
                <p>Whether we achieve these objectives for the present fiscal year and for coming
                    ones depends in the first instance on ourselves - on the ability of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff to deliver manuscript, hopefully
                    covering a year in a year. Critical to the solution of this problem is adequate
                    staff. It has been impossible fully to replace retirements or resignations. Only
                    one new member has been added to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    staff by recruitment outside the Department since the Committee met last
                    November. That is Mr. Mabon. We have had transferred to us from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> Project, now in abeyance, Evans
                    Gerakas. Meanwhile we shall lose Mr. Smyth at the end of the calendar year and
                    we retain the services of Mr. Reid only on the precarious basis of a retired
                    annuitant whom we could lose at any time either by his choice or the
                    Department’s decision. We may be able to secure for a period of two years,
                    possibly three, the services of two fairly well qualified Foreign Service
                    Officers of which there is a plethora now on hand. We don’t look gift horses in
                    the mouth but Foreign Service Officers rarely meet our minimum requirements and
                    can serve with us for relatively short periods of time. What we need, of course,
                    is permission to recruit outside for replacements for our losses and the
                    addition of two or three new men similarly recruited from outside and meeting
                    our own high standards of performance. At present no outside recruiting is
                    permitted and we are not sanguine that any exception will be granted in our case
                    though we are attempting to obtain one.</p>
                <p>Even if it were, there are two other serious roadblocks ahead of us. The first of
                    these is in the area of technical editing of our volumes.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="underline">Clearance and Technical Editing Problems</hi></p>
                <p>Within the Department the technical editing staff available for work on <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> has now been reduced to three full-time
                    and one part-time editor--the lowest number in more than a decade. This means
                    that much of the technical editing and all of the indexing is now contracted
                    out. The results in the case of the technical editing has been at least
                    satisfactory. This is emphatically not the case with the indexing. The last two
                    indexes sent to us for review were so bad that we could not in our own staff
                    even attempt to rework them into some reasonable form. Both have got to be
                    totally rewritten with the resultant delay and expense. One could wish that the
                    responsible officers would learn from this kind of experience but there are no
                    indications of it.</p>
                <p>The other major hurdle is the familiar one of clearance. In most cases clearance
                    within the Department itself has been no worse than in the recent past. The
                    elapsed time runs all the way from 13 months to the desired 3. Our main
                    problems, clearance-wise, have currently been with the Defense Department and
                    the National Security Council. Defense clearance has never in my experience been
                    expeditious or easy, but until recently Defense did confront us with seemingly
                    reasonable arguments for documents they wished us to delete. In the course of
                    the last year, however, we have met with some demands for deletion by Defense
                    which could really endanger the credibility and authority of the Series. This
                    new caution on the part of the Joint Chiefs especially seems to us to derive not
                    from concrete objections on security or other legitimate grounds, but on the
                    sensitivity of the military to current public criticism, and on the desire, as
                    the phrase goes, to show a low profile. This, of course, we can’t prove but
                    whatever the cause of this new caution it can be very damaging to <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Even more serious has been our failure, thus far, to get permission from the NSC
                    to publish documents originated by that body. This has held up the printing of
                    Vol. III, 1947, since December 1968 when clearance began.</p>
                <p>The Committee will realize the threat this poses for the Series if it is aware
                    that within two years of the establishment in 1947, the NSC had become the
                    ultimate arbiter of practically every major problem in U.S. foreign policy. It
                    seems to most of us impossible for the series to continue if it builds up the
                    arch of foreign policy documentation only to leave the Keystone out. I can only
                    assure the Committee that we are doing our utmost and will continue to try to
                    solve this problem. Failure to do so would seem to me to be nothing less than a
                    disaster for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>But I have taken too much of the Committee’s time already. In closing I can only
                    apologize that over the years my reports tend to contain a monotonous
                    similarity. They are full of problems and almost bereft of solutions. But we can
                    discern no easy solutions and can only hope that continuous plugging away at our
                    troubles may ultimately succeed in reducing if not eliminating them.</p>
                <p>If the Committee has specific questions about my report and the charts which have
                    been given them, the members of the staff will be only too pleased to attempt to
                    answer them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
