<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1971</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1971</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-19">May 19, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1971-11-05">November 5, 1971</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1971-11-05-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 694 KB, 16pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1971—Minutes. Limited Official Use.
                    Attachments 2 and 3 are present, but not posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn40">Footnotes 40</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn62">62</ref></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="minutes">
                <head>Record of the 1971 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 5, 1971</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Inis L. Claude, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs,
                                University of Virginia (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>David R. Deener, Provost and Dean of the Graduate School, Tulane
                                University (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Alwyn V. Freeman, Member, Board of Editors, <hi rend="italic">The
                                    American Journal of International Law</hi> (American Society of
                                International Law)</item>
                            <item>Walter LaFeber, Professor of History, Cornell University (American
                                Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Ernest R. May [Absent], Professor of History, Harvard University
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Richard C. Snyder [Absent], Director, Mershon Center, Ohio State
                                University (American Political Science Association)</item>
                            <item>Paul A. Varg, Professor of History, Michigan State University
                                (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Elmer Plischke<note n="1">Former member of the Committee,
                                    substituting for Dr. Snyder</note>, Professor of Government and
                                Politics, University of Maryland (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>John Richardson, Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>S. Everett Gleason</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin [Absent]</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>Rogers P. Churchill</item>
                            <item>Joan E. Brosius</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                            <item>Margaret G. Martin</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Morning Session - 9:15 am. to 12:25 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">OPENING REMARKS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
                        Richardson</hi> welcomed the Committee, commended the work of the Historical
                    Office, and indicated that the Department of State, recognizing the importance
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, had asked for funds to
                    bring the series five years closer to currency.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM I: ELECTION OF CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>The Advisory Committee, by acclamation, chose Dr. Inis L. Claude to serve as
                    Chairman.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM II: CHANGES IN THE <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN
                        RELATIONS</hi> STAFF</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM III: STATUS OF THE SERIES AND PUBLICATION PROSPECTS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> presented a report covering both of these
                    agenda items [see Attachment 1]. The Committee had before it a chart setting
                    forth the status of the series as of October 1971 [see Attachment 2]. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Aandahl</hi> distributed an additional chart indicating
                    the status of the series as of November 1971 [see Attachment 3].</p>
                <p>In reply to questions by <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi>, it was indicated
                    by <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> that the historian soon to join the staff and the three
                    additional positions requested by the Department but not yet approved at other
                    levels of the Executive Branch or the Congress would bring the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> staff to a total strength of 18 historians. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that there was great pressure within
                    the Department to hold down the personnel level and to recruit from within the
                    Department. The Historical Office, which obviously required professional
                    historians, had been fortunate in that the Deputy Under Secretary of State for
                    Management, William B. Macomber, Jr., had approved every recent HO request for
                    outside recruiting authority.</p>
                <p>In response to an inquiry by <hi rend="underline">Dr. LaFeber</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> discussed the implications of the
                    announced White House interest in special documentary projects on the Korean,
                    Lebanese, and Cuban crises. He explained to the Committee that in August, John
                    D. Ehrlichman, Assistant to the President for Domestic Affairs, had informed the
                    press that the President had requested that an interdepartmental committee,
                    chaired by Assistant Attorney General William Rehnquist, and already charged
                    with a review of Executive Order 10501 and government declassification
                    procedures, also investigate the feasibility of such special documentary
                    projects. A Department of State paper submitted to the Rehnquist committee
                    warned that a question of credibility would arise if such projects became “white
                    papers” not up to the scholarly standards of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. The Department paper pointed out that any such white
                    papers should at least have a preface explaining that the published volume did
                    not pretend to be complete but only included such documentation as was currently
                    available. The Historical Office did not want to take responsibility for any
                    published documentary which omitted important papers, such as those at the
                    levels of President and Secretary of State.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> commended the publication <hi
                        rend="italic">Documents on Germany, 1944-1975</hi> prepared by the
                    Historical Studies Division of the Historical Office and released as a Committee
                    print by the Committee on Foreign Relations of the U.S. Senate in May 1971. He
                    noted that the volume was very useful even though not complete in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> sense of the word, and he suggested
                    that the publications contemplated by the White House might be done in the same
                    manner. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Documents on Germany</hi>, which was a revision of an earlier version,
                    contained only previously published and released documents. He felt that special
                    documentary projects which contained some but not all of the important
                    unpublished records would be inadequate and unreliable. Only projects as
                    comprehensive and definitive as <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would
                    be acceptable. The Historical Office realized that it had no credibility with
                    the public to trade on, and a serious question of credibility would arise if
                    special documentary publications, less comprehensive and reliable than <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, were to be issued.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reminded the Committee that the 1942-1949
                    China volumes and the wartime conference volumes of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series had resulted from the request by Republican
                    Senators in the early 1950s for single-volume publications on China and the
                    wartime conferences. Congress had approved work on the comprehensive series on
                    China and the wartime conferences only after the Historical Office had
                    demonstrated that these topics could not be adequately documented in
                    single-volume works. The China volumes, whose publication had been speeded up
                    and then held back at different periods, were eventually incorporated into the
                    annual <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> sequence. He felt that any new
                    documentary project undertaken now should also be incorporated in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, as a first choice.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> pointed out that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes on the Korean conflict, which were already
                    in an advanced state of preparation, could be accelerated, thus making
                    unnecessary any less complete and less reliable publication on Korea. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Glennon</hi> reported that the record of U.S. policy in
                    Korea for 1950 would be completed in manuscript in December 1971. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said that he hoped that the Korean story
                    could be released in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series but
                    the more serious problem was how to handle publications on such incidents as the
                    Lebanon landing of 1958 and the Cuban crisis of 1962, which were topics far
                    ahead of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> wondered whether any partisan pressure had
                    been brought to bear to publish special documentary volumes, and whether this
                    would slow down <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Freeman</hi> also was puzzled by the White House selection of the three
                    particular crises. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> assured the Committee
                    that there had been no partisan pressure in the matter, and that the three
                    projects mentioned by the White House, namely, the Korea conflict, the Lebanon
                    landing, and the Cuban missile crisis, had been chosen apparently so as to have
                    one project from each of three Presidential administrations,</p>
                <p>In response to an inquiry from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> briefly described the nature and extent
                    of the classified studies prepared by the Historical Studies Division of the
                    Historical Office. It was pointed out that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes on the Korean conflict were being greatly facilitated
                    by a large special study on Korea and that many other <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> compilations in the period since World War II would be
                    similarly aided by such special studies. Unfortunately, such studies were only
                    done at the request of other offices and bureaus of the Department and did not
                    systematically cover all foreign affairs problems; but studies had been made of
                    most of the major crises of the last 20 years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> raised the possibility of releasing the 1950
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on Korea before the 1948 and
                    1949 volumes were published. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed
                    that in the past individual <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for
                    several different years had been released as they were completed irrespective of
                    the chronology. Headline-seeking journalists tended to speculate on the release
                    of volumes apparently out of order and to attribute dramatic but false political
                    or foreign policy motives to such releases. In order to avoid such harmful
                    publicity and to demonstrate that the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> was a strictly historical project with no connection to
                    current policy, the volumes were now being released strictly chronologically for
                    each year although not numerically within each year. The series could use
                    publicity, but not the sort which disturbed foreign governments or Departmental
                    officers. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> reminded the Committee that the
                    foreign press, particularly some foreign news services, closely followed the
                    publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and tended to take items
                    in the volumes out of context to make up stories with an anti-U.S. twist.</p>
                <p>There was a general discussion of various aspects of the problem of special
                    documentary studies for the 1950s and ’60s. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Plischke</hi> indicated he would be happy to see the publication of special
                    documentaries, even though they were less comprehensive than the <hi>Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, particularly in the absence of the now suspended
                    series <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents</hi>. He was
                    prepared to wait for the publication of the definitive <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> shared the view
                    that having partial documentation available early was desirable. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. LaFeber</hi> also felt the publication of special
                    documentary volumes would be helpful if their preparation did not interfere with
                    the preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He
                    pointed out that the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> though not
                    definitive was quite helpful to scholars. He felt there was a significant
                    documentary gap for the Korean war period and a real need both for an early,
                    secondary-level, partial documentary collection and for the complete <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> coverage. He held that an early if
                    partial documentary would permit more scholarship on Korea than was currently
                    possible, and any such special volume of papers could carry a preface which
                    clearly explained the limitations in scope and coverage. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Varg</hi> observed that there were two audiences for documentaries
                    which argued for the publication of two different types of documentaries. For
                    those scholars and teachers who were not often able to have access to the
                    archives, it was essential to maintain a complete and definitive <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series of the highest standard. There
                    was another audience, however, not interested in research, which urgently needed
                    the early publication of important although incomplete documentation on such
                    topics as the Korean War. The preface to such limited documentary publications
                    would have to apprise the readers of the restricted scope and coverage.
                    Throughout this discussion, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reiterated
                    that the central problem of producing special documentary volumes for crises of
                    the 1950s or ’60s was the inevitable incompleteness of such volumes. With the
                    addition of some of the previously classified records they would be more
                    substantial than the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> but far less
                    complete and authoritative than the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. Their shortcomings would be played up by every hostile critic, including
                    many scholars. He was prepared, however, to make the effort, if that was the
                    ultimate decision of the White House. He thought that the resort to a non-book
                    format and the use of photo-offset without annotation might afford a practical
                    method for presenting such special documentation with a minimum of criticism.
                    The Committee indicated general assent to this suggestion.</p>
                <p rend="center">[The Committee recessed briefly for coffee.]</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM III: STATUS OF THE SERIES AND PUBLICATION PROSPECTS
                    (Continued)</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi> presented a brief report on the status of
                    the wartime conference volumes. The volume <hi rend="italic">The Conferences at
                        Washington and Quebec, 1943</hi> was released during 1971. The last
                    conference volume, <hi rend="italic">The Conference at Quebec, 1944</hi>, would
                    be published early in 1972. Tardy British clearance of certain documentation had
                    delayed publication, but happily had afforded the opportunity to add certain
                    important papers to the collection. In reply to questions from <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Dougall</hi>
                    explained that the wartime conferences comprised 7 volumes in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The documentation on the
                    Argentia Conference of August 1941 was not the subject of a separate wartime
                    conference volume but was included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    194l, Volume I.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM IV: CLEARANCE AND TECHNICAL EDITING PROBLEMS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> reported to the Committee on current
                    clearance problems [see Attachment 1]. He circulated to the Committee the
                    galleys for the compilation on Italy for 1948 which indicated the extent and
                    nature of the deletions and revisions requested by the Italian Desk.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> explained that appeals of the clearance
                    decisions of Department officers were carried to the Assistant Secretary of
                    State level, sometimes even to the Under Secretary level. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Franklin</hi> observed that the Historical Office could always win
                    these appeals, given sufficient time. But since this might take years, the
                    problem was when to compromise.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> informed the Committee of the
                    establishment during the year of the Department’s Council on Classification
                    Policy under the chairmanship of Deputy Under Secretary Macomber. He explained
                    that the Council had been created to deal with declassification and security
                    problems, which had become acute after the revelation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pentagon Papers</hi>. The Council was not intended to deal specifically
                    with the Historical Office’s clearance problems, but it was hoped that it could
                    be so utilized. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> and <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Varg</hi> observed that the new Council might be regarded as a response
                    to the Advisory Committee’s recommendation of the previous year that top-level
                    Foreign Service officers be utilized to facilitate rapid clearance of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> described to the Committee the problem
                    which has arisen in connection with the clearance of National Security Council
                    [NSC] documents intended for publication in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. In the past the Department of State had assumed
                    responsibility for the declassification of Presidential papers on foreign
                    affairs, subject to the clearance of other interested government agencies. When
                    the first NSC papers were included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    compilations (those for 1947), the same procedure was attempted, but the NSC--a
                    statutory agency--has insisted on its authority to declassify its documents.
                    Procedures for NSC declassification were currently being developed and were
                    being given the very highest-level consideration. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Dougall</hi> explained that resolution of the problem had been made
                    difficult in the absence of direct contact between NSC officials and the
                    Historical Office. The only authorized official channel, through the Executive
                    Secretariat of the Department of State, was cumbersome and prone to delay. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> advised the Committee that he had been
                    unsuccessful in several efforts to get mutual friends to explain the situation
                    to Dr. Kissinger.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> indicated to the Committee that the NSC
                    clearance question, which was causing the most serious delay in the publication
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, had been compounded when
                    the NSC Staff also claimed responsibility for the clearance of all “Presidential
                    papers”. A number of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, otherwise
                    ready for publication, had to be referred to the NSC Staff for a review of such
                    papers, liberally defined. Recently, however, the NSC Staff had decided to
                    forego clearance of Presidential papers subject to their clearance by the
                    appropriate executive departments. In reply to a question by <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi>
                    indicated that the Council on Classification Policy might be used in helping
                    secure clearance of NSC papers. He also mentioned that memoirs and oral history
                    projects had already disclosed the substance of many NSC papers, and NSC 68 had
                    been written about in detail in books and articles.</p>
                <p>The discussion of the NSC clearance question led <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> to raise with the Committee the problem of whether the current
                    in-depth coverage of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series could
                    be maintained. He pointed out that Dr. Gleason had been more interested than
                    previous editors in documenting the formulation of foreign policy; but these
                    were the documents that were often the most sensitive and which held the series
                    back. He asked if the Committee wanted the series to be speeded up at the cost
                    of leaving out such documentation whenever it posed a clearance problem. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> commented that it would be useful to state a
                    goal for the series in the Committee’s report.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> characterized the clearance problem as a
                    dilemma of delay vs. exclusion. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> observed
                    that in a few cases delay did not solve the problem of exclusion. As an example
                    he mentioned certain military contingency plans that would be sensitive for 50
                    or 75 years. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Freeman</hi> appeared to feel that
                    contingency plans were not really necessary for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. The Committee indicated general agreement with this
                    view. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> mentioned that CIA intelligence
                    estimates could not be cleared for 75 years, but he did not believe such
                    estimates were essential for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    inasmuch as their principal points appeared in NSC papers. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out that the difficulties in clearing papers for
                    the 1947 volumes of the series demonstrated the unlikelihood of being able to
                    clear substantially complete special documentary studies on such matters as the
                    Cuban missile crisis in the near future.</p>
                <p>The discussion turned to the problems of clearance within the Bureaus of the
                    Department of State. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> suggested a
                    recommendation for reducing clearance delay by strictly limiting clearance to 6
                    months, and <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> thought that the bureaus wasted
                    much time over papers of no serious import. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Plischke</hi> asked why the maximum time for clearance was not enforced with
                    an ultimatum. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> felt that the speed of
                    clearance had improved, thanks in part to the efforts of the Committee in
                    previous years. The problem was now shifting to the substance rather than the
                    mechanics of clearance. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> agreed that the
                    speed of clearance had improved somewhat, though there were exceptions.
                    Currently the bureaus were taking, on the average, 8 months to clear volumes.
                    The Historical Office requested that clearance be completed within three months
                    but would be satisfied if it were completed in six. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Plischke</hi> suggested that there might be advantage in the designation of
                    a third-party arbiter in deciding clearance issues between the Historical Office
                    and officers of the Department. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> replied
                    that there was no place in the Department’s chain of command for arbiters. In
                    case of deadlock, the Historical Office had to appeal to the next higher
                    authority--in this case, the Assistant Secretaries and the Under Secretary of
                    State. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> thought an Under Secretary might
                    be too busy to take on such questions, and he wondered if some officer in the
                    Under Secretary’s office could be assigned responsibility for making clearance
                    and declassification decisions. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> believed
                    that such a downward delegation of authority would not be effective <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Deener</hi> felt that <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Plischke’s</hi> proposal was for a sidewards delegation of authority and he
                    thought it ought to be tried, particularly in view of the importance of this
                    problem in the Department’s public relations.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> told the Committee that action on
                    clearance delays would be sought through the Council on Classification Policy.
                    The Department, and particularly Deputy Under Secretary Macomber, recognized
                    that only the Historical Office systematically declassified documents, acting as
                    a declassification team. The Council on Classification Policy had considered the
                    possibility of giving the Historical Office the authority to declassify papers
                    of all but the greatest sensitivity, but no decision had been reached.
                    Responding to a question from <hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> indicated that it would not be useful to
                    take the difficult clearance problems to desk officers, because such actions
                    would probably elicit negative decisions. The question was whether the
                    Historical Office could assume greater clearance responsibility and go ahead
                    with the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    without reference to desk officers. He was aware that such a procedure would
                    have risks. The publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of
                    documents dealing with matters of current significance could result in hostile
                    press coverage and create problems that might be momentarily serious. Were the
                    Historical Office to assume the responsibility of publication without prior desk
                    clearance, it would have to become much more familiar with current foreign
                    policy issues around the world.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> asked if the Historical Office wanted the
                    support of the Advisory Committee in asking to be allowed to assume
                    responsibility for clearance. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> pointed out
                    to the Committee that efforts were being made to bring the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series up to 20 years behind currency. In keeping
                    with the spirit of the Bicentennial celebration, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> slogan was “’56 in ’76”. Were the series to draw so close to
                    currency, however, the Department would be unlikely to grant HO the
                    responsibility for clearance. The Historical Office hoped to achieve both the
                    20-year line and the responsibility for clearance, but the latter could probably
                    only be acquired gradually. In the meantime, the Historical Office would
                    probably have to continue to deal with Office and Country Directors in the more
                    sensitive clearance issues.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi> wondered if, after assuming greater
                    clearance responsibility and encountering several troublesome episodes, the
                    Historical Office might become more timid and turn more often to desk officers
                    in clearance questions. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> recognized the
                    dangers involved but welcomed the risk for sake of speeding publication. He felt
                    that turning to desk officers and country directors with clearance problems
                    meant giving up clearance responsibility and inviting Departmental officers to
                    stop publication of sensitive papers. He acknowledged that if <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, cleared without reference to country desk
                    officers, resulted in adverse reaction and complaints from ambassadors, the
                    clearance-declassification authority would be taken away from the Historical
                    Office. <hi rend="underline">Miss Brosius</hi> commented that Country Directors
                    would be reluctant to yield their authority for clearance. The wrath of an
                    ambassador was regarded by a Country Director as a very serious matter.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM V: LUNCH</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for lunch with Deputy Under Secretary of State William B.
                    Macomber, Jr.</p>
                <p>Afternoon Session - 2:45 p.m. to 3:45 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM VI: PROBLEMS OF ACCESS AND DECLASSIFICATION</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Kogan</hi> (Special Assistant to the Director of the
                    Historical Office) briefly reviewed current policy on access to Department
                    files. During the first ten months of 1971, the Department had issued 135 grants
                    of access to the Restricted Period. 11,000 pages of notes and documents had been
                    reviewed, some of which were referred to the Department of State from other
                    government agencies. The Historical Office had actively supported the National
                    Archives in persuading the White House to propose the declassification of World
                    War II records. This would in fact eliminate our Restricted Period and would
                    allow foreign scholars to have the access which they had unfortunately been
                    denied under the Department’s regulations.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> reminded the Committee that the Department
                    of State had in the past been in the vanguard of nations opening their archives.
                    Last year the United Kingdom had announced that they would open their archives
                    through World War II In January 1972. The declassification of most wartime
                    Combined Chiefs of Staff documents was a first step in that program. The
                    Canadians had decided to follow suit, and this combined action made everything
                    better for the scholars and easier for the bureaucrats.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Varg</hi> asked whether the declassification of World
                    War II records would result in the permanent elimination of the Restricted
                    Period. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> said he could not yet answer this
                    question. In principle he did not like the Restricted Period, and he thought
                    that everyone would agree that it would be better to have the files either open
                    or closed. But serious problems would have to be solved before the Open Period
                    could be advanced beyond 1945; more screening would undoubtedly be necessary.
                    The Historical Office was obliged to “feel its way forward” in the entire
                    problem.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> took the opportunity to apprise the
                    Committee of the attention being given within the government to the problems of
                    bulk declassification of documents. The Council on Classification Policy,
                    chaired by Deputy Under Secretary Macomber, had recognized that many government
                    documents older than 10 years no longer required classification but could not be
                    made available to the public because of the absence of an adequate
                    declassification procedure. Various procedures were being considered by the
                    Council. The procedure which appeared to have the most support was the bulk
                    declassification of segments of the files carried out by a special team of
                    officers. He had pointed out that such a procedure would be wholly
                    unsatisfactory. The cost in time and money of such an operation would yield
                    little of real value to the public; scholars and other perceptive observers
                    would recognize the uselessness of what was declassified, and the government
                    would suffer a further loss of credibility. He had maintained before the Council
                    on Classification Policy that it was important to declassify by subject and
                    “from the top down”. Unless the Department was willing to declassify the top
                    documents on any given subject, it would do no good to declassify the great bulk
                    of lower-level material. Furthermore, documents should not be declassified one
                    by one; they had to be compiled into meaningful stories, as was done for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM IV: CLEARANCE AND TECHNICAL EDITING PROBLEMS
                    (resumed)</p>
                <p>At the request of <hi rend="underline">Dr. Claude</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Gleason</hi> concluded that portion of his Report dealing with the problems
                    of technical editing [see Attachment l].</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> noted that much time and effort went into
                    the analytical indexes to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes,
                    and he asked the Committee whether they found the indexes useful enough to be
                    continued at this level. The Committee strongly endorsed the continuation of the
                    current indexes.</p>
                <p rend="center">NEW BUSINESS</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> raised the possibility of including in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series compilations of documents
                    dealing specifically with the methodology of American diplomacy. After being
                    assured that some such methodological papers were already included in the
                    current substantive-compilation format of the series, <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Plischke</hi> asked if it would be possible to enlarge the indexes of
                    volumes to include some of the more current conceptual intangibles of importance
                    to political scientists. <hi rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> and <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Gleason</hi> held out little hope that the current
                    indexing capabilities of the series would permit the inclusion of specialized
                    entries of the sort suggested.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by <hi rend="underline">Dr. LaFeber</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> explained that the publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series had been suspended in order to
                    add two historians to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series was a “service of
                    convenience” which the government could no longer sustain when <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> needed help so badly. Efforts to find academic
                    sponsors interested in continuing the series had so far been unsuccessful. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Franklin</hi> suggested that the three learned
                    societies represented on the Advisory Committee ought to be able to provide the
                    sponsorship necessary to continue the series. The Historical Office was prepared
                    to give its cooperation to any group that undertook this task.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Plischke</hi> recalled that during a discussion with
                    former Assistant Secretary of State Michael Collins, a suggestion had been
                    advanced that additional documentation of the sort previously included in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series be published in the
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Franklin</hi> said that the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> staff itself
                    could not undertake such documentary publication as a regular program. Such
                    materials would have to be prepared and processed by the Historical Office at
                    the expense of the work of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM VII: COMMITTEE’S PRIVATE MEETING</p>
                <p>The open meeting was adjourned at 3:45 p.m., the Historical Office staff
                    withdrew, and the Advisory Committee began its closed session.</p>
                <p>Attachments:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Report to the Advisory Committee, Fifteenth Annual Meeting, November 5,
                        1971</item>
                    <item>2. Status of Volumes, October 1971.</item>
                    <item>3. Status of Volumes, November 1971.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="attachment">
                <p rend="center">Attachment 1</p>
                <p rend="center">Report by Dr. S. Everett Gleason, Chief, <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Division, to the Advisory Committee Fifteenth Annual Meeting,
                    November 5, 1971</p>
                <p rend="underline">Changes in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    Staff</p>
                <p>I thought it useful, particularly for the new members of the Committee, to
                    provide a brief description of the organization of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Division, and recent changes in its staff.</p>
                <p>The Division has three branches, General, Western, and Eastern. The General
                    Branch, headed by Mr. Goodwin, covers our United Nations policy, and
                    multilateral U.S. diplomacy in general--foreign economic policy, atomic energy
                    policy, national security policy and the like. Besides Mr. Goodwin, there are
                    three historians assigned to the Branch. One of these, Miss Joan Brosius, is a
                    Foreign Service Officer, recently assigned to us. We hope for at least three
                    years. I will ask her to stand. Another valuable newcomer is David Mabon who has
                    been with us a little over a year.</p>
                <p>The Western Branch is headed by Fredrick Aandahl, well-known to most of you. His
                    branch is responsible for compiling the documentation on Western Europe, NATO,
                    the Marshall Plan, and European integration, etc. The only new member of this
                    group of five is Mrs. Margaret Martin, recently assigned to us from elsewhere in
                    the Historical Office. We have lost Howard Smyth through retirement.</p>
                <p>The Eastern Branch, until a few months ago, was headed by a real old-timer,
                    Rogers Churchill, who graciously accepted a special assistantship, enabling us
                    to promote William Slany, another Slavic specialist, to be Chief of this
                    branch.</p>
                <p>Regrettably, we shall lose Mr. Churchill, who for years has covered the Soviet
                    Union, by mandatory retirement next September. We have also lost through
                    retirement the services of another veteran, John Reid, who was our specialist on
                    China and the Far East. John Glennon has very capably taken over these
                    assignments, and before his departure Mr. Reid had finished all the volumes on
                    China through 1949.</p>
                <p>Another relative newcomer in this Branch, Evans Gerakas, has been assigned to us
                    from the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> project as was Mr. Glennon.
                    These shifts have unhappily caused <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> to
                    fall into limbo, we hope only temporarily, but without much assurance of revival
                    in the near future.</p>
                <p>The Eastern Branch is responsible for the documentation of U.S. policies in
                    Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union, the Near East and Africa, and the Far
                    East.</p>
                <p>I do not want to leave with the Committee the impression that these branches are
                    water-tight compartments. Lack of sufficient staff numbers in recent years has
                    made it necessary to shift members of one branch to work on compilations
                    theoretically the responsibility of another. It is a tribute to the staff’s
                    competence and flexibility that they produce just about as reliable a product in
                    fields where they profess no specialized knowledge as in ones where they do.</p>
                <p>As you all are aware our two major problems over the last few years, problems
                    which have caused the series to fall some 25 years behind the event, have been
                    insufficient staff and clearance. Until very recently, for instance, we have not
                    been permitted, with one exception, to recruit trained diplomatic historians
                    from outside the Department and the Foreign Service, i.e. from the universities.
                    Happily, there appears to be a thaw in the ice-cap. We are anticipating the
                    arrival of a trained historian from Ohio State by next January and the
                    Department’s budget office has agreed to permit us three more new historians for
                    the next fiscal year. If approval for these three additions actually survives
                    the gauntlet it must still run, there is little question that within a very few
                    years, lack of staff will no longer stand in the way of getting the series back
                    to a lag of twenty years or less, in the next five or six years.</p>
                <p>Clearance, however, is quite a different matter, and we will come to that
                    presently.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Status of the Series and Publication Prospects</p>
                <p>The most disheartening notes in the charts Mr. Aandahl has prepared are, of
                    course, that as of now four volumes for the year 1946 have yet to be published,
                    and that only two volumes were published during the last fiscal year. One of
                    these was, in fact, a Conference volume. Had it not been for clearance problems,
                    new and old, at least four would have appeared in FY 1971.</p>
                <p>We have reason to hope that the remaining volumes for 1946, one General, one on
                    the Far East, and two on China will be out by the end of this fiscal year, June
                    30, 1972.</p>
                <p>Of the eight volumes for 1947, five are in pages and ready to go when we finally
                    get Write House-NSC clearance. The remaining three are in galleys, and two
                    cleared except for the White House, and ready for paging when that clearance
                    comes. In short, we ought to make a very decent showing in the next fiscal year
                    to make up for our dismal showing in the last.</p>
                <p>Of the nine volumes for 1948, one is in pages, seven in galleys, one partially in
                    galleys. Only two have received clearance short of the White House.</p>
                <p>The eight volumes we plan for 1949 are in various stages from incomplete
                    manuscript to galleys. I will not go into detail on each of them, but we are
                    confident that the manuscript for all of them will have been completed by early
                    next summer. In short, most of the staff are now working on the 1950
                    compilations. We are in reach of our goal of compiling a year in a year. If we
                    succeed in getting the additional personnel mentioned earlier, we will easily
                    achieve or surpass this goal. The chief remaining obstacle to getting our
                    volumes out more rapidly will then be clearance.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Clearance and Technical Editing Problems</p>
                <p>Our, so to speak, normal clearance problems--clearance with the policy desks in
                    the State Department, and with Defense, AEC, and other Government agencies, have
                    continued at about their usual level or, with certain glaring exceptions, have
                    actually improved. Defense has been laggard, reflecting an unusual timidity or
                    desire to project a low profile in view of Congressional and public criticism of
                    so many aspects of the military establishment and its costs. This has reached a
                    rather silly stage in Defense when we are requested to omit the names of service
                    attachés, certain of their reports to the ambassadors, and the numbers of the
                    JCS papers we wish to print. CIA is also likely to give us difficulty even
                    though we do not propose to print their intelligence estimates as such.</p>
                <p>I will cite only one instance of what I have just described as glaring
                    exceptions. I refer to the rather long compilation on United States policy
                    towards Italy in 1948. Most of us recall that the main preoccupation of the U.S.
                    government in that year was to prevent a Communist take-over of Italy either by
                    constitutional means or by subversion. The main thrust of our documentation,
                    sent for clearance to the Italian desk in the Department, was naturally directed
                    to this aspect of our Italian policy. The galleys came back to us, after an
                    inordinate length of time, so completely gutted that the reader would scarcely
                    be aware of the existence of the Italian Communist party. The desk even
                    requested us to delete press conferences and quotations from Italian newspapers
                    of the time. If we cannot secure reconsideration of this wholesale slaughter, I
                    would certainly be obliged to recommend the excision of the entire compilation.
                    To print what would be permitted by the desk would simply amount to a fraud. We
                    have never been guilty of that! The galleys in question I have had brought over
                    and if you have time I suggest you glance at them. A quick glance will be quite
                    enough.</p>
                <p>Our major clearance problem, however, is a new one to most of you. It lies in the
                    White House and more particularly in the National Security Council Staff. I will
                    ask Mr. Franklin to go into the grim details of that situation since he knows it
                    at first hand and the rest of us only at second.</p>
                <p rend="center">****************</p>
                <p>Technical editing problems have decidedly eased in the past year. Although the
                    Publication and Reproduction Services Division, who are responsible for the
                    technical editing of our volumes, are worse understaffed than we are, the
                    contracting out of much of this work to the Crowell-Collier Company has been
                    satisfactory and I believe will further improve in time. Also the problem of
                    indexes which has vexed us in the past seems on the way to a satisfactory
                    conclusion. Small as it is the staff of PBR is still able to guide the
                    contractors and to save us from egregious errors on the technical side. The
                    technical excellence of the volumes and their indexes is still a matter of
                    considerable pride to us, quite apart from the substance of the volumes.</p>
                <p>If the Committee have questions of detail that Mr. Franklin and I have not
                    covered, the Branch chiefs, I am sure, can provide many of the answers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
