<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Arthur Kogan to William Franklin, September
                    1972</title>
                <title type="short">Kogan to Franklin, 1972</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-06-23">June 23, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1972-09-22">September 22, 1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1972-09-22-kogan-to-franklin.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 746 KB, 11pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-WW-9: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, Arthur
                    Kogan Files, 1945-1980 (83 D 230), Box 2, Access, History of. Drafted by Arthur
                    Kogan. Posted from an uninitialed carbon copy of the memorandum.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From Arthur Kogan (Special Assistant to the Director of the
                    Historical Office) to William Franklin (Director of the Historical
                    Office)</head>
                <dateline>September 22, 1972</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Access to the Department’s Records: Historical Survey</p>
                <p>First Phase (to 1921): Without Specific Regulations</p>
                <p>It appears that prior to 1921 no clear-cut rules or procedures were in existence
                    defining in precise terms the Department’s policy on access to its records by
                    outside researchers. But undoubtedly there were accepted procedures, practices
                    and traditions on the basis of which the responsible officers of the Department
                    made their decisions about admitting specific individuals or categories of
                    persons to the files. The ill-defined nature of the Department’s access policy
                    may be gauged from a report given at the meeting of the AHA in 1893 and
                    incorporated in the annual report of the AHA for 1894 in which it was stated
                    that “historical papers in the State Department are not accessible to the
                    historical student except as a special favor...”</p>
                <p>Even though the terms under which access to the files could be granted were not
                    clearly defined, there is sufficient evidence that the files of the Department
                    were used to a considerable extent by historical researchers in the first two
                    decades of the 20th century. On the basis of correspondence in decimal file
                    116.2 the following conclusions may be drawn with regard to the conditions under
                    which access to the files was granted:</p>
                <p>All the records since the beginnings of the Republic were in the custody of the
                    Department and were serviced by the personnel responsible for these materials.
                    Researchers had to make applications for access with each case being decided on
                    an <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> basis. There was no “open” period as we
                    would understand this term. Researchers had to submit their notes for clearance
                    by Departmental officers regardless of the period covered in their research. It
                    seems that there was relatively “free” access to the files up to 1850 or 1860
                    but that it was much more difficult to gain permission to consult materials of
                    the subsequent period. Yet even notes from documents of the pre-1860 period
                    could be withheld. Correspondence in the files indicates, for instance, that in
                    1916 notes were withheld relating to the diplomatic papers of 1849-1851
                    (116.2/34). There were even outright refusals of access to such early materials
                    as in the case of a Dominican scholar who had wanted to see diplomatic
                    correspondence relating to Santo Domingo in the period 1845-1869 (116.2/146). As
                    late as 1921, Henry Wriston, who had been allowed to see papers relating to the
                    Special Agents of the pre-Civil War period, was refused permission to expand his
                    research into the post-1861 period (116.2/203). In inter-Departmental
                    correspondence in 1920 it was stated explicitly that only under exceptional
                    circumstances had the Department allowed examination of its archives subsequent
                    to 1860. This statement was made in connection with a refusal of access
                    involving a researcher who had wanted to see secret files of the period
                    1861-1865 (116.2/195, 196).</p>
                <p>In this early period there was no relationship between the publication of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and access to the files. Since <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> stayed within 10 years to currency
                    until into World War I and as access was granted primarily to older records, the
                    question of tying <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to access could not
                    arise.</p>
                <p>During this early part of the 20th century researchers in the Department’s files
                    were accommodated only to the extent that the personnel was able to service the
                    records and deal with the researchers. Thus, after the United States entered
                    World War I, all applications for access were rejected because of the pressure
                    of business. For the next 2-3 years researchers were discouraged from making
                    application because the Department, as it informed one of them, lacked
                    facilities and personnel “to properly supervise procurement of records and
                    examination of notes” (116.2/175).</p>
                <p>Second Phase (1921-1938): The Departmental Orders</p>
                <p>The second phase of the Department’s policy on access was inaugurated by the
                    issuance of the first set of regulations dealing specifically with the question
                    of research access to records.</p>
                <p>Departmental Order 210 of May 28, 1921, was issued in compliance with the spirit
                    of the Congressional Act of March 3, 1901 (31 Stat. 1039) which provided that
                    “facilities for study and research in the Government Departments ... shall be
                    afforded to scientific investigators and duly qualified individuals, students,
                    and graduates of institutions of learning ... under such rules as the heads of
                    the Departments ... may prescribe.”</p>
                <p>The Departmental Order emphasized that space and personnel limitations would
                    permit servicing only a few researchers at a time; that records would not be
                    open to undergraduates; that the applicant must be known to the Department or be
                    “duly accredited by sources known to the Department”; that the Department must
                    be convinced of the “responsibility” of the applicant and of the purpose of his
                    research being “legitimate and useful”. The Order also stipulated that material
                    on “pending business” or material which might prove to be “injurious to the
                    public interest” must not be used and that notes, at the discretion of the
                    Department, were “subject to inspection”.</p>
                <p>Departmental Order 210 was superseded by Departmental Order 309, issued August
                    11, 1924. This Order did not change the basic policy set forth in the earlier
                    Order but it was more detailed with regard to procedures. It is to be noted that
                    neither Order limited access chronologically. Yet it can be assumed that there
                    was no departure from the existing practice of not giving access to any
                    materials less than 25 years old.</p>
                <p>A further revolution in the Department’s access policy was inaugurated by the
                    creation of an Archives Section in the Division of Publications which was given
                    custody of the Department’s records prior to August 1906. This new arrangement
                    also affected access policy, as reflected in Departmental Order 377 of June 15,
                    1926, which gave the Division of Publication supervision over outside
                    researchers. The Chief of that Division was given responsibility for conferring
                    with all interested offices in the Department “as to what, if any, of the
                    correspondence prior to August 16, 1906, may not be available for purposes of
                    research to competent students”. It was also stated that “the practice in this
                    regard shall be similar to that which is in use in the selection of documents
                    for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>”.</p>
                <p>Departmental Order 377 established a definite limit beyond which research in the
                    Department’s records was not to be carried out. Yet it would certainly not be
                    accurate to characterize the period prior to August 1906 as a truly “open” or
                    even a “restricted” period as we would understand it. A letter of June 1927,
                    written by Tyler Dennett, stated that the archives of the Department, for
                    purposes of general research, were not open beyond the year 1898 although
                    certain subjects “might be pursued down to 1906” (116.2/4440). Moreover, the
                    records were not available to all members of the public but only to “professors,
                    publicists, doctors, doctoral candidates and persons of established position in
                    the community”. A letter from Mr. Wynne, dated October 22, 1927, made it clear
                    that only persons in those categories would be given access to the pre-1906
                    files. Finally, notes taken by such persons were subject to review by the
                    Department which reserved the right to refuse permission to publish or to use
                    the material in the files (116.2/5640).</p>
                <p>While under the provisions of Departmental Order 377 access was not granted to
                    files after August 1906, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    were released within 9 years of currency. During the next twelve years, from
                    1926-1938, this gap between publication and currency increased to 15 years.
                    Access was still in back of the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> when significant changes in access policy occurred in the
                    period 1938-1939.</p>
                <p>Third Phase (1938-1946): Opening the Records in the National Archives</p>
                <p>An important event in the evolution of the Department’s policy with respect to
                    records was the establishment of the National Archives in 1936. Between 1937 and
                    1939 the Department transferred to the National Archives its basic file of
                    diplomatic and consular correspondence for the period 1789-1906 as well as
                    diplomatic and consular post records of the period 1793-1937 and other
                    miscellaneous groups of records. No restrictions were placed on the use of these
                    files, except for certain categories of the kind now covered by Restrictions
                    Statements. Thus, only after the transfer of the old policy records to the
                    National Archives can we speak of a truly “open” period of the files in the
                    present meaning of the term.</p>
                <p>Since the basic file of Departmental records of the period 1789-1906 was
                    generally open to researchers in the National Archives, a new Departmental Order
                    (751 of April 5, 1938) clearly applied only to post-1906 records. This Order
                    regulated the use of the Department’s records by outside researchers more or
                    less along the lines of the previous order, especially with respect to
                    applications and review of notes. No specific time limitations were placed on
                    the use of records but it was stipulated in this Order that files “which are in
                    current use or which cannot be made public without the disclosure of confidences
                    reposed in the Department or which adversely affect the public interest” should
                    not be made available to researchers.<note place="foot" n="1">Under the liberal
                        provisions of this Order of 1933 Samuel Flagg Bemis was allowed to examine
                        notes on records of the most recent period in connection with his study of
                        United States policy toward Latin America. But servicing the records for him
                        and examining and evaluating his notes proved to be a big burden to the
                        responsible officers of the Department. The limitation on access in the
                        Departmental Order of 1939 discussed in the next paragraph may have been
                        partly promoted by the experiences with Professor Bemis (116.2/926, 930,
                        931).</note></p>
                <p>But the provisions of Departmental Order 751 were soon changed under the pressure
                    of events preceding the outbreak of World War II. Revised regulations set forth
                    in Departmental Order 796 of June 19, 1939 stipulated that in view of the
                    international situation confidential or unpublished records of the Department
                    dated later than December 31, 1918, would no longer be made available to outside
                    researchers. But each year the Department would give consideration to the
                    situation then existing “with a view to advancing the date fixed whenever such
                    action is deemed possible”. Records dated prior to December 31, 1918, “or such
                    subsequent date as may be fixed by the Department” might be made available to
                    persons who are not officials of the United States Government, subject to
                    certain conditions. The categories of persons to whom permission might be given
                    to consult the records “through the date fixed by the Department” were similar
                    to those enumerated in the Departmental Order of 1926. It is also to be noted
                    that the Order of 1939 like the preceding one of 1938 allowed aliens to submit
                    applications for access to the records if they were accompanied by letters from
                    the respective foreign mission certifying that the applicant was “favorably
                    known” to that mission and that the latter was “familiar with the purpose of the
                    applicant’s work”.</p>
                <p>Thus, by 1939 there was a genuinely “open” period of the files as a result of the
                    transfer of unrestricted records through 1906 to the National Archives, while
                    the “closed” period (after 1918) and the “restricted” period (1907-1918) were
                    defined in Departmental Order 796 of June 19, 1939.</p>
                <p>By 1939, when the open period extended through 1906 and the restricted period
                    through 1918 the annual volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series had completed coverage through 1924. After the initial transfer of
                    records to the National Archives in 1938 and 1939, the end of the open period
                    was normally advanced when additional files of portions of files were sent to
                    the Archives. In November 1942 that date was advanced to December 31, 1910, and
                    in September 1945 to December 31, 1913.<note place="foot" n="2">This information
                        is based on various memoranda in our old “Access” and “Regulations” folders
                        drawn from items in file 116.2.</note> With respect to the records
                    transferred to the National Archives, it is to be kept in mind (as was mentioned
                    earlier) that certain restrictions were placed on specific categories of records
                    such as passport files, unsettled claims, Foreign Service inspection reports,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>Parallel to the advance of the terminal date of the “open” period as a result of
                    the transfer of records to the National Archives, there were two advances of the
                    “restricted” period. By Departmental Order 955 of July 18, 1941, the terminal
                    date of the period of restricted access (subject to applications to the
                    Department and review of notes) was moved from December 31, 1918 to December 31,
                    1920. By Departmental regulation 420.1 of March 15, 1946, that date was advanced
                    to December 31, 1932.</p>
                <p>Fourth Phase (1947-1963): The Three Periods of Access</p>
                <p>In 1947 the Department for the first time issued a regulation (420.1, May 5,
                    1947) which dealt with all its records in terms of three periods of access.
                    Unpublished records prior to January 1, 1922 (except for specially restricted
                    categories such as passports, citizenship, etc.) were “available for inspection
                    by the general public in the National Archives, subject to its regulations”. On
                    January 1, 1948, and each year thereafter until January 1, 1955, this date was
                    to be automatically advanced one year. Unpublished records in the period between
                    the open date and January 1, 1933 “or each subsequent date as may be fixed by
                    the Department” could be made available under basically the same conditions that
                    applied to the use of the post-1906 records under the Departmental Order of June
                    19, 1939. Records of the “closed” period (defined as dated later than January 1,
                    1933) were not to be made available to outside researchers except in
                    circumstances “determined to be exceptional”. A determination to permit access
                    to records of the “closed” period could be made only “on the grounds that the
                    interests of national policy are served thereby”.</p>
                <p>These regulations issued first in March 1947 were revised in March 1948 (420.1 of
                    March 12, 1948). This revised version of 1948 listed for the first time the
                    three periods of access as “open”, “restricted”, and “closed”. The open period
                    was the period prior to January 1, 1923; the restricted period was the period
                    between the end of the open period and January 1, 1933; and the closed period
                    was the period after January 1, 1933.</p>
                <p>In 1947 and 1948 when the regulations described above were issued, the annual <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for 1932 were being completed.
                    Therefore, the closed period of the files (after January 1, 1933) was
                    essentially the period in advance of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    But the special <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes “Peace and War:
                    United States Foreign Policy 1931-1941” and “Japan: 1931-1941” which featured
                    documents through 1941 had already been published in 1943, at a time when the
                    “restricted” period of access under Departmental Order 955 of July 18, 1941
                    terminated with December 31, 1920, and when the records in the National Archives
                    were not open beyond 1910.</p>
                <p>The Division into three periods of access (open, closed, and restricted) remained
                    a permanent feature of the Department’s regulations on access to records until
                    January 1972.</p>
                <p>In regulation 183.21-2 of January 4, 1951 the open period was defined as the
                    period prior to January 1, 1926. In January 1, 1952, and each year thereafter
                    until January 1, 1955, the terminal date of the open period was to be advanced
                    automatically one year.</p>
                <p>The period described as “restricted” in the regulations of 1948 was now
                    designated “limited-access” period and defined as the ten-year period
                    immediately following the open period. Use of the records of this period was to
                    be confined to “qualified researchers and other persons demonstrating a
                    legitimate need for the information requested”.</p>
                <p>The period following the “limited-access” period was designated the “closed”
                    period. Records of that period were not made “normally” available to
                    non-governmental researchers. Exceptions to this rule were to be limited to
                    “mature scholars” undertaking research regarded by the Department as being
                    “desirable in the national interest”. These regulations also contained detailed
                    provisions on the “limitations on the use of records”, i.e., on various
                    restrictions applying to specific categories of records, and on the clearance of
                    notes taken by researchers.</p>
                <p>Regulations 183.21-183.26 were revised on July 8, 1953. There was no change with
                    respect to the “open” period. Its terminal date was January 1, 1928 and it was
                    to be advanced one year each January 1 until 1955 as had been anticipated in the
                    regulations of 1951. But the “limited-access” period was now defined as the
                    period from the end of the “open” period to January 1, 1942. Thus, the terminal
                    date of the “limited-access” period was advanced four years beyond the date
                    which would have been reached under the automatic ten-year period established in
                    1951. The “closed” period was the period after January 1, 1942. The “larger
                    portion of the records of the closed period” was not available to
                    non-governmental researchers, but exceptions could be made in the case of
                    “qualified researchers undertaking broad studies regarded by the Department as
                    desirable in the national interest[”] and in the case of studies “more limited
                    in scope involving non-sensitive and generally unclassified materials”. The
                    advance of the “limited-access” period through 1941 presumably reflected the use
                    of the Department’s files of the early phase of World War II by prominent
                    historians who had been given special access to these materials.</p>
                <p>The next revision of these regulations issued December 7, 1956 (185.41-185.45)
                    eliminated the yearly advance of the terminal date of the open period. The
                    “open” period ended with January 1, 1930 and the “limited-access” period still
                    with January 1, 1942. Records subsequent to that date remained in the closed
                    period, but the exceptions provided for in the regulations of 1953 still
                    applied.</p>
                <p>Between 1948 and 1956 the terminal date of the “restricted” or “limited-access”
                    period advanced beyond the date covered by the most recent annual volume of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. In 1951 the
                    “limited-access” period terminated with December 31, 1936, while <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was completing coverage for 1934. In
                    1953 when the “limited-access” period terminated with January 1, 1942, <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had covered all of 1935 and was
                    beginning to publish volumes for 1936. By 1956, with the “limited-access” period
                    still terminating January 1, 1942, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had
                    brought out all but one of the volumes for 1939. But the special <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on the conferences at Yalta and
                    Malta published in 1955 contained material of 1944 and 1945 and thus opened up
                    highly significant materials that were not available to researchers in the
                    “limited-access” period. The special volumes on the conferences at Cairo,
                    Tehran, and Potsdam published in 1960 and 1961 put additional high-level
                    diplomatic papers of the period 1943-1945 in the public domain.</p>
                <p>Fifth Phase (since 1963): Access Tied to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi></p>
                <p>On August 15, 1963, new regulations were issued (1854.2-1854.5) which introduced
                    a significant change in the Department’s policy on access to records. As
                    explained in a memorandum of December 1963 by the Director of the Historical
                    Office, the three different periods of access were retained but the fixed dates
                    were replaced by a progressive opening of files tied to the publication of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The “closed” period was now
                    defined as the period in advance of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series and its beginning date was to be revised automatically as the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes were being released. The
                    “restricted” period (formerly “limited-access” period) was defined as the ten
                    years in back of the “closed” period. The “open” period covered the years prior
                    to the beginning date of the “restricted” period. The regulations of August 1963
                    no longer mentioned the possible exceptions with respect to access to records of
                    the closed period.</p>
                <p>Since <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had published through 1942 when
                    the revised regulations of 1963 were issued, the terminal date of the
                    “restricted” period was advanced to January l, 1943 and that of the “open”
                    period to January 1, 1933.</p>
                <p>On August 9, 1966 it was announced in Department of State press release 183 that
                    the Department’s records were now open in the National Archives up to 30 years
                    from the current year. This flat 30-year rule meant that records which
                    previously had been open through 1933 were now open to January 1, 1936. As <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had completed coverage for 1943 by
                    1966, the restricted period extended from 1936 through 1943.</p>
                <p>These changes were incorporated in regulations issued July 11, 1966
                    (1855.1-1855.4). It should perhaps be noted that the regulations of 1966
                    explicitly excluded foreign nationals from access to records of the “restricted”
                    period.</p>
                <p>The 30-year rule established in 1966 has remained a feature of the Department’s
                    access regulations to this day. The provisions applying to the “restricted” and
                    “closed” periods did not change until January 1972. But a significant new
                    element into the Department’s regulations was introduced as a result of the
                    passage of the Freedom of Information Act (Public Law 89-487) which came into
                    effect July 4, 1967. Departmental regulations issued July 5, 1967 (5 FAM 480)
                    and slightly revised May 21, 1968 incorporated in Appendix A the provisions of
                    CF[M?] 22, Part 6 which dealt with the availability of the Department’s records
                    to the public. Sections 6.1-6.8 contained provisions covering the right of
                    members of the public to request copies of “identifiable” unclassified records
                    from the Chief of the Department’s Records Services Division in accordance with
                    the Freedom of Information Act.</p>
                <p>Another innovation of the regulations of 1967 was a provision permitting “former
                    incumbents of senior positions” within the Department to have access to records
                    “relating to their own activities” unless the Secretary determined that such
                    access was not in the national interest. Persons who enjoyed such access which
                    could extend to records of the “closed” as well as “restricted” periods were
                    required to submit their notes or manuscripts for review by the Department prior
                    to publication.</p>
                <p>At the time when the revised regulations of 1967 were issued, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> was about to complete coverage for the year 1944.
                    Accordingly, the restricted period ended with 1944 and the closed period began
                    with January 1, 1945.</p>
                <p>On May 15, 1969, an announcement was made in press release 119 that the
                    Department, while not changing its “standing regulation” for the opening of
                    records 30 years old, had determined that the records of the years from 1939
                    through 1941 would henceforth be treated “as though they were in the ‘open’
                    period.” Thus, the effective terminal date of the open period was moved from
                    December 31, 1938 to December 31, 1941. As <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> had completed coverage of 1945 in the course of 1969, the
                    closed period began with January 1, 1946 and the restricted period extended from
                    1942 through 1945.</p>
                <p>No further changes in the access situation took place until 1972. On January 21
                    of that year the Department announced in press release 19 that it had
                    declassified almost all of its foreign policy records for the years 1942-1945
                    inclusive. This action “taken by special administrative decision” was not
                    intended, however, to void the Department’s “standing regulation” providing for
                    the opening of records 30 years old.</p>
                <p>This action by the Department eliminated for all practical purposes the
                    “restricted” period of access and left in existence only an “open” and a
                    “closed” period of the files. This became even clearer when the release of all
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for 1946 was followed by an
                    announcement by the Department in press release 193 of August 10, 1972, stating
                    that the Department had declassified almost all of its foreign policy records
                    through 1946. Like the earlier decisions regarding the records of the period
                    1942-1945, this opening of the files through 1946 was not to be interpreted as a
                    departure from the standing regulation providing for the opening of the
                    Department’s records 30 years old. Moreover, by August 19 the opening of records
                    after 30 years had become mandatory for all Government Departments under the
                    terms of Executive Order 11652 of March 1972, which became effective on June 1,
                    1972.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
