<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1972</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1972</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-19">May 19, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1972-11-03">November 3, 1972</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1972-11-03-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 231 KB, 12pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1972—Minutes. Limited Official Use. The
                    schedule of manuscript completion, mentioned under “Agenda Item 5,” is not
                    posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn67">Footnote 67</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Record of the 1972 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 3, 1972</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>David R. Deener, Provost and Dean of the Graduate School, Tulane
                                University, New Orleans, Louisiana 70118 (American Society of
                                International Law)</item>
                            <item>Alwyn V. Freeman, Member, Board of Editors, <hi rend="italic">The
                                    American Journal of International Law</hi>, Washington, D.C.
                                20008 (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Walter LaFeber, Professor of History, Cornell University, Ithaca,
                                New York 14850 (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Armin H. Rappaport, Professor of History, University of
                                California, La Jolla, California 92037 (American Historical
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Richard C. Snyder [Not present], Director, Mershon Center, Ohio
                                State University, Columbus, Ohio 43210 (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Paul A. Varg, Professor of History, Michigan State University,
                                East Lansing, Michigan 48823 (American Historical
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>H. Bradford Westerfield, Professor of Political Science, Yale
                                University, New Haven, Connecticut 06520 (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>William D. Blair, Jr., Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                                Public Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>Homer L. Calkin</item>
                            <item>John A. Bernbaum</item>
                            <item>Joan E. Brosius</item>
                            <item>Mary P. Chapman</item>
                            <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                            <item>Herbert A. Fine</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                            <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                            <item>Margaret G. Martin</item>
                            <item>Nina Noring</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>Lisle A. Rose</item>
                            <item>Beverly Z. Rowsome</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>Opening Session - 9:00 a.m. - 12:15 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 1: OPENING REMARKS</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin opened the meeting by introducing members of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> staff and also members of the Historical Studies
                    Division. Mr. Franklin observed that the work of the latter Division is closer
                    to that of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division than ever
                    before because of rising interest in the post-World War II period. Historical
                    Studies does both classified and unclassified projects, an example of the latter
                    being <hi rend="italic">Documents on Germany, 1944-1970</hi>, a compilation
                    prepared last year for the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations. Mr. Franklin
                    concluded by introducing Mr. Arthur Kogan, Special Assistant to the Director,
                    who is in charge of declassification and of liaison with the National Archives
                    and other agencies concerned with documentary problems.</p>
                <p>At 9:15 a.m. Mr. Blair joined the meeting. He welcomed the members of the
                    Advisory Committee on behalf of Secretary of State Rogers and stated that the
                    Committee’s advice over the years had been most helpful in speeding up the
                    production of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The past
                    year, he continued, had seen great strides in the acceleration of publication of
                    the series. In the century since the project began there had been a steady and
                    growing gap between diplomatic events and the publication of documentary
                    material relating to them in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. But in the past year alone, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had
                    produced no less than 10 volumes including the last one relating to the wartime
                    conferences, the last volumes dealing with 1946, and nearly all volumes dealing
                    with the events of 1947. Concurrently, there had been a substantial increase of
                    staff in the Historical Office although State Department rolls had been cut 15%
                    over the past several years. Moreover, the Historical Office had been successful
                    in obtaining a substantial increase in operating budget. For the fiscal year
                    1972, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had been allotted a budget of
                    $224,000 but had actually spent $256,000. For FY 1973 <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is budgeted at $336,000 and for FY 1974 the budget request is
                    $576,000.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair stated that there had been several reasons for this substantial
                    increase in support for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                    Scholars had encouraged the Department to reverse the widening gap between
                    events and their documentation in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. The
                    White House had responded and on March 8 President Nixon had issued his order
                    that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> close the gap to twenty years
                    within three years. William B. Macomber, Jr., Deputy Under Secretary of State
                    for Management, had played an important role in the impetus which had been given
                    to the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair stated that every effort would be made to meet the new target, but
                    cautioned that the battle had not yet been won. Even with the Presidential
                    directive and the related Executive Order on classification (of the same date)
                    there remained obstacles: conflicts over security policy, the sheer bulk of
                    work, and a manifold clearance problem. He promised that the Bureau of Public
                    Affairs would do everything possible to continue the substantial progress made
                    in the past year.</p>
                <p rend="center">[Mr. Blair left the meeting at 9:24 a.m.]</p>
                <p>Mr. Freeman asked how soon the budget increases would lessen the publication gap
                    to twenty years. Mr. Franklin replied that the budgetary projection for fiscal
                    1974 was “astronomical” by previous standards and that money of itself no longer
                    constituted any hindrance to narrowing the gap.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 2: SELECTION OF CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>Mr. Deener was elected unanimously to serve for the coming year.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 3: DATE OF MEETINGS</p>
                <p>Discussion turned to the possibility of choosing a new date for the Committee’s
                    meetings, since the first Friday in November had proved inconvenient for some
                    members. Mr. Deener’s suggestion of the second Friday in November was accepted
                    by the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 4: CHANGES IN THE <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN
                        RELATIONS</hi> STAFF</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted the retirement of S. Everett Gleason and the latter’s
                    replacement as Chief of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division by
                    Fredrick Aandahl, who had had long experience with the Historical Office and,
                    previously, with the Jefferson Papers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl noted the retirement of Rogers P. Churchill, for many years
                    responsible for documentation of Soviet-American relations. He introduced new
                    members of the staff. John Bernbaum had taken his doctorate at the University of
                    Maryland in June. Paul Claussen was a doctoral candidate at George Washington
                    University. Lisle Rose, a Ph.D. from the University of California at Berkeley,
                    had taught at the University of Nebraska and at Carnegie-Mellon University in
                    Pittsburgh. N. Stephen Kane, of the University of Wisconsin - Oshkosh, had
                    joined the staff as a visiting fellow sponsored by the National Historical
                    Publications Commission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin noted that the Historical Office was filling its vacancies and the
                    three new positions in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff with
                    professional historians, a development which had happily reversed the
                    Department’s practice of sending Foreign Service Officers to the Office for
                    temporary tours. FSO’s often considered duty at the Historical Office a
                    digression from their careers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport asked if FSO’s who did temporary duty with the Historical Office
                    might not be useful later in promoting the influence of the Office throughout
                    the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that in the past senior FSO’s had been assigned to the
                    Historical Office to aid in clearance procedures, and that this had been
                    beneficial. However, FSO’s regardless of grade had not always had the training
                    necessary for research in the files.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin agreed with Mr. Goodwin that Joan Brosius, an FSO currently assigned
                    to the Historical Office, was the exception that proved the rule.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 5: STATUS OF THE SERIES AND PUBLICATION PROSPECTS</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin described the reorganization of the geographical branches of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Division. A schedule of projected
                    manuscript completion dates through 1976 was passed out [copy attached]. Both
                    Mr. Franklin and Mr. Aandahl emphasized that manuscript completion dates were
                    not to be confused with publication dates, and that the clearance process
                    remained unpredictable.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Rappaport, Mr. Aandahl described the
                    manuscript preparation process. He noted in particular that each branch tried to
                    project in advance the major compilations and the space allowable for each. This
                    was now necessary because of the huge volume of documentation. Discovery of
                    important unexpected material could of course alter these projections.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin mentioned that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had moved
                    away from diplomatic correspondence to an emphasis on top-level policy goals and
                    policymaking. Planning was therefore more necessary than ever before in order to
                    exclude marginal compilations at the outset.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl then briefly outlined the compilation process and the various types
                    of files available in the Department to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> researcher.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber inquired whether the Historical Office was able to obtain documents
                    from the Presidential libraries. He also asked if use was made of the Acheson
                    papers. Messrs. Franklin, Aandahl, and Slany pointed out that we usually had
                    received excellent cooperation from the FDR Library, that the Truman Library
                    posed a problem because President Truman had not released many of his papers,
                    and that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> researchers who had recently
                    screened the Acheson papers had found them to contain few documents not already
                    in Departmental files.</p>
                <p>Mr. Varg asked if <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had access to the
                    files of other agencies that take part in the making of foreign policy. Mr.
                    Rappaport inquired if <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff were
                    allowed to make their own search of Defense Department files. In reply Mr.
                    Dougall noted that it was not necessary to make an initial search of outside
                    files because substantial materials from other agencies and interdepartmental
                    mechanisms (including NSC) were in Department files. Mr. Aandahl stated that
                    other agencies, including the Defense Department, generally provided the
                    Historical Office with copies of specific documents on request. Mr. Franklin
                    added, however, that some agencies had not yet established procedures for making
                    their materials available to scholars. Both Mr. Franklin and Mr. Dougall
                    stressed that the current main problem of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> was not access to other agencies’ files but clearance of
                    materials originating in them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield suggested legislation requiring past Presidents to turn over
                    their papers to the Library of Congress or National Archives. Mr. Franklin
                    pointed out such a law might lead to destruction of some papers and that current
                    practice was a compromise whereby presidential papers become the property of the
                    Government at the latest upon a President’s death. Presidents, however, retained
                    the option of bequeathing their papers to their heirs.</p>
                <p rend="center">[At 10:30 a.m. the Committee recessed for coffee.]</p>
                <p>Upon resumption Mr. Aandahl completed his exposition of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> production process, touching on the part played by
                    technical editors of the Publications Division (PBR), the contract editing
                    performed by Crowell-Collier, and the work of the Government Printing Office. In
                    reply to questions by Mr. Freeman and Mr. Rappaport regarding the security
                    handling of the documents by editors and printers in advance of clearance, Mr.
                    Dougall reviewed the procedures followed in the handling of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> manuscript and galleys, and Mr. Franklin emphasized
                    that the procedures had approval of the Department’s security unit.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that increased budget had enabled the Historical Office to work
                    out an arrangement with the Government Printing Office whereby the Office on
                    occasion paid a surcharge permitting the accelerated schedule for proofs,
                    printing and binding.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl pointed out that the schedule of dates for the delivery of manuscript
                    volumes to the technical editors was based on approximately eight months and two
                    full-time researchers per volume.</p>
                <p>To a question by Mr. Westerfield as to why the clearance process is begun after
                    galleys are in print, rather than in the manuscript stage, Mr. Aandahl replied
                    that printed proofs were much more acceptable to clearing officers. Mr. Goodwin
                    and Mr. Slany pointed out that for some documents bearing special security
                    classifications, clearance was in fact initiated before the galley stage.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin responded to a question from Mr. Freeman concerning the cost of
                    putting <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> into galleys before clearance.
                    The original manuscript was usually hard to read because of its bulkiness and
                    poor legibility . Galley proof provided a clean and well-printed version with
                    multiple copies for simultaneous clearance and proofreading. The busy desk
                    officers in the Department were likely to complete their review of copy much
                    more quickly in this galley form. Mr. Dougall pointed out the advantage that
                    proofreading of galleys could proceed at the same time as clearance.</p>
                <p>In answer to a question by Mr. LaFeber, Mr. Aandahl indicated that there was a
                    likelihood that the 1953 volumes would be published by 1976. Mr. LaFeber pointed
                    out that this was not a twenty but a twenty-three year lag in publication, and
                    that the slogan “1956 by 1976” apparently referred to compilation rather than
                    publication. Mr. Aandahl felt that unless the scope of coverage were sharply
                    reduced it would be unrealistic to expect to proceed faster.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport asked whether lack of personnel was the principal obstacle to
                    speeding publication. Mr. Aandahl replied that the most difficult problem was
                    clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin observed that there was some time lost in training before new
                    members of the staff became fully effective. He had recommended, when the
                    Presidential directive was being considered, that five years, rather than three,
                    should be allotted for bringing the series to the twenty-year line.</p>
                <p>Answering questions from Mr. LaFeber and Mr. Freeman as to when the twenty-year
                    line would be achieved, Mr. Franklin estimated that publication could be
                    expected a year or so after the compilation completion dates shown on the chart.
                    At least some volumes should be published at the twenty-year interval by 1976 or
                    1977.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber then made a comparison between the publication schedules presented at
                    last year’s meeting and those of the present meeting and noted that certain
                    volumes in the clearance stage last year were still in that stage. Mr. Aandahl
                    replied that NSC clearance had been the problem here. Recently, after three
                    years of effort, the Historical Office and the Bureau of Public Affairs had
                    succeeded in obtaining the clearance of NSC materials for the first time. Once
                    the 1948 volumes were cleared, NSC clearance for 1949 and 1950 should be much
                    easier.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber then asked about the progress of the new “crisis” compilations
                    suggested by the White House in August 1971. Mr. Franklin said the Historical
                    Studies Division’s pilot project in this area had not gained necessary
                    declassification action.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin emphasized that in such compilations covert operations figured
                    prominently, and he asked the Committee for help in deciding how to deal with
                    them. To include references to them might hold up clearance. Mr. Rappaport asked
                    whether clearances could be obtained if the material relating to covert matters
                    were eliminated, to which Mr. Franklin replied that even a minimum compilation
                    on the pilot project had not been cleared.</p>
                <p>In answer to a question by Mr. Deener as to whether the clearances for 1948 and
                    1949 would cover most types of clearance problems coming up through 1956, Mr.
                    Franklin answered in the affirmative, pointing out that he hoped for increased
                    speed after the current clearances were obtained.</p>
                <p>In response to Mr. Varg’s question concerning the availability in the National
                    Archives of documents deleted from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Mr.
                    Franklin explained that any document deleted from the series during the
                    clearance process is put in a special blue-bordered envelope and sent to the
                    National Archives together with a list of all such documents. If a researcher
                    begins work in a file where such a document occurs, the document is sent back to
                    the Department for review. Hopefully most such documents will be declassified
                    when thirty years old unless the head of the originating agency specifically
                    exempts them from automatic declassification.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport asked if Archives sent the blue-envelope documents back to the
                    Department without notifying researchers. Mr. Franklin replied that researchers
                    would probably know of their existence through references.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall noted that over the years one or two subjects had been totally
                    removed. One dealt with military bases, and had been covered by an editorial
                    note so that the volume in which it was to appear need not be held up
                    indefinitely.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin pointed out that documents were regularly omitted if they concerned
                    certain continuing problems between states abroad where the United States was
                    somewhat involved -- e.g., Latin American boundary disputes. Such documents were
                    excluded because of the extreme sensitivity of matters still in negotiation;
                    releasing them might impede current diplomatic business. Mr. Franklin said that
                    he knew of no case where deletion had been used to cover errors in policy or
                    personal mistakes, and he emphasized that he was striking sharply at this
                    accusation because it was now heard so frequently. The deleted documents tended
                    to deal with covert matters, with ongoing disputes, or with matters where a
                    position taken twenty years ago would still affect seriously the conduct of
                    current business.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question by Mr. Westerfield as to whether there would have to be a
                    time lag of decades if covert operations were to be covered, Mr. Franklin stated
                    that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had no intention of covering
                    covert operations as such, and that the discussion had been over incidental
                    references to them. Even the references would hold the series back.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield said that if the choice were between dropping back to twenty-five
                    years to include references to such operations or publishing at twenty years
                    without them, he would opt for the former. Mr. Deener was of the opinion that
                    dropping back to twenty-five years would not result in the inclusion of more
                    such materials in the series. Mr. Rappaport expressed the view that if the
                    question arose as to whether to hold up publication of a volume in order to
                    include coverage of covert operations, the decision should depend on the
                    individual case.</p>
                <p>When Mr. Deener called for discussion of any additional problems which might
                    exist in the areas of editing or clearance, Mr. Aandahl called upon the Branch
                    Chiefs. Mr. Goodwin pointed out that in the case of the General Branch, the
                    subject of national security policy was the principal source of clearance
                    difficulties. The compilation for the year 1950 was illustrative of this. It
                    involved all the sensitive agencies of the government: NSC, Defense, AEC, and
                    CIA. Volume I for 1947, which had been in clearance last year (as noted earlier
                    by Mr. LaFeber) was now cleared except for one document being reviewed by AEC
                    and CIA. Mr. Franklin pointed out that one of the clearance quirks of the moment
                    was that the NSC required clearance by the CIA before it would consider
                    clearance of its own documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon then reported on the work of the Eastern Branch. The Korean
                    compilation for 1950 had gone to the technical editors last March and was now
                    being put into galleys; 1948, volume VII, was being put in pages; and it was
                    hoped that NSC clearance of 1948, volume VIII, would be obtained soon. No major
                    clearance problems were expected over Korea for 1950.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany mentioned another clearance problem beginning in the 1950’s: the
                    National Intelligence Estimates. These were desirable documents to include in
                    the series. Mr. Glennon reminded the committee that some Estimates had already
                    been mentioned by name and number in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then raised another clearance problem: persons involved in the
                    current détente were nervous over publication of material which documented the
                    bitterness of the Cold War.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany pointed out that one effect of speeding up the series might be to
                    reassure persons who were afraid that publication would hurt their activities.
                    Publication of the Pentagon Papers seemed not to have caused an overwhelming
                    disaster. Readers would see what the staff had seen as editors, with scarcely a
                    paragraph lost. There would be guides to other material in the files in the form
                    of editorial notes. We would leave behind a trail of file numbers and tips for
                    further research. There would be no intrinsic reason why the sensitive agencies
                    should be hurt. Indeed, once they saw that no serious effects result from
                    publication, they might in fact start helping us.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl observed that we had held off in some of our assaults until we had
                    some indication that we could win. Now that NSC clearance was coming, it might
                    be easier to make progress with some of the other agencies.</p>
                <p>Technical editing was then discussed. Mr. Aandahl said that it would be desirable
                    to have a larger number of permanent State Department editors in addition to
                    outside contractors. Mr. Dougall pointed out that there had been a lowered
                    quality in technical editing over the past ten years in such matters as
                    consistency in headings, citations, and typefaces. Mr. Franklin remarked that a
                    more serious form of discrepancy occurred when, in the case of indexing by
                    outsiders, a different system of transliteration had been used from that in the
                    text. It was not good editing to have this sort of practice occur. It was,
                    however, cheaper to have technical editing done by outside contractors.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stauffer then mentioned the seminars which had been conducted by Mr. Slany
                    for a number of members of the staff. Mr. Slany pointed out that the meetings
                    had dealt with both the substantive and the technical sides of editing, and had
                    attempted to evolve an ongoing plan by exploring new areas not previously given
                    thorough coverage in the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin pointed out that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, in
                    keeping with its position as an official government publication, had formerly
                    contained relatively little annotation. At present, however, private
                    publications were cited, although this practice was limited to primary source
                    material and the memoirs of official participants. One problem was that a mere
                    reference to someone controversial might raise the question of our
                    objectivity.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany raised another editorial problem: that of making <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> responsive to the needs of those doing research. The
                    series had a role as the wedge of access. To be really effective in this
                    connection the series must relate and respond to other research and writing in
                    the field and be particularly conscious of the known points of dispute.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion at this point of the problems of citing personal
                    memoirs and oral history interviews in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    Emphasis was on both the value of these materials and the need for caution in
                    their handling. Mr. Goodwin made the point that sometimes such sources helped
                    establish some general point even when their factual integrity was at many
                    points uncertain.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin mentioned that the Senate Foreign Relations Committee was planning
                    to publish transcripts of executive-session testimony. This was an offspring of
                    the declassification question and might help to open up executive-session
                    material in the future. Mr. Freeman said that notice should be taken of what
                    time lag the Senate Committee followed. In response to an inquiry by Mr.
                    Westerfield as to whether clearance was obtained from the Senators involved, Mr.
                    Franklin answered that he did not know.</p>
                <p rend="center">[At 12:15 the Committee recessed for lunch with Mr. Macomber. It
                    reconvened at 2:45 p.m.]</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 8: PROBLEMS OF ACCESS AND DECLASSIFICATION</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall discussed the Executive Order on declassification of March 8, 1972.
                    He noted first that several proposals made by the Historical Office had not been
                    accepted in the final draft. He outlined provisions of the Freedom of
                    Information Act of 1967, which was the statutory basis of the Executive Order.
                    The Act was really designed for the citizen who wishes to obtain
                    declassification of individual documents, not for the scholar interested in
                    general declassification. For the latter, use of the Act to obtain
                    declassification is a lengthy, laborious, and usually unsatisfactory process,
                    and expensive to boot.</p>
                <p>The new Executive Order, he continued, gives an initial impression that all U.S.
                    Government documents will be declassified in ten years, but there are a
                    substantial number of exceptions, although the number of officials who may
                    classify documents and apply the exceptions has been greatly reduced. Moreover,
                    the new Order applies only to documents dated later than June 1, 1972.
                    Declassification of documents prior to that date must be effected through use of
                    the Freedom of Information Act.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall concluded his explanation of the Order by pointing out that probably
                    its most positive feature was extension government-wide of the thirty-year rule
                    (which originated in the Department of State).</p>
                <p>Both Mr. Franklin and Mr. Dougall drew the conclusion that the Executive Order
                    would make little difference to the serious scholar. Although it might be
                    possible under the coming computerized retrieval system to make available large
                    quantities of automatically declassified documents, the cream of the crop would
                    probably be excepted. In addition computer print-outs would cost money.</p>
                <p>Mr. Varg noted the existence of ill will among young scholars concerning the
                    current research situation. There was a great differential of competence within
                    the Archives staff, and when young doctoral candidates drew poor research
                    assistants they could be denied access to crucial available information. Mr.
                    Franklin suggested that Mr. Varg take up this matter with Archives directly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall stated that the discussion at this point again brought up the locator
                    feature of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Editorial notes
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> could point the young researcher to
                    documentation on a given problem for which there was not enough space in the
                    series itself. These notes could indicate that such documentation might well be
                    spread across the whole spectrum of lot and decimal files for a given year or
                    series of years, thereby providing the researcher with the key as to where and
                    how far to look.</p>
                <p>Mr. Varg added that the greatest problem scholars were facing was that
                    foreign-policy documents had been generated by a greatly increased number of
                    agencies after World War II and access to these documents was severely limited.
                    Young scholars had become impatient, and had taken to issuing “ten year
                    manifestoes” which didn’t cut to the heart of the real and basic problems which
                    had been discussed here.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl asked the Committee as a whole if outside scholars felt the
                    Historical Office had done an adequate job on the Cold War in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. LaFeber replied affirmatively. Mr. Aandahl
                    observed the series had always tried to cover all sides of the biggest issues,
                    and Mr. Rappaport noted that this had always been the mission of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber stated that one of his graduate students, interested in U.S.-Thai
                    relations, had consulted the appropriate volume for 1947 but had found nothing
                    on the subject. Mr. Glennon explained that a review of the matter had disclosed
                    that there was no body of documents worthy of inclusion in the series, and that
                    relations of the two countries were then of peripheral importance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin mentioned a similar criticism concerning the treatment of Korea in
                    the 1945 volume. The volume correctly reflected the fact that Korea had not then
                    been an important factor in American diplomacy so far as policymakers were
                    concerned. Both Mr. Franklin and Mr. Aandahl pointed out that the perspective of
                    twenty years did enable the staff occasionally to include material that was not
                    contemporarily relevant but became so later.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber observed that apparently the Executive Order would have no real
                    effect on the future of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He pointed out
                    that the Committee would have two obligations: First, to explain the Executive
                    Order to the scholarly community, especially to the American Historical
                    Association, and second, to stress the necessity of getting the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> publication interval down to twenty
                    years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin suggested that the Committee might investigate, through the various
                    learned societies to which its members belonged, how well scholars had done in
                    getting access to top-flight policy documents through the Executive Order. He
                    explained that the Order had had the effect of whetting scholarly appetites for
                    quicker declassification, but he was afraid that the results had been
                    disappointing to the scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber then asked whether the Historical Office thought that it needed more
                    staff to reach the twenty-year line in three years. Mr. Franklin replied that
                    this was impossible to determine at the moment. It would depend on how long it
                    would take new staff members to reach a level of sustained competence. He had
                    reserved the right to request further positions in the future if lack of staff
                    proved to be the main factor holding up production, but if clearance should be
                    the main source of slowdown, there would be no reason to ask for further staff.
                    Mr. Franklin again stressed the bottlenecks outside the Historical Office, such
                    as clearances from various agencies and governments, editorial work including
                    indexing, and the facilities and priorities of the Government Printing
                    Office.</p>
                <p>At 4:06 p.m. Mr. Deener adjourned the meeting so that the members of the Advisory
                    Committee could have a private discussion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
