<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Fredrick Aandahl Through William Franklin to
                    Carol Laise, November 1973</title>
                <title type="short">Aandahl to Laise, 1973</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1973-11-29">November 29, 1973</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1973-11-29-aandahl-to-laise.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 165 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Paul Claussen Files, 1972-2005 (Lot File 08 D 437), Box 2,
                    Foreign Relations Memoranda, Etc. 1974-1981. A copy of this memorandum was also
                    sent to Joseph A. Tambone (PA/EX).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn70">Footnote 70</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From Fredrick Aandahl (General Editor of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>) Through William Franklin (Director of Historical Office) to
                    Carol Laise (Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs)</head>
                <dateline>November 29, 1973</dateline>
                <p>Subject: An Optimum Program for the Foreign Relations Division</p>
                <p>The “optimum job possible” was defined for the Foreign Relations Division in the
                    President's directive of March 8, 1972:</p>
                <quote>“without impairing the quality and comprehensive nature of the series ... to
                    reduce the time lag to 20 years ... declassifying the appropriate materials to
                    the maximum extent consistent with the requirements of national
                    security.”</quote>
                <p>This is a tall order, and it involves three separate operations:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(a) compilation -- by the Foreign Relations Division</item>
                    <item>(b) editorial processing -- by PBR and GPO</item>
                    <item>(c) clearance and declassification -- by State, Defense, CIA, AEC, NSC,
                        other departments and agencies, friendly foreign government, and
                        international organizations such as NATO and the UN.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Only the first of these steps is directly under our control, but all three are
                    vital to our publication schedule.</p>
                <p rend="center">OPERATIONS</p>
                <p>To achieve optimum performance I recommend action on all three fronts:</p>
                <p>(a) <hi rend="underline">Compilation</hi></p>
                <p>In order to publish volumes at a 20-year line, we need to compile them at an
                    18-year line. We are currently at a 22-year line. We plan to cover each year in
                    about seven volumes. This means that to reduce the lag we must compile 12 to 14
                    volumes a year. The time and resources required vary considerably from volume to
                    volume, but in any event selecting and editing diplomatic papers can never be
                    fast work. At present we do not have enough players to cover all the positions.
                    To reach an 18-year line on compilation, we need three additional professional
                    historians, preferably with the following specialties: (a) international
                    economics, (b) Near East and Africa, and (c) Asia. We can meet some needs by
                    internal transfers, but this does not increase total output.</p>
                <p>(b) <hi rend="underline">Editorial Processing</hi></p>
                <p>Our present flow of work is slow and cumbersome. Our research is done in the
                    files in Main State; our compilation is done in SA-2; and our editorial
                    processing is done in Rosslyn. Since compilers and editors must be in constant
                    touch on all sorts of questions, and since new volumes are based on previous
                    ones still in the hands of editors, this separation is a major hindrance to
                    production. We now have 29 volumes (1948 through 1951) in various stages of
                    preparation, and nearly all are being worked on both in SA-2 and in Rosslyn,
                    with endless complications. Matters that could be cleared up promptly in person
                    are allowed to accumulate. For one or two volumes this would be a nuisance, but
                    for 29 it is highly inefficient.</p>
                <p>To remedy this situation I strongly recommend that the six or seven editors of
                    PBR who work full-time on “Foreign Relations” be brought back to SA-2, where we
                    worked together very smoothly. Originally (and indeed for many decades) these
                    editors were regular members of our staff. Since they are an integral and highly
                    respected part of our production line, I think that it would also be beneficial
                    to return them to the Bureau of Public Affairs from the Bureau of
                    Administration, which has different priorities and a different emphasis. Editing
                    “Foreign Relations” is a highly technical job, and I think that we could offer a
                    more rewarding career to those who are good at it. Even though much of the
                    routine editorial work can be done satisfactorily on contract, the Department
                    still needs some highly competent “in-house” people for the sake of continuity
                    and quality control. We cannot afford to become entirely dependent on outside
                    contractors.</p>
                <p>Whether the technical editors remain in PBR or are transferred to HO, we may need
                    one or two more of them to handle the additional volumes included in our
                    accelerated program. Additional staff would also be required by the Macmillan
                    Educational Corporation or other outside contractor.</p>
                <p>(c) <hi rend="underline">Clearance and Declassification</hi></p>
                <p>Our most conspicuous problem has been the slow pace of clearances. Since you and
                    we are already making a major effort to enlist the Secretary's support,
                    particularly at the NSC level, I need not say much about this. The one thing
                    that would really help would be a direct statement by Dr. Kissinger that he
                    favors full and timely publication of “Foreign Relations” as part of the policy
                    of openness. A strongly affirmative statement by the Secretary of State would
                    have great impact in the Department, elsewhere in the Government, and in the
                    world of public affairs.</p>
                <p rend="center">FACILITIES</p>
                <p>The efficiency of our operations depends in great measure on the facilities
                    available to us, and I think our productivity could be sharply increased by
                    improvements in these areas:</p>
                <p>(a) <hi rend="underline">Working space for research</hi></p>
                <p>Most of our research (searching for and selecting documents to be reproduced for
                    possible publication) is done in very cramped quarters in the Records Service
                    Center in Main State. FADRC provides space for our researchers, but the central
                    files are very crowded, and it is a burden on everyone's patience to have up to
                    20 persons of both HO divisions using one 15 x 46 room as their base of
                    operations. There is not desk space enough for all the regular users to work at
                    the same time.</p>
                <p>Dr. Franklin has received excellent cooperation from Mr. Donald Simon, Chief of
                    FADRC, but there is not much that they can do, given the limited space and the
                    large number of researchers. We would greatly appreciate your taking an active
                    interest in enlisting high-level support for an effort to find suitable space in
                    a secure area reasonably close to the files.</p>
                <p>(b) <hi rend="underline">Working space for compilation, review, and
                        clearance</hi></p>
                <p>While SA-2 could not be described as providing palatial quarters, it does have
                    sufficient cubic feet within walking distance of the central files. This is its
                    one advantage, which is an important one. The HO staff would of course prefer a
                    modern structure such as the new Columbia Plaza office building, particularly if
                    it had enough space to include the technical editors and some additional
                    historians, but we can survive in SA-2 as we have for eleven years. By no
                    stretch of the imagination, however, could the building be considered to provide
                    optimal working conditions.</p>
                <p>One practical amelioration might be possible even within SA-2. Both in editing
                    documents and in preparing research studies the staff of HO depends on a
                    miserably housed and seriously inadequate reference collection, which is used
                    intensively by all. Modern shelving to replace the rickety wood-and-glass boxes
                    would remove a safety hazard and save much space. Additional funds for essential
                    reference works and specialized journals would be most helpful.</p>
                <p>(c) <hi rend="underline">A copying machine</hi></p>
                <p>There is unanimous agreement in HO that we need an efficient copying machine of
                    our own. The Foreign Relations Division has eighteen historians and one
                    secretary. This staff ratio -- probably unique in the Department -- is possible
                    only if we can count on prompt reproduction of documents and other materials.
                    Existing facilities in SA-2 are quite unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>(d) <hi rend="underline">Travel funds</hi></p>
                <p>We need travel funds sufficient to cover an occasional trip to the Truman and
                    Eisenhower libraries and to other research centers. The most important materials
                    at Independence may be opened in the next few months. It would be helpful also
                    to have funds for attending meetings of professional associations.</p>
                <p>As I mentioned to you at the luncheon for the Advisory Committee on Foreign
                    Relations, we have a strong staff and a good program. Once we can surmount some
                    of the difficulties outlined above, I am confident that we can push forward
                    rapidly. 1974 will be the critical year for stepping up the momentum.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
