<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1974</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1974</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-19">May 19, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1974-11-08">November 8, 1974</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1974-11-08-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 532 KB, 9pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1974—Minutes. Limited Official Use. Posted
                    from a copy that is not signed by HAC Chair Walter LaFeber. Attachments are not
                    posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn71">Footnotes 71</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn73">73</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1974 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 8, 1974</dateline>
                <list>
                    <item>The Advisory Committee:<list>
                            <item>Dr. Robert A. Divine, Professor of History, University of Texas,
                                Austin, Texas 78712 (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Dr. Alwyn V. Freeman, Member, Board of Editors, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >The American Journal of International Law</hi>, Washington,
                                D.C. 20008 (American Society of International Law)</item>
                            <item>Dr. Walter LaFeber, Professor of History, Cornell University,
                                Ithaca, New York 14850 (American Historical Association)</item>
                            <item>Dr. Covey T. Oliver, Professor of Law, University of Pennsylvania,
                                Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104 (American Society of International
                                Law)</item>
                            <item>Dr. Armin H. Rappaport, Professor of History, University of
                                California, La Jolla, California 92037 (American Historical
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Dr. Richard C. Snyder, Director, Mershon Center, Ohio State
                                University, Columbus, Ohio 43210 (American Political Science
                                Association)</item>
                            <item>Dr. H. Bradford Westerfield [Not present], Professor of Political
                                Science, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut 06520 (American
                                Political Science Association)</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><hi rend="underline">Other Persons Present</hi></item>
                    <item>The Bureau of Public Affairs:<list>
                            <item>Carol C. Laise, Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>The Historical Office:<list>
                            <item>William M. Franklin, Director (Executive Secretary of the Advisory
                                Committee)</item>
                            <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                            <item>Fredrick Aandahl</item>
                            <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                            <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                            <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                            <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                            <item>William Slany</item>
                            <item>John A. Bernbaum</item>
                            <item>Joan Lee Bryniarski</item>
                            <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                            <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                            <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                            <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                            <item>Margaret G. Martin</item>
                            <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                            <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                            <item>Carl N. Raether</item>
                            <item>Beverly Z. Rowsome</item>
                            <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                            <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                            <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                            <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <p>[The meeting was not open to the public.]</p>
                <p>Opening Session - 9:07 a.m. - 12:01 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEMS 1 and 2: OPENING REMARKS AND SELECTION OF COMMITTEE
                    CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin called the meeting to order and extended welcome to the Committee.
                    Mr. Freeman nominated Mr. LaFeber for Chairman of the Committee. Mr. Oliver
                    seconded the nomination and the vote was unanimous.</p>
                <p>Assistant Secretary Laise joined the meeting at 9:10. She stated that the
                    Department of State was making a serious effort to speed up the publication of
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. She emphasized that the
                    Department, with the aid of the Historical Office, had lately been servicing
                    requests under the Freedom of Information Act much more quickly, and that she
                    was determined further to improve performance in this area. After her remarks
                    the Assistant Secretary remained at the meeting until 9:40 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 3: PROGRESS ON 1948-1951 VOLUMES AND PROBLEMS OF
                    DECLASSIFICATION</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl circulated a list detailing the progress of the volumes in
                    preparation [Attachment 1]. He noted that declassification was still the major
                    obstacle to publication. There had been particular difficulty and delay with
                    1948, Volume I, Part II, which contained high-level National Security Council
                    papers on the formulation of cold-war policy. The question was whether to
                    publish this volume now with summaries replacing the papers that cannot be
                    cleared yet, or whether to delay publication for an indeterminable time. Similar
                    problems have come up with the Far Eastern volumes for 1949 and 1950, and other
                    cases are expected.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield said he was opposed to printing incomplete volumes containing
                    only summaries of important documents that had not been declassified. Allowing
                    such an omission would be an easy way out which might establish an unfortunate
                    precedent. If the volume were delayed, on the other hand, pressure from outside
                    might develop and encourage clearance of the documents in question.</p>
                <p>Mr. Oliver remarked that it was of crucial importance for the series to print NSC
                    materials and high-level materials generally, since Cold War problems were of
                    such crucial importance to the “revisionist” debate among historians. The
                    concern of the Committee over refusal of clearance on such documents should be
                    expressed to policymakers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport said that historians would still be able to get the drift of policy
                    if the volume were published with the omissions. Mr. Divine stated that waiting
                    would delay the whole series and access to the files in the Archives. Mr.
                    Freeman said he was discouraged, but would rather see the omitted documents
                    summarized than allow the series to fall farther behind.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin pointed out that if the omitted documents were not declassified for
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, they would not be available when
                    the files were opened to scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl suggested the problem might be solved by the publication of a
                    supplemental volume at a future date. Supplemental volumes had been published
                    for the World War I period. Mr. Slany said that important documents often turned
                    up after the volumes on the relevant subjects had been published, and that this
                    constituted an additional reason for supplemental volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber, noting that the Committee was divided on the issue, suggested that
                    it be discussed further in conversations among the members.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 4: SCHEDULING OF COMPILATION FOR 1952-1954 AND
                    1955-1957; THE TRIENNIAL PLAN AS A MEANS FOR REACHING THE 20-YEAR LINE</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl read statistics [Attachment 2] showing that the productivity of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff had almost trebled since
                    fiscal 1971, but he noted that even with increased productivity <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was not making sufficiently rapid
                    progress toward the twenty-year line. Primarily for this reason the staff had
                    adopted a triennial format for the 1952-1954 volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked whether the Committee was being informed of or asked for advice
                    about the plan. Mr. Aandahl replied that if the Committee had overwhelming
                    objections to the plan it could be changed. Mr. Franklin added that the main
                    objective of the Triennial Plan was to meet the request of the Assistant
                    Secretary to bring compilation to a twenty-year line; more rapid publication
                    might follow, but that would not necessarily be the case. The new format would
                    serve to boost morale, and might put additional pressure on clearance
                    officers.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked whether the new plan meant that less total paper would be
                    printed. Mr. Aandahl replied in the affirmative. Mr. LaFeber inquired also
                    whether clearance problems involving 1954 documents might hold up 1952 material.
                    Mr. Aandahl answered that such might be the case, but that dividing the volumes
                    as necessary might offer a possible solution to this problem. Mr. Slany
                    suggested that the three-year plan aimed at more intensive planning of the
                    series, which would allow coming to grips with major clearance problems in an
                    early and rational manner. Mr. LaFeber commented that it seemed to him that the
                    new plan would retard rather than expedite access to the files. Mr. Divine
                    suggested that the conditions of access be changed to allow partial access as
                    the volumes are printed. Mr. Franklin responded that partial access might be
                    possible, but that getting far ahead on compilation would allow the option of
                    annual, biennial, or triennial volumes. Mr. LaFeber pointed out that compilation
                    was already two to three years ahead of publication.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield said he certainly had no objection to the publication of longer
                    time spans of documentation at once.</p>
                <p>In reply to Mr. Divine’s question as to what sorts of NSC material were in State
                    Department files, Mr. Franklin stated that for the period in question we had
                    files of considerable depth on the NSC papers themselves, but lacked the minutes
                    for formal NSC meetings. It was probable that such minutes had been made in
                    ribbon copy only and given to the President. These minutes might be in the
                    Truman and Eisenhower libraries.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 5: QUESTIONS RAISED IN THE SELF-SURVEY OF THE
                    HISTORICAL OFFICE</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall explained that the Bureau of Public Affairs had invited the
                    Historical Office to form two working-level committees--called “H” and “0”--to
                    study the Office’s functions and procedures in depth and to recommend changes
                    and improvements. Mr. Slany said Committee H, of which he was rapporteur, was
                    considering primarily <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Asked to examine
                    format alternations, it had decided tentatively after some study to recommend
                    that the series continue to appear in a printed-page format rather than in
                    microform. Whatever cost advantages might accrue from a microform format, the
                    committee considered that the series in microform would not meet needs and uses
                    of readers of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Freeman remarked that a microform format would cut the series off from the
                    general public. Mr. Westerfield agreed. Mr. Oliver asked if microform
                    publications received reviews. Several committee members expressed the opinion
                    that such reviews were rare. Mr. Rappaport commented that from the teaching
                    viewpoint a microform <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would be highly
                    unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany continued that although his committee was leaning away from microforms,
                    it was determinedly seeking ways to lower cost and speed publication while
                    keeping the series between covers. Advanced phototype-setting methods and the
                    letting of commercial printing contracts were both under consideration.</p>
                <p>A general discussion of those alternatives ensued.</p>
                <p>[Coffee was served at 10:32 a.m. Discussion resumed at 10:58 a.m.]</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany in continuing his presentation said Committee H was considering the
                    possibility of a microform supplement to the series consisting of unedited
                    documents--perhaps entire key files. He mentioned that Ambassador Laise was
                    interested in maximizing the amount of material made available to the public.
                    Committee H was also considering means of speeding declassification. They
                    included (a) requesting a letter from the Secretary of State which would endorse
                    the series and urge faster clearance and (b) asking the Secretary in his
                    capacity as Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs to allow
                    simultaneous clearance by NSC and other agencies of NSC papers. Mr. Slany also
                    stressed the advantage of having NSC declassify documents in manuscript rather
                    than in galley--NSC tended to move very slowly on clearance.</p>
                <p>Both Mr. Westerfield and Mr. Rappaport expressed their great surprise at the
                    present procedure whereby NSC insists that it review papers only after all
                    agencies whose heads are members of NSC have already done so. Mr. Franklin
                    pointed out that since NSC has its own staff, as a practical matter NSC
                    clearance represents an additional “layer” of clearance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany described two more clearance proposals. State’s Freedom of Information
                    machinery might be enlisted in the clearance of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> within the Department. Responsibility for clearing certain
                    types of material might be obtained for the Historical Office, thus reducing the
                    burden on desk officers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany pointed out that the Department has no full-fledged archivist and
                    described the deleterious effect of this lack on the condition of the
                    Department’s files. Committee H would propose a study group of representatives
                    of the Department and of the National Archives to look into this problem. Mr.
                    LaFeber asked if a Departmental archivist, once appointed, would be expected to
                    assist outside historians in their research in those declassified files which
                    remained temporarily in State’s custody, and Mr. Slany replied that this was one
                    of the functions contemplated for an archivist.</p>
                <p>Ms. Rowsome reported on the work of Committee O, which was concentrating
                    primarily on the work of the Historical Studies Division. The Division’s primary
                    role was within the Department but the committee was considering several
                    possibilities which would expand the Division’s role with regard to the public.
                    One was a proposal for a seminar, sponsored by the Office, perhaps twice a year
                    for 15-20 members of the academic community. This seminar would include
                    discussions with members of the Office about its work and about the files, and
                    tours of the files and the Operations Center. Another suggestion was that the
                        <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series be revived, perhaps
                    appearing several times a year in an expanded Department of State <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>. Committee O was also considering publication of
                    unclassified studies such as one on Law of the Sea.</p>
                <p>A narrative history of the 1945-1950 period was under very tentative
                    consideration. Mr. Westerfield stated his emphatic opposition to this proposal.
                    Mr. Costrell also spoke against this idea.</p>
                <p>Ms. Rowsome concluded by mentioning a proposal for documentary collections on key
                    crises, to be published in advance of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    Mr. Franklin pointed out that such a collection on Lebanon had been prepared two
                    years ago but had been killed because of opposition from the concerned
                    geographical bureau of the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked if it was proper for the Advisory Committee to make
                    recommendations concerning these proposals, which were still under internal
                    discussion. It was suggested that these matters could perhaps be discussed at
                    lunch with Ambassador Laise and Acting Secretary Maw, rather than taken up in
                    the Committee’s written report. Mr. LaFeber commented that he himself believed
                    that it would be proper to recommend certain things, such as an archivist for
                    the State Department and the revival of <hi rend="italic">Current
                    Documents</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said he thought that at lunch the Committee should concentrate on
                    bringing the problem of declassification of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to the attention of the Acting Secretary of State and that
                    the Committee’s report should be brief and should concentrate on the main
                    issues. He said he would try to bring the written report to the attention of the
                    Secretary of State. He suggested that the Committee write to Assistant Secretary
                    Laise about secondary issues.</p>
                <p>Mr. Oliver spoke against the revival of <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi>
                    on the ground that so much of its contents of interest to international lawyers
                    had already appeared elsewhere.</p>
                <p>Concerning the seminar proposal, Ms. Noring pointed out that the academic
                    community was not aware of the computerization of the Department’s filing
                    system. The seminars would acquaint scholars with this and other changes. Mr.
                    Franklin said that bringing scholars to Washington would be difficult to
                    finance. Mr. Rappaport reported that the Society for Historians of American
                    Foreign Relations would be meeting in Washington during his presidency next year
                    and that it planned to meet here every two years thereafter. Mr. Westerfield
                    recalled that the American Political Science Association meets in Washington
                    every three years or so. Mr. Landa outlined the idea more fully. He said that
                    the seminars would be held to coincide with professional meetings and during the
                    summer, when so many scholars did research in Washington. Mr. Oliver stated that
                    it seemed the financial problem was no obstacle and that the seminars, should
                    they materialize, ought to be widely publicized in order to avoid any appearance
                    of exclusivity.</p>
                <p>[At 12:01 p.m. the Committee adjourned for lunch with Ambassador Laise and Acting
                    Secretary Maw. The Committee reconvened at 2:28 p.m.]</p>
                <p>Afternoon Session - 2:28 p.m. - 3:36 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 7: PROBLEMS OF BUDGET AND TECHNICAL EDITING</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin said that lack of money had not caused major delay in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Printing funds had been
                    adequate, and the delays had come from clearance difficulties. Mr. Aandahl added
                    that the severest pinch was felt in the small editorial staff of the Publishing
                    and Reproduction Division, which was efficient but perennially understaffed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport asked if the series was being delayed, and its resources stretched
                    thin, because the Office was forced to deal with the GPO. Mr. Franklin answered
                    that the Office had several times suggested alternatives to the GPO, but going
                    elsewhere might require authorization by the Congress. Mr. Aandahl pointed out
                    that adoption of the linotron process might speed printing and cut costs even if
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> stayed at GPO. Members of the
                    Office then outlined the linotron process to the Committee. Mr. Kane cautioned
                    that the use of linotron for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> presented
                    some as yet unresolved technical problems.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl, in discussing the current revision of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> style manual, pointed out that revision is intended to speed
                    compilation, make the volumes more readable, and systematize identification of
                    lot files. Mr. Franklin remarked that a number of lot files had been destroyed
                    since being cited in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and that this was
                    damaging to credibility. Mr. Slany added that the Office was actively trying to
                    convince the National Archives appraisers to retain a larger proportion of lot
                    files.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl stated that part of the discussion at luncheon should be placed on
                    record, whereupon Mr. LaFeber remarked that at lunch representatives of the
                    Office and of the Committee had informed Mr. Maw that clearance by NSC of
                    certain key documents had on occasion necessitated personal review by the
                    Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs. Mr. Maw had also been
                    informed of the Committee’s dissatisfaction with the performance of the
                    Interagency Classification Review Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport stated that he had learned at lunch of Ambassador Laise’s great
                    interest in oral history.</p>
                <p>Chairman LaFeber asked if there were any more comments to be made on Item 7. Mr.
                    Franklin stated in summary that there was no immediate fiscal problem, although
                    the Office might face some stringency in FY 1976.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 8: DECLASSIFICATION AHEAD OF <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN
                        RELATIONS</hi> PUBLICATION</p>
                <p>Mr. Kogan distributed a survey entitled “Public Availability of Diplomatic
                    Archives” [Attachment 3]. He noted that the United States was still
                    declassifying foreign-policy materials well in advance of other governments.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rappaport commented that the survey deserved a wide distribution, and Mr.
                    Dougall suggested that a note on its availability could be included in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> of the Society for Historians of American
                    Foreign Relations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall reviewed developments under Executive Order 11652. Currently the
                    Office was resubmitting for declassification under the 30-year rule material
                    which had not been cleared for 1944 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes and which consequently had been withheld from researchers when the 1944
                    files had been opened early. All but about a half-dozen of such documents would
                    probably be declassified this year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dougall reported also that the charge per page for copies of documents
                    declassified under Freedom of Information procedures had been reduced from 60¢
                    to 10¢ a page although the search charge had gone up to $5 from $3.50 an hour.
                    No charge is now made for the time of reviewing officers. The latest cumulative
                    report shows that 45,000 pages had been requested of the Department under FOI
                    provisions. The Department had released 35,000 pages and refused clearance on
                    1,000; the other 9,000 pages were pending at the date the report was
                    compiled.</p>
                <p>There was a general discussion of how documents released under the FOI Act might
                    be better publicized. Mr. Franklin said that although he did want better
                    publicity for the declassified items and had tried to get a list of them
                    inserted in the Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, the Office
                    generally did not wish, through involvement in Freedom of Information work, to
                    lose man hours better devoted to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr.
                    Keefer said the Office hoped the Bureau of Public Affairs would augment the
                    Freedom of Information staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Franklin then briefly described the special problems encountered in the
                    declassification of foreign-government documents in our files. He noted that the
                    British are applying their own 30-year rule to such papers in their files.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 9: OTHER BUSINESS</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked Chairman LaFeber to send to the Office copies of any
                    correspondence with Assistant Secretary Laise. Mr. LaFeber replied that she had
                    requested the Committee to direct its letters to Mr. Franklin with copies to
                    her.</p>
                <p>[The Committee rose at 3:36 p.m.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
