<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1975</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1975</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-19">May 19, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1975-11-14">November 14, 1975</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1975-11-14-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 221 KB, 10pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1975—Minutes. Posted from a copy signed by
                    HAC Chair H. Bradford Westerfield. Attachments are not posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn77">Footnotes 77</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn80">80</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1975 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 14, 1975</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Robert A. Divine, Professor of History, University of Texas</item>
                    <item>Dr. Robert Ferrell, Professor of History, Indiana University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Paul A. Varg, Professor of History, Michigan State University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">[Drs. Ferrell and Varg, former members of the Committee, served as
                    substitutes for Dr. Lloyd C. Gardner, Professor of History, Rutgers University,
                    and Dr. Armin H. Rappaport, Professor of History, University of California, San
                    Diego, who were out of the country.]</p>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Richard C. Snyder, Director, Mershon Center, Ohio State
                        University</item>
                    <item>Dr. H. Bradford Westerfield, Professor of Political Science, Yale
                        University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">[Dr. Snyder extended his term as a member of the Committee to serve
                    as a substitute for Dr. Bernard C. Cohen, Professor of Political Science,
                    University of Wisconsin, who was out of the country.]</p>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Philip C. Jessup, Judge, International Court of Justice,
                        retired</item>
                    <item>Dr. Covey T. Oliver, Professor of Law, University of Pennsylvania</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John E. Reinhardt, Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>William D. Blair, Jr., Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>William J. Dyess, Director of the Office of Plans and Management
                        (PA/M)</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Fredrick Aandahl, Acting Director (Executive Secretary of the Advisory
                        Committee)</item>
                    <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                    <item>William Slany</item>
                    <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                    <item>Richardson Dougall</item>
                    <item>Ralph R. Goodwin</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>John A. Bernbaum</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>Joan M. Lee</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>Carl N. Raether</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                    <item>Harry F. Young</item>
                </list>
                <p>Professor David F. Trask of the State University of New York at Stony Brook,
                    Director-designate of the Historical Office, was also present during a major
                    part of the meeting.</p>
                <p>[As announced in press release No. 515 (Attachment 1), this meeting was closed to
                    the public.]</p>
                <p>Opening Session - 9:17 a.m. - 12:17 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEMS 1 and 2: OPENING REMARKS AND SELECTION OF COMMITTEE
                    CHAIRMAN</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl called the meeting to order and extended welcome to the Committee.
                    Mr. Divine nominated Mr. Westerfield for Chairman of the Committee. Mr.
                    Westerfield was elected by acclamation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl introduced Assistant Secretary Reinhardt, who had entered the meeting
                    with the members of the Committee. Ambassador Reinhardt noted that soon after he
                    had arrived in the Bureau last spring, one of his first meetings was with some
                    members of the Advisory Committee concerning the appointment of a director for
                    the Historical Office (HO), and that the discussions set in motion by this
                    meeting had led to the appointment of Mr. Trask. He further stated that he
                    regarded HO’s mission as an integral part of the Bureau’s “outreach” program and
                    he expressed his conviction that the new director would contribute significantly
                    to the program. He assured HO of his continued cooperation, and noted that he
                    viewed the Advisory Committee as an ally in solving problems which lay ahead.
                    After making his remarks the Assistant Secretary remained at the meeting until
                    10:22 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 3: CURRENT STATUS OF THE HISTORICAL OFFICE</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl briefly described the organizational structure of the Historical
                    Office. He stated that an African specialist would soon join the staff, and at
                    that point the Office would be at full complement. He noted that the Historical
                    Office worked closely with the Bureau of Public Affairs, citing the fact that HO
                    historians were regularly serving in the Freedom of Information Office. He
                    commented that the Committee might want to suggest ways for updating the
                    Presidential directive of three years ago which called upon the Secretary of
                    State and other high officials to cooperate in accelerating production of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in order to reach a 20-year
                    line.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 4: STATUS OF THE <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN
                        RELATIONS</hi> SERIES AND PUBLICATION PLANS AND SCHEDULES FOR VOLUMES FOR
                    THE YEARS 1948-1957</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany made a brief progress report on the publication of volumes for the
                    years 1948 and 1949, referring to a written report on the status of volumes as
                    of November 1975 (previously circulated to the Committee and included here as
                    Attachment 2). He noted that the publication of five volumes during June, July,
                    and August 1975 had been marked by a series of regrettable mishaps in the
                    Government Printing Office resulting in late distribution or non-distribution of
                    volumes to would-be purchasers. Mr. Slany took the occasion to express his
                    general discontent with the GPO as the printer-publisher of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and expressed the wish that
                    means could be found to go to a commercial or university press. Mr. Aandahl
                    observed that such action probably was not feasible in the case of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> because the materials and manuscript
                    remained classified through most of the production process.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany outlined the compilation program for the coming year and for the period
                    through 1981, which was presented in a paper he circulated to the Committee
                    (Attachment 3). He explained that the immediate target was the publication
                    during the current fiscal year of the remaining 13 volumes for 1948, 1949, and
                    1950. Highest priority was attached to the publication this winter of the two
                    remaining half-volumes for 1948. Part 2 of 1948, volume I, contained those most
                    important NSC papers that were precursors of NSC 68. The declassification of
                    these 1948 papers had been secured from the Assistant to the President for
                    National Security Affairs through the resolute support of Assistant Secretary
                    Reinhardt, Deputy Assistant Secretary Blair, and other officials. Part 2 of
                    1948, volume V had been postponed because HO recognized the vital importance of
                    preparing as complete a record as possible on the Arab-Zionist dispute of 1948
                    and the establishment of the state of Israel. The former director, William M.
                    Franklin, had devoted nearly all of his time to this project, right up to his
                    retirement in April 1975.</p>
                <p>Mr. Divine asked if HO could publish supplementary volumes in the future as
                    material that could not now be declassified became available. Mr. Slany
                    indicated that this might be possible. Were the Presidential papers so long
                    withheld during the probate of Mr. Truman’s will and now being processed at the
                    Truman Library to prove important and numerous, a supplementary volume might
                    well be published gathering papers for the period of the entire Truman
                    presidency. In response to a question by Mr. Oliver about the feasibility of
                    printing supplementary papers after a <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volume has been released, Mr. Aandahl explained that such documentation could be
                    included in a later volume in the series or might be published separately in the
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> or elsewhere.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany circulated to the Committee a compilation schedule for the sixteen
                    1952-1954 volumes currently being worked on by the staff (Attachment 4). He
                    explained that this “production schedule” had been resorted to in order to
                    intensify the effort toward reaching the 20-year line. He admitted that some
                    slippage had already been recognized, and some areas had been revealed where
                    more compilers might be necessary to stay on schedule. Mr. Slany observed that
                    the Committee report for 1974 had expressed some skepticism about the efficacy
                    of the three-year plan for compiling and publication, but he expressed his
                    belief that the triennial program would facilitate the achievement of the
                    20-year line. He noted the enthusiasm of the present <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> staff and expressed the conviction that the present program
                    would be both swift and professionally sound. Mr. Slany noted that the staff
                    would have to begin working on the volumes for 1955-1957 by June 1976 in order
                    to hold to the current speed-up schedule.</p>
                <p>Several members of the Committee raised questions about the triennial program of
                    publication. They expressed concern that coverage of the years 1952-1954 would
                    be too incomplete and too selective. Members of the staff responded almost
                    unanimously that the triennial program offered distinct advantages of
                    perspective and flexibility, in addition to enabling compilers to move at a
                    faster rate. Mr. Oliver said that he was concerned about the danger of
                    “pre-digestion”, whereby the compiler, in a sense, became the decision-maker.
                    Mr. Aandahl replied that the staff makes an effort to counteract this by
                    including copious references to documents that are not printed and more frequent
                    use of editorial notes. Mr. Petersen stated that he also favored the triennial
                    plan, but he expressed two reservations about it: (a) it is more difficult for a
                    compiler to coordinate with other compilers when everyone is spread over a
                    three-year span, and (b) if we had retained the annual format, we would have
                    been finished compiling the 1952 volumes. Mr. Slany said that we will try to
                    improve coordination between compilers for the 1955-1957 volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield asked if the triennial format would be continued. Mr. Slany
                    responded that it would be continued so long as it proved effective in reaching
                    the 20-year line.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl asked Mr. Slany if we had adequate staff to move ahead with the
                    triennial program. Mr. Slany commented that we needed two or three additional
                    historians and two paraprofessionals. Mr. Westerfield asked Mr. Slany if a
                    choice had to be made between the two, which would have the higher priority. Mr.
                    Slany responded that it would be more desirable to have the paraprofessionals in
                    order to allow the existing staff of historians to work more effectively.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield asked if there was a connection between the HO historians
                    assigned to FOI and Mr. Slany’s request for two additional historians. Mr. Slany
                    stated that the drain caused by HO service to FOI was merely one of several
                    diversions of manpower in HO, and that in the short run it was not particularly
                    serious. Mr. Aandahl pointed out that the FOI program was an important part of
                    the Bureau’s efforts to achieve its overall objectives and that HO was willing
                    to carry its share of the burden.</p>
                <p>[Coffee was served at 10:22 a.m. Discussion resumed at 10:42 a.m.]</p>
                <p>In resuming the discussion, Mr. Aandahl reminded the participants that the Deputy
                    Under Secretary for Management had determined that the meetings would be closed
                    to the public. This information was included in a press release on October 6 and
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Federal Register</hi>, and subsequently the Department
                    had received from the Center for Law and Social Policy a letter challenging the
                    legality of this decision. The matter had been reexamined, and the Department
                    stood by its earlier position.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 5: PROBLEMS OF ACCESS TO RECORDS OF OTHER DEPARTMENTS
                    AND AGENCIES</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that HO was attempting to gain wider access to the records of
                    other agencies, such as AID, DOD, and the Presidential libraries. In regard to
                    the latter, Mr. Petersen reported that two groups of HO historians had traveled
                    to Abilene for research at the Eisenhower Library, and that another group is
                    tentatively scheduled to make the trip in the spring. Both the Eisenhower and
                    Truman Libraries were quite cooperative, and we had found many valuable papers,
                    but we had encountered delays in getting access at the Truman Library to the
                    materials recently accessioned from President Truman’s office (after a long
                    period of probate and other complications). Judge Jessup and Mr. Snyder asked if
                    this was due to inertia or if someone was “blocking the road”. Mr. Aandahl
                    attributed the delay to the normal problems of organizing and accessioning
                    documents into a new archive, especially when their priorities were not always
                    the same as ours.</p>
                <p>Mr. Divine asked whether we had consulted the Dulles papers at Princeton. Mr.
                    Mabon replied that in the summer of 1973 he had looked at some of the Dulles
                    papers relating to Japan in 1951 and had found few valuable items. He also
                    reported that Secretary Dulles’ “personal and confidential” papers consisted
                    largely of speech drafts, that the microfilm portion of the collection was from
                    the Department’s central files, and that the international files had not proved
                    particularly useful.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany raised the question of gaining access to documents in the files of
                    other agencies. He noted the impatience among the staff members of HO to
                    approach the CIA, particularly with respect to events in Guatemala, Iran, and
                    Italy during the 1952-1954 period. He said that perhaps HO had been overcautious
                    in this matter, but he was concerned about the manner in which the approach
                    should be made. He also believed that efforts of this kind might divert the
                    staff from reaching scheduled deadlines. He observed that in the larger sense
                    all agencies should want to have the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series serve as the full record of American foreign policy and the proper
                    vehicle for the orderly declassification of major documentation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield stated that he hoped HO would not give up on the CIA. Mr. Slany
                    replied that we had no intention of giving up, but that the question of how best
                    to approach the agency was overriding. Mr. Claussen pointed out that the CIA had
                    cleared some intelligence estimates for publication. Mr. Westerfield agreed that
                    this was better than nothing, but he stated that distortions would occur if the
                    range of CIA materials in our volumes included only estimates and not operations
                    papers. Mr. Aandahl and Mr. Claussen suggested that it would be helpful if the
                    Committee reaffirmed the view that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was
                    the official record of American foreign policy, and not just an account of State
                    Department involvement.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ferrell expressed concern that, as he understood it, certain researchers
                    working on contract with the Department of Defense were using classified
                    Department of Defense records and perhaps the records of other agencies for an
                    official study which was so designed that the authors could later publish books
                    unofficially drawing on their privileged information. He thought that such
                    activity was unfair and improper and that it again raised issues that had
                    sharply aroused the scholarly world some years ago. He asked the Committee to
                    issue a statement deploring such activity. Several members of the HO staff noted
                    that this was a matter of direct concern to them. Mr. Westerfield commented that
                    it was better to get the record out, regardless of the manner, than not to have
                    it come out at all. Mr. Aandahl said that the normal rule was to release
                    information on an equitable basis and that he thought Defense sought to follow
                    this rule. Mr. Varg and Mr. Snyder expressed the view that the Committee should
                    move cautiously and take a positive approach on this issue, such as suggesting
                    that a general policy statement be drafted for government-wide use regarding the
                    line between official and unofficial research. Mr. Aandahl undertook to get in
                    touch with the Department of Defense on the immediate case brought up by Mr.
                    Ferrell.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 6: PROBLEMS OF DECLASSIFICATION AND CLEARANCE</p>
                <p>[Discussion of classified matters under this agenda item took place in both the
                    morning and the afternoon sessions. This discussion is covered in <ref
                        target="1975-11-14-hac-meeting-minutes-annex">separate classified
                        minutes</ref>.]</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 7: RELATIONS WITH THE NATIONAL ARCHIVES; OPENING OF THE
                    DEPARTMENT’S FILES FOR 1948 AND 1949</p>
                <p>Mr. Kogan described the Department’s policy for opening its records. He explained
                    that previously the records remained closed until all the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for a particular year had been published,
                    but that a change had occurred last summer with the 1948-1949 volumes, when
                    files were opened after all Department of State clearances had been obtained.
                    For these two years virtually all of State’s own files directly relating to
                    foreign policy were now open, with the exception of certain intelligence
                    materials and other specifically excluded categories, including classified
                    papers of other departments, agencies, and governments. Since the Department’s
                    records are organized in five-year blocks, and the next block covers the period
                    1950-1954, we must finish compiling the sixteen volumes for 1952-1954 before the
                    files for 1950 and 1951 can be moved to the National Archives. It would be
                    prohibitively expensive (and probably administratively impossible) to reorganize
                    the block of files, but once the whole block has been moved to Archives,
                    probably in 1976, it would be possible to open 1950 and 1951 separately whenever
                    the proper authorities agreed to their declassification. In reply to Mr.
                    Westerfield’s inquiry as to how this related to Recommendation No. 4 in the
                    Committee’s report last year, Mr. Aandahl said that this substantially met their
                    view that opening of files for a given year need not wait until all of the
                    volumes were published, but it also took into account the practical difficulties
                    of records management. HO would probably recommend opening the 1950 files (for
                    Department of State materials only) after the Department has completed its
                    clearance of the 1950 volumes. As with the 1948 and 1949 files, we would
                    probably not wait for final action by other clearing authorities.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kogan informed the Committee that the Presidential libraries had requested
                    help from HO in declassifying some of their older records, in part because they
                    were being “nibbled to death” by individual requests submitted under the Freedom
                    of Information Act. HO has suggested that the Bureau of Public Affairs ask the
                    Council on Classification Policy (CCP) to approve declassification authority for
                    HO on material over twenty years old in the Presidential libraries. He stated
                    that the Bureau supported the proposal, and that he was reasonably optimistic
                    the other bureaus would also. If they did, the Bureau of Public Affairs would
                    have a strong case when the proposal was presented to the CCP.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl mentioned an approach by the Canadian Government, which was
                    interested in the question of opening Canadian records in tandem with ours. He
                    stated that an informal agreement was being worked out whereby the Department of
                    External Affairs and the Department of State would make available to private
                    researchers in Washington and Ottawa pre-1949 papers dealing with United
                    States-Canadian bilateral matters. Mr. Westerfield inquired whether similar
                    arrangements had been made with other countries. Mr. Aandahl replied that such
                    arrangements existed with the British and the Australians, at least for the
                    period up to 1945.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 8: LUNCHEON</p>
                <p>[At 12:17 p.m. the committee adjourned for lunch with Ambassador Reinhardt and
                    Mr. Earl D. Sohm, Director of Management Operations. Mr. Lawrence S.
                    Eagleburger, Deputy Under Secretary of State for Management, had invited members
                    of the Committee and Mr. Trask to luncheon in the Henry Clay Room. Also invited
                    were Ambassador Reinhardt, Mr. Sohm, and Messrs. Blair, Dyess (PA/M), Aandahl,
                    Costrell, and Slany. In Mr. Eagleburger’s absence Mr. Sohm expressed
                    appreciation for the work of the Committee and said that the Department was
                    trying to solve the problems of slow declassification of basic documents and to
                    remove some of the bottlenecks that were holding up publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Ambassador Reinhardt added his
                    words of appreciation to the members of the Committee for their wise counsel
                    over many years and especially for their assistance in the process of selecting
                    a new director for the Historical Office. Mr. Westerfield responded for the
                    Committee (as noted below). The Committee reconvened at 2:33 p.m.]</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield summarized for the staff the remarks he had made at the luncheon.
                    He said he had complimented HO on its “impressive achievement” of recent years.
                    He had also emphasized the view that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    was the record of the foreign relations of the Unite States, and not exclusively
                    of the Department of State. And he had expressed his appreciation for the
                    cooperation extended to the Committee by the Department, especially with respect
                    to the adoption of the Committee’s recommendation on procedures for selecting a
                    new director.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 9: FREEDOM ON INFORMATION, <hi rend="italic">FOREIGN
                        RELATIONS</hi> AND THE PRIVATE SCHOLAR; THE QUESTION OF APPOINTING AN
                    ARCHIVIST FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF STATE</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany referred to Recommendation No. 5 approved by the Committee last year
                    endorsing the appointment of an archivist for the Department. Both he and Mr.
                    Aandahl stressed the importance of acquiring an archivist to develop a uniform
                    set of procedures for the protection and retirement of the Department’s files
                    and to oversee the preservation of their integrity. Mr. Slany asked the
                    Committee to reaffirm its earlier position.</p>
                <p>A general discussion ensued concerning the possible functions of an archivist,
                    and the problems resulting from not having one, such as the inadvertent
                    destruction of records during the “screening” process in the Foreign Affairs
                    Document and Reference Center (FADRC). Both Mr. Varg and Mr. Oliver raised the
                    possibility that the National Archives could perform archivist functions for the
                    Department. Mr. Costrell suggested the establishment of a State-Archives-Defense
                    committee to consider the issue. Mr. Blair expressed surprise over the fact that
                    some valuable records were being destroyed. He noted that FADRC would have to
                    hire the archivist, and that therefore FADRC would have to be included in all
                    discussions regarding the creation of an archival position.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield commented that the Committee was sympathetic to the staff’s felt
                    need for an archivist, but inasmuch as there was considerable uncertainty about
                    the archivist’s duties and responsibilities, the Committee did not have
                    sufficient information to make a recommendation. Mr. Aandahl suggested that in
                    its report the Committee express interest in the creation of an archivist’s
                    position, and also recommend the need for a thorough study of the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany referred to potential problems facing HO as a result of the
                    Department’s implementation of the Freedom of Information Act. He mentioned the
                    possible adverse effect of requests by private scholars for the same material
                    that was being used to compile <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and the
                    question of the extent of aid that should be given to private scholars seeking
                    information about classified materials. With respect to the first problem, Mr.
                    Oliver stated that any interference with the efforts to speed up publication of
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was regrettable, but that the Act
                    was the law of the land and took precedence. Mr. Ferrell asked whether we had
                    actually encountered difficulty in connection with the second problem. Mr. Slany
                    responded that we had begun to experience difficulty, and for that reason he was
                    seeking guidance from the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 10: PROBLEMS OF BUDGET, TECHNICAL EDITING, PRINTING,
                    AND DISTRIBUTION</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany reviewed the current problems in the technical editing sector. He
                    pointed out, for example, that the lag between the submission of finished
                    manuscript to PBR and the printing of galleys by the Government Printing Office
                    had reached eighteen months. Mr. Snyder commented that this figure indicated
                    that the time recently gained in compilation had been lost in editing. Mr. Varg
                    suggested that the Committee make a statement for the record that it was “deeply
                    disturbed” by this situation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl stated that the problem with PBR (Publishing and Reproduction
                    Division) could be largely solved by the addition of two or three
                    fully-qualified senior editors to the PBR staff. Mr. Westerfield raised the
                    possibility of a contract with a private editing firm. Mr. Aandahl responded
                    that this would not be feasible because of the need for continuity and
                    supervisory responsibility in the Department, which could not afford to become
                    completely dependent on outside contractors. Mr Ferrell remarked that what PBR
                    seemed to need was a shake-up rather than additional staff. Mr. Aandahl and Mr.
                    Dougall both disagreed with this. They said that the PBR editors were doing a
                    commendable job, but that they were seriously understaffed.</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 11: PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE HISTORICAL OFFICE
                    STAFF</p>
                <p>Mr Slany noted that as a result of a series of meetings within the Bureau called
                    last year by Assistant Secretary Laise, several proposals designed to enhance
                    the skills of staff members had been sent forward, including a recommendation
                    for released time to enable staff to engage in private research and/or study.
                    Ambassador Laise had responded favorably to the proposals for professional
                    development. Mr. Costrell spoke against proposals involving released time,
                    because they would weaken any argument advanced for needing new staff. Mr.
                    Aandahl noted the budgetary and manpower problems raised by proposals for
                    professional development but expressed readiness to pursue any program
                    authorized by the Bureau.</p>
                <p> Mr. Ferrell asked about the possibility of a flexi-time (10-hour day/4-day week)
                    arrangement, which would allow staff members one free day for research. In
                    response to a query from Mr. Aandahl, Mr. Dougall stated that this might
                    eventually be administratively feasible but that at the moment it involved
                    difficulties such as extra payment for overtime.</p>
                <p>Mr. Westerfield invited Mr. Trask to make some closing remarks. Mr. Trask stated
                    that he approached the position of director with enthusiasm. He had no “grand
                    design” for HO, but certain changes would be desirable. First priority would be
                    given to strengthening the relationship between the Office and outside
                    researchers. The question of professional development of the staff was also a
                    vital one, and he would make it a matter of high priority from the moment of his
                    arrival as director.</p>
                <p>[The Committee rose at 4:27 p.m.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
