<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Annex to Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting,
                    November 1975</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes Annex, 1975</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-19">May 19, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1975-11-14">November 14, 1975</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1975-11-14-hac-meeting-minutes-annex.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 39 KB, 2pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 2, 1975—Minutes. Confidential.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Annex to Minutes of the 1975 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 14, 1975</dateline>
                <p>[The discussion of classified matters under this agenda item took place in both
                    the morning and afternoon sessions. The discussion of other agenda items and the
                    list of participants are covered in <ref target="1975-11-14-hac-meeting-minutes"
                        >separate unclassified minutes</ref>.]</p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEM 6: PROBLEMS OF DECLASSIFICATION AND CLEARANCE</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl asked Mr. Trask to absent himself temporarily while discussion of
                    certain classified materials took place. Copies of documents concerning the Chou
                    En-lai approach of 1949 were then distributed to the Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl explained that the question facing the Historical Office (HO) was
                    whether to publish the 1949 China volume without these documents, or to wait
                    longer in the hope that we might obtain declassification. Mr. Dougall stated
                    that, in the opinion of HO, the omission of these documents would constitute a
                    serious distortion of the record. Mr. Varg, Mr. Snyder, and Mr. Oliver agreed
                    that this would be the case. Mr. Varg inquired as to the nature of the
                    Department’s objections. Mr. Dougall replied that officers in EA believed that
                    release would constitute a possible danger to Chou and his colleagues, and that
                    officials in the Department had expressed concern about possible adverse affects
                    on the delicate nature of United States relations with the People’s Republic of
                    China. Mr. Aandahl added that EA had indicated that it would take the matter
                    straight to Secretary Kissinger if PA raised the issue in the Department’s
                    Council on Classification Policy (CCP). EA was likely to maintain its opposition
                    for a long time, and this forced HO to decide whether to hold the
                    otherwise-cleared volume, perhaps indefinitely, or to release it with
                    indications that some documentation had not been available for publication.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl distributed to the Committee copies of a memorandum he had submitted
                    to Ambassador Reinhardt on June 26 setting forth the options available to HO. In
                    view of EA’s strong opposition, which PA did not feel it could overcome under
                    present conditions, it had been tentatively decided to publish the volume
                    without the contested documents, which would be replaced by short editorial
                    notes indicating omissions. The question was how informative these notes could
                    be. The members of the Committee agreed that it was important to call attention
                    to the omission of significant documents, and Mr. Blair said that an effort
                    should be made to obtain CCP support for reasonably explicit editorial notes.
                    Mr. Aandahl thanked the Committee for its advice on this matter and said that HO
                    will prepare explicit notes and seek to get them cleared.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
