<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Action Memorandum From William Blair Through Lawrence
                    Eagleburger to Henry Kissinger, November 1976</title>
                <title type="short">Blair to Kissinger, 1976</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-16">December 16, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1976-11-17">November 17, 1976</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1976-11-17-blair-to-kissinger.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 168 KB, 10pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-08D-4: Bureau of Public Affairs, Assistant Secretary and Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary Subject Files, 1975-1981 (82 D 297), Box 8, Public Affairs:
                    Historian’s Office 1977. Drafted by David Trask, November 16, 1976. Cleared by
                    Samuel Goldberg (H). An unknown hand added “12/8 Per Secto 32013 (?) Secretary
                    signed memo - to be dispatched on Sec’s return.” The attached memoranda are
                    neither initialed nor signed. See National Archives and Records Administration,
                    Record Group 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D760452-1128 and
                    P760188-2320.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn91">Footnote 91</ref></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="blair-to-kissinger">
                <head>Action Memorandum From William Blair (Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Public Affairs) Through Lawrence Eagleburger (Deputy Under Secretary of State
                    for Management) to Henry Kissinger (Secretary of State)</head>
                <dateline>November 17, 1976</dateline>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Future of the Foreign Relations
                        Series</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Summary</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, a major asset in our
                    openness program, faces serious problems of coverage and declassification,
                    particularly with regard to important papers of other agencies. These problems
                    also affect the schedule, and there is much pressure to speed up publication. We
                    need your decision on policy. Should the series continue about as at present, or
                    should we take steps to strengthen it? These would include asking President Ford
                    to issue instructions (similar to those of Presidents Kennedy and Nixon) calling
                    on State and other agencies to improve the documentary coverage and accelerate
                    declassification and publication. A memorandum to the President is attached for
                    your decision.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Discussion</p>
                <p>The Congress and the public are demanding ever more insistently that the Federal
                    Executive provide detailed and expeditious information about its activities. In
                    this context the Department’s <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> series assumes special significance, as the most venerable and
                    comprehensive effort of the government to provide an objective record of its
                    performance.</p>
                <p>At this juncture the future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series appears uncertain, because of two interrelated problems. One persistent
                    concern is that the series has fallen well behind the prescribed twenty-year
                    line. The delay now reaches to twenty-seven years, and further slippage seems in
                    prospect.</p>
                <p>This nagging problem, however serious, is less worrisome than the prospect that
                    the series may become less and less able to fulfill its prime mission--full and
                    fair representation of the foreign-policy process as it has affected the
                    important issues. Difficulties in this respect arise because many agencies
                    besides the Department of State now contribute importantly to foreign policy and
                    diplomacy. To compile an accurate record today, scholars from the Office of the
                    Historian must examine not only State Department records, but also those of the
                    Departments of Defense and Treasury among others, the Central Intelligence
                    Agency, the Energy Research and Development Agency, and above all the National
                    Security Council.</p>
                <p>In addition, Department historians must be able to facilitate declassification of
                    the other-agency documents selected for publication, so that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series can issue according to a
                    dependable and reasonably expeditious schedule. Unfortunately, it cannot be said
                    that the existing arrangements for access and clearance ensure fully
                    comprehensive coverage.</p>
                <p>If it proves impossible to maintain sufficiently comprehensive coverage and
                    reasonably expeditious issue, then the quality and utility of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series are bound to decline. Criticism
                    from the domestic foreign affairs community will increase. The hands of those in
                    the Congress and elsewhere who advocate unworkable standards of disclosure will
                    be strengthened (we expect a substantial effort to be made in the next Congress
                    to redefine the classification system by legislation, in part to require much
                    earlier and fuller release of documentation on foreign policy and defense). To
                    avoid serious difficulties of this kind and to strengthen public confidence in
                    our management of official information, the Executive agencies clearly must make
                    every effort to ensure the highest possible standards of disclosure consistent
                    with the real requirements of national security.</p>
                <p>Given the comprehensive nature of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series, encompassing materials from a broad range of agencies, it is arguable
                    that responsibility for conduct of this program might be exercised by the
                    National Security Council. Practical as well as theoretical consideration,
                    however, weigh heavily against any such rearrangement. The bulk of the work
                    remains in and with the State Department; the National Security Council Staff is
                    not now equipped to assume this charge, or designed to conduct operations
                    generally. Location of the function in the Department of State has stood the
                    test of a century’s experience and continues to produce a result reflecting
                    credit on the Executive as a whole.</p>
                <p>In these circumstances, the need appears to be to support the Historian’s Office
                    in responding to current condition and in assuring the continuing integrity of
                    the series. In broad terms, there appear to be two policy options:</p>
                <p>The first would be to continue as at present, accepting the consequences of
                    mounting deficiencies in coverage and increasing delays in publication. This
                    however would tend to contradict the Department’s posture of openness and impede
                    efforts to improve its credibility with Congress and public. Nevertheless, these
                    political costs might prove endurable in the short run and perhaps for some time
                    to come.</p>
                <p>A conceivable variant on this option might be to achieve acceleration by reducing
                    coverage, perhaps to the extent of documenting only the role of the Department
                    itself; but, because this course would force exclusion of patently indispensable
                    information, the net effect would be to destroy the usefulness of the volumes.
                    For this reason we not consider this variant as an acceptable alternative.</p>
                <p>The second realistic option would be to strengthen the series. This would mean
                    improving its substantive coverage of other-agency documentation and
                    accelerating its publication schedule--i.e., beginning to reduce the time lag
                    back toward the 20-year goal. This would require clarification of the series’
                    mission, by or in the name of the President, to ensure full cooperation of other
                    agencies. For full implementation, some additional manpower and printing funds
                    would also have to be found, for faster review and publication of more, and more
                    diversified, foreign policy materials, though a start could be made with present
                    resources.</p>
                <p>We believe that gains from this second option would far outweigh the essentially
                    modest additional costs associated with it. (We are not requesting resources
                    now, and if you decide in principle that we should move in the direction
                    recommended, we would expect to seek them through the normal budgetary
                    channels.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Recommendation:</hi> That you sign the attached memorandum
                    to the President to request an instruction to the foreign affairs agencies
                    concerning comprehensive policy content and accelerated publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="kissinger-to-ford">
                <head>Attached Draft Memorandum from Henry Kissinger to President Gerald Ford</head>
                <dateline>December 7, 1976</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Series</p>
                <p>The American people have a deep and abiding interest in the development of their
                    foreign policy, and our government has an unmatched record of accomplishment in
                    providing the basic information they must have in order to make wise decisions.
                    In this process a most effective instrumentality has been the series of
                    documentary volumes, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi>. For 115 years this distinguished collection has given a fair
                    and balanced publication of our principal diplomatic, economic, and military
                    papers. The 260 volumes covering the years from Lincoln to Truman include
                    documents from many departments and agencies. Widely respected for candor and
                    dependability, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series contributes
                    both to the credibility of the United States abroad and to public respect at
                    home for the integrity of the foreign policy record.</p>
                <p>However, the series today is in need of assistance if it is to maintain its
                    performance in the face of changing conditions. In the postwar period, numerous
                    agencies in addition to the Office of the President and the Department of State
                    increasingly have contributed to the formulation and conduct of foreign policy;
                    and the record of these contributions requires review for selection,
                    declassification, and orderly publication in the series, in accordance with the
                    same high standards of scholarship and prompt disclosure that have been applied
                    to the records of the traditional foreign policy sources. To ensure that this is
                    done, I recommend that you approve and sign the two attached memoranda directing
                    the responsible officials to take certain measures to strengthen <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and expedite the process of
                    declassification and publication.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="president-to-state">
                <head>Draft Memorandum From President Ford to the Secretary of State</head>
                <p>The official documentary series entitled <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</hi> was first published in 1861 as part of President
                    Lincoln’s annual message to the Congress. The series, which now includes some
                    260 volumes, has long provided the American people an indispensable perspective
                    on the nation’s history. The charge of Foreign Relations is to provide a
                    comprehensive review of U.S. foreign policy and diplomacy. In recent years the
                    volumes in the series have included considerable documentation from the records
                    of many agencies and departments besides the Department of State, reflecting the
                    expansion of governmental engagement in the foreign-policy process.</p>
                <p>President Kennedy in 1961 and President Nixon in 1972 indicated that the
                    lengthening interval between events and their description in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> should be shortened, without impairing the quality
                    of the volumes, in order to meet the public need for timely information about
                    how our foreign policy was made. I share the considerations that actuated my
                    predecessors. Therefore, while recognizing the difficulties involved, I ask that
                    you develop means of ensuring fully comprehensive coverage of American diplomacy
                    and of accelerating production of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. Our goal should be to publish the volumes about twenty years after the
                    events they record.</p>
                <p>In order to achieve these goals in the most expeditious and effective manner, I
                    am today instructing the Secretary of Defense, the Director of Central
                    Intelligence, the Administrator of General Services, and the Assistant to the
                    President for National Security Affairs to cooperate fully with you in supplying
                    and declassifying appropriate documents to the maximum extent consistent with
                    the requirements of national security.</p>
                <p>Gerald R. Ford</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="ford-to-agencies">
                <head>Draft Memorandum From President Ford to the Secretary of Defense, the Director
                    of Central Intelligence, the Administrator of General Services, and the
                    Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</head>
                <p>Subject: Improvement and Acceleration of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Series</p>
                <p>The documentary series entitled <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi>, published by the Department of State, is the means by which the
                    Presidents of the United States since Abraham Lincoln have provided a frank and
                    comprehensive record of the nation’s foreign policy and diplomacy for use of the
                    American people. To ensure the most authoritative coverage possible, it is
                    necessary for the compilers of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to
                    examine relevant records of the large number of departments and agencies which
                    contribute to the foreign-policy process.</p>
                <p>I have today instructed the Secretary of State to develop a program designed to
                    ensure full coverage of our foreign relations and to reduce the gap between
                    events and publication of the record to twenty years. The Department of State
                    will continue to seek the assistance of appropriate agencies and departments in
                    collecting and declassifying documents deemed appropriate for publication in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>I ask each of you to cooperate fully with the Secretary of State, to the maximum
                    extent consistent with the requirements of national security, in facilitating
                    thorough examination and expeditious declassification of the relevant parts of
                    the historical record in your keeping.</p>
                <p>Gerald R. Ford</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
