<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From William Slany and Edwin Costrell to PA/HO
                    Staff, October 1976</title>
                <title type="short">Slany and Costrell to HO Staff, 1976</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-27">January 27, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1976-10-26">October 26, 1976</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1976-10-26-slany-and-costrell-to-ho-staff.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 385 KB, 1p.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-WW-9: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, Arthur
                    Kogan Files, 1945-1980 (83 D 230), Box 2, Foreign Classified Documents General.
                    Drafted by William Slany. Copies sent to David Stauffer, Frederick Aandahl, and
                    Edwin Costrell (PA/HO). The attached Confidential airgram (A-678) was found in
                    the Foreign Gov. Inf: Great Britain folder in the same archival collection and
                    box, but is not posted. Posted from an uninitialed copy of the
                memorandum.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn88">Footnote 88</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From William Z. Slany (Associate Historian for Western Hemisphere
                    and Europe) and Edwin S. Costrell (Associate Historian for Asia, Africa, and the
                    Pacific) to PA/HO Staff</head>
                <dateline>October 26, 1976</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Limitations on the Inclusion in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> manuscripts of British and other foreign-originated
                    documents</p>
                <p>Over the past several years the experience of this Office with respect to the
                    clearance for publication by the British Foreign Office of texts of
                    British-originated documents has been uniformly disappointing. General1y
                    speaking the Foreign Office has been unwilling to concur in the publication in
                    our <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series of any British document save
                    for certain innocuous, high-level, courtesy correspondence. Some greater success
                    has been experienced in securing British concurrence to the publication of
                    multilateral documents.</p>
                <p>In a communication of September 20 of this year to the Embassy in London (a copy
                    of which is attached), the Foreign Office has again reiterated its
                    disinclination to agree to the publication of British documents in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>In view of the continuing unlikelihood of Foreign Office cooperation in the
                    matter of clearance of British documents, we must more consciously design our
                    selections of documents for the series with an eye to avoiding the inclusion of
                    British-originated documents except those which appear to be absolutely
                    critically important. We probably can continue to seek to print those of a
                    multi-lateral nature which we might reasonably expect to be cleared.</p>
                <p>The experience with the Foreign Office is by no means unique. The self-denying
                    ordinance applied to British documents should probably also be applied to the
                    documents of other friendly governments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
