<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Meeting Between Henry Kissinger and the HAC, November
                    1976</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting With Kissinger, 1976</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-24">December 24, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1976-11-12">November 12, 1976</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1976-11-12-hac-meeting-with-kissinger.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 388 KB, 23pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 3, 1976-Report. The Committee members
                    identified by last name in the participant list were: Dr. Covey T. Oliver,
                    Professor of International Law at the University of Pennsylvania; Dr. Bernard C.
                    Cohen, Professor of Political Science at the University of Wisconsin; Dr. Robert
                    A. Divine, Professor of History at the University of Texas; Dr. Lloyd C.
                    Gardner, Professor of History at Rutgers University; Dr. Harold K. Jacobson,
                    Professor of Political Science at the University of Michigan; and Judge Philip
                    C. Jessup, retired from the International Court of Justice. Committee member Dr.
                    Norman A. Graebner, Professor of History at the University of Virginia, was not
                    present.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref
                    target="../chapter-8#fn92">Footnote 92</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Meeting of Secretary Kissinger With Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi></head>
                <dateline>Secretary’s Conference Room, November 12, 1976</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">In Attendance</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Secretary of State Kissinger</item>
                    <item>Professor Oliver - Chairman</item>
                    <item>Mr. Trask</item>
                    <item>Professor Divine</item>
                    <item>Mr. Aandahl</item>
                    <item>Ambassador Jessup</item>
                    <item>Ambassador Reinhardt</item>
                    <item>Professor Cohen</item>
                    <item>Professor Jacobson</item>
                    <item>Professor Gardner</item>
                </list>
                <p>(The meeting was convened at 3:45 p.m.)</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, gentlemen, I first of all want to express my
                    appreciation to you for coming down here and for participating in what I, as
                    somebody who is extremely interested in history, strongly support- I don’t have
                    the time to give day-to-day attention to the important problem on which our
                    historians are working, but I’m extremely sympathetic to it; and this is a good
                    opportunity to find out what your recommendations are and what you think we can
                    do.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Well, thank you very much. We shall do that.</p>
                <p>If I may for just a moment, I am in the position of being the Transition Chairman
                    -- since this is my last year of service on a Committee that, as you know,
                    represents the interests of consumers of foreign affairs history in the United
                    States. And, in the groups we represent as claimant groups, we have found in the
                    four years that I have been here steady progress.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: You have?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: We have, indeed.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I’m glad of that.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Of course, we are very pleased that you, Mr. Secretary -- you
                    and your associates in the Department -- have seen fit to accept our strong
                    recommendation that David Trask become the Historian of the Department, and we
                    have seen progressively over the years the steady improvement in the scientific
                    process of aggregating and selecting the material that should go both into the
                    research work of the Department in foreign affairs history and into the
                    publication of a U.S. foreign relations series.</p>
                <p>At the present stage, my impression -- though we as a Committee have not had time
                    to caucus yet; we’ll do that later -- my impression is that this is a good year,
                    indeed. We find the relationship between the Bureau and the Office to be
                    excellent because we have--</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: The Bureau being John?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: The Bureau being, of course, our good friend the Ambassador,
                    and David and his associates in the Office.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Don’t be associated with Reinhardt. He’s the biggest con
                    artist in the building. I pity those poor Africans whom he gets to deal with on
                    those occasional trips! (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: We do find, as I say in my report -- we came to that conclusion
                    as we caucused. At the present time there are some production and engineering
                    problems mainly, and they’re largely problems of funding and money -- of how to
                    move the materials in that have been selected and Xeroxed into print. This
                    involves many issues, including the problems of the Government Printing Office
                    that perhaps haven’t come to your attention, but they do exist. The GPO is an
                    overworked institution and it sets its own priorities, and the historical
                    priorities are not of the highest.</p>
                <p>That’s one set of priorities. It’s funding for production -- an engineering and
                    production sort of job. There are a few scientific problems. Mainly there are
                    problems, as we have seen them, of delays asked for clearance, of very key
                    documents -- developments that should, if possible, go into the regularized
                    compilations.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Clearance from this building or clearance from other
                    agencies?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Both.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Both.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Mostly from other agencies though.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: They’re not many, but they happen to be salient.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Of course, clearance from this building we ought to be able
                    to expedite.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: On most occasions we have been able to.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Who does the clearing here?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: The Bureau. Where the document originates is the prime
                    mover.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: I think I’ve said enough in my very transitory role as
                    Chairman. I would much prefer that my colleagues on the Committee express
                    themselves to you in the brief time that I’m sure you can be with us. And I
                    want, on behalf of all of us, to thank you for giving us this time.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I’m delighted to do it. In fact, I expect to be a consumer.
                    (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: On the Committee? (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Yes. We look forward to that. My fellow Texan, Professor
                    Divine, has been serving in the Committee for some time. Perhaps he would like
                    to say something.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: I would just like to point out on the clearance problems it’s
                    not only the question of foreign relations but also the manuscript records. It
                    has to be cleared through the Department before it goes to the National
                    Archives. For many scholars it’s crucial -- not just to compile material for the
                    volume. It depends on the actual clearance. The clearance holds up the whole
                    scholarly process. Right now the scholars cannot get beyond 1949 in terms of
                    scholarship records, which means even the Korean war.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: What is the difference between manuscript records and
                    documents?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: Foreign Relations prints only a small percentage of the
                    high-level, more sensitive records.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Oh, I see, I see -- documents for Foreign Relations in
                    addition.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: Once they’re cleared for, the lesser documents are
                    automatically cleared as well; but everything proceeds on that basis --</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I see.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: -- and right now the compilations are only coming up to
                    ’49.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: What I have trouble understanding -- and I should have asked
                    my associates -- is how can any scholar work on the mass of material that is
                    flowing through the Department? Leaving aside now whether it’s cleared or not,
                    we get -- what? -- two-three thousand cables a day. Now, I have people sorting
                    them out for me -- sometimes well, and sometimes to keep me from forming an
                    opinion. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: Well, my colleagues working on the 19th Century find the new
                    documents are revealing, and those of us who work on the 20th Century find just
                    exactly the opposite.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Exactly. I worked on 19th Century. It wasn’t easy, but the
                    fact was with communications, whether worse or poor, they had to give detailed
                    instructions explaining their reasoning and they couldn’t give tactical
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>Today we don’t explain our reasoning. We tell the Ambassador: “When you go in,
                    say the following.” If we have something that involves conceptualization, we’re
                    more likely to send somebody out.</p>
                <p>What happens to talking points, for example? Do they disappear?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: No, they don’t; but they haven’t come up by ’49, to any
                    great extent --</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: Yes.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: --but they don’t disappear.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: In the new record-keeping, are they in the records?</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: They’ll be in our computerized retrieval system, yes.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: You know, when Jack goes on a trip to Africa -- even those
                    talking points aren’t all that helpful. They contain what you said. They don’t
                    contain why we said it, what the reasoning is.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: No.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: I’d like to raise two points; and I should repeat that since we
                    have not caucused, these are personal; they are not Committee. And they both
                    grow out of the acceptance of the documentary record. I’m sure earlier Dean
                    Acheson pressed for the creation of a page with a footnote, and the documentary
                    records of this are not very good and are not a basis for anchoring historical
                    reconstruction.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I don’t know. My fear is that they’re too good.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: Too good. Well, I wonder if that isn’t a problem of your current
                    need for fast decision as against the academic who’s got a lot of time to go
                    through the record.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: No. Even if you had -- for me I have no problem. I get what
                    I need to have. But then I know what I’m trying to do. so it’s not that there’s
                    too much for the Secretary of State. There probably is also. But I’m putting
                    myself in the position of a scholar who doesn’t know what one was trying to do.
                    Therefore, he’ll want to work through the document.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: Yes.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: What documents do we really consider relevant and which
                    don’t we consider relevant? What is your criterion of relevancy? That’s the
                    problem that’s going to exist on any negotiation. There are thousands.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: But I would go further and say no matter what your criteria are,
                    you probably would find that the documents aren’t sufficient -- I mean, you were
                    saying yourself that certain things were not in the record. So what I had in
                    mind was this -- two points: One is that since the Historical Office has been
                    reorganized so that the foreign relations function and the other ordinary
                    historical research functions of the Office are combined. We find ourselves in
                    the odd position that the charter of this Committee is only concerned with the
                    documentary -- the foreign relations function. And it seems to me that there
                    would be some point in enlarging the charge of the Advisory Committee to include
                    all the historical functions of the Historical Office and, in part, in order to
                    get to this Committee.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, I like that idea. Do we have a different group for the
                    other one?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: No. It’s the same group of people. They have now been
                    merged. They used to work separately.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: No, no -- but I mean in terms of the Advisory Group, do we
                    have a different Advisory group?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: No. This is the only Advisory Group.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, why don’t we expand their function?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: We can. Well, this suggestion was just coming up.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: Yes. And it seems to me that it would then permit the Committee
                    to go into all kinds of questions -- like what sources of data would be good for
                    the record, apart from those that exist in the documents.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: The present limitation shouldn’t restrict us, but some of the
                    expectant -- I won’t say “claimant” -- groups represented are more interested in
                    foreign relations than in the wide-ranging historical research. For example,
                    Judge Jessup and I represent the American Society of International Law and our
                    focus is a fairly sharp one if it’s international relations, but the historians
                    represented by the American Historical Association have a different view; and I
                    think it’s very sound that we try to expand the charter of the Advisory
                    Group.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JESSUP: But it seems to me, Mr. Secretary, that you have the
                    inevitable problem in the clearance of documents. The officers who are in charge
                    of a particular negotiation or a particular relation with a certain country in a
                    given time, when asked to clear a document -- they have to see the difficulties.
                    and if it comes to you, you are right apt to say, “Well, if you see this
                    difficulty, I think we better hold it up. History will take care of itself in a
                    few more years.”</p>
                <p>So HO is bound to lose out on that kind of thing. Now, it always has, and I’m
                    afraid it probably always will. Now, I hope when you cease to be Secretary that
                    you might have a different idea about the declassification of documents than you
                    might have had last week.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, I don’t think that I was -- no; I was quite
                    sympathetic to the declassification of documents, whenever decisions came to me.
                    Is that fair -- is that correct or not?</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: I think that is right, Mr. Secretary.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I think I was, but the normal tendency of a Secretary of
                    State is to back up his Bureaus.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Sure, sure.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: And the normal tendency of the Bureaus is to hold --</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: To hold tight.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: -- to hold tight. And the normal function of the agencies is
                    to avoid anything controversial, so the clearance is tough. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Might we without a caucus discuss how much time the Secretary
                    has? As far as foreign relations is concerned, the target is official
                    publication 20 years after the event. So for that you have until 1996, I
                    believe, or so; don’t you think? (Laughter.) But, as to the research side, what
                    would be a desirable minimum -- or maximum, rather?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: Time?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Classification period. How do you view as a research --</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Why should it be different?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: Different from what?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: From 20 years. Well, 20 years is the old-type, preselected
                    official range. People may want to delve earlier, I would suppose. I don’t
                    know.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: They can’t unless the records have been declassified .</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: I know, I know.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: But he’s asking the question whether we should focus in on a
                    different time frame.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Now we’re talking in the context of explaining the claim of the
                    Committee, so I thought it fair to raise this question.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: I would say -- five years? (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JESSUP: It used to be ten, didn’t it, for a while?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Yes.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Ten -- before you could go into the records, really.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR JESSUP: They tried to get foreign relations within ten years. That
                    used to be.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: When was that?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: When it originally began was the next year. It was published
                    the next year in 1862-1863.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: From the official correspondence, and it did not attempt really to
                    describe the overall process of formation and execution, so that we are
                    comparing oranges and pears; and I think we have to realize that the expanded
                    scope of the series makes it much more difficult, as it raises problems that did
                    not arise for our forebears, and we can’t talk about five years, but I think
                    --</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: No; of course, not.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR GARDNER: Didn’t I understand this afternoon that the 1949 China volume
                    was actually ready in 1952 or ’53?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: ’56.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR GARDNER: It was ready in ’56, and it was held up for 20 years almost on
                    account of a few documents that people can’t get clearance on.</p>
                <p>MR. AANDAHL: I think it was wider than that. It was held up by order of Secretary
                    Dulles in 1957 because the first volumes that came out had a bad political
                    effect. So the series as a whole were held up and Secretary Rusk later agreed
                    that the others were to come out with the other volumes for the same year. It’s
                    been held in galley proof for many years -- yes.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Well, we come to a celebrated case, Mr. Secretary, that has
                    been before our group for many years; and it does concern the foreign relations,
                    actually, as has just been stated; and it involves some very interesting, and
                    really quite revealing possibly, initiatives by Chou En-lai, as reported through
                    --</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: In what year?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR DIVINE: November ’49.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: ’49. And EA -- we may as well speak frankly here. EA has been
                    reluctant up to now to give its clearance; and we’re not trying, you know, to
                    bring you down on top of EA.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Even the present EA.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: What?</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Even the present EA.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Yes.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, what’s their initiative?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: I told Joe Dyess that they wouldn’t even consider releasing
                    this document. Now it has been reintroduced to EA and they still are unwilling
                    to release it.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: On what grounds now?</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: On grounds that things are not settled in China and that
                    this could be --</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Well, what’s in that damn document? I’d be interested.
                    (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: There was a lot of factionalism, as you realize; and there was, in
                    effect, a group that wanted to initiate relations with the United States in this
                    mid-1949 period. Nothing came of this ultimately, but there was a feeling in EA
                    that in some sense you might be pointing the finger -- you might be signing the
                    death warrant of some people who were on the side of that initiative -- and so
                    on. But they were of the feeling in some way this material might seriously
                    compromise some people still living in China and might embarrass us
                    politically.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: We mention it only as illustrative of the few problems of this
                    sort that arise; and for my part, not to bring you down on top of your Bureau,
                    as an old Assistant Secretary I wouldn’t want that to happen (laughter), but
                    it’s just one of those situations.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: It’s a good thing. Ambassador Reinhardt would confirm that
                    I’m going to be down on some Bureau for some reason. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: We’ll turn to EA. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: That’s my administrative principle -- never to let the
                    Bureaus think that I’m not watching. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: No. This has been a very bothersome problem for the reason
                    these gentlemen have pointed out. Nevertheless, we’ve had a certain sympathy
                    with the arguments that we’ve heard from EA. We’re going to have less sympathy
                    -- what has it been, six months after Chou’s death? A year from now I wouldn’t
                    know what their reasoning would be.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: And you wouldn’t release a volume with some documents
                    missing?</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: We feel that these documents are so important that not to include them
                    would go beyond the bounds of proper practice.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: But you might add that EA wouldn’t even let you put a note
                    there.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: They wouldn’t even let us put a footnote there.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: But we have now come back to make another request, and their views
                    might now be different. We can’t tell.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: I’m not sure that Hummel has yet focused on this as some
                    people under him have. Do you know?</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: We do not know, except we have some indications.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Probably the institutions are less efficient than academic
                    institutions (laughter), so the only ones that can generate more work than
                    faculty meetings are the Bureaus. (Laughter.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR COHEN: It’s a little bigger.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: But this case, while a special and unusual one, is a particularly
                    important one from the point of view of the principles involved; and that’s why
                    it interests us.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: What were you an Assistant Secretary of? (Addresses
                    Professor Oliver.)</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: ARA. My heart was really in E. I grew up with E from ’42 on,
                    but in the 60s I was tapped to run Inter-American Affairs. EB it’s called now.
                    In my time it was just E. But I used to come up through the arched doors past
                    Secretary Olney’s portrait to attend meetings of your predecessor in this
                    room.</p>
                <p>I don’t know whether we should mention the other cause celebre to the Secretary
                    or let it ride.</p>
                <p>Professor Jacobson, do you wish to address some memorials to the Secretary now
                    while we have the opportunity?</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR JACOBSON: It’s a slightly different topic.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Let’s move to a different topic.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR JACOBSON: As the range of foreign policy expands, the problems of
                    getting the record straight will increase-- when Labor takes a role, for example
                    -- getting documents from the Department of Labor -- and Agriculture and
                    Treasury and so on.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: But theirs are unclassified.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: It’s possible the ones that interest us will be classified.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I don’t exactly know this. It’s rather disgraceful for me to
                    admit, but I don’t know how these documents are selected. What do you do? You
                    try to get together -- what’s your definition of what a relevant document is? I
                    suppose the Bureaus give you copies of everything.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: We begin, of course, with the Department’s records; but many other
                    agencies are involved. We have various procedures for attempting to gain access,
                    and later to publish their records too.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Does that include Restricted classification cables that go
                    only to, say, me, and --</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: NODIS.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: NODIS, Limited.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: We haven’t come to that point in the historical period when we get
                    that sort of classification, but we will.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Because without it it means nothing.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: That’s right.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Well, there are far fewer of them. That’s where they are
                    now.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Because Top Secret I don’t even see -- use any more --</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Very seldom.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: -- and it has no significance anyway. (Laughter.) You know,
                    it’s the modifiers. I think the distribution of Top Secret -- I don’t know how
                    much less it is than Secret. But what really cuts down distribution is the
                    LIMDIS, EXDIS, NODIS and some other special ones. And I would say that for my
                    period and for the period preceding, if you don’t have access to those you can’t
                    write a history that’s worth a damn.</p>
                <p>MR. TRASK: This question arises for us in connection with our policy-related
                    research in various very recent materials but not as yet for the compilation of
                    the Foreign Relations Series.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: When they come to that point, presumably the historians
                    within the Department will have access; but they will have a monumental task of
                    getting clearance.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I would have thought that some of this would have been next
                    to impossible.</p>
                <p>Well, gentlemen, are there any other problems that we --</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Professor Gardner?</p>
                <p>SECRETARY GARDNER: No.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: I appreciate it very much.</p>
                <p>We’ll expand your charter, unless Jack has some objections which he --</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: I can see no objections.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: -- which he’s not eager to mention at this meeting
                    (laughter). But I think we ought to do both -- the research and the foreign
                    policy series.</p>
                <p>Thank you very much.</p>
                <p>PROFESSOR OLIVER: Thank you very much, Mr. Secretary.</p>
                <p>SECRETARY KISSINGER: Nice to see you.</p>
                <p>AMBASSADOR REINHARDT: Thank you, Mr. Secretary.</p>
                <p>(Whereupon, at 4:12 p.m., the meeting was concluded.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
