<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1977</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1977</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-03-24">March 24, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1977-11-11">November 11, 1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1977-11-11-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 260 KB, 15pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 3, 1977-Minutes.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1977 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi></head>
                <dateline>November 11, 1977</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Lloyd C. Gardner, Professor of History, Rutgers University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Norman A. Graebner, Professor of History, University of
                        Virginia</item>
                    <item>Dr. Betty Miller Unterberger, Professor of History, Texas A &amp; M
                        University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bernard C. Cohen, Professor of Political Science, University of
                        Wisconsin</item>
                    <item>Dr. Harold K. Jacobson, Professor of Political Science, University of
                        Michigan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Stevenson, Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, New York</item>
                    <item>Dr. Alona E. Evans, Professor of Political Science, Wellesley
                        College</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William D. Blair, Jr., Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>David F. Trask, The Historian (Executive Secretary of the Advisory
                        Committee)</item>
                    <item>Fredrick Aandahl, The Associate Historian</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Edwin S. Costrell</item>
                    <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                    <item>Mary P. Chapman</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                    <item>Allen H. Kitchens</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Harry F. Young</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Mary M. Brandt</item>
                    <item>Roberta L. DiGangi</item>
                    <item>Lynn K. Fliakas</item>
                    <item>Mark Garrow</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Steven Harper</item>
                    <item>Dana J. Johnson</item>
                    <item>Sharon Q. Johnson</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>Joan M. Lee</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>Carl N. Raether</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford, Jr.</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Mary Beth Stanton</item>
                    <item>Ilana E. Stern</item>
                    <item>Ruth M. Worthing</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Freedom of Information Staff:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Barbara Ennis, Director</item>
                    <item>Beverly Zweiben, Appeals Officer</item>
                </list>
                <p>As announced in press release No. 460, October 11, 1977, this meeting was divided
                    into open and closed sessions. The following persons from the general public
                    attended the open session: Professors Wayne S. Cole and George O. Kent of the
                    University of Maryland; Dr. John A Bernbaum of the Christian College Consortium;
                    and Mr. John Kotch of the Agency for International Development.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Public Session--9:05 a.m.-10:40 a.m.<lb/>Room
                        1205, Department of State</hi></p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEMS 1, 2, AND 3: OPENING REMARKS, INTRODUCTION OF NEW
                    MEMBERS, AND CURRENT STATUS OF THE OFFICE OF THE HISTORIAN (HO): DISCUSSION OF
                    REPORTS SENT TO THE COMMITTEE BY THE HISTORIAN</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask called the meeting to order, welcomed the members of the Committee, and
                    introduced Mr. Blair.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair welcomed the members in behalf of the Deputy Under Secretary of State
                    for Management, Ben Read, and the Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                    Affairs, Hodding Carter III. Mr. Blair stressed the dual importance of the
                    Office of the Historian to the Department of State, both as its official memory
                    and as the spearhead of records declassification through the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series and other means. This year a new Executive
                    Order on the declassification process is being drafted as the result of a
                    Presidential Review Memorandum (PRM 29). The Executive Order, which was to be
                    issued shortly, was expected to speed the process of putting classified
                    information on the public record by reducing the normal ceiling from thirty to
                    twenty years. This was a great step toward openness, but it would present some
                    problems. Mr. Blair stated that it was important to the Department that its
                    efforts to make progress in this area were known to the members of the
                    Committee, and that the Department in turn have the members’ assistance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask introduced the members of the Committee by name, and observed that the
                    past year had been a most interesting one. One objective of the Office was to
                    achieve publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series at a
                    line twenty years from the present; another and more important objective was to
                    preserve the quality of the series in the context of changing circumstances.
                    Like Trotsky’s Permanent Revolution, the series must constantly alter. Of these
                    changing circumstances, none was more important than the increasing integration
                    of national security policy into foreign policy, and the participation in this
                    process of a large number of governmental entities. Taking account of this
                    process was the single most important matter confronting the members of the
                    Office as professional scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that the Office had been able to establish the basis for a
                    schedule that would lead to a twenty-year compilation line in a few years and to
                    a twenty-year publication line a few years thereafter. This goal has been
                    repeatedly recommended by the Advisory Committee. The new Executive Order would
                    allow a liberalized bulk declassification of government records at twenty years,
                    which in turn would help HO’s efforts at compilation and publication. These
                    efforts would also be facilitated by a sounder resource base than in the
                    past.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then asked the members of the Committee to raise any questions they
                    might have, particularly with regard to the reports sent to them on November 2.
                    Mr. Gardner stated that he wished he could share Mr. Trask’s optimism, but found
                    it disturbing that the number of volumes presently scheduled in effect
                    represented a reduction of 66-2/3 percent in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. The preeminent series of its kind in the world, which
                    the Department of State had great pride in producing, was now to be reduced. Mr.
                    Gardner felt that not all of his colleagues on the Committee and in the
                    historical profession were comfortable that a mere qualitative improvement would
                    be adequate. To replace lost pages with microform supplements seemed not to be
                    an upgrading of the series, but rather a step backward.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen observed that the question seemed to be one of resource allocation
                    among competing functions. He felt that the Committee needed to know the
                    relative costs of these functions and the amount of resources available. Mr.
                    Trask replied that the resource question was only one of a range of
                    considerations which had led to the levels presently slated. There had been an
                    explosion in the volume of documentation in the post-World War II period. The
                    large number of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes published in
                    recent years reflected the greater availability of resources, but the government
                    had now moved from a period of relative affluence to a period of relative
                    stringency at a time of greater costs. The increase in volume of documentation
                    might be out of proportion to the quantity of records that were actually
                    important, although there was no question that the volume of important materials
                    had gone up. Where was one to stop in increasing the size of the series? The
                    Office had been losing time; part of the price of catching up was to do a little
                    bit less. HO now sought to obtain more productivity from its limited resources
                    by using computerized word processing techniques, from which it anticipated
                    major savings. A different use of personnel might also be necessary.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask went on to ask whether <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> should
                    continue to be what it was before, or whether changing circumstances suggested
                    changes in the series. He felt that relatively few historians actually used the
                    series, directly, because few worked in recent history. But the series was
                    important nevertheless. HO must publish in book form a thoroughly objective and
                    representative selection of available materials, but it should add an increasing
                    amount of guidance in the form of reference material for the benefit of those
                    who might later wish to consult unpublished materials. HO was making an
                    increased effort to annotate the volumes to reflect materials not printed in
                    full. Because the Office recognized the utility of making available as much of
                    the documentation as possible, it had begun to explore micrographic techniques
                    as a means of supplementing and deepening the volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that micrographic formats were less expensive and more easily
                    distributed and offered for sale in other countries. Documentation on the
                    postwar period was of increasingly greater interest to people all over the
                    world, yet a remarkably small number of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes were actually used outside the United States. While senior scholars
                    resisted the use of micrographic materials because of their unfamiliarity,
                    younger scholars did not. In the coming year HO would be investigating
                    micrographic reproduction both as a means of cutting costs and of permitting a
                    distribution not otherwise possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Graebner argued that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was used much
                    more widely than Mr. Trask had suggested, particularly in colleges and
                    universities. Mr. Trask replied that in the course of his own career he had
                    never once used a <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume past the year
                    1945 for teaching purposes, and suggested that scholars used the series only in
                    parts rather than as a whole. Mr. Graebner felt that decisions made now would
                    affect users of the series twenty or thirty years hence. Cutting back to the
                    equivalent of four volumes per year would push the series back to the ratio of
                    the 1920’s.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner noted that the total of twelve volumes currently projected for each
                    of the periods 1955-1957 and 1958-1960 included the crises and special
                    developments which had in the past sometimes been treated in special volumes.
                    Mr. Gardner stated that with all due respect he disagreed with practically
                    everything Mr. Trask had said, and expressed his concern for the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. In particular, he disagreed
                    with Mr. Trask’s suggestion that the series would fall 100 years behind if
                    twelve volumes per year were published. Many factors now delaying the volumes
                    would be eliminated as a result of the clearance breakthrough expected under the
                    new Executive Order and by the use of computerized word processing.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner noted that Mr. Trask’s report to the Committee had stated that HO was
                    exploring means for reviving policy-related research, and that once the series
                    had reached a twenty-year line some resources could be diverted to research. Mr.
                    Gardner felt that survival of this preeminent series was of greater importance
                    than achieving a twenty-year line in order to shift resources to other HO
                    projects. The coverage of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had already
                    been reduced by the triennial plan for 1952-1954, and further reductions would
                    be disastrous.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair observed that he was not certain that coverage was actually being
                    reduced by 66-2/3 percent. There were some economies in using triennial volumes,
                    although he did not wish to debate the numbers question to any great depth. He
                    asked the Committee what sort of trade-off it would feel was realistic, given
                    the financial realities. Were substantive standards more important than a
                    catch-up in the existing time lag?</p>
                <p>In response, Mr. Gardner asked why the series seemed to be losing on the budget
                    front. If resources were cut back, what had HO done to defend the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> budget? It might have been an
                    impossible fight, but why hadn’t HO come to the Advisory Committee to ask for
                    its help? Mr. Gardner felt that the use of technological advances ought to help
                    preserve the former level of documentation, and he restated his view that the
                    reduction of coverage proposed under the current triennial plan was
                    disastrous.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask pointed out that delays in the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> were related more to resources than to clearance problems. He
                    believed the series had reached the outer limits of what could be included. He
                    reminded the Committee that its mandate had been expanded to include the
                    policy-related research function of the Office. HO could and should help to
                    provide informed historical advice to the Department, and the research function
                    was also important as a means of maintaining and sharpening the skills of the
                    staff. The research program also had some public aspects in the form of
                    reference services and publications. A recent example of the latter was Homer
                    Calkin’s <hi rend="italic">Women in American Foreign Affairs</hi>. Mr. Trask
                    stated that the current plan reflected his desire to correct the former tendency
                    to rob the research resources of the Office in order to maintain the standards
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He felt that the Office had made
                    the most difficult but responsible choice by keeping both the compiling and
                    research functions in a relatively solid state.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen felt that the matter of trade-offs in resources was a complex question,
                    and he noted that the Committee had seen no examples of actual problems. With
                    respect to the question of speed versus comprehensiveness in the series, he
                    would be unable to choose from the options Mr. Blair had mentioned because he
                    did not know what was to be given up in return. Mr. Jacobson agreed that the
                    Committee could not give advice on trade-offs without having concrete
                    information on the policy-related research function of the Office and on the
                    actual impact of reduced coverage by <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson asked if there was some middle ground between what the Department
                    did for the news media at the point of breaking developments, and what <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> did for historians thirty years later.
                    Mr. Blair, acknowledging that such a gap existed, noted that the Freedom of
                    Information Act addressed the question. Access to the files in advance of a
                    twenty or thirty-year general opening was a controversial area. The Department
                    felt that the principle of equity was important, and that the files should
                    therefore be opened to everyone at the same time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany and Mr. Glennon pointed out that the Department’s now-discontinued
                    series, <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents</hi>, had
                    fulfilled the need for a middle-ground publication. Mr. Trask noted that a
                    similar function could be performed by the Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulletin</hi>, which was now being reappraised. Mr. Trask then addressed
                    the question of “court historians” and the serious problems raised by the
                    granting of privileged access to some, but not all, outside scholars in advance
                    of the general release of files. An alternative was available in the form of
                    official histories, written either by HO or by outside scholars on contract, but
                    such histories would also raise problems. Mr. Trask felt that the best solution
                    was to press for the earliest possible general release of documentation to the
                    public.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson asked whether perhaps 90 percent of the Department’s files could be
                    made available in some fashion after three years or so. Mr. Blair asked Mr.
                    Stevenson if he had any particular group of records in mind (the area of
                    international law, for example) that seemed promising for early release.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask suggested that one advantage of preserving and restoring the HO
                    research function was that unclassified research projects could be released to
                    the public. He suggested that the members of the Committee stimulate their
                    parent organizations to take an active interest in this and other questions, and
                    recommend that the Committee be more active in the future in order to be more
                    effective. Mr. Trask felt that there existed a remarkable amount of
                    misconception about the work of HO, but that a long period of outside mistrust
                    of the Department beginning with the McCarthy era was coming to an end.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner responded that he felt his earlier points had not been based on
                    misconception. He expressed his concern that resources were being shifted to
                    research at the expense of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Trask
                    replied that it was not a question of shifting resources but of promoting
                    efficiency. The Office could improve productivity by increasing the professional
                    competence of the staff. The Office was proceeding on the assumption that its
                    future growth would be limited. Now that additional contract personnel were
                    available, the Office would be watched to see if it delivered results. The ratio
                    of time spent on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to time spent on
                    research was currently 80 percent to 20 percent. When the Office reached the
                    point where one year of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> could be
                    compiled in one work year, more resources could be allocated to research, but HO
                    was not now shifting resources to research. Mr. Trask noted that the complexity
                    of the material made compiling an increasingly difficult and time-consuming
                    function. This was even without reference to the mandate to cover foreign policy
                    questions on a government-wide basis by including relevant documentation
                    originated by other agencies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner spoke in favor of supplementary compilations such as the one on
                    intelligence mentioned in Mr. Slany’s report to the Committee. He asked about
                    the impact of the new Executive Order, and stated that he had spoken with
                    members of the National Archives staff who feared it might have an adverse
                    effect on declassification, particularly when information given in confidence by
                    a foreign government was involved. Mr. Trask suggested that Mr. Gardner’s
                    concern was unwarranted. Mr. Gardner felt that representatives of the National
                    Archives should have been invited to the meeting of the Advisory Committee. Mr.
                    Trask pointed out that HO dealt extensively with the National Archives, the
                    Department of Defense, and the intelligence community. He pointed out that it
                    was a matter of the greatest importance to HO that he was chairman of a
                    Departmental working group for implementation of the Executive Order. This
                    represented an unprecedented sign of confidence in HO. The Office needed a power
                    base in the Department to fulfill its objectives, but it had to consider the
                    realities of the bureaucracy. It was right that the Office had to compete for
                    resources, and it ought to justify its operations on a regular and thorough
                    basis.</p>
                <p>Mr. Graebner asked again about the former <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> series as a remedy for the gap between the immediate release
                    of information and the ultimate opening of the Department’s files, noting that
                    he had found that series to be very helpful. Mr. Blair stated that the series
                    had been discontinued in a resource crunch following the publication in 1968 of
                    the last volume (that for 1967), and that no protests had been heard at the time
                    from the learned societies.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger went on record as opposing a reduction in coverage in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series of 66-2/3 percent. Mr. Trask
                    denied that coverage had been reduced to this degree, and stated that the
                    usefulness of the series depended on quality rather than on volume. The
                    question, he noted, was whether the cutback would help the scholarly
                    community.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jacobson asked if there were any operating rule of thumb for deciding what
                    material was to be considered for micrographic publication as opposed to
                    publication in printed book form. Mr. Trask noted that a pilot project was under
                    consideration, and that it would have to be carefully thought out.</p>
                <p>Returning to the question of the quantity versus the quality of documentation
                    presented in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Mr. Gardner congratulated
                    the Office on its volume for 1948 on the Palestine question and the recognition
                    of Israel (volume V, part 2), and on its ability to refute the suggestion by
                    Clark Clifford that certain issues had not been covered. Mr. Gardner felt that
                    the volume’s comprehensive treatment of the subject met the needs of scholars
                    and demonstrated the importance of detailed documentation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked whether any page limitations had been set for future volumes.
                    Mr. Trask stated that an average limitation of 1200 pages per volume had been
                    established. Mr. Blair noted that this limitation was set by HO rather than by
                    the Bureau of Public Affairs.</p>
                <p>In concluding the session, Mr. Trask emphasized that the Committee’s report to
                    the Secretary of State should reflect the best independent judgment of its
                    members as scholars.</p>
                <p>(The public session adjourned at 10:40 a.m.)</p>
                <p>From 11 a.m. to 12:15 p.m. members of the Advisory Committee (in three groups)
                    met informally with members of the HO staff, except for the six senior officers.
                    At 12:30 p.m. the Committee members, together with Messrs. Blair, Trask,
                    Aandahl, Kogan, Slany, and Glennon, were guests of Deputy Under Secretary Read
                    at a luncheon in the Henry Clay room. On behalf of Secretary of State Vance, Mr.
                    Read reaffirmed the Department’s commitment to openness, both current and
                    historical, and expressed its appreciation for the work of the Committee. Mr.
                    Cohen responded for the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session--2:20 p.m.-4:05 p.m.<lb/>Room
                        1205, Department of State</hi></p>
                <p rend="center">AGENDA ITEMS 4 AND 5: DISCUSSION OF POINTS RAISED IN INFORMAL
                    CONVERSATIONS WITH GROUPS OF HO STAFF MEMBERS; DISCUSSION WITH SENIOR OFFICERS
                    OF HO</p>
                <p>Present: Members of the Committee, and Messrs. Trask, Aandahl, Costrell, Kogan,
                    Slany, and Glennon.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask invited comments from the Committee members, and Mr. Cohen responded by
                    asking about the possibility of more frequent contacts, perhaps even a second
                    formal meeting of the Committee each year. Mr. Trask said that the Committee
                    might suggest more contact in its report, but he felt that more frequent
                    sessions were not bureaucratically feasible at this time. Mr. Trask expressed
                    the hope and the expectation that HO and the Committee could maintain closer
                    contact by correspondence. Perhaps, he said, HO could provide two or three
                    interim reports to the Committee during the course of the year to provide better
                    background for the annual meeting.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then asked the Committee how the three “buzz” groups with the HO staff
                    had gone. He indicated that differences of view were necessary and inevitable
                    and inquired if any questions had arisen from the sessions.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger said that the sessions were very helpful and thanked Mr. Trask
                    for the opportunity for such free discussions. Mr. Cohen agreed, adding that
                    there did appear to be some gaps between staff and management, the ventilation
                    of which was undoubtedly helpful both to the Committee and to HO management. Mr.
                    Jacobson said that it was a time of change in HO and asked Mr. Trask for his
                    views on consultation and the decision-making process.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that he was different from most State Department managers in that
                    he felt that decisions should be made at the lowest level possible in the
                    bureaucracy and not merely bucked on to higher authority. He indicated that he
                    consulted with the staff through his senior people on critical policy matters.
                    Opinion stating, of course, was not necessarily part of the decision-making
                    process. Opinion stating was encouraged although the final decision might well
                    diverge from the opinions of individuals. He felt that confidence building, by
                    letting the staff offer suggestions and express criticism, was important. He
                    went on to say that working with the staff was the top priority for him in the
                    coming year. He felt that he had acquired needed resources for the Office; now
                    was the time for us to deliver by proving that we could both speed up the series
                    and improve the quality at the same time.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger observed that these objectives might be paradoxical. How could
                    quality be maintained when a speed-up was in effect? Mr. Trask replied that
                    quality was all important. Quality would be maintained in the series and indeed
                    would be improved. Mr. Aandahl added that timeliness was an important aspect of
                    quality. Mr. Trask then pointed out that micrographics might help us both in
                    improving the quality of the offering and in allowing us to provide more
                    material to the reader. Mrs. Unterberger asked if a decision had been made on
                    the use of micrographic supplements. Mr. Trask said that no final decision had
                    been made; we were still, he said, committed only to a high quality product.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jacobson raised the matter of criteria for selection. He wondered if the
                    Committee might have access to figures for instance on the numbers of documents
                    chosen for publication out of the total number available and considered for
                    possible inclusion. He felt that public access to rejected material was also
                    important for an honest appraisal of the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that such information and more would be sent to the Committee and
                    the Committee would have to work harder as a result. HO would report in detail
                    to the Committee two or three times a year on HO’s activities; policy forming
                    documents would also be sent out by HO; finally, HO would consult with the
                    Committee’s members on an individual basis, e.g., seeking help for staff members
                    on individual compilations where the Committee members could provide
                    particularized assistance. This should provide a path to more and better contact
                    and consultation. HO wanted better advice and greater credibility in the
                    academic world.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner said that these were good ideas. He felt that the separate sessions
                    with the staff were excellent, but he came away with the feeling that there was
                    a gap between Mr. Trask and the staff. He felt that some of the staff members
                    were uncertain of his intentions and quite concerned about both the shift to
                    triennial volumes and the limitations placed on the number of volumes and the
                    pages within each volume. He wanted to raise specifically three questions: a)
                    the disposition of the 1950- 1954 record bloc; b) the clearance of the 1949
                    China volume; c) the retrospective volume for 1948-1951 dealing with
                    intelligence and national security matters.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask turned to Mr. Kogan to speak on the 1950-1954 records. Mr. Kogan said
                    that HO’s primary concern was to get these papers transferred to the National
                    Archives and Records Service (NARS), but NARS was not willing to take them until
                    they were all unclassified or unless NARS had authority to declassify them. This
                    was a change from their earlier policy. NARS, of course, could not declassify
                    State Department papers. The Department had also hoped to give NARS a number of
                    Lot Files, but again NARS would not take them until it had all the 1950-1954
                    records in declassified form. HO’s hope was now for early release of the volumes
                    through 1954, which would help to open up the records, and also for early
                    release of the proposed Executive Order which would establish a 20-year line for
                    declassification. This would involve a transition period and would not mean
                    immediate automatic declassification of all documents 20 years old, but it
                    should ease the situation considerably. Written guidelines were now being
                    formulated to implement the proposed Executive Order.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that part of the problem with NARS was that it was constantly
                    trying to gain its independence from the General Services Administration. It
                    wanted more resources and used this argument in the fight against taking the
                    1950-1954 records, claiming that more staff would be needed to service them.
                    There had been strains in the HO-NARS relationship, but HO was continuing to
                    work on this and he hoped that progress was being made.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked if it was correct that the opening of records at NARS was not
                    tied to the release of volumes. Mr. Trask said that that was right; the
                    connection was rather to HO’s systematic review of the records in preparing the
                    volumes. Mr. Gardner then remarked that scholars were now worse off than in the
                    days when records for a year were opened after the release of volumes for that
                    year. Both he and Mr. Trask agreed that something had to be done. Mr. Gardner
                    pointed out that 1950 volumes are out but the scholars have no access to the
                    papers. Was there, he asked, something the Committee could do about this? Mr.
                    Kogan interjected that FOI requests for documents in the closed period were
                    possible. Mr. Gardner said that restrictions of time might militate against use
                    of this avenue. Mr. Trask said that even though FOI was not designed for
                    scholars it was a most useful tool and could be employed by them to a far
                    greater extent than it had been. HO’s desire, he said, was to get material out
                    to the public as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that the written guidelines now being drafted might delineate
                    the area of sensitive documents. Mr. Trask said that the working group could be
                    of great help here by reassuring the bureaus in the Department that nothing
                    would be released under the new 20-year rule without first being processed. This
                    was an enormous job. Resources would be needed, and the Committee’s report could
                    strongly emphasize the need for resources to service the documents. The bureaus
                    would then feel that the question of sensitivity was being taken into
                    consideration. Mr. Slany then referred to the example of documents for 1948-1949
                    from the Central Files on Italy which were removed and re-classified by the
                    Department because of sensitivity. The documents had not been printed in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, but had been used by journalists and
                    outside scholars. Mr. Trask said that this was a bad policy, but perhaps
                    necessary. Like other organizations, the Department of State did not like
                    surprises. Often, he said, panic followed in the wake of surprise. Mr. Gardner
                    observed that that sounded bad. Mr. Trask responded that HO’s role in the
                    release of materials was to minimize surprises and to give advance warning to
                    those who might have to live with the results of documentary revelations. Mr.
                    Aandahl reminded the Committee that HO cannot declassify documents, only bureaus
                    can. Mr. Trask noted that most papers were not sensitive, but it was hard to get
                    the bureaus to act because they were too busy with other things. He continued,
                    responding to Mr. Cohen, that HO’s aim was to lift the burden off the backs of
                    the bureaus, but resources would be needed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson asked about documents in the more recent period, that is, up to 20
                    years old. Mr. Trask said that documents being generated now would be on an
                    automatic schedule calling for downgrading after passage of a certain number of
                    years. Mr. Stevenson said that there was no way yet for documents less than 20
                    years old to be made available automatically once declassified. Mr. Slany stated
                    that computerized records in the Department’s files might be made available more
                    readily if the machines could be programmed to “spit out” declassified
                    documents, which seemed within the state of the art. Mr. Trask agreed, saying
                    that the technological capability was there but was not yet in use. Here again,
                    the Committee could be of help by including such a proposal in its report.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner raised the matter of declassification and the possibility of appeals
                    to higher authority in case clearance was not granted by a bureau. Mr. Aandahl
                    said that for questions such as that of 1949, volume VIII, China, there was the
                    possibility of such appeal. Mr. Gardner then referred to last year’s meeting
                    with Secretary Kissinger at which the China volume and a sticky 1950 clearance
                    on Yugoslavia were mentioned. Why was the latter cleared and not the former, he
                    asked. Mr. Slany stated that the clearance on Yugoslavia came after normal
                    Foreign Service personnel transfers took people away from that desk who had
                    objected to publication. Messrs. Trask and Aandahl said that HO through PA was
                    keeping after EA on the China volume, but both HO and PA felt that little would
                    be gained by appeal to a higher level at this point.</p>
                <p>In response to a query from Mr. Cohen, Mr. Trask attempted to outline what
                    happens to the Committee’s report in the Department. It is directed to the
                    Assistant Secretary for PA and from there percolates up to the Secretary’s
                    office; it does not automatically come to the Secretary’s personal
                    attention.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson again pointed to the need for a publication for the period between
                    immediate news and the 20-year declassification line. He wanted to maintain the
                    high quality of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> but felt that it was
                    important also to provide adequate coverage of more recent materials. Mr. Trask
                    said that the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> publication was probably
                    the best answer to this need, but pointed to the problem of resources. He said
                    that there would be some resistance in HO to such a revival of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> and that the Bureau of Public Affairs would probably
                    frown on it. Perhaps a compromise solution could be worked out.</p>
                <p>Mr. Costrell then spoke to the question of the allocation of resources and the
                    placing of emphasis on certain programs within the Office. He said that he felt
                    that many of the projects done as Historical Studies served as valuable tools in
                    collecting and shaping the record for the compilers of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> who came along later. He pointed to the Korea Project done
                    years ago as a Historical Study which later became useful in compilation of the
                    1950 volume on Korea.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson observed that FOI must take up a great deal in terms of resources
                    in the Department. Because of its random character, it seemed a costly and
                    inefficient way to operate. It would be better to institutionalize the process
                    of declassification in some more systematic way. Mr. Trask agreed that the
                    process was very costly. He went on to speak of resource use in HO after the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> catch-up and said resources would be
                    put into policy-related research. He said his aim was to see HO’s productivity
                    go up without increasing its budget. He knew that this would be hard on the HO
                    staff, but he also wanted to make clear that he was not a stroker or a nice guy.
                    His contacts with the rest of the Department and the outside had improved HO’s
                    position in both areas. He had been brought in to make changes. Major changes
                    had indeed been made, which probably accounted for some of the irritation on the
                    part of the staff, but HO was now stronger. Now, however, HO had to deliver on
                    its promises. In a year the staff might feel no differently toward him, but he
                    would spend the year turning his attention inward toward HO and trying to
                    improve relations there. He was endeavoring, he said, to overcome the
                    quasi-authoritarian features of bureaucracy; he made no apology for his sins and
                    errors, but he was sure that they were present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson said that at the session he attended with the staff, he heard
                    expressions of desire for more contact by the Director with the staff down to
                    all levels. Mr. Trask said that he had tried to achieve such contact and would
                    try even harder. He realized that to this point he had not achieved the maximum
                    of success in this area, but his attention in the next year would be directed
                    inward toward the Office. He said that he had no desire to be loved; he did wish
                    to be efficient in carrying out his responsibilities.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger said that mutual respect was most important and she felt that
                    Mr. Trask should be aware of the fact that there was a perception of a
                    fundamental lack of respect now on both sides. Mr. Trask replied that respect
                    should and would stem from performance. It would take time--perhaps five, six,
                    or seven years--but the end result would be a mutual respect and affection based
                    on solid performance. Mrs. Unterberger then said that the point she had been
                    trying to make was that the staff members felt that Mr. Trask had no respect for
                    them. Mr. Trask repeated that this was the year he was going to work on that
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner stated that the staff knew that many of the problems in the Office
                    had been inherited by Mr. Trask and that it would take time to turn things
                    around. He said that the frankness of the discussions with the staff was a
                    tribute to Mr. Trask’s regime.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask asked for any criticisms which the Committee might offer which would be
                    informative and have a worthwhile effect. He hoped that the Committee would be
                    even more effective in future and also welcomed any individual comments and
                    criticisms which the members might be willing to pass on to him.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask adjourned the formal meeting of the Committee at 4:05 p.m., whereupon
                    he and the other senior officers of HO withdrew. Members of the Committee then
                    met in private session until 5 p.m. to consider the general outlines of their
                    annual report to the Secretary of State. The Committee chose Mr. Gardner as its
                    Chairman.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
