<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1978</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1978</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-03-24">March 24, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1978-11-03">November 3, 1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1978-11-03-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 457 KB, 23pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 3, 1978-Minutes. The referenced briefing
                    papers are not posted. The minutes were approved by HAC Chair Bernard Cohen on
                    January 17, 1979.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited (from an identical copy in another archival collection) in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of the Foreign Relations
                    of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 8, <ref target="../chapter-8#fn108"
                    >Footnote 108</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1978 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 3, 1978</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Lloyd C. Gardner, Professor of History, Rutgers University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mack Thompson, Executive Secretary, American Historical Association
                        (in place of Dr. Norman A Graebner)</item>
                    <item>Dr. Betty Miller Unterberger, Professor of History, Texas A &amp; M
                        University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bernard C. Cohen, Professor of Political Science, University of
                        Wisconsin</item>
                    <item>Dr. Harold K. Jacobson, Professor of Political Science, University of
                        Michigan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Alona E. Evans, Professor of Political Science, Wellesley
                        College</item>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Stevenson, Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, New York</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William D. Blair, Jr., Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>David F. Trask, The Historian (Executive Secretary of the Advisory
                        Committee)</item>
                    <item>Fredrick Aandahl, The Associate Historian</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Arthur G. Kogan</item>
                    <item>David H. Stauffer</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                    <item>Allen H. Kitchens</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Lynn K. Fliakas</item>
                    <item>Ruth Harris</item>
                    <item>Dana J. Johnson</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>Robert J. McMahon</item>
                    <item>Aaron D. Miller</item>
                    <item>Carl N. Raether</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford, Jr.</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Freedom of Information Staff:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Barbara Ennis, Director</item>
                    <item>Joan M. Lee, Appeals Officer</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Foreign Affairs Document and Reference Center (FADRC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Price, Director</item>
                    <item>Frank M. Machak, Chief, Document and Reference Division</item>
                </list>
                <p>The National Archives and Records Service (NARS):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Allen Thompson, Chief, Declassification Division</item>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Diplomatic Branch</item>
                    <item>Dane J. Hartgrove, Archivist, Diplomatic Branch</item>
                </list>
                <p>Department of State press release No. 384, October 10, 1978, provided for open
                    and closed portions of the meeting, but no closed portion was held. The
                    following persons from the general public attended the meeting: Professor Jules
                    Davids, Georgetown University; Professors Wayne S. Cole and George O. Kent of
                    the University of Maryland; and Ilana E. Stern.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">First Session--9:00 a.m.-11:00 a.m.<lb/>Room
                        1205, Department of State</hi></p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Greetings and Selection of Chairperson for FY
                        1979</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask called the meeting to order at 9:00 a.m., welcomed the members of the
                    Advisory Committee, and introduced Mr. Blair, who explained that he was filling
                    in for the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, Hodding Carter III.
                    Mr. Blair said that this was both a difficult and promising time for the Office
                    of the Historian, which made the counsel of the members of the committee and
                    those they represented especially important. He had good and bad news to report.
                    The good news was that this was a creative and fertile time for HO. He pointed
                    in particular to the introduction of word-processing equipment, the feasibility
                    study of microform as a supplement to printed volumes, efforts to gain greater
                    access to documents of other agencies, and the impact of Executive Order 12065
                    on classification and declassification of records. His own view was that under
                    the Executive Order, which was to become effective on December 1, the bulk of
                    records used in preparation of the series <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</hi> would be declassified within 20 years.</p>
                <p>The bad news, according to Mr. Blair, was that budgetary pressures were as tough
                    as or tougher than at any time he could remember, and the outlook for a major
                    improvement was not good. He stressed that the Department took the counsel of
                    the Committee very seriously, adding that the briefing papers supplied to the
                    members this year were in response to their concern about using their time more
                    effectively.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask, noting the crowded agenda, asked the committee to select a chairperson
                    for the forthcoming year. Mr. Gardner expressed the Committee’s happiness at
                    being present, and said that he wished to endorse everything Mr. Blair had said
                    concerning the Committee’s importance. Mr. Gardner nominated Mr. Cohen as
                    Chairperson. The nomination was seconded by Mr. Stevenson, and Mr. Cohen was
                    elected by acclamation. Mr. Trask and Mr. Blair thanked Mr. Gardner for his
                    service as Chairperson during the past year.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">General Developments (Briefing Paper No.
                        1)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that it had been a year of great activity and change in the
                    Office of the Historian. To give advice, the Committee must have information,
                    and the distribution of briefing papers in advance was intended to allow more
                    time for comments and suggestion at the meeting. Mr. Trask summarized some of
                    the major developments in HO during the past year. The reorganized Office had
                    shaken down and appeared to be working as well as one might hope. Contract
                    historians were providing additional compilation time, as well as professional
                    stimulus and colleagueship. The Office had been able to complete its word
                    processing and electronic typesetting system, and the printing money thus saved
                    had been used to hire contract historians. The Office had made considerable
                    process on microform feasibility studies. HO’s outreach had also been improved,
                    and this provided ongoing and useful association with the user community.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask expressed pleasure at the continuing praise the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series had received, and noted that this was an
                    incentive for further improvement. Executive Order 12065 provided an
                    institutional basis for the acceleration of the series. The Office, he said,
                    continued to contribute to the research needs of the Department, although the
                    contributors to this program were not recognized outside the Department. Mr.
                    Trask noted that the joint Soviet-American publication project had achieved
                    significant breakthroughs after a difficult start. He felt certain it would be a
                    landmark in cultural diplomacy and in scholarship. In all the activities of HO
                    he acknowledged the support of the Bureau of Public Affairs and the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask asked for comments and questions on briefing paper No. 1. Mr. Gardner
                    asked whether the Linolex word processing system was now fully operative. Mr.
                    Trask replied that the Office had completed its pilot study, working on an
                    actual volume. There had been administrative problems in acquiring machinery,
                    but these were well on the way to resolution. He expected the system to be ahead
                    of schedule by the end of the current fiscal year. Mr. Gardner asked if any
                    volumes had yet been completed by this method. Mr. Trask then introduced Ms.
                    Wells, who was responsible for the HO Secretariat staff, and asked her to
                    comment on the progress of the Linolex operation. Ms. Wells stated that of the
                    first volume to be keyboarded in HO under the system (volume I for 1952-1954),
                    984 manuscript pages had been typed and corrected, 925 had been typed but not
                    corrected, and 495 were still to be typed. In answer to Mr. Gardner’s query as
                    to when Linolex processing of this volume had begun, Ms. Wells said the work had
                    started in March 1978. Mr. Trask remarked that he was very well pleased with the
                    system and fully confident of its feasibility. It was the key to HO’s future
                    plans.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked for an estimate of the number of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes HO expected to process each year on the system. Mr.
                    Trask answered that he hoped as many as 10 volumes a year could be completed if
                    personnel turnover was kept down, but plans were to produce six per year. HO had
                    built redundancy factors into the word processing system by designating
                    personnel who could be used as backstops in case problems arose. A further
                    complication was that the security people were concerned about the
                    susceptibility of the system to microwave intelligence. Ms. Wells then noted
                    that about 60 percent of the word processing for 1952-1954, Volume I, had been
                    completed in full, and she hoped the entire volume would be completed by January
                    1979.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner observed that, although the processing of this volume was taking from
                    March through autumn to complete, the system would have to produce a volume
                    every 1.2 months in order to do 10 volumes per year. Mr. Trask agreed, and noted
                    that he expected the word processing group to be able to produce 250 pages per
                    week, when fully in operation. The Office had the capability to do 350 pages per
                    week, provided the support staff was completely filled. Mr. Slany added that the
                    word processing program had begun in March, and that this autumn the average
                    rate for operators reached 5 pages per hour. [The start-up experimentation has
                    now been completed. It is anticipated that the system, when fully equipped and
                    staffed, can process between 10,000-15,000 printed pages per year, a rate of
                    more than sufficient to produce planned volumes, unless the size and number of
                    such volumes should be revised.]</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked whether it took time to train operators, and he wondered what
                    would happen if an operator left. Mr. Slany responded that while training did
                    not take a great deal of time, it took time for operators to reach their maximum
                    speed on the machine. In answer to Mr. Cohen’s inquiry as to how proofreading
                    was done, Mr. Trask said that the committee would receive a demonstration of the
                    word processing equipment later in the day. Mr. Aandahl then briefly described
                    the technical processing of the manuscript.</p>
                <p>Ms. Evans asked whether the HO staff was doing much research for use within the
                    Department of State, and whether research would slow down the production of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Trask replied that there was an
                    unsatisfactory ratio between <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and the
                    research effort. Acceleration of the series, which would take a few more years,
                    would allow a more favorable ratio. He stated that the Office had not done so
                    much research as in the past, although some of the research was on exceedingly
                    important subjects that reflected current high priority items for the
                    Department, such as the Camp David negotiations and Presidential trips to the
                    Middle East and Africa. He mentioned that Mr. Kitchens’ history of the Sinai
                    Support Mission had been declassified and prepared for publication.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson asked to what extent this research was requested by other offices
                    and to what extent it was originated by HO. Mr. Trask answered that it worked
                    both ways, but more often than not HO responded to requests from elsewhere in
                    the Department. He said that although the resources of the Office were limited,
                    users seemed pleased with the product. Mr. Stevenson asked whether the users of
                    HO’s research were spread throughout the Department or concentrated in one area.
                    Mr. Trask answered that the pattern of research moved according to the rise and
                    fall of issues. Lately it had concentrated on the Middle East, reflecting the
                    Department’s interests in that area. Nina Noring had compiled an extensive
                    project on the Middle East for 1973. HO Research also dealt with such issues as
                    ecology, oceans, science, and technology. Mr. Stevenson asked if HO was involved
                    in any joint projects. Mr. Trask said that the Office had not worked closely
                    with other areas of the Department in its research, but its work dovetailed with
                    research in other U.S. Government agencies. He mentioned as an example the
                    Soviet-American project, in which the National Archives and Smithsonian
                    Institution were also participating. Interagency collaborative research was
                    likely in the future, given the interrelationship of problems. Mr. Stevenson
                    asked whether the Policy Planning Staff ever made requests for research. Mr.
                    Trask replied that there had been a close and extensive relationship with the
                    Policy Planning Staff in connection with a project on human rights.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen referred to Briefing Paper No. 1, page 1, paragraph 4, and asked
                    whether there had in fact been a drift away from work on research to work on <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Trask said that there was
                    misperception on this issue, and that such a drift had begun a long time ago. He
                    had felt when he came to the Department that the research program ought to be
                    thought about. He himself might inadvertently have given the impression in the
                    past that some additional research would be undertaken, but this was not the
                    case. The trend has been in the opposite direction, consistent with the
                    acceleration and increased complexity of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Mr. Trask noted that he had been the principal culprit in
                    withdrawing resources from research to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    because he believed that only when the series had caught up to a 20-year line
                    would there be enough time and energy for an adequate program of research. The
                    Advisory Committee received two memoranda demonstrating the trend toward more
                    commitment of budget and personnel to compilation, especially since 1976. He
                    added that the research function was not lying fallow in the interim. The Office
                    continued to experiment with ideas and methods. The research projects HO was
                    turning out were very good but few in numbers. A great tragedy, Mr. Trask
                    believed, was that the Department of State desperately needed research based on
                    historical perspective. HO was the one body that could help. The major research
                    component of the Department, the Bureau of Intelligence and Research, did
                    research on other countries, not on the policy process.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked whether cutting the number of pages had helped to accelerate
                    publication of the series. Mr. Trask said that the triennial approach had had
                    that effect. Mr. Aandahl said that HO needed to get better control of the total
                    product. For many years, until the volumes for 1946, the series had been
                    relatively unplanned. The volumes were now including more material on the
                    formulation of policy at high levels, and less on operational details.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner cited the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on Israel
                    for 1948, noting that it had received wide and deserved praise in the academic
                    community. Because it was done so thoroughly, the Office had been able to refute
                    inaccurate information. There was a danger in presenting only the main outlines
                    and therefore eliminating the kind of detail which made the Israel volume so
                    useful. By arbitrarily limiting pages in advance the series risked opening
                    itself to a decrease in quality and to scholars’ criticisms that important
                    documents were left out.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl said that the office was able to make exceptions in the matter of
                    pages, and that the treatment being given to the Suez Canal Crisis was an
                    example. Mr. Blair said that Mr. Aandahl’s point was absolutely right. The
                    Department might get caught up in its own projected page figures, but the
                    projections were not sacrosanct. It was only necessary for those who wrestled
                    with budgets to have an idea of the total product. In the past, the Department
                    had made some conservative page estimates, which it now found it could
                    exceed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that some of HO’s planning was based on the hope that it could use
                    microfiche supplements. If the feasibility study showed that this was not a good
                    idea, the Office would have to rely entirely on the printed word. If HO was not
                    able to expand coverage through microfiche by five- or ten-fold, it would need
                    to rethink the process immediately. The Office could make changes and reprogram
                    its resources and staff energies at later stages. Plans even for the 1955­1957
                    triennium were not set in concrete, and the Office would be glad to have the
                    thoughts of the members of the Committee on the subject of pages. Any expansion
                    of a large nature would, he reminded the Committee, offset the delivery date of
                    future <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger asked if what was being contemplated was an expansion of printed
                    pages or merely a reallocation of existing page units. Mr. Trask stated that HO
                    planned to produce at least 20,000 printed pages for 1955-1957. [Recent counts
                    suggest that this estimate may be low.] This figure could be raised or lowered.
                    He reemphasized that the Office would be happy to receive advice on the subject
                    from the Committee. The microfiche supplement was the very key to planning. If
                    it should prove unfeasible, HO would have to reconsider its program.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair said that the figure of 20,000 pages for the 1955-1957 triennium was an
                    example of flexibility. A figure of between 12,000 and 14,000 pages had been
                    loosely thrown around last year, but that was an overconservative budgetary
                    projection. The new figure also reflected the concern about page cuts expressed
                    by the Advisory Committee and others during the past year. Mr. Trask added that
                    last year HO had been cautious so that it would not be overpromising. People had
                    mistakenly assumed that the Office was talking about hard decisions when it was
                    talking only about loose projections and planning figures. HO’s desire was to
                    publish as much as possible in whatever format. The question was which mode of
                    presentation would satisfy the whole range of user constituencies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen asked that discussion of microfiche be continued later, and there was
                    general agreement.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Access Matters (Briefing Papers No. 2a and
                        2b)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then turned to the question of access to the records of the Department
                    and other agencies. He believed that great progress was being made in this area,
                    and pointed to a conversation on this question that he and other members of the
                    staff had had the previous day with representatives of the National Security
                    Council. The objectives in seeking greater access were to expand other-agency
                    coverage and to expand the usefulness and helpfulness of annotation as a guide
                    to future research.</p>
                <p>Citing the declassification of some portions of the Forrestal Diaries by the
                    Defense Department as an example, Mr. Gardner asked whether HO would support a
                    scholar’s request for the opening of the Dulles material at Princeton University
                    for the 1950-1954 period, now that the State Department central files for that
                    period were in the process of being transferred to the National Archives. Mr.
                    Blair responded that HO would be glad to see the Dulles material opened, but
                    because the material pertained to events also covered by records of the
                    Department of State and other agencies, expedited review would be difficult to
                    obtain. Mr. Kogan remarked that the Dulles collection at Princeton consisted
                    largely of copies of Department of State documents. Princeton had no authority
                    over the material. The principles for declassification of this material would be
                    the same as for declassification under the new Executive Order. The guidelines
                    would probably be sent to Princeton. Mr. Trask added that the question of what
                    was a historical record and what was not was tangled. The new Executive Order
                    dealt with the question of Presidential Papers, and its provisions were a
                    victory for proponents of openness. Mr. Trask then commended Mr. Kogan as one of
                    the leading experts in the entire Government on records policy, and introduced
                    Mr. Gustafson and Mr. Allen Thompson of the National Archives and Records
                    Service (NARS), who had joined the meeting.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair said it was expected that within the next few months the National
                    Archives would accession the 1950-1954 block of Department of State central
                    files. Mr. Stevenson asked whether the Freedom of Information Act was the only
                    way to obtain declassified records less than 20 years old, and Mr. Kogan replied
                    that this was the case, except for the mandatory review of Presidential records.
                    Mr. Stevenson asked what percentage of State Department material was classified.
                    Mr. Kogan and Mr. Trask said that for the period 1950-1969 the Department of
                    State had an estimated 78 million pages of documents, of which 27 million were
                    classified.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask introduced Mr. Price and Mr. Machak of FADRC, who had joined the
                    meeting. Mr. Price observed that in terms of implementing the General
                    Declassification Schedule (GDS) which had gone into effect in 1972, time was
                    overtaking his operation. FADRC must get together with the Bureau of Public
                    Affairs to discuss the problem of making available to the public those documents
                    that in 1972 had been scheduled for release in six years.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Executive Order No. 12065 and Transfer of
                        1950-1954 Records (Briefing Papers No. 3 and 4)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask introduced Mrs. Ennis, Director of the Freedom of Information Staff,
                    who joined the meeting. Mr. Blair pointed out that within Executive Order 12065,
                    the most important item as far as scholars were concerned was the provision for
                    the release of most documentation after 20 years. In order to implement this
                    provision, the Department of State was about to take some fairly revolutionary
                    steps, which involved removing the declassification function from the various
                    bureaus and centralizing it in one central staff. Mr. Blair commented that, in
                    his personal opinion, this plan would be adopted in the near future. [The new
                    system has since been adopted.] It would be an enormous step forward by way of
                    implementing the 20-year line of the new Executive Order. Mr. Blair also
                    explained that the President had allowed Executive agencies ten years to reach
                    the 20-year line, but the Department planned to reach it in half a dozen
                    years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked about the sort of input the Office of the Historian would have
                    on the central staff. Mr. Blair responded that, in his personal opinion, the
                    Office would continue to play an indispensable role. A steering committee would
                    be formed, headed by the Under Secretary of State for Management, and the Bureau
                    of Public Affairs would be involved in that committee. The central staff would
                    screen a selection by HO from the Department’s files and draft guidelines for
                    the declassification program of the National Archives. Mr. Gardner asked whether
                    Executive Order 12065 would help to clear away <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> clearance problems. Mr. Blair replied that it was a great
                    step forward. It would be a drastic shock to many desk officers to learn that
                    the President wanted documents declassified after 20 years. Mr. Mack Thompson
                    asked why, if documents could be cleared under the Freedom of Information Act,
                    they could not simply be released without going through the FOI process, Mrs.
                    Ennis stated that documents had to be reviewed on an item-by-item basis, but
                    that most FOI requests were successful. Mr. Price added that under the General
                    Declassification Schedule, documents would soon be made available automatically.
                    Mr. Mack Thompson asked for an elaboration of the restraints on getting the
                    record out. Mr. Blair responded that the problem in one word was resources. Mr.
                    Price agreed and expanded his earlier remarks concerning the General
                    Declassification Schedule by noting that even though it provided for the release
                    of 80 percent of the documentation after six years, that group would not include
                    the most important foreign policy documentation. Mr. Machak confirmed the latter
                    point and noted that under Executive Order 11652, FADRC had had to prepare
                    annual declassification lists of all documents released.</p>
                <p>Mr. Machak then described the problems involved in making documents declassified
                    under the GDS available to the public. The task of segregating the declassified
                    material from the main body of files would become much easier once the period of
                    computerized record keeping had been reached. Before this time, however, FADRC
                    would have a resource problem, and the Committee should remember that FADRC’s
                    first duty was to service the information needs of the Department of State.
                    FADRC looked to the National Archives for help in providing scholars with
                    documentation. One problem was that records managers had not yet reached an
                    educated judgment as to how long an agency needed to retain records. Most
                    agencies currently operated on a 20-year retention basis. Mr. Gustafson said
                    that the National Archives wanted to accession records as soon as they were no
                    longer needed by the originating agency and as soon as they could be opened to
                    the public. Mr. Stevenson inquired again about the resource question, and
                    observed that a system of automatic declassification ought to be much cheaper to
                    administer than the FOI operation. Mr. Trask noted that when Congress drafted
                    the Freedom of Information Act, it had persons with individual interests in mind
                    rather than scholars with general interests. This fact had complicated the
                    situation ever since, because the FOI Act was the only way for scholars to gain
                    access to government documents before they were subject to automatic review. The
                    multiplicity of systems for the review of documents made it exceedingly
                    difficult for records managers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Price recalled the paper explosion after Pearl Harbor. The files prior to the
                    introduction of the GDS and the Department’s Automated Data System caused
                    particular problems, but once FADRC reached the computerized period, it would be
                    a simple matter to segregate the material and “repackage” the documents. Plans
                    had not yet been made for the computerized period but were under examination.
                    Mr. Trask noted that the Department hoped to reach the 20-year line well before
                    the 10-year mandate.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner remarked that the subject reminded him of “Magic.” Two years ago, he
                    had learned from a representative of the National Security Agency that it still
                    held documents relating to Pearl Harbor that were not in the public domain. Mr.
                    Gardner wondered what other material was still being withheld. He then asked
                    whether <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> clearance problems were
                    currently greater or lesser than during the period the 1949 China volume was
                    withheld. Mr. Trask referred the question to Mr. Glennon, who responded, with
                    reference to the present difficulties, by saying, “Clearance stinks.” Mr.
                    Gardner then asked how the new system was going to break down the clearance
                    blockage. Mr. Blair replied that the job would be done not by desk officers but
                    by a central declassification staff, composed of individuals who had been
                    Foreign Service officers. The staff would work full time on declassification
                    matters. Mr, Blair felt that the central staff was a great step forward and that
                    it would gain expertise and take a dispassionate approach to
                    declassification.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask explained that the Department of State in adopting the central staff
                    was producing economies of scale. In his opinion, resources were 90 percent of
                    the access problem; clearance was only 10 percent. Nervousness accompanied
                    periods of change, and the Department was operating in a period of much greater
                    openness than before. A good deal of sentiment for openness did exist in the
                    Department. He had great hopes that the new Executive Order would make a
                    measurable difference. Mr. Blair cautioned that the millennium had not arrived.
                    Mr. Price pointed out that under the new system, at least a decision about a
                    document would be reached one way or the other, instead of the long delay in
                    decision-making that was currently the case.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask asked Mr. Allen Thompson of NARS to comment on the new guidelines that
                    were to be written. Mr. Thompson replied that NARS also viewed the new Executive
                    Order as a major step forward, but had reservations concerning its ability to
                    cope with the anticipated deluge of paper. NARS estimated that it would take 10
                    years to make the transition. In the world of the 20-year line, Mr. Thompson
                    noted, more categories of documents would be withheld than at 30 years, and NARS
                    would need more guidance than before on what should be withheld. His office had
                    no idea of what percent of the documents would be withheld at 20 years, but it
                    was obvious that the provision exempting foreign government information would
                    mean that a very high percentage, probably 10 percent, would be held back. This
                    would require a substantial amount of declassification work at 30 years. He
                    added that NARS had neither the money nor the personnel to do the review
                    required under the new Executive Order, and the 30-year line would remain until
                    the resources were obtained.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that intelligence matters had become a larger part of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, and that the series would have
                    to be rethought in terms of what the users wanted from it. Mr. Gardner felt that
                    former Foreign Service officers would be leery of reversing clearance decisions
                    already made on intelligence material. Mr. Allen Thompson stated that 90 percent
                    of the material withheld beyond 30 years related to intelligence. The Government
                    was going to continue to withhold intelligence documentation for a longer period
                    than the historical community would wait for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Mr. Gardner commented that intelligence matters played an
                    increasingly important role in recent U.S. foreign policy, and that what was
                    being said about clearance at the meeting was very serious and bad news. Mr.
                    Blair agreed with Mr. Gardner and said he had no solution to offer. Mr. Trask
                    felt that the new system would produce a centralization throughout the
                    Government that would help HO obtain documents from other agencies. Hopefully,
                    such highly trained personnel as those in Mr. Thompson’s office at the National
                    Archives would gradually replace retired Foreign Service officers as members of
                    the central staff. Mr. Blair referred to the recent decision to place the
                    central staff in the Bureau of Administration. He observed that some members of
                    the Bureau of Public Affairs felt that their Bureau had been created by God to
                    handle declassification, but God had chosen otherwise. Mr. Blair felt that the
                    decision to place the central staff in the Bureau of Administration was probably
                    for the best, because the steering committee would be headed by an Under
                    Secretary, and this would provide a bureaucratic strength to the operation.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Russo-American Documentary History (Briefing
                        Paper No. 5)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask introduced Mr. Sampson and Mr. Landa as the two principal HO historians
                    working on the Russian-American documentary history project, acknowledged Mr.
                    Gustafson’s role as an American editor of the project, and pointed out that Mr.
                    Slany had also been deeply involved. He commended the National Archives for its
                    leadership in the enterprise. Mr. Cohen remarked that he could understand Mr.
                    Trask’s enthusiasm for such a project and asked whether there were any comments
                    concerning Russian cooperation that had not been expressed in the briefing
                    paper. Mr. Sampson observed that getting documents from the Soviets had been a
                    bit like pulling teeth, but that they had become more cooperative over time. At
                    first there had been hesitancy and anxiety on both sides over what the project
                    would actually involve. As the scope of the project grew, cooperation between
                    the two sides increased. Mr. Gustafson explained that the original concept had
                    been much more limited: both sides would separately collect documentation,
                    compare their findings, and then select from this group certain documents for
                    publication in a rather slim volume. The Department of State had desired
                    something more, however, and with its influence and resources, better documents
                    were obtained than before. The final product will consequently be much better
                    than originally intended.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask observed that the project involved a carrot-and-stick process, and that
                    it was part of the cultural diplomacy of the United States. Problems could still
                    arise if there was a change in U.S.-Soviet relations that would prevent
                    publication of the final product. Mr. Mack Thompson volunteered that while
                    speaking with Tikhvinsky, the principal Soviet editor for the project, he had
                    learned that the Soviets were thinking of two volumes instead of one. Mr.
                    Thompson inquired as to what the United States attitude was toward this. Mr.
                    Trask responded that the subject of a second volume could possibly become a
                    subject of negotiation in subsequent talks. Currently, the Soviets were
                    contemplating a second volume on World War II or the last ten years. Many
                    possibilities were involved and at some point the American side might discuss
                    them with the Soviet side.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask suggested that similar collaborative efforts might be worked out with
                    other parts of the world, such as a Middle Eastern area or Japan, and noted that
                    the Japanese had already expressed interest in the idea. Mr. Trask then
                    expressed his belief that the Russian-American project was of enormous political
                    significance. He noted, however, that the resource question was relevant, and
                    that the Office had had to transfer two historians from work on <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in order to compile the volume. Mr.
                    Blair advised the Committee that HO had been permitted to make this tradeoff of
                    increasingly scarce resources and engage in the Russian-American project only
                    because a U.S. foreign policy objective was involved: the opening up by a tiny
                    bit of some of the functioning of the Soviet Government by providing access to
                    Soviet archives. This objective did not necessarily apply to other parts of the
                    world. Where no foreign policy objective existed, it would be difficult to
                    justify an expenditure of resources on a similar project. Mr. Gustafson agreed
                    with Mr. Blair that the joint project would help open Soviet archives to U.S.
                    scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then announced the need to recess this part of the meeting so that the
                    Committee might proceed to the Office of the Historian for a demonstration of
                    the Linolex word-processing system, microfiche technology, and meetings with the
                    staff.</p>
                <p>Mr. Allen Thompson added that if any members of the Committee desired to take a
                    look at his declassification operation at the National Archives, it could be
                    arranged either for that day or during a subsequent visit to Washington.</p>
                <p>The meeting was recessed until 2 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center">SECOND SESSION<lb/>2:18-4:05 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Microform Supplements (Briefing Paper No.
                        6)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask reopened the meeting at 2:18 p.m. and welcomed Ilana Stern, a former
                    member of the Office. Mr. Aandahl said that before discussion of the microform
                    issue, he wished to record a conversation with the Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs, David D. Newsom, who had hosted the luncheon for the Advisory
                    Committee. Secretary Newsom recalled that in the past he had both cleared some
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> galleys as a desk officer and had
                    presented <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes to foreign statesmen.
                    He expressed his hope that there was a reasonable ground between the concern of
                    historians about publishing the foreign policy record and the concern of
                    diplomats about not including especially sensitive material.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner and Mr. Cohen, referring to earlier remarks by Mr. Slany, asked why
                    documents printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes would also
                    be included in the proposed microform supplement. Mr. Slany explained that the
                    advantage of doing so was that the scholar would be able to compare the printed
                    text with a facsimile text in order to assure himself that the compilation
                    editor had not distorted the meaning of the document, either through annotation
                    or deletions.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that he was presuming different groups would use the microform
                    edition of the printed volumes. A scholar would be interested mainly in the
                    original documents; he would use the printed volume principally as a guide to
                    the documents. It was a planning assumption that the microform edition was
                    intended primarily for scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl noted that a question had arisen at the luncheon concerning the
                    experience of the National Archives with microform. Mr. Gustafson stated that
                    diplomatic records had been microfilmed through 1910; but thus far only selected
                    files with the highest research potential had been microfilmed for subsequent
                    years. The program was based on filming a file only when it was declassified and
                    arranged and could be filmed in its entirety.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cole stated that he differed from Mr. Trask over the use of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>. He noted that he used the volumes frequently and
                    also did archival research. He considered the volumes to be more than finding
                    aids, however, and often used them for classes for the study of secondary topics
                    where there was no need to go into further depth. He consequently questioned
                    whether the assumption that scholars would rely primarily on the microfiche
                    supplement was indeed a valid one. Mr. Trask replied that he intended no lack of
                    respect for those satisfied with the volumes in their present form. He stated
                    that for individuals such as Mr. Cole, whose main research interest, the
                    domestic side of international politics, did not focus upon State Department
                    documents, the volumes might well be sufficient. However, he reiterated that the
                    microform supplement would be of great utility to scholars in diplomatic
                    history, those studying official relations between states, who desired to pursue
                    given topics in depth. Mr. Aandahl pointed out that the microform supplement
                    would also serve as a clearance tool. If the principal papers in the files were
                    cleared, others would follow.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner stated that the researcher would not be satisfied to rely solely on
                    240,000 pages of documents in microfiche. He pointed out that the microfiche
                    would cover many different topics, and that those documents of interest to a
                    particular monographist would still not eliminate his need to visit the National
                    Archives to consult the original files. He believed that although the idea of a
                    supplement was nice, the Office should not undertake the project with the notion
                    that it would make scholars happy. Mr. Slany replied that the supplement was
                    simply another benchmark, a way of capturing more documents, and that it was not
                    intended to make further research unnecessary. Because of the rapid
                    deterioration of files after they were moved to other depositories, it was
                    desirable to capture the results of HO’s research as soon as possible. Many
                    scholars would still have to go to the Archives to do further research. For
                    other <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> users, the microfiche supplement
                    and printed pages would be enough. The microfiche supplement would improve the
                    value of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, although it was not expected
                    to solve all problems.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jacobson asked what time limits had been set for a decision on the issue of a
                    supplement and whether it would be in the form of microfilm or microfiche. He
                    also asked what percentage 240,000 pages represented of the total number of
                    available documents, how the selection would be made, and how much staff time
                    would be allocated to the process. Mr. Trask replied that there would first be a
                    feasibility study. If it was successful, HO would write an options paper and
                    formally propose the project to Mr. Blair. The options paper would include
                    information and suggestions from the Committee. He emphasized that no final
                    decision had been made and that none had been asked for.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair indicated that he was leaning in the direction of the microfiche
                    supplement, and that if the Committee felt the Department was headed in the
                    wrong direction, he would like to hear about it immediately. There were many
                    tradeoffs, but the key one was that within a certain ceiling of money, HO faced
                    an explosion of documentation. It was still possible to stay totally with
                    printed volumes, but with no prospect of an increase in the budget ceiling,
                    there would be a continuous decline in the fraction of the significant record
                    the Department could publish. Should the Department sacrifice something and use
                    part of the budget to publish a much larger number of documents than would be
                    available in the printed edition? Mr. Blair concluded that the answer to this
                    question appeared to be that the Department should use a fraction of the budget
                    for microform. The Department was close to reaching a firm decision, and one
                    would undoubtedly be made before the Committee met again. If the Committee
                    thought these conclusions were wrong, the Department would like to hear their
                    views.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that a microform supplement might be used as part of the
                    declassification procedure under the new Executive Order, and that this was why
                    a decision had to be made soon. Mr. Slany pointed out that he did not anticipate
                    that a microfiche supplement would detract in any way from the printed edition.
                    He further explained that under the old system, a compiler would develop a large
                    number of working papers from which he or she would make a final selection for
                    inclusion in the series. Under the new system, the working papers, most of which
                    would go into the supplement, would become the basis for declassifying the files
                    under the new Executive Order. In order to underscore the selective nature of a
                    fiche supplement Mr. Slany stated that from 5 to 10 percent of the total
                    available important documents would be microfiched. Mr. Blair emphasized that
                    production of the microfiche supplement did not entail a separate selection
                    process, but that it would consist of the preliminary selection, which would be
                    made in any case.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Unterberger asked whether the use of documents from other agencies would
                    increase clearance problems. Mr. Slany answered that clearance would always be
                    difficult. The Office could nevertheless blank out microfiche frames containing
                    documents that could not be immediately declassified, and later release the
                    unexpurgated original selection when everything had been cleared. Mr. Trask
                    pointed out that the relative ease of blanking out uncleared documents by means
                    of a modern camera gave the microfiche a distinct advantage over the printed
                    volumes, since subsequently cleared material could never be added to printed
                    volumes except through a supplement. He said that by maintaining a master set of
                    microfiche containing all the original documents, the eliminated frames could be
                    easily reinstated in the publicly available microfiche as the withheld material
                    was declassified. In the brief discussion which followed, note was taken of the
                    great advantage to scholars in knowing where documents had been excluded because
                    they had not been declassified.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen stated that he had concluded that the feasibility question was
                    substantially an economic one. He asked whether a feasibility study had been
                    made on the technical and economic aspects of the microfiche supplement. Was it
                    economically possible, for example, for the Department to sell a single
                    microfiche card at a time for 25 cents? Mr. Slany responded that it was not
                    worthwhile for commercial publishers to sell single microfiche cards, and that
                    they preferred to sell sets. Mr. Trask added that a microfiche card cost far
                    less than a printed page. Mr. Cohen conceded that production costs would
                    probably be less but asked whether distribution costs would not be excessive.
                    More specially, he questioned whether the office could economically sell
                    microfiche cards in small amounts. Mr. Aandahl commented that the Government
                    Printing Office could sell cards for 25 cents. Mr. Trask, however, stated that
                    the Office of the Historian could prepare microfiche masters with its own
                    personnel more cheaply than the Government Printing Office. [Mr. Trask did not
                    mean to imply that HO would <hi rend="underline">market</hi> microfiche. HO
                    would make masters available to the publisher. The publisher would manage
                    distribution and sales. Obviously the smaller an order the higher the unit cost
                    to the purchaser as a general rule.] With regard to the merits of the various
                    kinds of microforms, he believed microfiche to be the most efficient. Mr. Cohen
                    agreed but suggested that it was unwarranted to assume that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> users would buy microfiche cards even if the
                    Department could sell them. It would be impractical to assume that historians
                    would have microfiche readers at home; they would use their libraries. The
                    Department could not afford to sell a microfiche card for 25 cents, he believed;
                    the cost to the Department, with handling, might be $5.00.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask replied that many historians who used microform documents owned
                    microfilm readers. Such readers cost $100 ten years ago. The more a scholar was
                    involved in multiarchival and multilingual research, the more likely he was to
                    buy his own reader and his own film. The microfiche supplement was aimed at a
                    small group and there was a much broader interest in the printed volumes.
                    However, the supplement provided the research scholar with his own files. Mr.
                    Trask emphasized that the microfiche supplement would be used not only by
                    Americans but also by researchers throughout the world. Scholars, who perhaps
                    could not visit the Archives, would have access to the microfiche supplement. It
                    was a small group, but an important one. Researchers, particularly in the Third
                    World, would find the microfiche edition a treasure.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stevenson stated that while he considered the microfiche supplement to be an
                    excellent idea, he was concerned that it might supplant the printed volumes. Mr.
                    Trask responded that there was no thought of this. Mr. Stevenson then stated his
                    interest in more recent documents and asked whether the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> series could be revived. He stated that these
                    volumes, combined with a microfiche supplement containing documents currently
                    available, would be immensely useful to political scientists, the legal
                    profession, and many other interested groups. He felt that the revised
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> was not adequate. In
                    financial terms, <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> with a microfiche
                    supplement might save money in the long run by expediting the general
                    declassification process. He expressed the opinion that a revived <hi
                        rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> would put pressure on desk officers to
                    declassify materials scheduled to appear in the current volume and would
                    increase the accessioning of documents to the Archives, particularly the
                    materials automatically declassified in six years. He did not think reactivating
                        <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> would be that costly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair replied that ideally he and the HO Staff would like to see the revival
                    of the series and that perhaps the issue should be looked at again. He pointed
                    out that the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> had expanded its scope in order to
                    help fill the gap left by <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi>. Mr. Blair
                    noted that budgetary limitations were the main impediment to reactivating <hi
                        rend="italic">Current Documents</hi>, and that he himself had turned down
                    proposals for its revival because he could not find another operation from which
                    to take the resources. He added that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    served as the spearhead in the declassification process. Mr. Blair concluded
                    that the issue was a question of priorities, and asked the Committee whether it
                    would be willing to see resources taken from <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to revive <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi>. Mr.
                    Stevenson then inquired whether the persons who selected documents for the <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> could assemble a microform supplement. Mr. Blair
                    replied that perhaps the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> staff could make a
                    better selection of documents, if this would help.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner returned to the question of the preparation and distribution of the
                    proposed microfiche supplement. He asked whether the Office of the Historian
                    would handle small orders for fiche and whether the Government Printing Office
                    would be willing to take orders for a single microfiche card. He also questioned
                    whether HO could afford the resources that would be needed to review and update
                    a supplement. He pointed out that staff members would have to proofread 240,000
                    microfiche frames for legibility and completeness, and then periodically revise
                    them, inserting subsequently declassified documents. How, he asked, could the
                    staff meet its current responsibilities to the printed <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes, do additional research such as that for
                    Russian-American project, and still have time to do justice to microfiche? Mr.
                    Gardner suggested that the feasibility study of microform include a study of
                    HO’s ability to do all these things, and Mr. Blair agreed. Mr. Slany stated that
                    equipment was available that would facilitate the replacement of microfiche
                    frames. He added that with respect to the review and proofreading of documents
                    to be published in microfiche, the Office would exploit the Group Chiefs, who
                    could review the microfiche supplement in addition to their regular review of
                    manuscript for the printed volumes. The actual collection and selection of
                    documents for a microfiche supplement could be efficiently accomplished through
                    the organization of the staff to avoid duplication of effort. With regard to the
                    question of microfiche production and sales, Mr. Slany explained that there were
                    no good answers yet. GPO and commercial producers could give no precise
                    estimates until they knew exactly what the requirements of the Office were.
                    Therefore, a pilot project for the 1955-1957 period needed to be completed
                    before exact costs could be ascertained. Other pilot projects, such as a
                    possible joint Department of State-National Security Council undertaking, could
                    also provide the needed information and could concentrate on documents that were
                    easily reproduced and that did not require a great deal of editing. Mr. Trask
                    stressed the advantage of being able to introduce into a set an entire new
                    microfiche card when previously-deleted documents were declassified, whereas
                    pages could not be added once a printed volume had been published. He reiterated
                    that regardless of the final cost of producing microfiche, it would be much
                    lower than that for printed pages. Mr. Cohen again voiced his skepticism that
                    the Office would be able to afford to sell individual microfiche cards. He
                    stated that as the editor of a professional journal, he had found that the sale
                    of individual reprints resulted in a net loss for the publication because of
                    high bookkeeping and processing costs. He believed the issue needed to be
                    carefully studied. Mr. Trask replied that reprint costs would not be critical
                    because the Federal Government would subsidize microfiche production and
                    distribution much as it subsidized publication of the printed volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jacobson said that although he favored the microfiche supplement, the
                    Advisory Committee would like a fairly exact estimate both of its cost and of
                    what the same amount of money would achieve if used to augment the printed
                    volumes. The Committee needed this information to be effective in defending the
                    supplement to the scholarly community. Committee members would need to show that
                    a given amount of money allocated to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series could reproduce, for example, either 1.1 percent of
                    available documents in the printed volumes or a combination of 1 percent on
                    printed pages and an additional 9 percent on microfiche. Mr. Trask replied that
                    Government Printing Office had estimated the cost of reproducing 240,000
                    document pages on master fiche cards to be $84,000, which included the subsidy
                    element. He added that this figure, which included distribution, was a maximum
                    one. He expressed the hope that majority of supplementary materials would be
                    documents from other agencies but presumed that at first a heavy percentage
                    would originate in the State Department. The total number of documents to be
                    reproduced in both printed and microfiche form would be less than 1 percent of
                    the unpublished material, not 5 to 10 percent. He pointed out, however, that the
                    microfiche supplement would increase the number of published documents tenfold.
                    The estimated cost per frame of microfiche was 35 cents, compared with $60 per
                    printed page under the present system, or $25 per page under the word processing
                    system.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner questioned whether the value of the microfiche supplement to
                    researchers could really justify the staff time and expense required for its
                    preparation. He was not certain how many researchers in the Third World had
                    access to reader/printers, Even in the United States, he pointed out,
                    reader/printers in libraries seemed to be broken half the time. In doing
                    research, a scholar might need to have as many as three or four <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes open at one time to compare
                    different documents. One could not use three or four microfiche readers
                    simultaneously. It was difficult to locate documents on fiche cards and even
                    more difficult to compare documents unless one had the money to make copies. In
                    addition, one needed a darkened room. The process was not simple even for
                    Americans accustomed to these problems. The notion that a major tool was being
                    provided to the Third World must be checked out. Mr. Gardner asked why the
                    Office could not concentrate on putting out higher-quality printed volumes on
                    the basis of the new savings under word processing in printing costs, which were
                    down from $900,000 to $300,000 per year. Microform could be left to the National
                    Archives, whose microfilm publications were superbly done. While he recognized
                    the needs the Office was attempting to fill by means of a supplement, he
                    believed that the drain on staff resources presented a real problem. The time
                    required to train contract historians who would serve only a limited time in the
                    Office compounded the problem. Mr. Gardner concluded that he would much prefer
                    to see the HO staff concentrate on maintaining the high standards of the printed
                    volumes than try to do too many things at once.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair replied that if the consensus of the Committee was that microfiche was
                    not an effective research tool, the Department would have to look at it again
                    and perhaps postpone it. In the meantime, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series would go downhill. With all due respect, the
                    Department could not leave the problems to the National Archives. What the
                    Department produced was what the scholarly community would get. The Department
                    should provide expanded coverage, but it was not locked into any of the figures
                    cited. Mr. Blair stated that what attracted him as a layman, assuming that
                    microfiche was a little more acceptable than Mr. Gardner had described it, was
                    the possibility of experimenting to see if the idea of a supplement was worth
                    pursuing. Mr. Blair was impressed by the fact that 5 to 10 times as many
                    documents could be made available. The figures might be wrong, but that was
                    secondary. The main point was whether or not the experiment was worth
                    making.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner stated that as he read the figures, the Department could increase the
                    size of the printed volumes and still experiment with microform, because of the
                    savings made under the new word processing system. Mr. Blair agreed that this
                    should be possible. Mr. Trask also agreed, but reemphasized the importance of
                    pursuing the microfiche supplement. His generation had pioneered in using fiche
                    and had made a great contribution to the study of international relations. <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> for the year 1898 had only a couple of
                    cocktail conversations on the Spanish-American War.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that in the past microfilm and microfilm readers had often been
                    miserable to work with. He also noted that microfiche legibility could present
                    some difficulty in the future supplement. But he emphasized that there would be
                    no alternative to the microfiche supplement should it not be produced. Mr, Trask
                    again stressed the importance of the supplement to the Third World, and recalled
                    from his own experience an Indian researcher at the British Public Record Office
                    who ordered documents microfilmed for use at home. He pointed out that making
                    microfiche copies of documents readily available to researchers all over the
                    world would introduce a whole new concept of scholarship.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kane stated that the Office must be conscious of the tradeoffs a microfiche
                    program would bring in the allocation of staff time. If the four HO Group Chiefs
                    were indeed to be made responsible for reviewing documents intended for
                    microfiche reproduction, he doubted whether they would have much time to remain
                    active compilers for the printed volumes. Mr. Aandahl replied that perhaps
                    arrangements could be made to have the documents intended for microfiche
                    reviewed outside the Office. Mr. Trask stated that he believed Mr. Kane’s
                    concern to be sound, and added that HO would have to rethink who did what under
                    the new format. The selection and review of documents for the microfiche
                    supplement was a complex process. Another element of the feasibility study was
                    to reprogram the tasks of people in the Office. The next stage would be a pilot
                    project.</p>
                <p>At this point Mr. Cohen noted that since the Committee had addressed most of its
                    attention to the first portion of the afternoon agenda, he hoped that there
                    would be enough time to cover the other items. Mr. Trask consequently asked Mr.
                    Aandahl to introduce the next scheduled topic.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Schedule (Briefing
                        Paper No. 7)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl discussed the production schedule, emphasizing recent delays in the
                    declassification of manuscripts. He added that the Office would not be able to
                    maintain its schedule for attaining the 20-year line unless favorable
                    declassification action proceeded more rapidly, and unless adequate resources
                    were continually available. Mr. Aandahl then invited comments from the
                    Committee, and none were forthcoming. Mr. Trask stated that the Office was
                    within shouting distance of finishing the portion of the series covering the
                    1955-1957 triennium.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">McGovern Amendment (Briefing Paper No.
                    8)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then turned to the McGovern Amendment, expressing pleasure that
                    Congress had taken note of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                    He added that the Amendment, which had been introduced without the knowledge of
                    the Office of the Historian, had led Congress to misunderstand the Office’s
                    intentions. He noted that the provision for joint State-Congressional
                    consultation in the final legislation was a positive development which could
                    have relieved the initial misunderstanding had it been allowed to occur earlier.
                    Mr. Gardner said that the Briefing Paper had overstated the Amendment by saying
                    that it precluded the use of microform. He noted that the purpose of the
                    original Senate version of the Amendment, not included in the briefing material,
                    had been to establish a floor on printed pages in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes. Mr. Trask, referring to page 2 of Briefing Paper No.
                    8, noted that the conference committee report described the original Senate
                    Amendment as seeking to prevent the replacement of printed pages with
                    microfiche. Mr. Gardner quoted testimony of Ben H. Read, Under Secretary of
                    State for Management, before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, concerning
                    page cuts in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Secretary Read
                    stated that he had received no budgetary request for the series that had been
                    turned down. He continued that if there had been a change in policy, he would
                    have heard. Mr. Read also promised to let the Foreign Relations Committee know
                    if there was a change in policy.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen asked whether the formal consultation was to be conducted through the
                    Secretary of State or Mr. Trask. Mr. Trask said he had asked the same question.
                    He wanted to begin the process immediately, and did not think the word “formal”
                    had any significant meaning. Mr. Cole felt that it was not a throwaway word. He
                    believed the Amendment was designed to establish a minimum number of pages for
                    the printed volumes. He further interpreted the Amendment as a warning to the
                    Department not to reduce the number of printed pages too much in behalf of the
                    microfiche supplement, and that if the Department envisioned such a development,
                    Congress would want to discuss it first. Mr. Trask reemphasized the importance
                    of consultation with Congress, and restated his belief that the misunderstanding
                    inherent in the McGovern Amendment would not have arisen if consultation had
                    been instituted earlier. He added that Congress now knew what the Office was
                    doing and vice versa. He pointed out that 1955-1957 volumes would satisfy the
                    page requirements of the original version of the Amendment which stipulated that
                    no three-year triennium of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> should have
                    less than two-thirds the number of pages contained in the volumes for 1947-1949.
                    He emphasized that the Office was not locked into a specific number of pages for
                    the 1955-57 period. It was possible to authorize an increase in the number of
                    pages for the 1955-57 triennium from 15,000 to 20,000 if it proved necessary.
                    Mrs. Unterberger expressed surprise that the page limits for the 1955-1957
                    triennium were so flexible. It was her understanding from last year’s Advisory
                    Committee meeting that the level of 15,000 pages would be an absolute maximum.
                    This was also the understanding of a large number of individuals in the academic
                    community. Mr. Trask apologized for this misapprehension; he hoped to avoid such
                    misapprehensions in the future.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Outreach (Briefing Paper No. 9)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask turned to the Outreach activities of the Office. He stated that through
                    participation in various activities of the scholarly community, the HO staff had
                    developed a better perception of user interest in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. He indicated that one area the Office needed to explore
                    further was the role it could play at the community college level. He pointed
                    out that the outreach program was important for the staff because it tended to
                    relieve the sense of professional isolation and rejection sometimes experienced
                    by official historians. He added that the Office program had staff support, and
                    he felt that the results achieved thus far suggested that the program should be
                    continued. Mr. Trask then asked for comments, and, eliciting none, went on to
                    the next topic.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Strengthening of the Advisory Committee
                        (Briefing Paper No. 10)</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Trask invited comments or suggestions on the composition and functions of the
                    Advisory Committee. He pointed out that changes in the Committee’s charter, if
                    any, must be instituted by December 1978. Mr. Stevenson questioned whether the
                    current term of four years was too long, and suggested a more frequent rotation
                    of members if no increase in the size of the Committee were possible. Mr. Trask
                    replied that fiscal constraints limited the size of the Committee. Mr. Aandahl
                    stated that the length of terms of individual members should not be reduced too
                    drastically, because a member’s first year was mainly devoted to
                    familiarization. Mr. Cohen suggested that a three-year term appeared to be the
                    most reasonable compromise.</p>
                <p>Introducing a new subject, Mr. Gardner asked whether the Office had made plans to
                    publish a retrospective volume covering the years 1945 to 1950 and primarily
                    containing Truman Library materials not available when the volumes for these
                    years were compiled. If nothing had been done, he formally requested a
                    feasibility study on the issue. Mr. Glennon replied that a retrospective volume
                    on intelligence for the years 1947-1951 was under discussion. Mr. Petersen
                    mentioned that a manuscript on intelligence had been prepared covering the years
                    1947 to 1954. It was currently a basis for discussion and review with INR and
                    CIA, but the current clearance outlook was grim, and the Office was not sure how
                    to proceed. Mr. Trask said that as resources became available the Office would
                    consider doing topical but not strictly chronological volumes. Mr. Gardner
                    stated that he favored a chronological approach in cases where a major source of
                    documentation such as the Truman Library had previously been closed to <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compilers. He felt that HO would gain
                    tremendous credit from a retrospective volume. Mr. Trask replied that the more
                    such volumes the Office could do, the more pleased it would be. The main problem
                    was one of resources, which the Office would have to subtract from somewhere.
                    One argument against compiling retrospective chronological volumes was that most
                    of the newly-available material would have been absorbed in the work of
                    independent scholars, and was in any event available to the public at the
                    Presidential libraries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Aandahl suggested that a microfiche supplement covering earlier material was
                    worth considering. With respect to retrospective volumes, Mr. Trask noted that
                    Professor John Gaddis was currently filling in gaps left by earlier <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. However, he felt that HO’s
                    capabilities exceeded those of private scholars in doing justice to this kind of
                    task, and he would like the Office to do such volumes if the time and money
                    could be spared. Mrs. Harris then described her work on intelligence materials
                    for years 1955-1961.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask concluded by paying tribute to the competence of the staff and by
                    introducing the contract historians (Mrs. Harris, Mr. Patterson, Ms. Wells, Ms.
                    Pitts and Mr. McMahon) to the Committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask adjourned the meeting at 4:05 p.m. Members of the Committee then met
                    informally to discuss their report.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
