<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From Gale Allen to David Baehler, October 1979</title>
                <title type="short">Allen to Baehler, 1979</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-22">January 22, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1979-10-28">October 28, 1979</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1979-10-28-allen-to-baylor.pdf">PDF</ref>, 170 KB, 5pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-WW-9: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, Arthur
                    Kogan Files, 1945-1980 (83 D 230), Box 2, Declassification Denials &amp;
                    Challenges. Secret. Allen’s signature was present, but not declassified for
                    release. David Baehler’s last name (corrected here) was misspelled “Baylor” in
                    the original document.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn16">Footnote 16</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From Gale W. Allen (Chief of the Classification Review Division at the
                    Central Intelligence Agency) to David Baehler (Adviser on Declassification at
                    the Historian’s Office)</head>
                <dateline>October 28, 1979</dateline>
                <p>Dear Dave:</p>
                <p>This letter is in response to two letters dated September 27, 1979 from Mr. John
                    Glennon concerning several Agency deletions from Volumes XIII, “Indochina,” and
                    XV, “Korea,” of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> series. The points in Mr. Glennon’s letters were discussed with
                    the Directorate of Operations which has the greatest direct Agency interest in
                    this material. We would like to pass the results of these discussions to you and
                    your associate historians concerned with the various area volumes of the FRUS
                    because in the main, the Agency rationale for handling a particular subject
                    matter will apply uniformly:</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="underline">Official Disclosure</hi>. The attachment to your letter
                    concerning Volume XV equates references from open literature to authorized
                    executive disclosure of previously classified information. We cannot accept that
                    equation as valid. Such citations of the open literature may be useful in
                    alerting us to public treatment of a topic on which there are classified
                    holdings, but they do not oblige us to make executive disclosure of the same or
                    comparable material. The fact of publication of numerous unofficial works places
                    no obligation on this Agency to make authorized executive disclosure of
                    statements made in those unofficial works. To reason otherwise would, in the
                    face of the First Amendment entitlement of most Americans and aliens legally
                    resident in the United States and the weakness of our statutes with respect to
                    the protection of official secrets, place us in an untenable position. Such
                    rationale would leave us vulnerable to the Ellsbergs and Agees of this world
                    who, having purloined official classified material and had it published, could
                    then point to the fact of publication as a basis for requiring the Agency to
                    make official confirmation.</p>
                <p>Publications such as the Rozitske, Colby and Cline books are sometimes referred
                    to as “semi-official memoirs.” The fact of the authors’ prior association with
                    CIA and even (in two cases) of review of the manuscripts by Agency personnel
                    does not give these books status as authorized executive disclosure.</p>
                <p>The Church Committee’s “Final Report” is, of course, legislative and not
                    executive disclosure. The rule that we have followed with regard to that
                    particular publication and others like it is this: If the publication quotes
                    from a document which was supplied officially by CIA to the Congress, we
                    generally acknowledge the existence of the document if Congress chooses to
                    reveal its existence, and generally, we disclose the quoted segment, but only
                    that. Of course, if additional executive disclosure was made subsequent to the
                    legislative disclosure of portions of a CIA document, we must take that
                    executive disclosure into account.</p>
                <p>Concerning another aspect of the same problem, the disclosure of the Agency’s
                    classified material by another component of the Executive Branch does not
                    constitute <hi rend="underline">authorized</hi> executive disclosure <hi
                        rend="underline">by this Agency</hi> unless competent authority of this
                    Agency, and more particularly in the case of Directorate of Operation’s
                    information, of the Directorate of Operations, has concurred. This is pertinent
                    with reference to the citation of “The Pentagon Papers” in the DOD version. It
                    is even more pertinent to memoirs such as those by Edward G. Lansdale, written
                    and published without Agency acknowledgment that they constitute authorized
                    executive disclosure. (Mere review of a manuscript by the Agency does not
                    constitute authorized executive disclosure.)</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="underline">CIA Presence</hi>. Objection has been raised to our
                    denial of the letters “CAS” when “mere mention of CIA presence” is at issue. Our
                    standard Agency practice, in compliance with Section 6 of the CIA Act of 1949,
                    is not to disclose CIA locations abroad. “Mere mention of CIA presence” is
                    clearly disclosure if authorized release is made. That information is
                    classifiable under Section 1-301, E.O. 12065.</p>
                <p>Recognizing that certain distinctions could be made with regard to Vietnam and
                    Laos, the DCI did, on 4 May 1979, determine that disclosure of CIA stations and
                    bases in those countries would be made in connection with the Agency’s response
                    to Freedom of Information Act requests for MIA reports. Of course, authorized
                    executive disclosure made in one context is also applicable to other contexts
                    and generally cannot be withdrawn. It is in recognition of that fact that the
                    Directorate of Operations practice with regard to disclosures concerning certain
                    CIA stations and bases in Vietnam and Laos must be limited as follows:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>a. Laos, Vientiane Station - 17 July 1966 through 16 November 1968;</item>
                    <item>b. Vietnam, Saigon Station - 17 November 1968 through 30 April
                        1975;</item>
                    <item>c. Vietnam, Hue - 22 October 1967 only;</item>
                    <item>d. Vietnam, Can Tho - 17 June 1967 through 26 March 1974;</item>
                    <item>e. Vietnam, Nha Trang - 5 December 1969 through 12 June 1972.</item>
                </list>
                <p>It will be immediately apparent to the knowledgeable that certain CIA locations
                    in Laos and Vietnam are not included in the disclosable list. The decision is
                    interpreted to mean that unlisted locations should <hi rend="underline">not</hi>
                    be disclosed. Furthermore, disclosure of the presence of the <hi
                        rend="underline">listed</hi> locations during the specified periods does not
                    obligate disclosure of the same stations or bases for prior or subsequent
                    periods if, indeed, they existed at those earlier or later periods.</p>
                <p>You will note that, whereas the period covered by the DCI’s decision to disclose
                    varies for different locations, that time-frame is later than that which applies
                    to the documents in question. Therefore, to the extent that documents either are
                    dated or refer to periods other than those for which disclosure has been
                    authorized, “mere mention of CIA presence” must continue to be denied.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="underline">Foreign Liaison</hi>. Another point that bears mention is
                    our obligation, by statute, not to reveal the fact of or details concerning
                    intelligence liaison relationships between CIA and foreign intelligence and
                    security services. If disclosed, “mere mention” of the receipt of reports from a
                    foreign intelligence service carries with it revelation of the existence of a
                    relationship, particularly when the text makes clear that the reference is to a
                    relationship that involves CIA. As you are aware, we do not make that type
                    revelation in authorized executive disclosures, and cannot do so for the sake of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series which
                    epitomizes authorized executive disclosure.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="underline">CIA Internal Documents</hi>. One item (458 JAN) relates
                    to what we refer to as an appraisal of the situation, a specific type of CIA
                    field station report that is defined in CIA regulatory issuances. Those
                    issuances make the point that the appraisal of situation is intended primarily
                    for internal (CIA) use as a guide to the operational environment existing at
                    that time and place. It is not a vehicle for making policy recommendations
                    regarding future action of the U.S. Government, and such recommendations must
                    not be included in the appraisal of situation reports. Of course, such
                    appraisals may be disseminated to other U.S. officials by CIA Headquarters, but
                    a specific authentication statement is mandatory. That statement includes (and
                    included in the past a comparable reminder) as follows: “Prepared primarily for
                    internal Agency use, it is disseminated in the belief that it may be useful to
                    others in their own assessment of the situation.” Your opinion of the document
                    in question (458 JAN) as “a perceptive analysis by the unnamed senior CIA
                    representative [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] does not reduce
                    our responsibility to respect the controls that were applied when dissemination
                    was made, if 458 JAN was, indeed, an appraisal of the situation as contrasted to
                    a situation report. The accompanying statement that “we are unable to see how
                    intelligence sources and methods would be compromised by declassification of
                    this document” is presumably true. That is, however, but one aspect of our
                    responsibilities under Section 6 of the CIA Act of 1949. We do not release
                    appraisals of the situation for these <hi rend="underline">additional</hi>
                    reasons:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>a. Disclosure would confirm the presence of a CIA station (at a time not
                        covered by the DCI’s decision of 4 May 1979);</item>
                    <item>b. Disclosure would facilitate external analysis of CIA’s capacity to
                        judge the operational environment under a particular set of
                        circumstances;</item>
                    <item>c. Enhancement of external analysis increases the capacity of hostile
                        elements to disrupt, penetrate, or thwart current efforts in the same or
                        similar location.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Obviously, our most important reasons relate to the protection of sources and
                    methods. Were the specific report to be reconsidered, in disregard of
                    established practice with respect to this type of report, we still would have to
                    go back to the sourcing of the individual paragraphs of the report to determine
                    sourcing. In sum, our entitlement to the denial of disclosure of appraisals of
                    the situation is, in our view, greater on numerous counts than the finding that
                    a given document “deserves to be part of the official record.”</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>: With regard to the item appearing
                    in documents 62-63 CHI concerning the status of the U.S. Consulate in Hanoi
                    after the armistice, one factor we -- with at least some judicial sanction --
                    must take into account to determine identifiable damage to the national security
                    is the <hi rend="underline">present day</hi> impact of disclosure. The fact that
                    an issue was an important foreign policy matter is not sufficient justification
                    for us to ignore the possible present day difficulties that could result from
                    disclosure. We believe that your Area Desks share our concern in this
                    regard.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="underline">Text not declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>The remainder of the text under “Discussion” and the text under “Recommendation”
                    simply reiterates some of the key points noted above and remains classified for
                    the applicable reasons identified above. Summarizing the individual points
                    listed, the CIA and Directorate of Operations particularly are well-advised not
                    to release official information that makes clear to host country authorities
                    that CIA has or had a station in the country, or that CIA has or had an
                    intelligence liaison relationship with intelligence services of the host
                    country. I might recall one recent event for its value as an analogy. You will
                    recall the furor in the United States that followed disclosure by <hi
                        rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi> of classified information in a 9
                    August 1979 article headlined “Foreign Spy Activity Found Rampant In U.S...” A
                    comparable or worse reaction must be anticipated in certain countries when the
                    situation is reversed. [<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified.</hi>] Our
                    concern is not that disclosure of this sort is embarrassing but that it has a
                    definite impact on current or future diplomatic and operational environments in
                    which CIA must carry out intelligence activities. Briefly stated, then, this is
                    the identifiable damage to the national security that in our view unauthorized
                    disclosure reasonably could be expected to cause.</p>
                <p>7. I want to reiterate that the above represent the position of the Directorate
                    of Operations but also is essentially the Agency position on these matters. I am
                    forwarding them to you in the hope it will aid you and your staff in appraising
                    what information in these categories we would consider classified and want to
                    protect from disclosure.</p>
                <p>Gale W. Allen</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>