<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From John Glennon to Gale W. Allen, September
                    1979</title>
                <title type="short">Glennon to Allen, 1979</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-22">January 22, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1979-09-27">September 27, 1979</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1979-09-27-glennon-to-allen.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 132 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-WW-9: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, Arthur
                    Kogan Files, 1945-1980 (83 D 230), Box 2, Declassification Denials &amp;
                    Challenges. Confidential. Posted from a copy that bears Glennon’s initials in
                    place of a signature. Drafted by Neal Petersen (PA/HO) on September 28 and
                    cleared by David Mabon (PA/HO).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn15">Footnote 15</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From John Glennon (Associate Historian for Asia, Africa, and the
                    Pacific) to Gale W. Allen (Chief of the Classification Review Group at the
                    Central Intelligence Agency)</head>
                <dateline>September 27, 1979</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Allen:</p>
                <p>I am writing in response to your letter of July 9, 1979, to Mr. Fredrick Aandahl
                    concerning the review by the Central Intelligence Agency of documents of
                    intelligence interest slated for publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations of the United States</hi>, 1952-1954, Volume XIII; “Indochina”. As
                    a result of that review CIA recommended that deletions be made in seventeen
                    documents and that two papers be removed entirely. Your letter of August 27 to
                    Mr. Aandahl conveyed the request that a deletion be made in an additional
                    document.</p>
                <p>As indicated in the attached list this office concurs in some of the proposed
                    deletions. However, we recommend that a number of items be reconsidered.</p>
                <p>In general, our areas of disagreement are confined to a limited number of points;
                    we feel that mere indication of the CIA presence in Indochina, sometimes
                    connoted by the abbreviation CAS, should not be grounds for the deletion of a
                    passage, since no question of the compromising of intelligence sources and
                    methods is involved. Secondly, we are concerned by deletions related to CIA
                    interest in the development of anti-Viet Minh guerrilla units. The passages
                    proposed for elimination serve to indicate that the agency had <hi
                        rend="underline">not</hi> been engaged significantly in such activities
                    prior to the armistice, July 1954, due to French recalcitrance. This is an
                    important point which should appear in the official historical record, and a
                    point which is difficult to consider sensitive.</p>
                <p>With regard to CIA activities in Indochina in the post-Geneva Conference period,
                    actual or contemplated, nothing in the recommended excisions reveals information
                    beyond that imparted in, Edward G. Lansdale, <hi rend="italic">In the Midst of
                        Wars</hi> (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1972); United States Department of
                    Defense, <hi rend="italic">United States-Vietnam Relations, 1945-1967</hi>, 12
                    vols. (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1971) (“The Pentagon Papers”);
                    and <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> version of the Pentagon Papers
                    (New York: · Quadrangle Books, 1971) -- see for example excerpts from the
                    Lansdale Team’s report, pp. 54-67.</p>
                <p>Finally, our charter does not permit us to substitute our own language for that
                    of the original document, as is proposed in several instances in your letter of
                    July 9.</p>
                <p>Here follows a list of comments on specific documents.</p>
                <p>1. The galley citations listed below refer to documentation involving CIA
                    recommendations for deletions in which the Office of the Historian is prepared
                    to concur:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>217 JAN</item>
                    <item>427 JAN</item>
                    <item>419 BER</item>
                    <item>175 NED</item>
                    <item>126-127 CHI</item>
                </list>
                <p>2. The galley citations listed below refer to deletions which seem to be based
                    exclusively on mere mention of CIA presence or the appearance of the letters
                    “CAS”, and are therefore contested:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>149 JAN</item>
                    <item>210-211 JAN</item>
                    <item>216 JAN</item>
                    <item>320 CHI</item>
                    <item>392 CHI</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>4. The statement of 458 JAN which, according to your letter of July 9, cannot be
                    declassified, is a perceptive analysis by the unnamed senior CIA representative
                        [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified.</hi>] It was circulated at the
                    highest levels of government and deserves to be part of the official record. We
                    are unable to see how intelligence sources and methods would be compromised by
                    declassification of this document.</p>
                <p>5. We urge reconsideration of the proposed deletion on 292 BER. Since the text as
                    a whole makes it clear that the President approved in principle the operation
                    under consideration, hypothetical participation by the CIA hardly seems
                    sensitive. In any event, the principles of compilation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series preclude the possibility of substituting our
                    own language for a portion of the original text, as suggested.</p>
                <p>6. With regard to the deletion proposed on 300 BER, a portion of the same
                    document, including the objectionable passage, was selected for publication in
                    Volume XII. In your letter of April 13, 1979, CIA objected to the release of
                    only the portion of the sentence beginning with the word “indeed,” whereas in
                    this instance, the entire sentence is recommended for deletion. Regardless, the
                    points raised in my letter of August 29 (in response to your letter of April
                    13), continue to pertain. That CIA contemplated special operations in Indochina
                    in the event of French defeat is public knowledge as a result of the publication
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Pentagon Papers</hi>, the Lansdale memoirs, and
                    numerous unofficial works.</p>
                <p>7. The proposed deletions on 321 BER, 326 BER, 343 BER, 344 BER, 354 BER, and 355
                    BER should also be reconsidered. The passages in question appear sensitive only
                    in that they mention the well-known CIA presence in Indochina and confirm that
                    the CIA had <hi rend="underline">not</hi> been involved in anti-Viet Minh
                    guerrilla training prior to mid-1954.</p>
                <p>8. The proposed deletion on 360 BER also deserves another look. No more than the
                    mention of the CIA studying the possibility of developing more dynamic
                    Vietnamese leadership seems to be involved. Again, the suggested modification of
                    language in the original text is not feasible.</p>
                <p>9. The memorandum of conversation on 62-63 CHI, a State Department document,
                    illuminates an important foreign policy matter, the status of the Hanoi
                    consulate after the armistice. We urge reconsideration.</p>
                <p>10. The telegram on 441-444 CHI is printed in its entirety in the Defense
                    Department version of the <hi rend="italic">Pentagon Papers</hi>, Book 10, pp.
                    811-813. The passages recommended for deletion on 442 CHI are therefore already
                    declassified.</p>
                <p>11. In your letter of August 27, 1979, you recommend deletion of a passage on
                    galley [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] the area of planning for
                    Guerrilla warfare. We urge reconsideration of this item on grounds delineated
                    above.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>John Glennon</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
