<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum of Conversation Among HO and CIA Officials,
                    September 1979</title>
                <title type="short">HO-CIA Meeting, 1979</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-22">January 22, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1979-08-15">September 25, 1979</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1979-09-25-ho-meeting-with-cia.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 350 KB, 11pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-08D-4: Bureau of Public Affairs, Assistant Secretary and Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary Subject Files, 1975-1981 (82 D 297), Box 6, The Historian’s
                    Office 1979. An unknown hand, but presumably Deputy Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Public Affairs William Blair, underlined passages in the text. For these
                    annotations, refer to the scanned copy of this document.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn14">Footnote 14</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum of Conversation Among HO and CIA Officials</head>
                <dateline>September 25, 1979</dateline>
                <p>On September 25, 1979, representatives of the Office of the Historian (PA/HO) met
                    with representatives of the Central Intelligence Agency's declassification
                    operation at the latter's offices [<hi rend="italic">text not
                    declassified.</hi>] The primary purpose of the meeting was to discuss CIA
                    objections to the publication in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series of certain documents dealing with Asian matters in v. XII, 1952-54. The
                    meeting lasted from 2:00 P.M. to approximately 3:40. Present from PA/HO were
                    John Glennon, Dave Mabon, Dave Baehler, and Ron Landa. The following were
                    present from CIA:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] Information Review Officer
                        in the Directorate for Operations (DDO)</item>
                    <item>Gale W. Allen, Chief, Classification Review Division (CRD), Information
                        Systems Staff, Directorate for Administration</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for
                        Directorate of Operations, (CRD)</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for
                        Directorate of Administration, CRD</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] Latin American Branch,
                        CRD</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] Southeast Asia Branch,
                        CRD</item>
                </list>
                <p>Allen delayed the beginning of the meeting until [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] arrived. When [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] entered, he took the place at the head of the table, with
                    Allen sitting to his right.</p>
                <p>Allen then opened the meeting by explaining that CRD's philosophy diverged from
                    the one set forth in the letter John Glennon sent to him concerning volume XII,
                    dated August 29, 1979. Regarding the documents in dispute, he said CIA had begun
                    with a conservative approach, but would retreat whenever possible. The important
                    thing was to strike the proper balance between HO's and CIA's interests. In that
                    regard, he asked [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] to explain what
                    CIA meant by “official disclosure,” which was the criterion by which FR material
                    was reviewed for declassification.</p>
                <p>In his remarks, [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] revealed a theme
                    which he consistently returned to in the course of the meeting: Legal exigencies
                    imposed by the CIA's statutory authority severely limited the kinds of
                    revelations that could be made in the <hi rend="italic">FR</hi> series. He cited
                    Section 6 of the 1949 CIA Act, which imposed on him the necessity to protect
                    sources and methods. If he violated this act, he said, he would be liable in
                    court. In this regard, he was guided by the term “authorized executive
                    disclosure.” If the CIA had not released information officially, and even if
                    another agency had released the information, then CIA was bound by the 1949 act
                    not to allow its publication in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. If [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] did permit its
                    publication, he would be liable in court.</p>
                <p>Continuing, [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] said that the memoirs
                    of former CIA officials mentioned in Glennon's letter did not constitute
                    “authorized executive disclosure” in the CIA's view. The memoirs were merely the
                    reminiscences of private individuals who, because of a secrecy contract signed
                    as a condition of employment, had to submit their manuscript to CIA for
                    clearance before publication. The disclosure was theirs, not the CIA's.
                    “Authorized executive disclosure” was the explicit release of information by the
                    CIA itself. FOI cases, mandatory review under E.O. 12065, approved public
                    statements by CIA representatives, in their official capacities, on intelligence
                    sources and methods were examples. Evidence of prior “authorized executive
                    disclosure” on a certain matter would justify the printing of relevant
                    documentation in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                    Publication of memoirs by retired CIA or other government officials does not.
                    Since CIA is not aware of all the “authorized executive disclosures” that have
                    taken place, they do appreciate having this kind of disclosure brought to their
                    attention.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] stated that CIA also has the
                    residual legal right to protect intelligence sources and methods relating to the
                    work of the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) in World War II. Because of the
                    abundance of documentation and memoirs on OSS activities, CIA has developed the
                    “reasonable man” approach to OSS material. This means that information can be
                    divulged when it becomes clear to “reasonable man” that so much information on a
                    given subject was already generally known that “disclosure” was not in fact
                    taking place by CIA release of material.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] went on to say that, as a result
                    of the disclosures about the OSS era, CIA was now concentrating on protecting
                    sources and methods for the period after the CIA was formed. He also said that
                    the CIA was using the “reasonable man” approach even on the later material. In
                    the course of the ensuing discussion, he reiterated repeatedly the term
                    “reasonable man” approach in describing CIA's declassification efforts.</p>
                <p>Mabon asked whether Colby's memoirs constituted “authorized executive disclosure”
                    since he himself had been DCI. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>]
                    replied that only statements by a “sitting” DCI fell into this category.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] explained that insistence on
                    “authorized executive disclosure” was necessitated by the “Ellsberg syndrome,”
                    the feeling that some people had that they could steal classified documents and
                    claim First Amendment protection to have them published.</p>
                <p>Glennon said he understood the meaning of authorized executive disclosure as
                    described by [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] but he thought it
                    was largely legalistic hair-splitting. He state that “officiality” is attached
                    to Cline's, Lansdale's, and Colby's memoirs because of their former positions
                    and because they expressly indicate the books have been cleared with C.I.A. The
                    general view is that these memoirs constitute “official disclosure.” The same is
                    true with memoirs of Secretaries of State and of Ambassadors, like Allison in
                    Japan.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] replied, sticking to the legal
                    basis of his argument, that the CIA's position is that, with the President
                    excepted, “their disclosure is not our disclosure.”</p>
                <p>Mabon said that such a position makes the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series less comprehensive and authoritative than these other
                    publications.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] agreed, but said it was not
                    possible in a number of sensitive areas officially to reveal information.</p>
                <p>Glennon pointed out that some things were so well-known they were not sensitive.
                    PA/HO was concerned with broad policy, not with the nuts and bolts of
                    operations, the documents in dispute reflected this concern with policy.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said that upon reconsideration CIA
                    was prepared to withdraw certain objections. For example, it no longer objected
                    to the identification of Allen Dulles or Frank Wisner, but it did object to
                    identifying Lansdale. Their guiding principle was to protect CIA participation
                    in certain activities. At this point, [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] interpretation of the CIA charter seemed to go beyond a
                    strict adherence to the “sources and methods” language in the 1949 act to
                    include “locations and activities” of the CIA. He stated that, under the
                    charter, any document that confirms the CIA's presence in another country is not
                    legally subject to release by the CIA regardless of what other agencies or
                    individuals do with it.</p>
                <p>Allen supported [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] by saying that any
                    information that connotes CIA presence or operations in a foreign country cannot
                    be revealed. He cited the 1949 CIA act as prohibiting disclosure of the location
                    of CIA activities. Any reference to “CIA cables from country X,” or “information
                    received from the CIA representative in country X” would have to be deleted.</p>
                <p>Glennon raised the issue of the appearance of “CAS” in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FR</hi> series. He pointed out that the 1948 volume on Latin America
                    included CAS (controlled American source) in the list of abbreviations. If CIA
                    objected, however, to continued use of CAS, PA/HO was prepared to delete it and
                    bracket in “a source” or something similar. Glennon asked what the basis was for
                    CIA's objection to the use of “covert.”</p>
                <p>Allen replied there was no objection to “covert” <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>
                    but only to where it connoted CIA activities in a specific country.</p>
                <p>Landa said that C.I.A. activities and its presence in some countries, [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] were much more widely known than
                    many OSS operations from World War II. He asked why the “reasonable man”
                    approach could not be applied in these cases as well.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Paragraph not declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Reverting to the use of “CAS,” [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>]
                    pointed out that many individuals had incorrectly used “CAS” to refer to CIA
                    headquarters, and this error occasionally showed up in the documents. Moreover,
                    he recalled that the 1948 Latin America volume had not tied CAS to the CIA, but
                    had merely identified it as “Controlled American source.” Hence, this was not a
                    real disclosure. Besides, CIA was not bound to accept as precedent improper
                    disclosures made by other agencies. He cited the recent release, apparently
                    inadvertent, by the Department of State of the current acronym for CIA station
                    to Philip Agee, whom he labeled a defector to the Russians and the Cubans.</p>
                <p>Landa stated that CIA prohibitions on even revealing its presence in a given
                    country made it impossible in many cases for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series accurately and fairly to describe American policy.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said there had been one exception
                    to this rule. That involved Indochina during the period 1963-1975 with respect
                    to Americans missing-in-action. For legal reasons, it was necessary to
                    acknowledge which agency had obtained information on their whereabouts. He said
                    that this single exception opened the floodgates to requests for thousands of
                    documents and placed a great burden on C.I.A.</p>
                <p>Baehler asked how the “reasonable man” approach related to litigation.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said it was a fuzzy area, because
                    one reasonable man's judgment often differs from another.</p>
                <p>Glennon remarked that it seemed that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series documentation was being reviewed according to guidelines stricter than
                    those used in FOI cases and in clearing for publication memoirs of former CIA
                    officials. He wondered whether this was true, and whether it might be due to the
                    fact that PA/HO has no clout, that it cannot bring suit against the agency as a
                    private individual can.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said that in the past, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series was given a low priority because
                    there was no statutory provision and no machinery in CIA for reviewing it. He
                    said the CRD had recently assigned it number one priority.</p>
                <p>Glennon speculated on the possibility that it might be better to have CIA clear
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in the same way it does the
                    memoirs, i.e., with a “cold stare” that did not constitute “authorized executive
                    disclosure”</p>
                <p>Allen said that the burden of work and an inability by CRD and PA/HO to reach
                    agreement might make this course desirable, but he shuddered at the thought of
                    the kind of information that would thereby be revealed and the negative impact
                    it would have on our foreign relations.</p>
                <p>Landa pointed out that in any event desk officers in the Department of State, as
                    well as agencies besides CIA, have to clear the documentation and the concerns
                    are often similar to the C.I.A.'s.</p>
                <p>Allen proposed that attention be focused on the 13 documents in dispute and on a
                    CRD paper commenting further on those documents. [<hi rend="italic">Text not
                        declassified.</hi>] A document-by-document discussion ensued, with Allen and
                        [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] doing most of the talking for
                    CRD and Glennon and Mabon for PA/HO. During the discussion, [<hi rend="italic"
                        >name not declassified</hi>] said that in the pre-l959 period it was
                    difficult to locate CIA cable traffic, since the microfilm of serial files of
                    incoming and outgoing cables prior to that year had been destroyed. It was
                    impossible to provide, for example, all traffic from a given post for a certain
                    period. Specific telegrams, with some difficulty, might be found in a project
                    folder if one knew beforehand the subject of the telegram.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said they had serious objections
                    to the document that specified [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>.]
                    He asked whether these objections were shared by other clearing officials in the
                    government.</p>
                <p>Glennon replied that the same kinds of objections were encountered throughout the
                    clearance process and indicated that the Department had problems with those [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] documents.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said the crucial test was the
                    immediate impact of disclosure.</p>
                <p>Allen provided the example of a 1951 document he had recently seen about the
                    contingency [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>.] He said that this
                    document would be dynamite if it were released today.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said that many documents easily
                    lend themselves to distortion by journalists and disreputable people.</p>
                <p>Baehler said the advantage of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    was that it placed documentation in its proper context and discouraged
                    sensationalism and distortion. He said that for the FR series to remain silent
                    on certain issues that are already public knowledge will seriously damage its
                    credibility.</p>
                <p>Glennon quoted a retired historian in PA/HO who had once described the compiling
                    of the FR series as “transferring documents from one obscure place to another.”
                    Mabon emphasized that the FR volumes appeared very quietly.</p>
                <p>Landa said that release of information may cause momentary embarrassment to some
                    people, but we were not aware of any “identifiable damage to national security”
                    caused by the publication of the FR series.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said it was better not to run the
                    risk. Once the damage was done, it would be too late.</p>
                <p>Allen said that in cases of information provided by foreign governments, the
                    presumption under the new executive order was that release would be
                    damaging.</p>
                <p>Discussion resumed on the specific documents. Mabon said that deletion of names
                    from texts as proposed by CIA would distort meaning. [<hi rend="italic">Name not
                        declassified</hi>] replied that PA/HO would be allowed latitude in
                    bracketing in substitute words for deleted names to preserve accuracy. He said
                    they were not asking to “prostitute” the series.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Paragraph not declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Regarding this documentation, [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] said
                    it would be easier if PA/HO selected only the final approved paper, and not
                    previous drafts as well. Including drafts makes unnecessary work for the
                    reviewers.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said the ground rule as
                    established by his superior, the Deputy Director for Operations, was that
                    reference to CIA participation in a broad program was permissible, but the
                    specifics of the program were not. [<hi rend="italic">text not
                    declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] replied that such references were
                    too specific and inadmissable. References to CIA involvement in American efforts
                    to combat Communism worldwide would be all right.</p>
                <p>Allen demurred. He said he had seen a number of such documents on Italy and
                    France and, in his view, such general references fell within the Deputy
                    Director's guidelines for material that can be released. In short, Allen stated
                    and [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] seemed to agree that general
                    CIA activities in specific countries were subject to revelation, but that
                    specific CIA activities in specific countries were not. The final impression was
                    that this was a grey area, that the “reasonable man” approach would prevail
                    here, and that each instance would be decided on an ad hoc basis.</p>
                <p>Glennon made clear that discussion of these documents did not represent PA/HO's
                    acceptance of CRD's position. In fact, he stated there was still a long way to
                    go to reach agreement. He inquired what steps would be followed if agreement
                    were not reached.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] answered that there was still some
                    flexibility in CRD's position and that they were willing to continue discussion
                    on these documents. If, after further discussion, agreement cannot be reached,
                    CRD could transmit PA/HO's views to the Deputy Director for Operations for his
                    final review. A decision by him which was still unacceptable to PA/HO could be
                    appealed to the ISOO (Information Security Oversight Office).</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] concluded by saying the CRD
                    objections on the [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] compilation
                    left the reader with an “honest” picture, that the U.S. was intensely interested
                    in the elections and was in close touch with [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>] on the matter. Mabon demurred, noting that this is
                    nothing new and that documents do exist that would reveal new information if CIA
                    would let HO publish them.</p>
                <p>As an aside, Allen raised an objection regarding another kind of document, one in
                    which an ambassador offered a scathing indictment of a [<hi rend="italic">text
                        not declassified</hi>.] The issue was not the scathing nature of criticism,
                    but he wondered why that document was selected, why it was singled out for
                    special treatment. He thought the U.S. government should not display its
                    internal disagreements in public. But the primary objection he had to the
                    document was that it revealed the CIA's presence in that country.</p>
                <p>Mabon responded by saying that this document was not singled out for special
                    treatment and that PA/HO does not select documents on the basis of their
                    revelation of inter-agency bickering on minor issues. But where important
                    differences on policy matters existed, PA/HO feels an obligation to provide
                    documentation.</p>
                <p>Glennon said that the documents on [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]
                    in 1952 supplemented similar documents already in print in FR, 1951, VI.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said there was perhaps some more
                    flexibility in CIA's position on the question of CIA presence in a country than
                    they had so far suggested. Where the presence was not identifiable in a given
                    edifice, [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] they might find
                    references to the CIA acceptable.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] asked whether it was not possible
                    to substitute for certain troublesome documents less sensitive sources that
                    conveyed essentially the same information.</p>
                <p>Glennon answered that this could be done in some cases from other documents, from
                    memoirs or autobiographies, from documents released under FOI - but it was not
                    always possible.</p>
                <p>Landa asked [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] if he could give any
                    specific examples where CIA presence in a country might be acknowledged so long
                    as it did not place the CIA in a particular “edifice.”</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said that the Dominican Republic
                    in 1965 was one such case, because there was such a massive U.S. presence that
                    it could reasonably be assumed the CIA was providing information back to
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>Allen said that warlike conditions, like [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>] the Vietnam War, justify the CIA presence and therefore
                    make it easier to admit that presence.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said that problems arose where the
                    opposition was less definable. The overriding concern was not to allow enemies
                    of the United States to unravel intelligence operations. But CIA was also
                    concerned about the embarrassment which disclosure of certain information might
                    cause some governments. [<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified</hi>.]</p>
                <p>Glennon thanked the CIA representatives for their courtesy and for expressing
                    their views so frankly, but he emphasized that PA/HO differed sharply from those
                    views and that it seemed that we faced a long road before agreement might be
                    reached.</p>
                <p>Allen said that they were ready to discuss their position on SE Asian materials
                    at HO's convenience. They would then proceed to the Latin American and European
                    compilations, in that order.</p>
                <p>In retrospect, it appears that during the meeting [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] effectively cut the ground from under us on the issue of
                    whether the FR series is a legitimate vehicle for <hi rend="underline"
                        >initial</hi> executive disclosure for CIA materials by issuing his
                    hard-line opening statement identifying the single criterion for
                    declassification of FR documents as <hi rend="underline">prior</hi> executive
                    disclosure (as CIA defines it). In other words, we were precluded during the
                    session from discussing the question of using the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series as one of several forms of CIA executive disclosure of
                    new material on previously undisclosed subjects. Glennon alluded to the issue by
                    asking that FR material be treated as fairly as mandatory review material,
                    another form of executive disclosure which does not require prior official
                    acknowledgement of CIA involvement in order for release of documents to take
                    place. The CIA participants assiduously avoided discussing this apparent
                    contradiction in the treatment of the “executive disclosure” question.</p>
                <p>We were therefore confined to arguing on the relatively narrow grounds that
                    material already publicly but unofficially released was proper subject matter
                    for treatment in FR. We never addressed the larger issue of how to get the CIA
                    to recognize that the FR series should be a prime vehicle for the initial
                    disclosure of some of its secrets, just as is the release of documents under
                    FOI. And the reason we never addressed the question is that [<hi rend="italic"
                        >name not declassified</hi>] argued from the outset that the CIA charter
                    legally prevented him from making such decisions, although he did intimate that
                    decisions of this sort can come from the director of CIA, as in fact they have
                    in the case of the CIA presence in Vietnam in the 60s and 70s and as they do
                    repeatedly in FOI releases. The implication is that he -- [<hi rend="italic"
                        >name not declassified</hi>] -- is bound legally by the charter but that his
                    superiors -- or at least the DCI -- are authorized by the charter to make
                    exceptions on an <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> basis. Whether it can be done <hi
                        rend="underline">only</hi> on an ad hoc basis is an open question, but it
                    seems fair to ask whether HO and the State Department might consider approaching
                    the DCI for an across-the-board decision on material destined to be published in
                    FR, subject, of course, to the legal restrictions on revealing sources and
                    methods. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] never explicitly
                    recommended that we do so, but the implication was left from some of the other
                    things he said that this was an option we might pursue, however distasteful it
                    might be to the CIA. Some of those other things he said included the reference
                    to the fact that the DCI had already opened by executive disclosure knowledge of
                    the CIA presence in Vietnam in the 60s and 70s (albeit only for legal reasons
                    relating to MIAs); that in fact the CIA did want to take a “reasonable man”
                    approach to declassifying material that was no longer sensitive; and by his
                    admission that there was a wide grey area where reasonable people can disagree
                    on what is still sensitive and what is not. If he had seen the rule about prior
                    authorized executive disclosure, which he enunciated at the very first, as
                    absolutely fixed, there is no reason why he should have mentioned any of these
                    things, which were in some cases entirely unsolicited.</p>
                <p>A second impression left by [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] was
                    that the CIA was not about to venture into the area of judging the effect on
                    U.S. foreign relations of the release of a document and to use that judgment as
                    a criterion in reviewing a document. Allen and [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] wondered what the effect of the release of certain kinds
                    of information might be on our foreign relations, but [<hi rend="italic">name
                        not declassified</hi>] stuck strictly to the legal authority argument,
                    basing his position on the CIA charter.</p>
                <p>A third impression, related to the second, was that the CIA's interpretation of
                    its charter, which calls for protection of sources and methods, had been to
                    broaden it to include the concealment of locations and activities of the CIA. It
                    seemed that the legal argument used by [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] was being stretched to the breaking point in this
                    instance. The withholding of certain information about location and activities
                    may be argued on foreign relations grounds -- which is the State Department's
                    and not the CIA's bailiwick -- but probably not on legal grounds.</p>
                <p>The final impression was that [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] was
                    very much in charge and that he in turn had gotten his marching orders from the
                    Deputy Director for Operations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
