<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum of Conversation Among HO and CIA Officials, August
                    1979</title>
                <title type="short">HO-CIA Meeting, 1979</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1979-08-15">August 15, 1979</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1979-08-15-ho-meeting-with-cia.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 272 KB, 6pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD-08D-4: Bureau of Public Affairs, Assistant Secretary and Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary Subject Files, 1975-1981 (82 D 297), Box 6, The Historian’s
                    Office 1979. Drafted by David Baehler and Paul Claussen, September 7, 1979. An
                    unknown hand, presumably Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
                    William Blair, underlined passages in the text. For these annotations, refer to
                    the scanned copy of this document.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn18">Footnotes 18</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn82">82</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum of Conversation Among HO and CIA Officials</head>
                <dateline>August 15, 1979</dateline>
                <p>On August 15, representatives of the Central Intelligence Agency's
                    declassification operation and the Office of the Historian (PA/HO) met to
                    discuss problems of clearance and access for the series <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS). Present from HO were
                    David Trask, Bill Slany, Paul Claussen, and David Baehler. The following were
                    present from CIA:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] Information Review Officer
                        in the Directorate for Operations (DDO).</item>
                    <item>Gale Allen, Chief, Classification Review Division (CRD), Information
                        Systems Staff, Directorate for Administration.</item>
                    <item>Jack Pfeiffer, CIA Historian</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for National
                        Foreign Assessment Center, CRD.</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for
                        Directorate of Administration, CRD.</item>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for
                        Directorate of Operations, CRD.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The last three are each subordinates of Allen. [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] Chief, Branch for Directorate of Science and Technology,
                    CRD, was not present.</p>
                <p>Allen opened the discussion by indicating the CRD's role in the declassification
                    operation of the CIA. It is the equivalent of the Systematic Review Staff of the
                    Department's Classification/Declassification Center. The major difference is
                    that it reviews at the 20-year line all of CIA's documents, not just a sample.
                    It also reviews all FRUS material sent to the Agency for review. FRUS galleys
                    and manuscript sent to CIA receive priority attention, as reflected in the
                    recent fast turn-around time.</p>
                <p>After the CRD completes its review of each FRUS compilation, it sends it to [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] group in the Directorate for
                    Operations. In response to a question, Allen indicated that the DDO was the only
                    directorate of the four to which FRUS material was automatically referred for
                    follow-up review, because the DDO was the area of greatest sensitivity. Material
                    was referred to the other directorates only if it was sensitive to those areas.
                    It was revealed later that 80 or 90 percent of CIA's mandatory review requests
                    fell within areas covered by the DDO, and the declassification operation there
                    was consequently much more developed than in any other directorate. To review
                    FRUS material, the CRD was using consultants or contractors who were familiar
                    with a specific area by virtue of having served in the field. They were brought
                    on board as needed either for FRUS or for systematic review assignments.</p>
                <p>Allen broached the issue of substantive clearance, admitting that there was a lot
                    of room for disagreement on the decisions taken. Even within the CRD, any two
                    analysts might disagree on declassifying the same document, different copies of
                    which turn up in separate collections. If could happen within CIA, it stood to
                    reason that CIA and HO might disagree on decisions. Trask briefly outlined HO's
                    new procedure for submitting FRUS material for review under E.O. 12065, noting
                    that it was pointless for HO to submit material that was not going to be
                    cleared. There would, however, be cases where HO felt material should be
                    declassified and CIA did not.</p>
                <p>Allen then discussed the criteria by which CIA reviewed FRUS material. It was
                    hard to be one hundred percent certain at any given time about what material was
                    in the public domain. The range was great, from the recently published report on
                    assassinations, to the Pentagon Papers, to information that had been
                    specifically cleared by CIA's Publication Review Board. Allen volunteered that
                    he could arrange meetings between his analysts in a given area and the
                    appropriate Department of State historians. If HO could show that knowledge of
                    an incident or policy had already been revealed by “executive disclosure” (i.e.,
                    officially divulged), CIA would consider approving it for publication. In
                    response to a question by Slany, [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>]
                    stated that this excluded memoirs written by foreign government figures after
                    they left office. Otherwise, manuscripts and publications approved by CIA's
                    Publication Review Board constituted a second category of executive disclosure.
                    If any given information has already been cleared by the Board, it will be
                    approved for publication in FRUS. CIA's problem is that prior to 1977 there were
                    no good records of what was officially approved and what was not. CIA has a
                    bibliography of all manuscripts officially approved since the beginning of
                    1977.</p>
                <p>A third category of executive disclosure is the release of documents through
                    mandatory review. Slany asked whether the CIA had a method of keeping track of
                    the documents that have been declassified in this way. [<hi rend="italic">name
                        not declassified</hi>] answered that the DDO has a computer that indexes all
                    of the documents retrieved for purposes of replying to FOI requests arriving in
                    that directorate. In addition, the Information and Privacy Staff, which is the
                    mandatory review counterpart to CRD, indexes everything requested of the entire
                    agency. Allen did not recommend that HO make use of the computerized system
                    because the record was not as complete as it could be and the information might
                    not be retrievable in a form that HO could use. Trask pointed out that this body
                    of computer-stored information could itself be considered an official record,
                    reviewable after 20 years.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] stated that if the Department of
                    State were to make a revelation concerning an incident or policy related to
                    CIA's Directorate of Operations, the DDO would not feel obliged to confirm that
                    disclosure. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] felt particularly
                    conscious of the statutory obligation to protect intelligence sources and
                    methods because CIA was constantly faced with litigation. CIA based its actions
                    on section 6 of the Central Intelligence Agency Act of 1949, which includes
                    language obliging the Director of Central Intelligence to protect sources and
                    methods from unauthorized disclosure. [<hi rend="italic">Name not
                        declassified</hi>] acknowledged that in some cases CIA was dealing with
                    personalities rather than certainties, so contact between HO compilers and CIA
                    reviewers would be useful. In response to a question by Trask, Allen indicated
                    that he was prepared to facilitate such contact, beginning with the FRUS volumes
                    for 1952-1954 on which there were differences of view mentioned in Trask's
                    letter of July 23.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by Baehler, [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] acknowledged that ClA considered FRUS to be the maximum
                    form of executive disclosure. Because of this, the Agency was very careful about
                    each clause, sentence, or document that it cleared for publication. The CIA knew
                    that the Soviets would scrutinize each new FRUS volume, as would the British and
                    the French. He emphasized that there was no going back once publication had
                    occurred, so CIA reviewers must be cautious beforehand.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] distinguished between review of
                    various types of material. NIE's and SNIE's, for example, did not often present
                    a clearance problem. [<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified.</hi>] Slany asked
                        [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] whether there were guidelines
                    by which decisions on these various categories of material were made, pointing
                    out that because HO had not had access to the greater body of material, its
                    historians did not know what categories of material might lie beyond in the area
                    of covert operations. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] responded
                    that the guidelines were established initially in his [<hi rend="italic">text
                        not declassified</hi>] head, and then discussed. The inference was that
                    nothing has yet been written by way of guidelines. In response to a question by
                    Trask, [<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] indicated that CIA had
                    supplied the National Archives with agency guidelines for systematic review, to
                    be applied to material found in the files of other agencies.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] stated that in cases where CIA was
                    involved, the Agency might have to extend classification beyond 20 years because
                    of the sensitivity of an issue. He cited Stephen Kane's compilation on Guatemala
                    for 1952-1954 as an example. CIA would have to resist the publication of
                    anything more than the basic fact that the Agency participated in the overthrow
                    of the Arbenz regime. It could not allow publication of details concerning how
                    it was done, what incidents were involved, or what sources or methods were used,
                    even though Kane was being granted access to documentation on matters. Trask
                    indicated that HO was not interested in publishing details concerning the
                    mechanics of operations. But were policy issues -- for example, whether or not
                    the Ambassador was fully cognizant of the operation and whether or not he was
                    part of its planning -- also excluded under [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified</hi>] criteria?</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] said CIA would defer to the
                    Department of State on the foreign relations aspects of an issue. If the
                    Department, taking into consideration relations with a given country today,
                    determined that no foreign relations problem was involved, such information
                    could be published. Trask asked if it was the sensitivity of an operation that
                    was really issue. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] then returned
                    to the wording of E.O. 12065: would its release contribute to “identifiable
                    damage” to the national security? That was the key phrase, he said, not
                    sensitivity. He then reiterated that CIA would defer to the Department on the
                    foreign policy aspects of an issue. Asked about CIA's justification for
                    withholding material beyond 20 years, [<hi rend="italic">name not
                        declassified</hi>] mentioned the 30-year rule for foreign government
                    information, CIA's statutory mandate for protecting sources and methods, and
                    problems of forgery of internal CIA documents by unfriendly governments if the
                    format of a CIA document was revealed.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] volunteered that the FRUS
                    editorial note was a useful device for maintaining the integrity of the series
                    by acknowledging CIA's presence in a given country while at the same time
                    avoiding detailed coverage of CIA activities in any given operation. Most
                    friendly foreign governments would recognize the validity of this sort of
                    treatment. Slany pointed out that in order to prepare editorial notes, the
                    Department's historians would need access to CIA documents. The possibility of a
                    partnership existed in which FRUS could perform a useful service. There was some
                    general discussion of the access question. [<hi rend="italic">Name not
                        declassified</hi>] noted that HO had recently gained access to various
                    documents through Pfeiffer's office. Access to documents originated by the DDO
                    area was at the discretion of individual area division chiefs, some of whom
                    might be reluctant to hand over material. Trask noted that HO understood that
                    its channel for access after Pfeiffer's operation ceased at the end of 1979 was
                    to be the Center for the Study of Intelligence. Allen [<hi rend="italic">text
                        not declassified</hi>] explained that the Center was a unit of CIA's Office
                    of Training, under the Directorate of Administration, to which fellows were
                    assigned for 9 or 12 months' study. The Center also has a permanent staff. There
                    was some discussion of why the Center might have been designated to service HO's
                    needs.</p>
                <p>Claussen noted that in CIA's review of FRUS material during the past year there
                    were some inconsistencies, oversights, and possible inaccuracies in what was
                    recommended for deletion, both within and between volumes. It would therefore be
                    highly desirable for FRUS compilers to meet with appropriate CIA
                    declassification analysts to discuss the four volumes cited in HO's letter of
                    July 23, as well as other volumes now outstanding. He pointed out that the
                    charter under which FRUS is prepared requires that there be no alteration of the
                    texts of documents and no deletions without an indication of where in the text
                    deletions are made. The obligatory indication of ellipsis or bracketed notations
                    might in some cases suggest to readers familiar with other published accounts of
                    a given event that more sinister actions were undertaken than was actually the
                    case, or that more had been deleted from a given document than was actually
                    removed.</p>
                <p>Allen once again suggested meetings between FRUS compilers and his
                    declassification analysts to talk about specific instances of disagreement on
                    declassification actions. [<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>]
                    applauded and encouraged liaison for the sake of omitting “inconsistencies,
                    oversights, and inaccuracies.” He said that some CIA officers, when faced with a
                    declassification decision, did not have all the necessary information, and would
                    therefore welcome consultation with HO specialists. Allen proposed that the
                    meetings be held informally, but that the conclusions reached be documented. It
                    was agreed that Baehler and Allen would arrange appointments. Volumes for
                    1952-1954 on Latin America and Indochina would probably be the first two to be
                    considered.</p>
                <p>Trask observed that from HO's point of view there were three categories of
                    material: first, that which was clearly not releasable; second, that which was
                    clearly releasable; and third, that about which HO was unsure. This third would
                    be the subject of discussion. HO could be more helpful if it knew the
                    appropriate guidelines.</p>
                <p>Baehler briefly described the new declassification system within the Department
                    of State and pointed out that in the future CIA would receive the documents the
                    Department wished to publish in raw, unedited photocopy form. [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Name not declassified</hi>] expressed concern about whether or not HO could
                    always recognize CIA matters contained in State Department documents. Claussen
                    pointed out that such matters would be identified by experienced officers on the
                    Department's central declassification staff.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Name not declassified</hi>] asked whether HO had approached
                    the National Security Council on access to and declassification of the sort of
                    material HO sought from the CIA. He said that on questions of policy concerning
                    covert activities, CIA was really only an executive secretariat to the NSC in
                    the later 1950s and 1960s. NSC had a more important role than the CIA, and HO
                    would do well to get into the NSC files if it wanted to publish the documents on
                    intelligence operations of greatest historical interest.</p>
                <p>Trask emphasized in conclusion that HO wanted to be sure that it had done
                    everything possible to put in the published record what was appropriate. At the
                    same time, he was sure that it had been made clear during this exchange of views
                    that HO intended to act responsibly.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
