<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From Thomas White to David Trask, July 1980</title>
                <title type="short">White to Trask, 1980</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-22">January 22, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1980-07-28">July 28, 1980</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1980-07-28-white-to-trask.pdf">PDF</ref>, 176 KB, 3pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Administration, Office of
                    Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification, Historical Documents Review
                    Office Record Files, 1950-1993 (Lot File 95 D 113), Box 1, CIA General. This
                    copy bears a stamped signature for Thomas H. White. A copy of the letter was
                    also sent to [name not declassified].</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn17">Footnote 17</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From Thomas H. White (Chief of the Information Services Staff at the
                    Central Intelligence Agency) to David F. Trask (Director of the Historian’s
                    Office)</head>
                <dateline>July 28, 1980</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Trask:</p>
                <p>This is in response to your letter of 6 February 1980 to Mr. Gale Allen
                    concerning our policies with respect to classification decisions made on
                    material requested for publication in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</hi> (FRUS) series. I apologize for the delay in
                    responding but I hasten to point out that it is incumbent upon all of us to
                    insure the full exploration of matters such as these before making decisions the
                    effect of which might have long lasting and unforeseen repercussions. Thus, you
                    can be assured that this response is being made only after lengthy, in-depth
                    discussions here at CIA.</p>
                <p>I also want to assure you that we consider the FRUS series extremely important
                    and have and will cooperate with the Department of State in its publication to
                    the fullest extent possible consistent with the responsibilities to protect
                    intelligence sources, methods and activities levied upon the Director of Central
                    Intelligence by statute, Executive order and other directives.</p>
                <p>At the outset, I want to state that in order to be able to freely contribute to
                    FRUS, all final decisions with respect to the declassification or the continued
                    classification of information concerning CIA and its activities, whether
                    contained in CIA originated documents or documents of other Government
                    department and agencies, must be made by officials of this Agency who have been
                    delegated such authority by the Director of Central Intelligence. The
                    intelligence business is unique and such decisions can only be made, if we are
                    to avoid damage to national security, by persons fully knowledgeable of all
                    relevant facts in any given instance. We will of course be willing to discuss
                    the reasoning behind any of our decisions which you are not happy with, but the
                    final decision must be based on what we feel is necessary to fulfill our
                    responsibilities. This rationale is recognized in law and especially throughout
                    Executive Order 12065, particularly Section 3 thereof. Your [<hi rend="italic"
                        >text not declassified</hi>].</p>
                <p>Having said the above, I want now to state our views regarding the points you
                    raise in your letter. We are aware of the mandated role of the FRUS and its
                    importance as the official history of United States foreign policy. It is this
                    role however which causes us particular concern since anything appearing in the
                    FRUS is official Executive disclosure of United States Government information.
                    As such, it leaves no doubt as to its veracity. Hence, we must be extremely
                    careful that information regarding CIA appearing therein not be such as to
                    damage the national security of the United States. As pointed out in your
                    letter, information may become desensitized with the passage of time. While that
                    proposition may often be valid, it is much less so in the case of information
                    concerning intelligence agencies and their activities. Individuals may serve as
                    intelligence sources for many years. They have the right to expect that their
                    clandestine relationship with the United States Government will not redound
                    against them or their families. The period of potential repercussion will
                    normally last many years beyond their active association with the intelligence
                    process. The premature release of information regarding intelligence sources
                    creates the impression that such sources will not be protected and deters others
                    from serving in an intelligence capacity. Indeed, changes in the world situation
                    over time may in fact increase the degree of damage which could be done even
                    when all of the actors have long since departed the scene.</p>
                <p>We cannot accept your position that <hi rend="underline">any</hi> information
                    already in the public domain has lost its sensitivity and that its omission from
                    the series would weaken the credibility thereof. Such matters must be explored
                    on a case-by-case basis. However, unless information in the public domain has
                    been placed there through official release, as a general rule we will not permit
                    its re-release based on that principle alone. To do so would be to recognize the
                    validity of everything that has been published regarding the intelligence
                    process over the years whether right or wrong, sensitive or not, and we simply
                    cannot take this position.</p>
                <p>Finally, with respect to your penultimate paragraph, we cannot accept your
                    interpretation of the meaning of “intelligence sources and methods.” Your
                    statement that the location of Agency facilities, general Agency activities,
                    foreign liaison relationships and intelligence reports are not included under
                    the term “intelligence sources and methods” is so narrow that were it true we
                    would be unable under our charter to protect a vast area that is vital to our
                    objectives and without which we would be rendered useless to a great extent.
                    Even if we could accept your interpretation, the final sentence of that
                    paragraph sets forth additional reasons which would justify the withholding of
                    the kind of information mentioned in the paragraph. And the decision as to
                    whether identifiable damage may result from any particular release can only be
                    made by officers of this Agency authorized to do so based on knowledge of the
                    damage that would occur as a result of such release.</p>
                <p>I will be happy to discuss this matter with you further. If you so desire, let me
                    know and I will arrange to meet with you at your convenience.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,<lb/>Thomas H. White</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
