<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From David Trask to Gale Allen, February 1980</title>
                <title type="short">Trask to Allen, 1980</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-22">January 22, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1980-02-06">February 6, 1980</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1980-02-06-trask-to-allen.pdf">PDF</ref>, 165 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Administration, Office of
                    Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification, Historical Documents Review
                    Office Record Files, 1950-1993 (Lot File 95 D 113), Box 1, CIA General. An
                    unknown hand wrote comments in the margins and underlined passages in the text.
                    For these annotations, refer to the scanned copy of this document.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn17">Footnote 17</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From David F. Trask (Director of the Historian’s Office) to Gale W.
                    Allen (Chief of the Classification Review Division at the Central Intelligence
                    Agency)</head>
                <dateline>February 6, 1980</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Allen:</p>
                <p>We appreciate the opportunity some of our historians had last fall to discuss
                    with you and your colleagues certain specific questions relating to
                    declassification of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> manuscripts.
                    Specifically, your careful reconsideration of the documents selected for
                    publication in volume XII, 1952-54, has been helpful to us, and we welcome your
                    adherence to the rule of reason in surveying the material we have submitted for
                    declassification review.</p>
                <p>We are anxious to insure that our efforts to declassify material for the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series comports with the general spirit
                    of “openness” reflected in E.O. 12065. Still troubling us are several points
                    arising from our discussions and from your letter of October 28 presenting the
                    rationale for your review of documents selected for publication in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>1. The legal role of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in
                    executive disclosure of material containing CIA equities is of key importance.
                    Mandates issued over the years make clear that the series is a prime vehicle for
                    initial disclosure of information on foreign policy. In 1972 President Nixon
                    stated that the publication provided “an indispensable perspective on our
                    Nation’s history.” He instructed the Secretary of Defense, the Director of
                    Central Intelligence, and the Assistant to the President for National Security
                    Affairs “to cooperate fully in collecting and declassifying the appropriate
                    materials to the maximum extent consistent with the requirements of national
                    security.” The Congress has repeatedly recognized the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series as the official record of US foreign policy, most
                    recently in the course of the hearings on the Foreign Assistance Authorization
                    Act of 1979. ISOO Directive No. 1 confirmed the executive mandate expressed by
                    President Nixon in 1972. It also instructed all agency heads to help the editors
                    of the series meet their mandated goal of publishing twenty years after the
                    event by facilitating access to classified material and expediting
                    declassification of selected items. Accordingly, the legal bases of the series
                    require us, subject to the needs of national security, to publish the material
                    adjudged important regardless of whether it has been previously disclosed. We
                    would be in violation of our mandates if we limited ourselves only to
                    publication of material on US foreign policy that has already been released
                    through “prior authorized executive disclosure.” Furthermore, we are unable to
                    locate in law any countervailing authority for applying as a standard for
                    declassification the criterion of “prior authorized executive disclosure.” The
                    only legal standards applicable to CIA’s review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> documentation are the “identifiable damage” criterion in E.O.
                    12065, Section 6 of the 1949 CIA Act, pertaining specifically to “intelligence
                    sources and methods,” and E.O. 12036, which speaks of “intelligence sources,
                    methods, and analytical procedures.”</p>
                <p>2. Retention of classification at the point of systematic review under E.O. 12065
                    is discretionary. The “identifiable damage” criterion, as you acknowledged in
                    your letter of October 28, is one that the State Department desks apply
                    carefully in reviewing the same material. The key issue is whether, despite the
                    passage of time, the information, if released, would cause identifiable damage
                    to US foreign policy. Even then, the balancing test may be applied in some cases
                    to decide whether the damage would outweigh the public’s right to the
                    information. [<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified</hi>] must be adjudged
                    detrimental to the national interest at present in order for these materials to
                    remain classifiable. Publication of the material would reveal only that the CIA
                        <hi rend="underline">had</hi> a station there and carried out activities
                    there 26 years ago. They say nothing, nor could they say anything, about whether
                    the CIA <hi rend="underline">has</hi> a station there at present. The
                    distinctions between whether the CIA “has or had a station in the country” and
                    whether it “has or had an intelligence liaison relationship” are fundamentally
                    important. Certainly if a true source or method is likely to be unveiled as a
                    result of publishing anything from that period, we will be responsive to CIA’s
                    request fr excision. But if publication raises in the mind of the reviewer the
                    possibility of “identifiable damage” to US foreign relations, as interpreted
                    under the discretionary provisions of E.O. 12065, we are obligated to weigh
                    carefully arguments in favor of release against those favoring retention. This
                    rule holds true in all cases, but it is particularly true when the State
                    Department recommends release and the CIA recommends withholding. In the
                    particular case specified in volume XIII (CHI 62-63) and in numerous other
                    similar cases, the State Department judged that no identifiable damage to US
                    foreign relations would result from release of the material.</p>
                <p>3. Apart from the legal strictures governing the content of the series, which
                    require us to compile as complete a record as possible and to examine rigorously
                    recommendations for excision against national security criteria, we have other
                    compelling reasons for including the broadest scope of documentation in the
                    publication.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>a. In the first place, the series, which has been published continuously
                        for 128 years, is widely recognized as the most authoritative documentary
                        publication of its kind on foreign policy issues. To omit significant
                        categories of foreign relations material from it would compromise its
                        authoritative character.</item>
                    <item>b. Secondly, failure to publish material concerning information already in
                        the public domain -- as is very often the case with documents a quarter of a
                        century old -- weakens the credibility of the series. By direct inference,
                        it also weakens the credibility of the agency responsible for withholding
                        that information. The presentation of evidence by this office to show that
                        certain information is already in the public domain is therefore not
                        intended to establish “authorized executive disclosure,” but rather to
                        pinpoint areas in which the credibility of both the series and the
                        responsible agency would be damaged by further withholding of the
                        documentation.</item>
                    <item>c. The publication represents the last chance that the US government has
                        to reveal publicly the record of it foreign policy in its full context.
                        Documentation released out of context, even a few years later either through
                        Freedom of Information procedures or at the National Archives, if far more
                        susceptible to sensationalist treatment in the press or elsewhere than is
                        documentation released in its proper setting. The history of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series proves the point.</item>
                    <item>d. Finally, publication at a remove of 25 or 30 years normally assures
                        that the information presented has become desensitized. As E.O. 12065
                        recognizes, the passage of time can be fundamental to determining whether
                        identifiable damage to US foreign relations can occur. [<hi rend="italic"
                            >Text not declassified</hi>] illustrates the point, although the recent
                        publication of this information only reiterates disclosures made eight years
                        ago. Because many of the historical actors are still on the political scene,
                        events of 1971 are very likely to remain sensitive today. Events dating from
                        1954 or earlier are likely to be desensitized because most or all of the
                        actors have departed the scene.</item>
                </list>
                <p>4. Although we fully recognize the statutory obligation of the CIA to protect
                    “intelligence sources and methods” the Charter of 1949 does not protect
                    locations, general agency activities not disclosing methods, foreign liaison, or
                    appraisals of situations. The legislative intent was not to inflate the
                    definition of the term “sources and methods” beyond its normal meaning. In
                    enacting the statutory authority the legislature referred only to protecting
                    “intelligence sources and methods” and the “organization, functions, names,
                    official titles, salaries, or numbers of personnel employed by the Agency.” The
                    former phrase refers explicitly only to sources and methods; the latter only to
                    human sources. Information concerning other intelligence-related matters such as
                    locations, activities, liaison, and appraisals can only be withheld under the
                    “identifiable damage” criterion embodied in E.O. 12065.</p>
                <p>I hope that these comments clarify our position. We request an opportunity to
                    discuss the foregoing points further at your convenience.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,<lb/>David F. Trask</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
