<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From David Trask to the Historical Advisory
                    Committee, January 1980</title>
                <title type="short">Trask to HAC, 1980</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-05">May 5, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1980-01-16">January 16, 1980</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1980-01-16-hac-meeting-1979.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 134 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the
                    Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 3, 1979-Report. A draft of the minutes of the
                    1979 HAC meeting, with extensive corrections and annotations, is present in the
                    1979-Minutes folder (in this box). No final version of these minutes has been
                    found.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From David F. Trask (Director of the Historian’s Office) to the
                    Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation</head>
                <dateline>January 16, 1980</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation, November 8-9, 1979</p>
                <p>The Executive Secretary, Dr. David F. Trask, called the meeting to order at 1:15
                    p.m. on November 8. Sessions were held that afternoon and at 9:00 a.m. on
                    November 9. Committee members present were:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Alona E. Evans, Wellesley College</item>
                    <item>Dr. Alexander L. George, Stanford University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Norman A. Graebner, University of Virginia (2:15 p.m.)</item>
                    <item>Dr. Harold K. Jacobson, University of Michigan</item>
                    <item>Dr. Arnold H. Taylor, Howard University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Betty M. Unterberger, Texas A&amp;M University</item>
                    <item>Mr. John R. Stevenson, New York City (9:00 a.m., 9 November)</item>
                </list>
                <p>Drs. Trask, William Z. Slany, and Arthur G. Kogan represented HO, and Mr. William
                    P. Blair, Jr., represented PA. Numerous staff members of HO attended the
                    sessions. Certain members of the general public attended the Thursday session,
                    but the Friday session was closed to the public.</p>
                <p>There follow comments on the various subjects discussed during the first session
                    (open) and the second session (closed).</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">FIRST SESSION</hi> (1:15-4:00 p.m.)</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="underline">Output of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi></hi>. It was
                    announced that only two volumes had been published during the fiscal year. It is
                    anticipated that at least four will appear during the next twelve months. The
                    staff hopes that seven will be published, with ten the maximum number possible.
                    The pace of publication depends principally on the outcome of efforts to
                    complete declassification actions. Declassification was discussed in depth
                    during the second session of the committee and is summarized below.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="underline">Pagination for the triennium 1958-1960</hi>. It has been
                    decided to prepare a triennial set of 16 volumes for 1958-1960 consisting of
                    28,000 pages. This size compares favorably with the average pagination per
                    triennium of volumes treating the period since the Second World War.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="underline">Word processing</hi>. For some years HO has experimented
                    with in-house word processing to prepare nine-track tapes capable of running
                    printing machinery at the Government Printing Office. This enterprise has
                    established the feasibility of in-house activity. The Office has recently
                    installed a Xerox VT 3 text-editing system that clearly meets requirements. HO
                    still has not gotten into full production because of personnel losses in its
                    support staff. When these losses are replaced, the Office foresees no difficulty
                    producing the necessary materials on time. In the meantime contracts are being
                    let to test the feasibility of contracting word processing and typesetting to
                    outside firms. Two areas of difficulty exist. Can the Department locate firms
                    with personnel cleared at the necessary security level? Can outside firms reduce
                    the cost to the level attained in-house?</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="underline">Microform supplements</hi>. Final feasibility tests are
                    now being arranged with outside contractors. In response to inquiries from
                    committee members it was stated that the work associated with preparation of
                    such supplements would be minimal. Most of its work is already planned in
                    connection with preparation of materials to be examined by the
                    Classification/Declassification Center. Projected feasibility tests will map
                    optimal procedures for relating microform to printed volumes. The cost would
                    also be minimal, probably at the most rising to no more than one-tenth the cost
                    of the printed edition.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="underline">Classification/Declassification Center</hi> (CDC). The
                    Department has now centralized the process of conducting mandatory review and
                    systematic declassification review of its records. HO is cooperating to the
                    fullest extent possible with the Center during its early development. HO’s
                    ability to release published volumes will depend on the extent to which the CDC
                    is able to maintain a schedule of work that should allow it to attain a
                    twenty-year line in systematic declassification review by the middle of the new
                    decade.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="underline">Lot Files</hi>. HO made it clear that it sustains a
                    lively continuing interest in insuring the retention of permanently valuable lot
                    files, although the responsibility for the files lies with the Foreign Affairs
                    Document and Record Center (FADRC).</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="underline">Russian project</hi>. The work of preparing the
                    manuscript of the joint Soviet-American documentary collection treating the
                    period 1765-1815 is now essentially complete. There remains the task of seeing
                    the volume through the press, aiming at simultaneous publication of both the
                    Russian and the English volumes during the summer of 1980.</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="underline">Reorganization</hi>. The Office of the Historian was
                    recently reorganized in response to recommendations of the team of inspectors
                    that looked at the Office of the Historian as part of a regular inspection of
                    the Bureau of Public Affairs. This reorganization eliminated the Operations
                    Staff, created a general editor for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, added a third
                    geographic division, and centralized responsibility for declassification and
                    research at the level of the office director. This reorganization should be
                    helpful in improving the productivity of the Office.</p>
                <p>9. <hi rend="underline">Acceleration of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi></hi>. The
                    Office remains committed to attainment of a twenty-year line in publication. We
                    hope to approach a twenty-year line in <hi rend="underline">compilation</hi> in
                    the near future. The work of the Classification/Declassification Center is now
                    scheduled to permit attainment of a twenty-year line in <hi rend="underline"
                        >publication</hi> by the mid-1980s. If budgetary support is maintained at
                    the same level and systematic declassification review kept on schedule, the
                    program of acceleration can succeed. The series must now take into consideration
                    a great deal of other-agency material, but delays caused by the complexities of
                    the modern series can be counteracted by improved productivity in HO.</p>
                <p>10. <hi rend="underline">Usership survey</hi>. To develop accurate information
                    concerning the perceptions, interests, and desires of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> readership, the Office is preparing a questionnaire intended as a
                    survey instrument among users.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">SECOND SESSION</hi> (9:00 a.m.-12:15 p.m.)</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="underline">Budget matters</hi>. It was explained that HO’s budget
                    had remained generally constant in real dollars for some years and that planning
                    was based on the assumption that resources would remain generally constant for
                    the foreseeable future. Therefore, to improve the quantity and quality of output
                    HO would have to emphasize productivity gains. In response to inquiries from
                    members of the Committee, HO indicated that it had maintained a reasonable
                    output. It planned to complete compilation of the triennial set for 1955-1957
                    during the coming year (1980) and complete the set for 1958-1960 early in 1981.
                    HO’s belief that it could achieve an average of about two years of work for each
                    triennial set was based on the presumption that modernization of procedures
                    would result in enhanced efficiency. One problem was whether the Department
                    would maintain effective centralized services. HO is dependent on such services
                    in many areas, notably contracting, records management, declassification,
                    personnel, equipment procurement, and editing.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="underline">Declassification</hi>. The Office must contend with two
                    related problems. How could it obtain <hi rend="underline">expeditious</hi>
                    responses to requests for declassification from the Department and from other
                    agencies? How could it obtain <hi rend="underline">favorable</hi> responses?
                    Members of HO explained the process to be followed in appealing negative
                    decisions. In response to inquiries from members of the Committee, explanations
                    were given concerning (a) appellate jurisdictions in the event of negative
                    decisions; (b) guidelines for decisions concerning declassification; (c)
                    unofficial disclosures as basis for official declassification; (d) expedients to
                    be adopted in the event of unsuccessful denials, e .g., summaries and
                    disclaimers; (e) possibility of preparing “sweeper” volumes to include material
                    declassified after publication of the volume for which it was originally
                    selected.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="underline">Chairman for 1980</hi>. The Advisory Committee elected
                    Dr. Graebner as its chairperson for the coming year.</p>
                <p rend="underline">OTHER ACTIVITY</p>
                <p>The Committee attended a luncheon in the Department of State for which Mrs. Lucy
                    Wilson Benson, the Under Secretary for Security Assistance, Science and
                    Technology, served as hostess.</p>
                <p>The Committee met by itself during the afternoon of November 9 to discuss the
                    contents of its annual report.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
