<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1980</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1980</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1980-11-13">November 13, 1980</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1980-11-13-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 1.2 MB, 25pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, 1981—Minutes, Report.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn62">Footnote 62</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1980 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on
                    Historical Diplomatic Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 13-14, 1980</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Gary R. Hess, Professor of History, Bowling Green State
                        University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Arnold H. Taylor, Professor of History, Howard University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Betty Miller Unterberger, Professor of History, Texas A &amp; M
                        University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Alexander L. George, Professor of Political Science, Stanford
                        University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Enid Curtis Bok Schoettle, The Ford Foundation</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Seymour J. Rubin, Executive Vice President and Executive Director, The
                        American Society of International Law</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William J. Dyess, Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>Francis T. McNamara, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>Frank Gomez, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs</item>
                    <item>Leon Ramey, Director, Executive Office</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>David F. Trask, The Historian (Executive Secretary of the Advisory
                        Committee)</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Deputy Historian and General Editor</item>
                    <item>Arthur Kogan</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Nina Noring</item>
                    <item>William Sanford</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Madeline Chi</item>
                    <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Kay Herring</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Robert J. McMahon</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>Nina Neve</item>
                    <item>David Patterson</item>
                    <item>Delia Pitts</item>
                    <item>Carl N. Raether</item>
                    <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Classification/Declassification Center:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Clayton McManaway, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State</item>
                    <item>Laurence Pickering, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs and Information and Management Center:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Price, Director</item>
                    <item>Paul M. Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division</item>
                    <item>John Ellsworth, Chief, General Editing Branch</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker, Deputy Chief, Foreign Relations Editing Section</item>
                </list>
                <p>The National Archives and Records Service:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief Diplomatic Branch</item>
                </list>
                <p>Department of State press re1ease No. 277, October 6,·1980, provided for open and
                    closed portions of the meeting. The following persons from the general public
                    attended the open portion of the meeting: Professor Wayne S. Cole, University of
                    Maryland, Professor George O. Kent, University of Maryland.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">First Session (November 13, 1980; 1-4
                        p.m.)<lb/>Room 1207, Department of State<lb/>Opening the Meeting</hi></p>
                <p>The Executive Secretary, <hi rend="underline">David F. Trask</hi>, called the
                    meeting to order at 1 p.m. on November 13. He Introduced <hi rend="underline"
                        >William J. Dyess, Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs</hi>, who
                    extended his greetings to the Advisory Committee. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Dyess</hi> emphasized how much the Department valued the historical
                    documentary record. He welcomed the Committee's advice and comments for
                    improving the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He viewed the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series as a vital nonpartisan task in
                    understanding foreign policy successes and mistakes of the past and favored the
                    opening up of records as rapidly as possible. Assistant Secretary Dyess also
                    noted the “security constraints” under which the Department of State operated in
                    releasing documents. He looked forward to talking to the Committee again the
                    next day.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> then introduced <hi rend="underline">Francis
                        T. McNamara</hi>, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs,
                    who had 'special responsibility for the Office of the Historian. He also
                    introduced the new members of the Advisory Committee, <hi rend="underline">Enid
                        Curtis Bok Schoettle</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Gary R. Hess</hi>. He
                    then briefly mentioned the agenda they would follow during the afternoon.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Status of the Foreign Relations series</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> summarized a written report he had prepared
                    on the status of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series (attachment
                    A). He recalled the prediction last November that seven to ten volumes would be
                    published in the coming year. He regretted that only one volume was released in
                    the interim--1951, vol. I (March 1980)--while the other six to nine volumes plus
                    11 others for the 1951-1954 period had been delayed pending re-review by the
                    Department's Classification/Declassification Center (CDC). He was optimistic,
                    however, that others would be published during the coming year, depending on the
                    speed of declassification, technical editing, and printing. Nine <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes have been designated as
                   “fast-track” volumes, and he briefly summarized the status of each of these
                    volumes, all of which were, he hoped, likely be printed during 1981.</p>
                <p>The budget did not appear to be a factor in the delay of publication. If six or
                    more volumes were, in fact, released next year, the budget might be a problem,
                    but he trusted that the Department would find the financial resources in such a
                    case.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> also indicated that all but one of the 12
                    volumes for 1955-1957 triennium had been completed in manuscript. The remaining
                    volume would be completed before the end of 1980. The 1955-1957 triennium would
                    comprise more than 28,000 printed pages as compared to the more than 33,000
                    pages expected for the 16 volumes of the 1952-1954 triennium. Some 28,000
                    printed pages are planned for the 16 projected volumes of the 1958-1960
                    triennium, although the total may be larger when the work is completed. Current
                    planning calls for completion of most of the manuscripts for the 1958-1960
                    triennium by the end of 1981. While work was being completed on the 1958-1960
                    triennium during the latter part of 1981 work would begin on compiling the
                    projected 16 volumes of the 1961-1963 triennium. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Slany</hi> circulated to the Committee three charts (copies attached)
                    indicating the status of the 1950-1954 volumes, the 1955-1957 triennium, and the
                    1958-1960 triennium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> also discussed the Office's search for
                    modern, efficient ways to produce <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes. The conversion by the Government Printing Office from linotype to
                    computerized printing required the introduction of word processing and
                    nine-track magnetic tapes. He outlined five ways to convert manuscript copy into
                    the final printed product: (1) word processing in the Office of the Historian
                    and transfer of finished tapes to GPO for printing or contract printing; (2)
                    word processing in some central Department of State facility and transfer of
                    finished tapes to GPO for printing or contract printing; (3) word processing by
                    commercial firms and transfer of finished tapes to GPO for printing; (4) word
                    processing by GPO or by a GPO sub-contractor and completion of printing by GPO
                    or a contract printer; (5) word processing and printing done in whole or part by
                    one or a combination of outside private contracting firms. All these options
                    have been explored in the past few months, feasibility studies have been
                    undertaken, and the options will undergo continued study in the future. Up to
                    five volumes for the 1955-1957 period will be done on the word processing system
                    in PA/HO. Other volumes for this period will be done in commercial firms, and
                    still others in GPO. The Office hopes to get comparisons on costs from these
                    various methods. Feasibility studies for microform supplements have been
                    delayed. Small-scale tests may be tried for 1955-1957 but large-scale
                    supplements will not appear until the 1961-1963 triennium.</p>
                <p>On personnel matters, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> noted the small
                    turnover of staff and that the Office was at relatively full strength. The
                    Office currently had two vacancies among the professional staff of 28, and the
                    support staff totaled eight. There were also two part-time professional
                    vacancies, one of which had been filled for a brief time, but there has not been
                    success in filling these particular positions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> inquired about the status of 1958-1960
                    volumes. If the bulk of the compilations were to be finished in 1981, when would
                    these documents be declassified? <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> emphasized
                    that the Office intended to submit documents for declassification now, or as
                    soon as possible, rather than wait for the printing galley proofs. The problem
                    in the past had been the declassification of documents late in the compiling and
                    editing process. The new system called for the declassification process to begin
                    earlier.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> inquired about the completion date for the
                    1961-1963 triennium. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> replied that the
                    current tentative target date for completion was the end of 1982. He expected
                    some of the 1961-1963 compilations to be begun next year.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked whether the nine “fast-track”
                    volumes scheduled for publication have been re-reviewed. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Pickering</hi> (A/CDC) explained that the re-review will be completed
                    in November 1980. This project does not take into account the appeal to higher
                    authorities of negative declassification decisions. <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        Unterberger</hi> assumed that most volumes would be appealed, and she
                    wondered how long the appeal process would require. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Pickering</hi> speculated a month might be required, but the process might
                    stretch out further. <hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> felt this was
                    too optimistic. She wondered how the process could be accelerated. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> suggested that the experience PA/HO has had
                    in the handling of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952-1954, Vol.
                    XVI, The Geneva Conference, indicated that at least seven months was required
                    between the end of the declassification process and publication of a volume. The
                    expected date for the publication of 1952-1954, Vol. XVI is March 1981. If the
                    A/CDC re-review and subsequent appeals for the nine “fast-track” volumes were
                    completed in the next few months, then all of them could conceivably be printed
                    by the end of 1981.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> wanted more definite information on the
                    budget for printing FRUS volumes in 1981. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi>
                    explained that the printing of seven volumes in one year would require
                    $700-800,000. The current Office budget provided for about one-half that amount
                    for printing. The Office was reasonably certain, however, that it could persuade
                    the Department to make a special case and provide the additional funds if they
                    were actually needed. <hi rend="underline">Mr. George</hi> inquired about the
                    basis for this optimism. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> asked that further
                    comment be deferred until the report of those responsible for the PA Bureau
                    budget later in the afternoon.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Hess</hi> asked how HO determined the number of pages
                    for each triennium. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> responded that the page
                    totals for 1955-1957 triennium were originally planned to be smaller than in
                    previous years. The compilations and volumes were, however, expanded to accord
                    with the importance of the subjects documented. Substance, not budget, is the
                    criterion in determining page totals for the 1955-1957 triennium and later
                    series. In response to another question, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi>
                    reiterated that the page totals for the 1961- 1963 triennium would be in the
                    same range as the 1955-1957 period. Would there be a special volume on the Near
                    East for the 1952-1954 period, <hi rend="underline">Prof. Hess</hi> asked. Mr.
                    Slany said no final decision had been made on Iran. Original plans called for
                    the volumes to be published as compiled. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi>
                    added that microform supplements were the solution; they were a way to make much
                    more documentation available to scholars.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Managerial Planning and the Problem of Central Services</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> then commented on the activities of the
                    Office of the Historian in the planning area. He stressed the changes that had
                    been and were taking place. One was the preparation of manuscript for
                    publication; the remarkable change has been the conversion from linotype to cold
                    type. Systems analysis was involved in modernizing and making operations more
                    efficient. He also described various reforms in HO. The first was the
                    reorganization of the Office. This involved reorganizing the staff, reducing the
                    number of supervisors to five, and according priority to the preparation of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> over other tasks. Also involved was the
                    triennialization of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> which allowed for
                    economies of presentation, and expanded annotation. The introduction of word
                    processing and other equipment had also permitted the speeding up of production
                    and the reduction of costs, but would not be effective until production of the
                    1955-1957 triennium. A problem was that the number of people cleared to handle
                    classified materials under the old linotype operation at GPO is not very great.
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> also pointed to HO's leadership in the
                    Department's efforts to declassify documents on a systematic, efficient basis,
                    which led to the creation of the CDC and its centralized review of classified
                    documents within the Department.</p>
                <p>The results, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said, were notable in terms of
                    productivity. The Office would be close to the 21-year line in compilation by
                    the end of 1981, and 20-year line by 1983. He believed HO was coming along
                    fairly well in this regard. He could not make the same claims for publication of
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He did not believe that
                    the nine “fast-track” volumes would all be published by the end of 1981. He
                    hoped this adequately answered <hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger's</hi>
                    earlier question on this point.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> then identified the principal problem
                    currently confronting the Office -- the delivery of Department of State's
                    central services. The internal planning and realignment of PA/HO activities was
                    well advanced. Now there would have to be much improved integration of PA/HO and
                    central services. He pointed to the use of systems methodologies that would be
                    required for improved relationship between PA/HO and central services. These
                    services were centralized in the Department in the 1950s and 1960s to obtain
                    economies of scale. HO was not the only office making demands on central
                    services. The problem was not unique to HO but was widespread in the Department
                    and the government. The Executive Office in the Bureau of Public Affairs was
                    designed to help the offices in PA to obtain the needed central services. He
                    compared this Office to the country desk officer who to serves the needs and
                    interests of his Chief of Mission abroad.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> itemized the central services upon which HO
                    depends: (1) Budget. Publishing costs are increasing at a greater rate than the
                    HO budget. To overcome this the Office was increasing productivity. The
                    introduction of modern cold-type production systems would also improve
                    productivity. The Office did not know exactly how much it would cost to publish
                    upcoming volumes because the Department had been unable to obtain unit cost
                    estimates from GPO.</p>
                <p>(2) Personnel. The Office has had problems with personnel in the past, but was
                    now near full complement. There were some systemic problems: (a) HO could not
                    recruit or hire until a vacancy actually occurred, and security clearances
                    resulted in delays; (b) Support staff requirements could not be met through
                    current Civil Service system definitions because HO's equipment required more
                    modern word-processing and office skills. The Executive Office of PA has done a
                    good job for HO on personnel.</p>
                <p>(3) Technical Editing. The technical editors had been removed from HO years ago.
                    The Office found it difficult to integrate its work with that of the technical
                    editors. One solution was to improve communication; another was to reintegrate
                    the technical editors into HO. The Office was working on this problem.</p>
                <p>(4) Printing. HO believed it did not have optimal relations with GPO, especially
                    in light of the revolution in printing from linotype composition to computerized
                    phototypesetting. HO was now exploring how to improve its relationship with GPO.
                    The other option is to find other printers and HO was exploring this through
                    feasibility studies.</p>
                <p>(5) The centralized Records Management System of the Department. HO was dependent
                    on the Foreign Affairs Information and Management Center (FAIM), as were all
                    other areas of the Department. The biggest problem was copying. A new system was
                    needed to avoid the delays HO was experiencing.</p>
                <p>(6) Declassification. The Department had moved to a system of centralized
                    declassification which was the long-range solution to the delay problem.</p>
                <p>(7) Miscellaneous centralized services: (a) space was inadequate for HO's needs,
                    but the Bureau of Public Affairs was committed to the allocation of adequate
                    space to the Office. (b) Contracting services were used to gain the services of
                    historians in 1978-1979, and HO was now contracting for feasibility studies of
                    word processing. (c) Housekeeping is a problem; the Office for example, had
                    great difficulty getting a plug installed for its new Xerox machine and having a
                    new air conditioning system installed to support the word-processing system. (d)
                    HO had to acquire expensive new equipment, but it had for the moment
                    considerable problems in getting processing machinery. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> said that every link of the central services chain had to work or
                    HO would not be able to publish the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. He noted that he was not attempting to make excuses in discussing the
                    problems related to central services, and added that HO would not be satisfied
                    until it reached the 20-year line.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> observed that there must be great
                    competition among Offices for the central services of the Department, and he
                    asked what kind of system of priorities of access had been worked out within the
                    Bureau of Public Affairs. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> replied that HO
                    had first priority in some cases, second in others, but that PA was not the
                    problem. Those in charge of central services establish priorities among
                    competing elements of the Department and HO had to wait in line. The problem was
                    not resources but how those resources were fitted together. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Trask</hi> stated that he believed that current staff levels and
                    funding levels were adequate to do the job, and added that he was not going to
                    complain about the budget until HO had achieved optimal efficiency and
                    productivity.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Foreign Relations Budget</hi></p>
                <p>After a break of 15 minutes, the committee heard a report from <hi
                        rend="underline">Deputy Assistant Secretary Gomez</hi> on the PA budget. <hi
                        rend="underline">Leon Ramey, Director of the PA Executive Office</hi> also
                    participated in the discussion. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Gomez</hi> echoed <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> in stating that the problems HO faced in
                    producing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series could be met, in
                    good part, by the efficient use of existing resources, rather than by an
                    increase in the PA/HO budget. Productivity gains, in his view, were dependent
                    upon technological advances in word processing and printing processes. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Gomez</hi> noted that he was prepared to weigh in, in
                    conjunction with <hi rend="underline">Mr. Ramey</hi>, to help tackle problems
                    relating to the provision of necessary central services. With regard to the
                    coming fiscal year, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Gomez</hi> stated that cost
                    accounting projections were difficult to make without more precise knowledge
                    about such factors as volumes to be produced, inflation, or conversion to a less
                    expensive word processing system. In response to a question from <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. George</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Gomez</hi>
                    indicated that he had received preliminary assurances that the necessary
                    additional funding would be made available to print any volumes cleared for
                    publication during the current fiscal year.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The New Classification/Declassification Center</hi></p>
                <p>At this point, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> introduced <hi
                        rend="underline">Deputy Assistant Secretary Clayton McManaway</hi>, head of
                    the Department's Classification/Declassification Center, who discussed the new
                    centralized system of declassification in the Department, and its implications
                    for the Office of the Historian and the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. <hi rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> explained CDC's operating
                    mandate, which included responding to Freedom of Information Act and mandatory
                    review requests, systematic declassification of older documents, and the
                    preparation of guidelines for the use of the National Archives (NARS). He
                    explained that the decision to re-review the 1951-1954 <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes was a result of CDC's conclusion that some of the
                    desks had done a poor job on initial review and the passage of time has seen a
                   “re-sensitization” of documents. Also there had been an assessment of the impact
                    of special events, especially Iran. <hi rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi>
                    noted that he had “very reluctantly” recommended the re-review of the
                    pre-1955-1957 volumes. He added that in spite of the heavy commitment of
                    resources to re-review, CDC had continued work on the 1955-57 volumes,
                    completing three of six. He stressed his desire to work closely with NARS in the
                    preparation of guidelines for the 1950-1954 records. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        McManaway</hi> felt that with its new experience CDC could accelerate the
                    declassification process for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in
                    the future.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked how many of the 19 volumes CDC
                    re-reviewed had gone completely through the appeals process; <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> responded that one volume had. <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked what percentage of the volume
                    had been restored in the appeals process; <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        McManaway</hi> responded that the original decision was upheld. In the
                    re-review, he stated, CDC had in a few cases actually released more material
                    than had the original reviewers. <hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> asked if
                    the declassification guidelines were open to the public. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. McManaway</hi> replied that the general guidelines were unclassified.
                    Detailed country-speciflc guidelines would obviously remain classified. He felt
                    the problem areas were foreign government information, intelligence sources and
                    methods, and military plans.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> asked about the size of the CDC staff. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> replied he had about 115 retired Foreign
                    Service Officers working part time. These officers had been nominated by the
                    bureaus. <hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> asked how many historians were
                    on the CDC staff. <hi rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> replied that some of
                    the retired FSOs had degrees in history. <hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi>
                    expressed his concern that exclusive reliance on FSOs with Cold War backgrounds
                    and lack of historical training would result in their withholding too much
                    documentation. These reviewers might not be good judges of what was sensitive
                    and might not be aware of what had reached the public domain. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> stated that the CDC depended on HO to
                    supply for the background information for declassifiers. He did not believe that
                    the Cold War had scarred the FSOs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Hess</hi> turned the discussion to a consideration of
                    foreign government information and its impact on the clearance process. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. McManaway</hi> explained the difference between foreign
                    originated documents and sensitive foreign government information in US
                    documents . He noted that CDC reviews this foreign government information on a
                    case-by-case basis. CDC feels the need for more consultation on these matters
                    with foreign governments.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Problems of Records Management and Transfer</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> next introduced <hi rend="underline">William
                        Price, Director of the Foreign Affairs Information Management Center</hi>
                    (FAIM). <hi rend="underline">Mr. Price</hi> discussed the automated
                    recordkeeping system in the Department and the services that FAIM provided for
                    HO. At the conclusion of <hi rend="underline">Mr. Price's</hi> presentation, <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked if declassification guidelines
                    for 1950-1954 block of documents were completed. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Pickering</hi> indicated that they should be ready by the spring of 1981.
                    Negotiations concerning the guidelines were going on now with NARS. He was not
                    sure when the documents would go to NARS. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Gustafson</hi> noted that NARS was not yet satisfied with the guidelines,
                    especially those dealing with foreign government information. He added that NARS
                    wanted a greater degree of cooperation from CDC--especially the making available
                    of a CDC representative at NARS for assistance in reviewing the documentation.
                    The afternoon session on November 13 concluded with a discussion of <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Price's</hi> briefing.</p>
                <p rend="center">Morning Session<lb/>(November 14, 1980, 8:30 a.m.-12:30 p.m.)</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Election of Chairperson</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> opened the morning session on November 14 by
                    announcing that it was a closed session at which HO would present its views on
                    the declassification situation. At this point <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        George</hi> nominated <hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> as
                    chairperson of the Committee for this year and she was elected by
                    acclamation.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Joint U.S.-U.S.S.R. Documentary Project</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> introduced the recently-published volume <hi
                        rend="italic">The United States and Russia: The Beginnings of Relations,
                        1765-1815</hi>, noting that it was a major contribution to the study of
                    Russian-American relations. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> pointed out to
                    the Committee that the joint U.S.-U.S.S.R. project was not without its
                    detractors and that a degree of controversy could be expected in the months
                    come. The publication had been released without publicity in mid-August and no
                    reviews have yet appeared. The Committee examined the volume.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The 1979 Committee Minutes and Report</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> then noted that the Committee had not
                    received copies of the minutes of last year's meeting. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> responded that he was not sure of the cause of problem but
                    promised to make copies available. He noted that <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        McManaway</hi> had wanted to be present for this session. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> felt such attendance might be inappropriate
                    but left to the Committee the decision on whether to talk to him later if it so
                    desired. <hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> noted that the Secretary of
                    State had failed to reply to last year's letter from the committee. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi>
                    agreed that this was probably due to turmoil during the last year in the higher
                    echelons of the department.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Declassification Problem</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> announced that the only agenda item for the
                    day was a consideration of the declassification problems growing out of the
                    re-review experience. He began by stating that there was no reason to believe
                    that CDC would not maintain a reasonable schedule. He was convinced that the
                    system would be more efficient in getting a decision on declassification. The
                    question at issue, however, related to the kind of decisions HO would get from
                    the system. Some 20 volumes had so far gone through the process within the State
                    Department. To illustrate the problems growing out of the re-review experience,
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> distributed a collection of materials to
                    the Committee.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> began a review of this documentation by
                    calling attention to a November 20, 1978 memorandum by Under Secretary of State
                    for Administration Ben Read establishing the new declassification program. He
                    then introduced a draft memorandum of May 2, 1980 from Hooding Carter (former
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs) to Mr. Read. This memorandum,
                    which was never sent, detailed HO's criticisms of CDC. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> continued with a September 1980 memorandum by Arthur Kogan
                    tracing the background of the 20-year line publication target. He then
                    introduced another proposed memorandum to Read (May 2, 1980) outlining arguments
                    against consultation with foreign governments about the release of information
                    in U.S. documents. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> noted that other U.S.
                    officials, such as Allen Thompson of the National Archives, were actively
                    negotiating with the British on this matter. <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        Unterberger</hi> asked if this was the first time the problem of foreign
                    government clearance of U.S. documents had arisen. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> replied that this was not the case and added that policy had
                    always been to maintain the sovereignty of U.S. documents. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Slany</hi> noted that the issue had arisen many times in the past.
                    During the Eisenhower Administration efforts were made to clear memoranda of
                    conversations abroad. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Kogan</hi> noted that the
                    definition of “foreign government information” in Executive Order 12065 was
                    quite ambiguous. This could result in a good deal of U.S. documentation being
                    withdrawn from declassification review at 20 years and being put back for review
                    at 30 years. <hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked if governments
                    other than those of the Commonwealth had been consulted on the question of
                    foreign government information in U.S. documents. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> replied that they had not yet been but noted that a precedent was
                    being set. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Rubin</hi> asked if the sensitivity of these
                    documents was the only issue at stake. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi>
                    replied that so far that was the case but other issues could arise.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> then introduced a CDC memorandum of March 19,
                    1980 to then-Deputy Assistant Secretary of State William D. Blair, Jr., setting
                    forth CDC's decision on the need to re-review the 1951-54 FRUS volumes. He noted
                    that Mr. Blair was in the process of retiring from the Department at the time.
                    He then introduced a memorandum of a discussion among Messrs. Trask, Blair and
                    McManaway that took place on March 27 just before Mr. Blair's departure. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> had pressed HO's objections to re-review in
                    this discussion. Since that meeting HO has continued to object that re-review is
                    costly and time-consuming and that it should not have been undertaken unless the
                    prior review was incompetent. HO does not feel that the incompetence of the
                    prior review has been established. CDC claims the prior Bureau review was
                    incompetent and that certain documents had reacquired sensitivity in the years
                    since the review.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> observed that the negative precedents
                    established by the CDC during the re-review of 1950-1954 volumes negated the
                    possible advantage of early submission of documents for declassification. In
                    effect it was possible for the CDC to undertake a further re-review of all <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compilations and volumes even after the
                    completion of the present re-review. The Historical Office could be forced into
                    a position of double jeopardy. <hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi>
                    reluctantly came to the conclusion that there would never be a final decision on
                    declassification until the time of publication. Therefore, the early review by
                    the CDC was not really a help to the series.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> inquired if any FRUS volumes had been
                    withdrawn after publication because of the CDC re-review. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Trask</hi> reported that none had been withdrawn but some volumes were
                    already bound, nearly bound, or in advanced page-proof status when the re-review
                    occurred.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> explained that in his view it was a great
                    mistake to attribute declassification problems to the new centralized system.
                    The current security-conscious climate in the Department and the rest of the
                    government would lead to similar declassification results under any system. And
                    it was an equally serious error to view the earlier decentralized
                    declassification system as some sort of golden age for FRUS. The previous system
                    had been ineffective and corrupt. Once the CDC system completed its “shake-down”
                    it would be a vast improvement over the old system.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> sought to contrast the decentralized system
                    of the past with the current centralized declassification procedures. He pointed
                    out that FRUS clearances were the result of <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi>
                    arrangements made between HO and Bureau officials. When these Bureau officials
                    were sympathetic to the series, the clearance of FRUS volumes was usually
                    successful. The arrangements were behind the scenes and the result of quiet
                    negotiation. With the CDC all declassification was placed “up front” for all to
                    see. The experts in CDC were able to standardize declassification
                    practices--often at the lowest common denominator of release. HO's flexibility
                    had been seriously reduced.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> expressed the feeling that the intrusion
                    of a new declassification institution created a “layering” of the Department
                    bureaucracy which was bound to work against the FRUS series. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Rubin</hi> said that on the basis of his 40 years of
                    experience with classification and declassification it seemed to him that the
                    old process, however disorderly, had merit because it succeeded in getting
                    documents declassified. He felt that CDC probably did not view openness as its
                    highest priority. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> stated that HO's opinion
                    is that the new system needs to be given a fair test. It had inevitable start-up
                    problems. Furthermore, the original system had not been implemented. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Baehler</hi> added that, based on returns so far, it
                    was not true that HO was able to declassify more under the old system. He felt
                    that HO was not necessarily doing any worse under the new system. It was too
                    early to give an accurate or complete assessment. <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        Unterberger</hi> questioned this assessment and asked for amplification. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that the re-review was working both
                    ways: to release some documents that had formerly been withheld while
                    withdrawing others. The real issue was what was being released, not how much.
                    Was CDC applying sound criteria for declassification? Thus far the system that
                    has emerged is not the one the Department ordered. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Slany</hi> observed that it was inevitable that the new CDC review will
                    delete more documents and information than the original Bureau review. The CDC
                    re-review was based on the premise that documents previously clearable had
                    become resensitized. The CDC review was aimed at finding these additional
                    documents and information. <hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> noted that he
                    admired the vigor and detail with which <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> and
                    his staff had argued HO's case in the memoranda he had read. But he failed to
                    understand the basis for optimism in the future. He felt that despite HO's
                    efforts the people higher up in the Department had not been convinced of the
                    necessity to redesign the system. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> reiterated
                    that the new system deserved a fair test. That, he felt, was the only way to
                    find out if the system would work. In addition, in terms of expedience, it was
                    unlikely that the new system would be dismantled. <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        George</hi> felt that once the system became institutionalized it might
                    never be dismantled. He added that, in his opinion, the new system would lead to
                    much more conservative decisions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schoettle</hi> asked if the Office could describe for
                    the committee what documents had been lost to the CDC review. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Baehler</hi> responded that HO did not know yet what
                    had been lost because the appeal process was not yet complete. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Glennon</hi> noted that HO had lost up to 10 percent of
                    the documents in the volumes produced by his division. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Baehler</hi> said that the first returns were tentative results. Those
                    results looked much worse than results under the old system. They were designed
                    to elicit a response from HO. He reiterated his view that the returns were
                    mixed. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Glennon</hi> said that he did not share <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Baehler's</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask's</hi> optimism in this regard. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Baehler</hi>
                    noted that he was not optimistic, but felt that the old system was no better.
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> supported Baehler's assessment; he was
                    not optimistic about the new system, but would not be more optimistic about the
                    old system. He was strongly opposed to the decisions being made now. It seemed
                    to him imperative to concentrate on revision of the new system. <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> asked why the new centralized system was
                    not working. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that the Oversight
                    Committee and other arrangements had not yet worked out and until they did he
                    could not say the system was unworkable. The resignations of Secretary Vance and
                    Assistant Secretary Hodding Carter left PA and HO without leadership during
                    (these) bureaucratic fights this spring and summer. The onset of the election
                    campaign and the general preoccupation in the Department with Iran had also
                    contributed to HO's difficulties. The result has been that there has been very
                    little bureaucratic follow-through on these issues.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Comments By the Division Chiefs</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schoettle</hi> asked the division chiefs to comment on
                    how bad the deletions made by the CDC were.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Status of Re-Review of General and European Volumes</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Sampson</hi> reviewed the status of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes under the General and European
                    Division. Eight volumes of the period 1950-1954 remained to be cleared for
                    publication. Volume IV for 1950 was bound and ready for release, but it had been
                    held up by the CDC. Volume III for 1951, Western Europe and Germany, had been
                    completely in page proofs when it was caught by re-review. In that process, some
                    22 items were deleted, appealed, and removed from the page proofs, but material
                    from documents declassified by the Joint Chiefs of Staff and from memoir
                    literature had filled the gaps caused by the deletions without loss of quality.
                    A similar situation in the case of 1952-1954, Volume V, Western Europe. A
                    formal decision had yet to be received from CDC, but even if all material CDC
                    had identified informally was deleted, HO would use declassified JCS material to
                    fill the gaps. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Sampson</hi> emphasized that the loss
                    was in time and money, not in quality.</p>
                <p>The remaining five volumes fell into two categories. In the first category were
                    1952-1954, Volume II, National Security Policy, and 1952-1954, Volume VII,
                    Germany. Here the deletions were relatively light, although heavier than in the
                    original review. He anticipated that discussions with CDC and the infusion of
                    JCS and other declassified material would result in no loss of quality. The
                    remaining three volumes were 1951, Volume IV, and 1952-1954, Volumes VI and
                    VIII. The first two dealt with Western Europe and the third dealt with Eastern
                    Europe. In the case of all three volumes the deletions were heavy, amounting in
                    the extreme case to 30 percent of the material. While returns on the latter two
                    volumes had only recently arrived and a careful examination had not yet taken
                    place, it was clear that little declassified material could reasonably be found
                    to compensate for such deletions. The compilation on France, Italy, and
                    Yugoslavia were badly “cut” both in quantity and quality. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Sampson</hi> concluded that the general picture with respect to the
                    CDC's re-review of these eight volumes was mixed.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Status of Re-Review of Western Hemisphere, African, and Middle
                    Eastern Volumes</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Claussen</hi>, speaking for the Western Hemisphere,
                    African, and Middle Eastern Division, stated that a greater quantity of
                    significant material intended for publication in <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> had been declassified under the old system prior to the
                    establishment of the CDC, even though that system may been uneven and dependent
                    on <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> arrangements. He noted that six volumes for
                    which his Division was responsible were being re-reviewed by the CDC. In only
                    one case, that of 1952-1954, Volume IV, American Republics, did the re-review
                    represent an improvement over the initial review. This was the result of a
                    country desk's reconsideration of a particular group of related documents, but
                    under the old system HO would in any case have appealed the original decision to
                    the desk.</p>
                <p>In the case of other volumes, a higher rate of deletion was evident under the new
                    centralized system. Volume I for 1952-1954, for example, dealing with general
                    economic and political matters, had originally been cleared for publication by
                    desks and Bureaus of the Department with only five small excisions. After the
                    re-review, CDC requested that portions of 18 documents be excised and that a
                    19th document be deleted in full. Another example was Volume IX for 1952-1954,
                    covering the Near and Middle East, originally cleared for publication by the
                    appropriate geographic bureau with five excisions. Preliminary returns from the
                    CDC re-review called for the deletion of all or parts of 220 documents.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Claussen</hi> mentioned several general characteristics
                    of the CDC declassification review process that he had observed: One was a
                    tendency by CDC to formalize its grounds for denying declassification of
                    material in any one area and extend them as precedents to all other areas. At
                    the same time, there was some inconsistency between and within volumes in what
                    various CDC reviewers chose to declassify what they chose to withhold. Under the
                    old system, HO spoke and negotiated directly with other geographic and
                    functional components of the Department. The results were sometimes successful,
                    sometimes unsuccessful, but least HO had the advantage of dealing directly with
                    the interested parties. Under the new centralized system, HO had to rely on CDC
                    as an intermediary to convey the views of the desks to HO and in turn to convey
                    HO's counter-arguments fully, accurately, and persuasively.</p>
                <p>Another aspect of the new system was its greatly-expanded concern with foreign
                    government information, including such information in documents of U.S. origin.
                    In such cases CDC had a tendency to delete entire documents rather than to
                    remove only the portions that actually contained sensitive foreign government
                    information. In making excisions in documents, CDC frequently deleted more words
                    or sentences than was actually necessary to protect sensitive information. The
                    work of some CDC reviewers indicated that they had been insufficiently briefed
                    on the nature and scope of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series,
                    or on the applicable government regulations concerning it. CDC reviewers were
                    often unaware of precedents in the public domain that might facilitate
                    declassification. Despite informal suggestions by HO historians that CDC
                    reviewers acquaint themselves with the precedents that appear in
                    previously-published <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, memoirs
                    and historical literature, and documents previously declassified, CDC continues
                    to rely on HO to discover relevant precedents for declassification. In oral and
                    written exchanges, CDC has usually placed on HO the burden of proving that
                    information was non-sensitive. CDC had not in certain cases been forthcoming in
                    explaining, in accordance with Executive Order 12065, specifically where the
                    sensitivities lie in material it proposes for deletion.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Evaluating the CDC Review</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Rubin</hi> asked who the CDC reviewers were who had
                    reviewed this <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> material. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Claussen</hi> said that the CDC employed about 115
                    retired Foreign Service Officers on a part-time basis. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Rubin</hi> said that a friend who was now working for the CDC had been an
                    excellent Foreign Service Officer, but was not the sort of person he would want
                    to see reviewing documents for their sensitivity. He recalled an anecdote in
                    connection with the publication of the Egypt-Israel peace treaty by the American
                    Association of International Law. There were protests against this publication,
                    even though the treaty and exchanges were in the public domain.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> compared the old and new declassification
                    review systems in the Department. Before the establishment of the central
                    system, reviewing was frequently done by junior desk officers; now it was done
                    by Senior Foreign Service Officers. He cited the factor of time required in the
                    review process and expressed the belief that time would be saved under the new
                    system. If time were not saved, the CDC system would be a failure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> said that he was not persuaded by this
                    analysis. The new system deprived HO of direct access to desk officers. New
                    middle men, who were not sympathetic to declassification, had interceded. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> replied that if the CDC were staffed as
                    originally proposed, the new system would work. He said that if there had been
                    better coordination and consultation between the parties at the outset, the
                    present problems would have been avoided. It was difficult to compare the review
                    process of 1976 with that of 1980. The context was different and a 20-year line
                    was now the objective, but he perceived no dramatic difference in volume and
                    quantity of deletions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Claussen</hi> raised a further point concerning the new
                    system. As the system was originally planned, CDC was to review as a “sample” a
                    collection of documents prepared by HO containing approximately 10 times the
                    number of documents in the compilations themselves. But CDC had in fact been
                    reviewing only the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> manuscript, and had
                    not had time to review the large quantity of backup material HO had
                    submitted.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Status of the Re-Review of the Asian Division's Volumes</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Glennon</hi> prefaced his remarks on the particular
                    effects of re-review on the Asian volumes for 1951-1954 by saying that he
                    believed that no method of systematic review could possibly succeed because, in
                    his experience, systematic review was anything but systematic. On the contrary,
                    it was arbitrary, capricious, and highly subjective. As an illustration of this
                    point, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Glennon</hi> related his experience with the
                    recent re-review of one country compilation in a 1952-1954 Volume. In this
                    instance the CDC re-review list of denied documents and the previous bureau list
                    of denied documents stemming from the first review contained only three common
                    items out of a total of several dozen. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Glennon</hi>
                    felt that the only reasonable approach to bulk declassification was to allow the
                    passage of time to be the sole determinant of declassification, so that files
                    would be opened and volumes published at an agreed period after
                    currency--possibly 30 years--without exception.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> concluded that HO must recognize sensitivity
                    and not select documents that have no chance of surviving the clearance process.
                    HO had to change the practice of its compilers and do some initial screening for
                    sensitivity in the future. This was not a welcome thought for the historians in
                    the Office, and <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> noted that he was
                    uncomfortable with the idea too. But HO had to avoid the accusation of being
                    unconcerned with security.</p>
                <p>The Committee took a short break at this point.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">More on Declassification</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> resumed after the break with a consideration
                    of a memorandum of a conversation of April 4, 1980 regarding the re-review of
                    all volumes for the 1950-1954 period. HO resisted re-review because of the delay
                    and expense involved. Moreover no convincing rationale for the reconsideration
                    had been adduced. The re-review was confirmed in a series of memoranda between
                    EUR and PA during the week of April 11 to April 18, 1980. These memoranda
                    formalized and legitimized the re-review decision-making process. On April 15
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> spelled out in a memorandum the details
                    of HO's plan to resist re-review. It was never fully implemented because Carter
                    soon left the Department. Among the papers outlining the story of re-review was
                    a letter from CIA requesting the opportunity to re-examine all unpublished
                    volumes. HO has resisted this request for re-review.</p>
                <p>A series of documents followed, indicating how the question was pursued through
                    the normal channels, which meant in effect pursuing the re-review issue to the
                    Oversight Committee headed by Ben Read, Under Secretary of State for Management.
                    The concluding portion of this series of documents dealt with various HO
                    arguments, steps taken, and those HO felt should be taken, at the highest levels
                    of the Department. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> worked on the premise
                    that HO would get a better and fairer hearing at higher Department levels. He
                    continues to feel that has proven to be the correct presumption. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> informed the Advisory Committee on June 11
                    that the decision had been made at the June 5 meeting to continue the re-review
                    but that appeals were allowable. These appeals would be made through
                    established, substantive-oriented channels to the Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs. At the meeting of June 5 it was also decided that a rationale
                    for re-review would be prepared, but such a rationale has yet to be
                    perfected.</p>
                <p>In view of the affirmation of the principle of re-review, <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Trask</hi> initiated the second phase of the Office's resistance to the
                    process. He filed a dissent channel protest. This is a Department administrative
                    procedure to bring extraordinary problems to the attention of the Secretary of
                    State. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi>'s dissent challenged the presumption
                    that an adequate case had been made for the necessity of re-review, and noted
                    the cost and delay involved. HO's object in filing the protest, <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> noted, was not to oppose the new
                    declassification system but to get it to work as intended. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Trask</hi> believed considerable progress has been made in this
                    respect. The result was a memorandum of October 14, 1980, that re-affirmed
                    re-review, emphasized the “balancing test” in conducting declassification review
                    and noted the necessity to make use of the Oversight Committee.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, HO continued to file appeals of specific denials in accordance with
                    the decisions of June 5. One such appeal that for 1951, Vol. III (European
                    Security and the German Question) had already gone through this process. The
                    views of HO and CDC were presented at a meeting with Under Secretary Newsom. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> felt the result was what might be termed a
                   “split decision.” HO won some arguments and lost others. A series of rulings
                    were given by this “judge.” <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> felt that this
                    meeting represented considerable gains, especially in assuring that “due
                    process” would be followed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> asked whether the Advisory Committee
                    members could keep any of the documents presented. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> said that they would not be allowed to. He confirmed to <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi>, however, that they could look at
                    the documents later that afternoon during their private meeting. He also said
                    they could keep the memorandum on his meeting with representatives of the
                    Organization of American Historians on October 17, 1980.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that the appeals had been narrowed to
                    those involving fundamental principles of great importance. He would continue to
                    appeal and use this appeals channel as necessary. He hoped the use of this
                    channel would become less necessary as orderly processes are implemented.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> asked what the standard was for the
                    release of a volume after the re-review and appeals process. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> replied that if it was determined that other
                    materials could be used as substitutes for the deleted documents, the volume
                    would be published. Exceptions would be made in the case of those deleted
                    portions deemed critical, such as documents in the 1949 China volume. HO would
                    go ahead with publication wherever possible because it was already so far behind
                    schedule. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> assured the committee, however,
                    that HO would not publish a volume that had been seriously distorted by
                    deletions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Hess</hi> asked whether the assumption was that the
                    appeals process would open up the documentary record. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> replied that there were problems on both sides of the fence. PA
                    should take security considerations more seriously, and other Department
                    officials should take openness more seriously. The dissent channel was for
                    extraordinary cases and could not be used too often.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Baehler</hi> pointed out the importance of the
                   “balancing test” called for in Executive Order 12065. The assumption was that
                    older documents were easier to release but not all Department officials are
                    aware of this distinction.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Hess</hi> observed that the burden seemed to be
                    shifting to HO to “prove” that documents should be declassified. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that the question was whether to fight
                    wherever we could fight or do nothing and allow FRUS to go down the drain. ' He
                    of course had chosen the former course. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi>
                    pointed out that the amount of staff time involved in the re-review, including
                    appeals to the Under Secretary for Political Affairs, confirmed that the burden
                    of proof was now on HO.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> reiterated that use of the dissent channel
                    was an extreme measure. HO would vigorously pursue the options open in the
                    appeals process and in reference to the Oversight Committee. He cited an S/P
                    memorandum, especially the last paragraph, as a rebuff to CDC. This type of
                    response illustrated the purpose of HO's strategy. He was not aware of any other
                    channel open to HO. He hoped sound Department policy on declassification would
                    emerge from this experience.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Self-Denial or Self-Censorship in Compiling</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> said that he was disturbed by an earlier
                    statement by <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> that he wanted the HO staff to
                    be more careful not to submit very sensitive material for declassification. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Schoettle</hi> said it was her understanding that HO
                    was specifically charged with submitting sensitive material. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> responded that a determination of
                    sensitivity in the clearance process was a very subjective matter. He added that
                    an inclination on the part of the professional staff to print documentation
                    relating to matters such as covert operations presented clearance problems. He
                    believed that good common sense needed to be exercised by the historians in the
                    office.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> said that he was disturbed by what <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> had said here and on an earlier occasion to
                    the effect that his staff should anticipate negative decisions higher up and
                    reduce the number of controversial items sent forth. On what basis had <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> claimed the staff was inattentive? <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> agreed with <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        George</hi> but said that HO historians were employees of the U.S.
                    Government and should be aware of the Executive Order guidelines. If the staff
                    wanted to print an obviously sensitive document, he would question whether the
                    substance of the document justified printing it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> commented that it was important not to
                    allow HO staff to be pushed into a conservative posture, by making preliminary
                    judgments, and <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> agreed. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Prof. George</hi> said that this was especially important because the
                    committee had heard testimony that any two groups of reviewers could come up
                    with entirely different deletions in the same body of material.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> remarked that it may be urgent for HO to
                    collect all sensitive materials so that Department officials can identify them.
                    This would be a service to them. HO was uniquely capable of presenting the
                    complete and comprehensive record; the CDC was not able to do this by
                    itself.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said he wanted HO only to recognize early on
                    when a given document was sensitive. He was not favoring censorship but good
                    judgment in recognizing when to stop arguing. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Slany</hi> said HO should rely on presenting a full documentary record. <hi
                        rend="underline">Prof. Unterberger</hi> said HO should always present
                    everything, maintaining the integrity of the record. <hi rend="underline">Dr.
                        Rubin</hi> said he did not know what the most sensitive documents were, and
                    that judgment was obviously involved, but that prejudice in the direction of
                    openness should be the guiding principle.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Staffing the CDC</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> asked whether any effort had been made to
                    include professional historians in staffing the CDC. <hi rend="underline">Mr.
                        Trask</hi> responded that there were no funds for such historians but only
                    for retired FSOs. The decision was made on that basis. He wanted to bring this
                    issue to the Oversight Committee. The Inspector General would take a look at
                    this in two or three years. He wanted such an inspection to take place and was
                    recommending this to the PA Bureau. We could not expect much action in the
                    policy area until after the transition to the new administration. <hi
                        rend="underline">Dr. Rubin</hi> commented that the Assistant Secretary for
                    Public Affairs might, on the other hand, say “Why not?” He might believe he had
                    nothing to lose in promoting reforms before he was removed by the new
                    administration.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Problem of Editorial Notes for Deleted Documents</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> said there was one more issue. HO must
                    develop new editorial procedures to deal with identifying the complete
                    documentary record. The question at issue was how to deal with those documents,
                    or parts of documents, that were not declassified. CDC and some Bureaus were
                    opposed to any editorial indication of substance or agency involved in the
                    deletion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> observed that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series was becoming more and more a guide to the documentary
                    record, but some of this was being questioned within the government. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> believed that the editorial content of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes was the responsibility of
                    the Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, and HO would look to him alone for
                    instruction on this matter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> asked whether HO or CDC had the final
                    judgment on editorial handling of deletions. Was there a clear understanding?
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said this still remained an unresolved
                    issue. For example, if a Dutch document denied by the Dutch government but
                    summarized in an editorial note was later denied by the CDC, HO would have to
                    accept. the CDC judgment as correct. But HO still determined editorial policy.
                    There were problems in defending autonomy in editorial judgment. Some deletions
                    in editorial notes had been accepted, others would be contested. Both wanted to
                    be able to explain ellipses and documentary material denied clearances. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> mentioned that in the case of NSC documents,
                    notes had been inserted in earlier <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes that the materials were not printed at NSC request. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mr. Claussen</hi> noted that introductions to the volumes can in the future
                    point to this issue.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Disposition of Office “Lot” Files</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> asked about “lot” files. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said these files were important, especially
                    for understanding the decision-making process. <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        Taylor</hi> asked whether these lot files were being preserved. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Baehler</hi> said he could not say whether all were
                    being preserved, but none were being destroyed in contradiction to the Federal
                    Records Act. Files could be destroyed if they duplicated other records. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> added that the National Archives was the
                    ultimate decision-making agency. If NARS rejected files as duplicating other
                    records, it would send them back to the Department, which might then destroy
                    them. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said this was a difficult battle. The
                    solution, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Price</hi> said, is the digital system,
                    whereby the Department would have in effect only one file. HO would do
                    everything possible, <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> contended, to preserve
                    the lot files.</p>
                <p>The meeting recessed at 12:30 p.m. to reconvene in Mr. Trask's office after
                    lunch.</p>
                <p rend="center">Afternoon Session<lb/>(November 14, 1980; 2:45-3:30 p.m.)</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">The Status of Research and Reference Projects</hi></p>
                <p>The meeting reconvened in <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask's</hi> office at 2:45
                    p.m. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Petersen</hi> reported on the research and
                    reference functions of the Office. He said that HO did research in response to
                    Department requests. These studies could be from one page to several volumes in
                    length and involve administrative histories, crisis management studies,
                    compiling or updating of reference works (<hi rend="italic">United States Chiefs
                        of Mission</hi>, for example). These studies served as an institutional
                    memory for the Department. They helped to identify and preserve relevant files
                    and also were useful in preparing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Petersen</hi> said that he was now the only HO
                    historian doing in-house research on a full-time basis. HO had some discretion
                    in refusing requests; for example, it could say that it did not have enough
                    resources to do a study. For larger projects the Office formed task forces. <hi
                        rend="underline">Mr. Petersen</hi> circulated to the Advisory Committee a
                    list of larger projects completed during the past five years and gave highlights
                    of the past year. He mentioned, for example, 10 large studies concerning
                    legislative constraints in the conduct of foreign relations; a compilation
                    involving narratives, public statements, and chronologies on Iran, 1941-1979; a
                    list of public statements and narrative studies on Cuba; Madeleine Chi's study
                    on U.S. relations with Sri Lanka for the ambassador-designate; and a study on
                    the evolution of the position of the national security adviser from
                    1947-1980.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> recalled that during the past winter HO had
                    been asked to prepare in 24 hours for possible use for White House studies on
                    the 1956 Soviet intervention into Hungary and the 1968 Soviet intervention into
                    Czechoslovakia. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Sampson</hi> had gathered together the
                    requested materials. One of the items was a long, detailed study, prepared
                    several years earlier, on the Czechoslovak case. President Carter and National
                    Security Adviser Brzezinski both publically acknowledged the significance of the
                    HO report in assessing the decisions to be taken in connection with the Soviet
                    invasion of Afghanistan. The President privately commended the Office on its
                    work.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Claussen</hi> pointed out that the entire office had
                    been involved in the Iran project, and that HO was commended for its
                    objectivity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> commented that policy-oriented research
                    increasingly involved the Third World, since less was known about it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. George</hi> asked how much HO time was devoted to this
                    type of research. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said it was hard to judge
                    but he was very interested in this aspect of office work. It involved the
                    question of how to do research that is policy-relevant. HO was still
                    experimenting with various modes. At present he wanted to catch up with
                    compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series after which
                    more time could be diverted to policy-related research. His goal is expend about
                    10 percent of HO resources, which was less than that devoted by HO in the
                    past.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Schoettle</hi> said she was excited about this aspect of
                    HO work, and wondered why an ERDA study on India had to be written by a
                    professor on the outside. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that HO was
                    interested in interagency research but felt that the other agencies were not. He
                    felt HO had to forge links with other agencies to transcend fiefdoms. The
                    indications were that HO research had been more helpful to the Department in the
                    past year but the overall productivity of Office had also increased. <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> production remained on schedule. He
                    also noted that word processing equipment in-house has been a great help in
                    producing and revising these research papers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Prof. Taylor</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Prof.
                        Unterberger</hi> asked whether these research papers went into a Department
                    file or the central files. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> said that there
                    were HO lot files, and some papers would be in the central files.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Petersen</hi> reported that HO had written 30 papers for
                    the Policy Planning Staff which highlighted public statements on issues. These
                    were unclassified studies. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> speculated on the
                    purposes of these studies. He did not know what finally happened to them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Slany</hi> remarked that HO research papers did not have
                    full standing, as they were not cleared in the Department by other concerned
                    Bureaus. One on Cuba, however, was reviewed, cleared, and sent to the White
                    House. <hi rend="underline">Mr. Trask</hi> remarked that HO might not want these
                    papers cleared because the result might be compromising to the integrity and
                    objectivity of the studies.</p>
                <p>The meeting concluded at 3:50 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
