<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1981</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1981</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-05">May 5, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1981-11-13">November 13, 1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1981-11-13-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 274 KB, 26pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, 1981—Minutes, Report.</hi></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1981 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 13, 1981</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Arnold B. Taylor, Department of History, Howard University,
                        Washington, D.C.</item>
                    <item>Dr. Ernest R. May, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard
                        University, Cambridge, Mass.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Richard N. Rosecrance, Center for International Studies, Cornell
                        University, Ithaca, N.Y.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Gaddis Smith, Department of History, Yale University, New Haven,
                        Conn.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Seymour J. Rubin, Executive Vice-President and Executive Director, The
                        American Society of International Law, Washington, D.C.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Raymond G.H. Seitz, Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                    <item>Francis D. Gomez, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Acting Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Acting Deputy Historian and Adviser on Research</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Acting General Editor of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>)</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>William Sanford</item>
                    <item>Nina Noring</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Sherrill Wells</item>
                    <item>David Baehler</item>
                    <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                    <item>Paula Lorfano</item>
                    <item>Nina Neve</item>
                    <item>Luke Smith</item>
                    <item>Robert McMahon</item>
                    <item>Edward Keefer</item>
                    <item>James Miller</item>
                    <item>Kay Herring</item>
                    <item>Karen Bryfogel</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff</item>
                    <item>David Patterson</item>
                    <item>David Mabon</item>
                    <item>Carol Becker</item>
                    <item>Margaret Gourlay</item>
                </list>
                <p>Classification/Declassification Center (CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>Laurence Pickering, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs and Information and Management Center (FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Paul M. Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division (PS)</item>
                    <item>John Ellsworth, Chief, General Editing Branch</item>
                    <item>Margie Wilber, Chief, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker, Deputy Chief, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                    <item>Charlotte Shahin</item>
                    <item>Leo Masciana</item>
                    <item>Elee Roeder</item>
                    <item>Vicki Ettleman</item>
                </list>
                <p>The National Archives and Records Service (NARS):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Alan Thompson, Chief, Records Declassification Division</item>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Diplomatic Records Division</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Arthur G. Kogan, retired</item>
                    <item>Beverly Zweiben, Bureau of International Organization Affairs, Department
                        of State</item>
                    <item>Prof. George O. Kent, University of Maryland</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Morning Session</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Slany called the meeting to order at 9:17 a.m. He introducing Mr. Seitz, who
                    welcomed the Advisory Committee on behalf of Dean Fischer, Assistant Secretary
                    for Public Affairs and Department Spokesman.</p>
                <p>Mr. Seitz stated that he was very interested in the function of the Historical
                    Office, and noted its contributions to both the Department of State and to the
                    academic community. He stated that the Department had a commitment to the quick,
                    efficient release of historical documentation, and that HO had a commitment to
                    maintaining its high standard in the publication of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> series. He called attention to HO’s special research program and
                    noted that although this function had been neglected in recent years, the
                    Department had renewed interest in research by HO. Mr. Seitz solicited the
                    Committee’s advice, which he considered vital, in determining the proper balance
                    between quick disclosure and the secrecy required for national security.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany called upon the Committee to elect a chairman. Prof. Taylor was
                    nominated by Prof. May, seconded by Prof. Rosecrance, and named chairman by
                    acclamation.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Acting Historian</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then proceeded to summarize his written report on the current status of
                    the Office of the Historian. He reminded the Committee that the departure in
                    July of David F. Trask (the former Historian) was the major event of the year.
                    The Office Director position will be filled as a Senior Executive Service
                    position. Applications will be accepted until the end of the month. The
                    retirement at the end of 1980 of Arthur G. Kogan was also a great loss to the
                    Office.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that the problems experienced in publishing <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> had not eased over the year. Declassification had always been a
                    problem, but the documentation from the Cold War period of the 1950s presented
                    additional difficulties. Many people in the Department are involved in trying to
                    resolve the problems of preparing, clearing, and publishing <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. The Department has demonstrated continued support for the
                    series. It falls to HO to recommend solutions for the problems that delay the
                    timely release of volumes. There are no magical solutions. The advice and
                    support of the Committee are vitally needed. HO is doing the best that it can;
                    its resources have not been reduced, and the Department stands behind it.</p>
                <p>He said we need to work with A/CDC in accelerating the release of the volumes
                    while at the same time making sure that the integrity of the series is
                    maintained. As we get better in compiling, the problems in gaining clearance
                    increase. Even with deletions, the volumes are far superior to those of 20 years
                    ago. HO seeks to meet the highest standards of scholarship. Coverage is a
                    problem particularly in regard to intelligence matters. We have to consider
                    whether what we are trying to do is what we should be trying to do. Should the
                    series chronicle the intelligence activities of the Government? It is hard to
                    gain access to materials about such matters from other agencies. Do triennial
                    volumes meet the needs of scholars? Mr. Slany indicated HO’s intention to
                    conduct a user’s survey. Microform is another concern of HO. It will soon
                    undertake test projects. We need to know how to relate microform to printed
                    volumes. The above survey will provide some insight into <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>-users’ views of such matters. Mr. Glennon interjected that it
                    probably will be sent out early next year.</p>
                <p>Publication of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> also encounters a production problem.
                    GPO is in a period of transition as regards technology. Fourteen <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes remain in lead plates, but not all may be
                    clearable by 1984 when GPO loses its last linotype operator and converts fully
                    to word processing technology. HO is already involved in word processing of its
                    own. It has taken one year to publish volumes that have already been cleared.
                    Mr. Glennon noted that Volume XVI, which was on a fast track, took 10 months to
                    print even after it had been cleared. Mr. Slany noted that we hope to speed it
                    up. HO hopes to find a way to edit on-line working with a word processor
                    system.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that the 1978 Executive Order on declassification was in the
                    process of being revised. This would affect on HO and the Department. He said we
                    are concerned about the staffing level of A/CDC, with which we have a close
                    relationship. We are anxious to devise better methods of collecting
                    documentation and to work out guidelines for the transfer of the records to
                    NARS.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany indicated that HO had resumed the <hi rend="italic">American Foreign
                        Policy: Current Documents</hi> series that had been suspended with the 1967
                    volume. One had been virtually finished last month on the Carter years;
                    retrospective volumes on the Nixon and Ford years would follow. It is hoped that
                    the first would be out by the end of the year and the annual volume on 1981
                    could be issued by early 1982. The two other retrospective volumes are scheduled
                    for 1982. It is a necessary and useful series which reinforces <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. He expressed interest in the Committee’s views. At one time <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was itself its own <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> and put current foreign policy before the public and
                    the Department. We are interested in the Committee’s opinion about the value of
                    the resumed series.</p>
                <p>The great concern of the Department is that historians be able to help foreign
                    policy makers. The research function we are working on is mutually
                    supportive.</p>
                <p>There are questions about the research program.</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>How effective is it?</item>
                    <item>What kinds of things can historians do for policy makers in the
                        Department?</item>
                    <item>There is real concern that the research program not become a subsidiary to
                        public relations activities. At the same time we must be supportive of the
                        public relations functions of the Bureau. What does the Committee
                        think?</item>
                </list>
                <p>There are problems in the administration of the Office. There are vacancies, and
                    HO is hiring historians. But we can’t hire as we did in the past. The Civil
                    Service Act of 1978 and the Foreign Service Act of 1980 require that we
                    interview candidates from within the Department or that OPM provide us with a
                    register of historians -- people who didn’t necessarily know they were applying
                    for HO jobs, but were simply on the midlevel register. If you know of students
                    or colleagues who are interested, he said, please have them put their names on
                    the registry and make themselves known to HO.</p>
                <p>The Advisory Committee is one of a number which the Department maintains.
                    Although the Department continues to provide support for the Committee it may
                    not be able to continue to do so in the future. What effect would a reduction of
                    financial support have on Committee meetings? What are your views on attendance,
                    format, membership, and place of future committee meetings?</p>
                <p>Prof. Rubin asked what is the extent of financial support now?</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany responded that it was several thousand dollars. We haven’t tried to
                    achieve any particular geographical distribution. Members are selected because
                    they were recommended by constituent societies.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Acting General Editor</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon began the summary of his report by requesting that the committee
                    members consult their own copies of his report for the statistics that show that
                    the number of volumes published has dwindled in the past several years because
                    of the declassification difficulties. In 1977, 7 volumes were published. Three
                    will be published this year and 8 will hopefully be published in 1982. Five of
                    the eight are already through the declassification process.</p>
                <p>Prof. Rosecrance asked which five? Mr. Glennon responded: 1952-1954 Vol. XIII,
                    Indochina; 1951 Vol. VII, Korea and China; 1952-1954 Vol XI, Africa and South
                    Asia; 1951 Vol V, Near East and Africa; 1952-1954 Vol I, General.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon then said that CDC is now responsible for handling the
                    declassification apparatus, and is in contact with other parts of the
                    Department, other agencies, and foreign governments. In the Spring of 1980 CDC
                    decided to rereview all volumes for 1951-1954. That is where the action is now
                    in declassification. HO and CDC haven’t gotten to the 1955- 1957 volumes yet. At
                    the beginning of this year the last volume for 1950 was released: Volume IV.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon observed that he had seen reference in print to the question of
                    whether <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> will become a White Paper. He
                    said that HO is determined that will not happen. The Historical Office can
                    appeal decisions of the CDC in the first go-around. If we’re not satisfied, HO
                    can sit on the volumes to insure their integrity. In the past HO has had to
                    delete whole topics from the series. It has always been the case that HO isn’t
                    allowed to publish certain topics, for example the El Chamizal boundary dispute
                    with Mexico. We have had to take out compilations on Iceland, Greenland, and
                    Albania in recent years. On numerous occasions documents on the Peru-Ecuador
                    boundary dispute have not gone to press. For the 1949 volume VIII on China, the
                    declassification process took six years. HO withheld the volume waiting for the
                    deaths of Chou En-lai and Chairman Mao -- (without HO intervention). We are
                    convinced the decision was correct and worth waiting for because the material in
                    the volume was so important.</p>
                <p>HO has compiled sixteen volumes for the period 1952-1954. Out of the sixteen,
                    only two have been released. This gives an indication of the time lag involved.
                    Mr. Glennon had personally predicted that we would have the least problems with
                    volumes III and XVI. These are the two which have been published. Six are
                    included in the list to be published in 1982; eight probably won’t be published
                    until 1983 or 1984.</p>
                <p>For the period 1955-1957 there are twelve volumes, but none have been
                    declassified because we were focusing attention on 1952-1954. For 1958-1960
                    sixteen volumes are projected. Of these, four, or possibly five have been
                    compiled. Six are well under way and the remainder are in initial stages. For
                    1961-1963 we project sixteen more volumes. We have just begun to collect the
                    material. Recently four of the historians flew up to the Kennedy Library to make
                    the first systematic effort to collect documents there.</p>
                <p>We have slowed down the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> assembly lines
                    that existed from 1976 to 1981. During that period everyone in HO had been
                    working on the volumes, but that won’t happen again. The 1958-1960 and 1961-1963
                    cycles will be slower.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Personnel</hi> We are currently in the process of filling
                    five professional vacancies. It is a long process going through the Civil
                    Service procedures. In the past year HO has had one retirement (Dr. Kogan) and
                    five resignations or transfers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Technology</hi> We have done three volumes on in-house word
                    processing equipment and will be doing more in the future. Several volumes of
                    1955-1957 are targeted for microfiche supplements on a trial basis. One will be
                    volume VII on the Suez Crisis. The other will be the China volume because there
                    are important U.S.-PRC conversations which we can put verbatim in the
                    supplements.</p>
                <p>A paper on the “Status of Declassification” of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> 1951-1954 is included in the packet of materials provided to
                    the Committee.</p>
                <p>Prof. Smith asked for more information on the proposed microfiche supplements.
                    Mr. Glennon said that a microfiche supplement would allow additional material to
                    be included for Vol. VII on the Middle East. There would not be room in the
                    volume itself. Prof. Smith asked whether the microfiche supplement would be
                    distributed separately. Mr. Slany responded yes. We had thought about putting it
                    in pockets in the volumes, but the librarians didn’t like that idea. We probably
                    would have to package it separately in small units. One wouldn’t have to buy the
                    entire supplement. Mr. Slany added that microfiche is attractive because it can
                    capture whole series of documents such as briefing books that can’t be included
                    in the printed series. Prof. May asked whether original documents would be
                    filmed. Mr. Slany said yes. Prof. Smith said that this whole thing should be
                    encouraged. Mr. Slany noted that we have to take care to select the best copy of
                    a document for filming.</p>
                <p>Prof. Taylor stated that in 1978, the Advisory Committee report expressed concern
                    that material in lot files was being destroyed. He asked whether microform will
                    help this problem. Mr. Slany replied yes; moreover he hoped that what HO thinks
                    is critically important can be preserved by including it in the supplements. Mr.
                    Glennon added that the Secretariat puts together wonderful files. It would be
                    good to photograph them in toto. Others are weeded out. We have given the
                    Committee lists of numbers of lot files which HO has used in the preparation of
                    the series. We have used them and feel they should be retained.</p>
                <p>COFFEE BREAK</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the CDC</p>
                <p>After a short break, Mr. Slany introduced Ambassador John Burke, the new director
                    of the CDC. Ambassador Burke, a Foreign Service officer for 26 years, obtained
                    B.A. and M.A. degrees in history at the University of Wisconsin where he studied
                    under Prof. Fred Harvey Harrington. Ambassador Burke feels he brought an
                    historian’s skepticism to his Foreign Service career. He hopes that in his
                    position he can serve the academic community as well as the Department of State
                    and the national interest. He noted that the CDC was initially established to
                    bring order out of the chaos of filling F.O.I. requests, a task that was not
                    considered a priority activity by the desk officers who reviewed the requests.
                    Ambassador Burke realizes, however, that the Advisory Committee’s interest is in
                    systematic review, not mandatory review. He commended Mr. Pickering to the
                    Committee as a man who has brought the experience of a teacher and a Foreign
                    Service Officer to that task. Mr. Pickering and his staff have prepared
                    guidelines for the National Archives to use in declassifying the 1950-1954
                    diplomatic record block. The current budgetary constraints on NARS have
                    prevented the accessioning of the records so far.</p>
                <p>The CDC uses retired diplomats, as does the British Foreign Office
                    declassification process, to review documents. They bring sensitivity and access
                    to political and functional desks because of their past experience, and they
                    consult with the desks.</p>
                <p>The problems in the future are budgetary, especially with respect to NARS’s
                    inability to accession the 1950-1954 record block. Ambassador Burke has met with
                    the Archivist Warner, and would like to work cooperatively with NARS. He has
                    outlined the problem to the Under Secretary for Management, and he solicited the
                    Committee’s suggestions and assistance in supporting the National Archives so
                    that it could have the resources necessary to continue to accept State
                    Department records.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke observed that the CDC’s Systematic Review staff accords top
                    priority to completing the review of the 1952-1954 volumes and 1951 volumes.</p>
                <p>The publication prospect for 1981 looks better. 1982 looks even more promising.
                    Amb. Burke was impressed with HO’s development planning for a microform
                    supplement to <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. He proposes to give CDC support to HO
                    for this microform project.</p>
                <p>Amb. Burke reported briefly on a summer 1981 meeting in Washington with the
                    British Foreign Office officials in an effort to discuss mutual declassification
                    problems. HO and NARS participated in the meetings. The British Foreign Office
                    uses retired diplomats as reviewing officers. The policy of the British is to
                    make foreign affairs information 30 years old or older available to the public.
                    2-3% of the records are considered too sensitive and withheld from release. He
                    wants to organize a meeting with the Canadians and is in the process or doing
                    that now as a means of getting faster clearances on information which involves
                    both parties. He added that there is a partnership here between the CDC and HO
                    and the academic committee and the public it represents.</p>
                <p>Prof. Rosecrance said that there is a slight difference between the U.S. and the
                    British over what each considers sensitive. The U.S. apparently has an
                    additional policy of avoiding needless embarrassment to individuals. The British
                    don’t seem to care about that. Prof. Rosecrance would not want reasons of
                    personal delicacy to hold back publication of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes. Amb. Burke replied that gratuitous comments might be excised if the
                    person still held positions of responsibility in public life. Dr. Thompson of
                    NARS interjected that he thought the British were more sensitive than the
                    Americans in regard to protecting individuals. They are much more conservative
                    than the U.S. Edward Keefer noted the British are releasing documentation which
                    is critical of second-level military and diplomats. Prof. Smith seemed to feel
                    that the British diplomats have more frequently commented on other diplomats
                    than the U.S. Foreign Service did in diplomatic reports. American diplomats tend
                    more frequently to comment on each other in a derogatory way. Amb. Burke said
                    that from his personal experience in 26 years of reading telegrams, etc., he
                    couldn’t think of many instances where comments on American individuals were
                    made. It is not considered part of the job. He had reported on diplomats of
                    other countries and the quality of the representation of other countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that the original charter of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    series of 1925 required that information causing needless offense to individuals
                    not be included. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> editors have traditionally, until
                    recently, deleted that information. In the last years the tendency has been for
                    HO compilers to leave to the Bureaus the task of such deletions. The
                    responsibility has been dumped into the hands of someone else. CDC has done what
                    the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> editors did before.</p>
                <p>Prof. May asked about the budget cuts that Ambassador Burke had mentioned. The
                    Ambassador responded that the cuts are primarily affecting NARS at this point.
                    Mr. Thompson added that NARS does not yet know how deep the cuts will be, but
                    that they will certainly affect the declassification effort. He said that NARS
                    anticipates budget cuts of 12%, which will in effect end systematic review
                    there. For the time being, NARS is asking agencies to keep their own records,
                    because NARS does not have the resources to accession sensitive records at
                    all.</p>
                <p>Prof. Rosecrance asked what percent of sensitive documents are declassified by
                    publication in the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series. Mr. Thompson replied that
                    only about 10% are declassified in that fashion.</p>
                <p>Prof. Smith asked whether documents withheld now will be automatically reviewed
                    again according to a schedule. Mr. Burke replied that there is no schedule
                    except for FOI cases. However, when NARS finally accessions the State Department
                    records, a schedule for automatic re-review is adhered to.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke brought to the attention of the Committee actions in Congress
                    that might well affect the declassification process. Amendments are to be
                    introduced to the FOIA; hearings are to be held later this session. Executive
                    Order 12065 is likely to be revised. Drafting is in progress.</p>
                <p>Prof. Rosecrance asked if any U.S. effort is being made to release very sensitive
                    material from World War II. He pointed to the British government publication
                    dealing with wartime cryptography. Mr. Thompson responded that the U.S. has
                    never released the details of its code breaking story. He added that a concerted
                    effort by historians both inside and outside the government would be required to
                    pressure the U.S. government into supporting that kind of retrospective project
                    embarked on in Britain.</p>
                <p>Prof. Taylor asked whether the CDC anticipated any cuts in its own staff. Amb.
                    Burke said that future personnel levels were still not certain. Prof. Taylor
                    then asked whether the hiring of retired historians as well as retired Foreign
                    Service Officers was contemplated, as recommended in previous Committee reports.
                    The Ambassador replied that the matter was under consideration, but personal
                    security clearance problems associated with hiring historians were
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>Prof. May asked if the creation of a historical office and the appointment of an
                    historian at the CIA had improved relations with CIA as far as clearances were
                    concerned. Both Amb. Burke and Mr. Slany remarked that so far there had been no
                    effect.</p>
                <p>Returning to the issue of hiring historians for the CDC, Mr. Slany added that it
                    is important to remember that substantive bureaus in the Department need to be
                    comfortable with the persons from the CDC who are declassifying their documents.
                    Moreover, the CDC has functioned as a buffer in the sometimes uncomfortable
                    relations of the past between HO and the geographic bureaus. Amb. Burke added
                    that the CDC has taken advantage of the bonds of confidence and respect that
                    sometimes exist between bureaus and the retired FSOs who are now working for the
                    CDC and who had at one time been senior officers in those same bureaus. Prof.
                    Rubin commented that this former relationship may sometime work to the detriment
                    of release of information. The reviewers may have a vested interest in
                    protecting policies they devised. Amb. Burke explained that the CDC tried to
                    assign reviewers who specifically were not involved in the creation of the
                    documents they are subsequently asked to declassify.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that HO assists CDC in the declassification process by
                    identifying pertinent information in the public domain. In response to Prof.
                    Taylor’s query as to when HO provides this information, Mr. Slany responded that
                    heretofore the information was provided to the CDC only after the CDC has
                    actually proposed informally to deny declassification of a document or portion
                    of a document.</p>
                <p>Prof. Taylor asked what the usual tenure of a CDC reviewer has been. Amb. Burke
                    responded that some reviewers have been with CDC since its establishment three
                    years ago. He added that the productivity and ability of each reviewer is
                    closely monitored; some reviewers have been let go for non-performance. The CDC
                    is not a “club” for former officers. It is usual for a new reviewer to start
                    with mandatory review and then move into the systematic review program if he is
                    satisfactorily productive. Amb. Burke added that HO research on previous public
                    disclosure of sensitive information is very helpful to the CDC and might well be
                    given to the CDC at an earlier stage in the declassification process.</p>
                <p>Prof. Smith asked if information in U.S. documents about foreign governments is
                    reviewed by foreign governments in the same way that a foreign government’s own
                    documents are reviewed by them. Ambassador Burke answered that there is no
                    obligation to do so.</p>
                <p>Both Prof. Smith and Prof. Rosecrance asked why some foreign government
                    clearances take so long. Was it that the information is so sensitive, or is it
                    that the issue gets low priority in foreign ministries. Specifically, he
                    inquired about the holdup of certain documents in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>,
                    1952-1954, Volume V? Mr. Glennon explained that the problem seems to be one of
                    jurisdiction within the German Foreign Ministry. Mr. Pickering added that the
                    U.S. desk in the German Foreign Ministry has been asked to help resolve the
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Prof. Taylor expressed concern that in the 1960s, the U.S. began to have
                    relations with many smaller countries that will probably not have the resources
                    to respond to requests for permissions to print their documents. Mr. Glennon
                    responded that no procedure had been developed as yet for such an eventuality,
                    but that suggestions from the Committee were welcome. Mr. Slany added that
                    frequently the smaller foreign governments do not have adequate archives of
                    their own and thus do not have or cannot find their copy of the documents that
                    we want to publish. Examples of the problem have already begun to occur with
                    certain Middle Eastern countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gustafson asked whether the U.S. is required by law or international practice
                    to get permission to publish foreign government documents in the possession of
                    the State Department. Mr. Slany responded that since the 1920s the State
                    Department has in practice treated it as a legal obligation. Prof. Rosecrance
                    asked whether permission to print documents is requested from all governments or
                    only on a reciprocal basis. Amb. Burke replied that we ask permission only of
                    those governments with which the U.S. has “good” relations. Mr. Glennon added
                    that certain countries such as the Eastern bloc with strongly divergent
                    ideologies are not asked for clearance.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at noon for luncheon.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Afternoon Session</hi></p>
                <p>The meeting resumed at 2:15 p.m.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany called on Neal Petersen to report on our renewed and rejuvenated
                    policy-related historical research program.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Adviser on Research</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen reported that the Office of the Historian performs historical
                    research for the Department of State and for publication. Since World War II,
                    the office has prepared almost 1,300 studies and memoranda, most upon direct
                    request of Department officials. This research has ranged from brief papers on
                    specific historical questions to multi-volume studies on broad policy issues.
                    The research and analysis has focused on historical treatment of U.S. policy as
                    opposed to more present-oriented analyses of conditions in foreign countries
                    performed by the Bureau of Intelligence and Research. The work constitutes the
                    institutional memory of the Department of State.</p>
                <p>The historical research for the Department of State has been varied. The Office
                    has produced studies on bilateral relations with other countries such as Gabon
                    and China, studies on major foreign policy issues such as the Middle East
                    controversy, administrative histories of offices and bureaus; narratives dealing
                    with crisis management in such cases as the <hi rend="underline">Pueblo</hi>
                    incident, and regularly updated reference works such as U.S. defense commitments
                    and foreign travel of U.S. presidents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen reported HO studies played a role in the Department’s policy-making
                    process. For example, in 1979, HO prepared a study on congressional constraints
                    on the conduct of U.S. foreign affairs for the Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs. At the time of the invasion of Afghanistan, the White House
                    consulted an HO study on the U.S. response to the invasion of Czechoslovakia in
                    1968 and developed courses of action based on that earlier experience.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen also stated that HO also produces books, articles, and briefs for
                    publication. Salient examples are the major joint documentary <hi rend="italic"
                        >The United States and Russia: The Beginning of Relations, 1765-1815</hi>,
                    published in 1980, articles on terrorism and other subjects published in the
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Short History of the Department of State</hi> which appeared both as a <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> supplement and a separate publication. In
                    addition, the Office staff field hundreds of requests and questions of a
                    historical nature each year from the Department, other agencies, and the
                    public.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen went on to recount some of the more significant projects completed
                    in the last five years: U.S. Policy Toward the People’s Republic of China,
                    1950-1951, Human Rights Since 1945, U.S. Foreign Economic Policy, Women in the
                    American Foreign Service, Quadripartite Berlin Negotiations of 1954-1961, and
                    the South African Nuclear Problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen listed many of the nearly thirty research projects and memoranda
                    that have been completed in the past year. These included articles on early
                    bilateral relations with the Netherlands, Bulgaria, and Yugoslavia; a
                    publication on the diplomatic implications of the Battle of Yorktown in
                    connection with the bicentennial celebration; a brief history of the Department
                    of State; an article on the construction of the Berlin Wall for use in marking
                    the 20th anniversary of that event; a study of bilateral relations with Gabon
                    for use by the U.S. Ambassador-designate; a study of the response of NATO to the
                    Hungarian Revolution of 1956 and the Czechoslovak crisis of 1968; an examination
                    of U.S. base rights in the Azores; studies of U.S. organization for crisis
                    management since World War II, and the economic summits of the past decade.
                    Recently, the Office compiled and indexed an extensive documentary compilation
                    on negotiations leading to the release of U.S. hostages by Iran.</p>
                <p>He reported that the Office is now in the process of expanding and upgrading its
                    research function. He said we hope to launch a number of classified
                    policy-related projects and to establish a systematic oral history program. He
                    declared that the upgraded program would conform to the following
                    principles:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>It would be responsive to the needs of the Department and at least some
                        aspects of it should be more directly policy-related. More concise, timely
                        papers should be written for direct input in the policy process.</item>
                    <item>Certain work must attempt to anticipate critical situations, although HO
                        must always engage in detailed consultations with consumers before
                        consigning resources to a project.</item>
                    <item>The program would take into account the mission of the Bureau of Public
                        Affairs. This entails relating work to PA priority issues and producing more
                        publications on the historical background of current issues.</item>
                    <item>Part of the program should involve more timely transfer of studies to the
                        Archives following declassification.</item>
                    <item>The Office would avoid being constrained by old modes of operation and
                        formats, adopt a flexible approach, and continue to engage in a variety of
                        research activities.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Petersen stated that HO believes that our intensified research program would
                    benefit the scholarly community and the public at large as well as the
                    Department of State, and he asked for the Advisory Committee’s support.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gaddis Smith asked if HO had a special staff to deal with these research
                    requests. Mr. Petersen replied that we did not. He explained that the Office was
                    divided into geographical divisions, and that the request was usually assigned
                    to the Division most qualified to handle it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany added that the Office’s new research program would also aid in
                    declassification of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He stated
                    that in the past few years HO had lost contact with the Bureaus in the
                    Department. By embarking on an expanded and more relevant historical research
                    program HO would reestablish contact and gain credibility for itself and the use
                    of history in the Department of State. In doing so, it would help break down the
                    adversary relationship between HO and the Bureaus which recent declassification
                    differences had served to create.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Prof. Smith, Mr. Slany explained that there was
                    not a direct cause and effect relationship between the creation of the CDC and
                    the development of this adversary relationship. On the contrary, he suggested
                    that the problem predated the creation of the CDC. The <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, he pointed out, was attempting to document some of
                    the more sensitive episodes in the history of American foreign policy. To the
                    extent that HO does its job well -- and he stressed that HO believed it was
                    doing it quite well -- problems are inevitably encountered during the
                    declassification process.</p>
                <p>Prof. May asked how HO found out what Bureaus needed to know? Mr. Petersen said
                    we found out through personal contacts, through attendance at staff meetings,
                    and through the PA leadership. Mr. Slany added we needed to gain greater access
                    to staff officers. Currently, HO was definitely outside of what is going on in
                    the Department.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Ambassador U. Alexis Johnson</p>
                <p>Former Ambassador and Under Secretary of State U. Alexis Johnson, who had joined
                    the meeting, offered a critique of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    vol. XVI, 1952-54, The Geneva Conference. His presentation, Mr. Slany explained,
                    would be an attempt to assess how well the series was doing what it wanted to
                    do: to document the development and implementation of U.S. foreign policy. Amb.
                    Johnson first offered some general comments on the volume. He indicated that the
                    selection of material was good, noting that he could not think of anything
                    significant which was omitted. He did note that the volume did not include much
                    documentation on intelligence matters, and stressed that a key factor is what
                    intelligence the President and Secretary of State are being given to read each
                    morning. Within the constraints of available material the volume was
                    comprehensive. He did note, however, that because the United States was not the
                    principal actor at the Geneva Conference on Indochina, the U.S. documentation on
                    the conference was necessarily incomplete. On the question of selectivity, he
                    said that he did not see how HO could do a better job than it has been doing.
                    Amb. Johnson recalled his own role at the Conference, his talks with Chinese
                    representative Wang Ping-nan, his relationship with Secretary John Foster
                    Dulles, his habit of always having his phone conversations monitored, and
                    various thoughts about the manner in which things get done effectively in
                    Washington. In response to a question from Mr. Slany about the organization of
                    documents into a separate volume on the Geneva Conference, Amb. Johnson said
                    that he did not see any alternative ways of presenting with the material. He did
                    suggest that it would be very valuable for historians to know who had drafted
                    the documents, who had signed and cleared them, and particularly who had read
                    them. He felt that long documents tend not to be read by busy officials. He
                    always favored short documents himself.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked how HO could get access to more accurate records of meetings or
                    conferences. Ambassador Johnson suggested we could get the Secretariat to make a
                    record after the event or crisis, but that it was not reasonable for HO to
                    expect to be in on the crisis management meetings of an event and expect policy
                    makers to make decisions with HO members present. Mr. Slany asked if we should
                    supplement the written documents with oral testimony from the participants. The
                    Ambassador said yes. He added that chronologies of events would also be useful
                    in the volumes.</p>
                <p>Report on <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> series</p>
                <p>Mr. Claussen gave a presentation on the recently resumed publication: <hi
                        rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Basic Documents</hi>. This resumed
                    publication was a project repeatedly recommended by previous Advisory
                    Committees. In recent weeks the greater part of the HO staff had been committed
                    to the preparation of a volume covering the years 1977-1980. Mr. Claussen noted
                    that the necessary time away from the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series was a trade-off which would result in a publication of use to academics
                    and policy makers. He said the <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy:
                        Current Documents</hi> project was also a production experiment which would,
                    if successful, have application to the more efficient preparation of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. There was a good chance, he
                    pointed out, that the 1977-1980 volume would be out in early 1982. Mr. Claussen
                    stressed the important non-State Department sources that were being used in the
                    series, explaining that approximately 75 to 90 per cent of the material used in
                    these volumes (excluding the 1977-80 volume) would not have appeared previously
                    in the Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>. He also discussed
                    the prospects for a microfiche supplement to cover important documents that
                    could not fit into the printed volume. Mr. Claussen emphasized that HO wanted
                    the Committee’s views on the <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> volumes,
                    noting that the renewal of the series was an experiment. HO’s thrust, he added,
                    was toward the greatest number of users; he noted that people all over the world
                    would use the volume, especially in the Third World.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Final Remarks</p>
                <p>Mr. Taylor asked whether HO’s expanded activities -- <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi>, the intensified research program, etc. -- were coming at the
                    expense of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany responded that initially they were. But he noted that these expanded
                    activities would not affect the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes between now and 1985 because all the volumes
                    scheduled for publication during that period are already completed. He explained
                    that HO’s expanded activities in other areas would only affect the series if HO
                    did not resume compiling at even a moderate rate by sometime in 1981. Mr. Slany
                    was sure that this would not happen. Mr. Slany said his goal was to help HO
                    survive within the State Department. He also noted that while his colleagues in
                    HO were not currently working on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> on any
                    significant scale, and would probably not be doing so for the next few months,
                    they would resume compiling sometime in 1982.</p>
                <p>Prof. Taylor stated that he gathered that HO was not unhappy with the CDC. He
                    asked if HO’s position was that it could work with the CDC, and that CDC was
                    better than what existed before.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany agreed with Mr. Taylor’s observations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then asked the Chairman whether he would like to hold a private meeting
                    of the Committee. He offered to stand by to answer any questions.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Users Survey</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon asked the Committee members to respond to the draft <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> Users Survey in their briefing material after they
                    returned home. He pointed out that some of the questions in the survey, such as
                    those concerning the 20-year line, would have to be reformulated.</p>
                <p>Prof. Smith asked what was the anticipated circulation of the Survey.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon replied that it would be sent to 2,000 members of the professional
                    societies. The Advisory Committee was the first presample group to see it.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Adjournment</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 4:05 p.m. so that the Committee could meet
                    privately.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
