<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Office of the Historian Research Project on Department of
                    State Publication of Foreign Government Documents, June 1981</title>
                <title type="short">Kogan FGI Study (RP 1261), 1981</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-27">January 27, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1981-06">June 1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1981-06-kogan-fgi-study-rp1261.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 3.34 MB, 25pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Research Projects File, 1955-2011 (Lot File 13 D 289), Box 7,
                    R.P. No. 1261: Department of State Publication of Foreign Government Documents.
                    Documents cited in the study were present, but are not posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 6, <ref
                    target="../chapter-6#fn22">Footnote 22</ref>; Chapter 7, Footnote <ref
                    target="../chapter-7#fn65">65</ref>; and Chapter 9, Footnotes <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn66">66</ref> and <ref target="../chapter-9#fn67"
                >67</ref>.</p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Office of the Historian Research Project on Department of State Publication of
                    Foreign Government Documents</head>
                <dateline>June 1981</dateline>
                <p rend="center">Research Project No. 1261</p>
                <p rend="center">Arthur G. Kogan<lb/>(edited by David F. Trask and David M.
                    Baehler)</p>
                <p rend="center">Office of the Historian<lb/>Bureau of Public Affairs<lb/>Department
                    of State</p>
                <p rend="center">DEPARTMENT OF STATE PUBLICATION OF FOREIGN GOVERNMENT DOCUMENTS</p>
                <p>A. <hi rend="underline">Early Policies and Procedures</hi></p>
                <p>In the course of the late 19th and early 20th century the United States gradually
                    accepted the European practice of not publishing diplomatic papers received from
                    foreign governments without their consent except in the case of war. The
                    principle of foreign government consent to publication, however, was not
                    “definitely and conclusively written into international law”; it rested “upon
                    comity and reciprocity and not upon international legislation.”<note n="1"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn1">E. Wilder Spaulding, “Consent to the Publication of
                        Diplomatic Papers,” <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Year Book</hi> 1951,
                        pp. 33–40.</note> Although the United States observed the principle in the
                    case of papers involving negotiations, it apparently did not ask foreign
                    governments for permission to print their documents until 1919. Publication of a
                    number of notes from foreign governments in the <hi rend="italic">Digest of
                        International Law</hi> compiled by Green H. Hackworth, Legal Adviser of the
                    Department of State, without requesting the permission of foreign governments is
                    another indication that the United States did not accept the rule of previous
                    consent to the release of documents in every instance.<note n="2" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn2">E. R. Perkins, “Foreign Relations of the United States,” “<hi
                            rend="italic">The Department of State Bulletin</hi>, December 22, 1952,
                        pp. 1002–1007; Spaulding, <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.</note></p>
                <p>The principle of obtaining permission to publish the diplomatic papers of other
                    governments was incorporated into Secretary of State Frank B. Kellogg’s
                    directive of March 26, 1925, setting forth the principles to be observed in the
                    publication of the Department’s documentary series <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS). According to this directive, the
                    Chief of the Division of Publication, who at that time was responsible for the
                    preparation of volumes in FRUS, was expected “to initiate, through the
                    appropriate channels, the correspondence necessary to secure from a foreign
                    government permission to publish any document received from it and which it is
                    desired to publish as a part of the diplomatic correspondence of the United
                        States.”<note n="3" place="end" xml:id="fn3">Printed in FRUS, 1914,
                        Supplement I, III–IV.</note> For many years subsequent revisions of
                    Kellogg’s directive did not alter the substance of this provision. Department of
                    State Regulation 2 FAM 1350, issued June 15, 1961, setting forth the principles
                    currently guiding the compilation and editing of FRUS provided that “the
                    Historical Office shall refer to the appropriate foreign governments requests
                    for permission to print as part of the diplomatic correspondence of the United
                    States those previously unpublished documents which were originated by the
                    foreign governments.”<note n="4" place="end" xml:id="fn4">Printed in FRUS, 1942,
                        Volume IV, <hi rend="italic">The Near East and Africa</hi>, III–IV.</note>
                    On January 13, 1981, however, the Foreign Affairs Manual was revised to vest
                    this function in the Office of Systematic Review, a part of the
                    Classification/Declassification Center. The relevant passage provides that “In
                    coordination with the responsible geographic bureaus, determines whether
                    material referred by the Historical Office (<hi rend="underline">sic</hi>)
                    containing foreign government information should be the subject of communication
                    with the foreign government which provided the information, and undertakes such
                    communication if and when deemed appropriate.” (1 FAM 247.2)</p>
                <p>At a very early stage the question was raised whether consent of foreign
                    governments was required only in the case of publication of documents originated
                    by a foreign government or also in other cases where the documents dealt with
                    matters of interest to foreign governments. In May 1926 Margaret Hanna, Chief of
                    the Office of Coordination, reflecting the views of the Office of the Solicitor,
                    stated that it was Department practice “as an international courtesy to request
                    foreign government permission before publication of a foreign communication and
                    to advise the other government in advance whenever we propose to publish one of
                    our own communications which may deal with a delicate or much discussed
                        question.”<note n="5" place="end" xml:id="fn5">Memorandum by Hanna (office
                        of Coordination and Review), May 20, 1926. (File 811.114/4517)</note></p>
                <p>Dr. Tyler Dennett, Chief of the Division of Publication responsible for the
                    preparation of the FRUS, was apparently concerned that a policy of seeking
                    foreign government permission to publish correspondence originated in the
                    Department of State might establish a dangerous precedent for FRUS and “would
                    surrender too much in principle.” Subsequently, however, Dennett acknowledged
                    that a distinction was to be made between a “delicate or much discussed
                    question” and the “routine publication of a general resume” of the
                    correspondence in FRUS. While Dennett was strongly in favor of doing “whatever
                    is necessary in delicate negotiations to preserve the international courtesies”
                    he emphasized that it had not been the practice of the Department “to ask
                    formally for the privilege of publishing correspondence originating in the
                    Department in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.” In fact, in the case of
                    some countries deemed “rather reluctant to have the facts published,” the
                    department had even gone so far as to intimate “that it proposed to publish its
                    own correspondence and that every one would be better satisfied to have both
                    sides of the story told.” Dennett was willing to concede that in one or another
                    case the Department might agree not to publish some of its own correspondence at
                    the request of another government and that it had so decided in the past. But he
                    was convinced that “if we were to concede to these countries the right to
                    indicate what the Department should include in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> the differences of opinion would be considerable and the
                    possibility of publishing a record sufficient fully to explain the policy of the
                    United States would be well-nigh impossible.”<note n="6" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn6">Memoranda by Dennett (Division of Publication), May 12, 1926
                        and May 25, 1926. (File 811.114/4517)</note></p>
                <p>Discussions about whether to obtain the consent of foreign governments for
                    publication of documents other than those originated by the foreign governments
                    continued in the Department, although the policy for obtaining consent for the
                    publication of foreign-originated documents only was clearly set forth in the
                    Kellogg directive of 1925 and subsequent revisions thereof. One particular type
                    of Department of State correspondence stood in the center of these discussions,
                    namely memoranda and reports by American officials of conversations with
                    representatives of foreign governments.</p>
                <p>On March 10, 1927, Dennett set forth the reasons underlying the Department’s
                    policy of not asking consent to the publication of the Department’s own records
                    of conversations with foreign officials. Under Secretary of State Joseph C. Grew
                    read this memorandum in part to the British Ambassador, and it met with the
                    Ambassador’s approval. The principal arguments against seeking the consent of
                    foreign governments to the publication of this type of document were these:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. It would badly encumber the work of editing since all correspondence
                        would have to be scrutinized with reference to the claims of each government
                        and requests for permission to print would therefore have to include many
                        more documents than were currently submitted.</item>
                    <item>2. One government ought not to be placed in the position of having to give
                        approval to the reports made to another government by the latter’s own
                        representative.</item>
                    <item>3. Each government should assume the entire responsibility for the
                        publication of correspondence originating among its own
                            representatives.<note n="7" place="end" xml:id="fn7">Memorandum by
                            Dennett (Division of Publication), March 10, 1927 (763.72119.12298 cited
                            in memorandum by E. Wilder Spaulding, Division of Research and
                            Publication, Mar. 11, 1940.) (FW 026 Foreign Relations*)</note></item>
                </list>
                <p>Although the Department continued to reaffirm its policy of not submitting
                    reports of conversations to foreign governments, as it did in correspondence
                    with the Japanese Government in 1935, in some instances it requested the
                    permission of foreign governments to publish such reports. According to a
                    memorandum of March 1, 1940, by Dr. E. Wilder Spaulding, Chief of the Division
                    of Research and Publication, however, submission of a few such reports had
                    recently involved the Department in some difficulties, especially with Chile,
                    which refused to authorize publication of four reports of conversation for the
                    reason “that there is no record in the archives of the Ministry of the
                    conversations in question.” Accordingly Dr. Spaulding had proposed to Assistant
                    Secretary of State Breckinridge Long that the Division of Research and
                    Publication follow the Department’s practice “as far it seemed practicable” of
                    refraining from submitting such reports of conversations to foreign governments.
                    At the same time Spaulding requested that Assistant Secretary Long approve
                    submission of reports of conversations “in exceptional cases when the great
                    importance or the expressed confidential character of the reports seemed to us
                    to make that course desirable.<note n="8" place="end" xml:id="fn8">Memorandum by
                        Spaulding (Division of Research and Publication) to Long (A–L), Mar. 1, 1940
                        (FW 026 Foreign Relations 1456).</note>”</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="underline">Challenge to the Policy: The Mexican Case, 1957–1962
                        Mexican Concerns and Initial Department Reactions, 1957–1961</hi></p>
                <p>A specific challenge to the established policy of generally not clearing reports
                    of conversations with foreign officials with the foreign governments concerned
                    arose in the late 1950s when certain concerns expressed by Mexican officials
                    prompted the Office of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs (CMA) and the Bureau of
                    Inter-American Affairs (ARA) to attempt changing the Department’s policy in such
                    a way that henceforth the consent of foreign governments would have to be
                    obtained for the publication of certain U.S. documents. The Historical Division
                    and the Bureau of Public affairs strongly resisted these attempts, and the
                    intradepartmental controversy over this issue was not settled until 1962.</p>
                <p>On August 15, 1957, Robert C. Hill, American Ambassador to Mexico, reported
                    having been told by “a prominent Mexican Government official” that the latter
                    “shuddered” whenever he read in the papers “excerpts from recently published
                    volumes on United States foreign relations.” Citing references therein to his
                    political ambitions, the Mexican official commented that Americans had a
                    tendency “to reduce everything to writing and send it on to Washington.” Thus,
                    speaking “in a frank and friendly fashion” with American officials might some
                    day “have the result of my political downfall.” The Mexican official felt that
                    the speed of the publication of the FRUS volumes “is a sort of a nightmare
                    because I never know when my own name may hit the headlines again.” In
                    forwarding this report Ambassador Hill stated that the Department might find
                    interesting these comments by a Mexican friend of the United States “who felt
                    justified in raising that issue.”<note n="9" place="end" xml:id="fn9">From
                        Mexico City, Despatch 180, Aug. 15, 1957, confidential.</note></p>
                <p>The Department’s response of October 8, 1957, to Ambassador Hill, drafted in the
                    Historical Division (HS) and cleared by the Mexican Desk, first clarified that
                    the specific references attributed to FRUS by the Mexican official were actually
                    contained in the published record of a Senate hearing rather than in FRUS. As
                    for the basic issue raised in the Ambassador’s despatch, namely the concern over
                    “possible unfavorable reactions from the publication of records of conversations
                    with officials of a foreign government,” it called for “sound judgement and a
                    well-informed understanding of the situations involved.”</p>
                <p>On one hand, the Department’s regulations and long established practice committed
                    it to the publication of “a substantially complete record of the diplomatic
                    activities of the United States including the facts which contributed to the
                    formulation of policies.” On the other hand, the Department was “obligated to
                    preserve the confidence imposed in it by individuals and by foreign
                    governments.” Since so much of diplomacy was carried on in conversations and so
                    much of the information upon which action was taken came in the form of reports
                    of conversations, it was evident “that no substantially complete record could be
                    published if such reports were excluded.” Under the Department’s practice,
                    however, “strictly personal references of a derogatory character . . . are not
                    included and quoted statements of responsible officials are submitted for
                    clearance.”</p>
                <p>It was also pointed out in the Department’s response that “with the lapse of time
                    much that was confidential at the moment obviously ceases to have that
                    character.” The compilers of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had this
                    situation in mind, and appropriate policy officers carefully reviewed the
                    galleys before final printing. Over a period of many years very few specific
                    complaints about FRUS had come to the Department’s attention, although from time
                    to time “there has been apprehension of what might happen.” Summarizing the
                    Department’s position, it was stated in the instruction that the Department’s
                    practice was to submit to foreign governments for clearance prior to publication
                    in FRUS “only previously unpublished documents originating with the government
                    concerned, or which directly quote unpublished statements by foreign officials.”
                    The Department, the instruction continued, “reserves the right of publishing its
                    own documents, but . . . only after careful consideration of the issues
                    involved. “<note n="10" place="end" xml:id="fn10">To Mexico City, Department
                        instruction A–208, Oct. 8, 1957, confidential.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">ARA Recommendation for Changes in the Clearance
                        Procedures</hi></p>
                <p>The Department’s instruction of October 8, 1957, apparently did not assuage the
                    concern of American officials dealing with Mexican Affairs, although it had been
                    drafted in the Historical Division and had received the concurrence of the ARA
                    Bureau. That Bureau appears to have adopted as its own the view previously held
                    by the Ambassador in Mexico that Department of State documents reporting
                    conversations with foreign officials should not be published without prior
                    clearance with those officials or their governments.</p>
                <p>Following some earlier exchanges with the Historical Division, Melville Osborne,
                    of the office of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs (CMA) on September 22, 1958,
                    requested G. Bernard Noble, Chief of the Historical Division, to comment upon a
                    CMA recommendation for a change in the Department’s policy, which would require
                    foreign government clearance for publication of records of conversations with
                    foreign officials. Osborne indicated that the recommendation by his Office was
                    being made for the following reasons:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Mexican officials were reluctant to confide in American
                        representatives, knowing that records of their conversations “may be
                        published by the United States at will.” There had been some instance when a
                        Mexican official had wanted to excise parts of records of conversations
                        prepared by U.S. officials, because the officials preferred “not to have in
                        writing certain statements he had made,” even though the record “fully and
                        accurately outlined the substance of the discussions.”</item>
                    <item>2. It was inconsistent to clear the publication of documents originating
                        with foreign governments but to ignore the views of foreign governments on
                        records containing “the confidences and frequently independently expressed
                        opinions of their officials.” Courtesy required consultation in both
                        cases.</item>
                    <item>3. Memoranda and despatches concerning such conversations were much more
                        likely to contain material whose release might be injurious to a foreign
                        government official. Its release ought not to depend exclusively on the
                        judgment of Department of State officials.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In arguing his case Osborne took pains to emphasize that he had no quarrel with
                    the desire to publish a substantially complete record of major U.S. foreign
                    policy decisions and that the objectives of his office and those of the
                    Historical Division were the same despite differences in their respective
                    responsibilities. He also stressed that material should not be excluded from
                    FRUS “merely because it reveals elements of conflict or friction.” But it was
                    impossible for any office in the Department to assess the “unfortunate
                    repercussions” of the Department’s publications in U.S. foreign relations or to
                    assess the extent to which confidences had been violated as a result of
                    publication.</p>
                <p>Osborne also wished to have it understood that clearance of records of
                    conversation should not be made a matter of right or law but rather of courtesy
                    of the kind already practiced in clearing exchanges of correspondence. There was
                    no doubt that the documents involved were “our documents,” but possession or
                    ownership neither determined the issue nor was pertinent to it.</p>
                <p>Finally, Osborne was willing to recognize that the suggested new procedure would
                    create additional problems. It might result in eliminating in advance from the
                    record of conversations to be cleared anything that might be offensive or “that
                    we might for any other reasons not want a foreign government to see.” Also,
                    clearance might be interpreted to mean approval. Such an implication might be
                    avoided, however, by explaining to a foreign government “that we were not
                    seeking its approval of publication or of the accuracy of the record” but that
                    it was merely being consulted to learn “if there might be any objection to
                    publication of the document at that particular time.” If a government merely
                    objected because it had no record or a different record of the conversation, it
                    would have to be informed that publication could not be deferred for those
                        reasons.<note n="11" place="end" xml:id="fn11">Memorandum by Osborne (CMA)
                        to Noble (HD), Sept. 22, 1958, official use only.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">The Historical Division’s Opposition to the CMA
                        Proposal</hi></p>
                <p>In a memorandum of November 3, 1958, G. Bernard Noble, Chief of the Historical
                    Division (HD), took issue with the position set forth in Osborne’s memorandum of
                    September 22. Noble declared that the suggested extension of clearance practices
                    “would be most unfortunate in circumscribing the freedom of our Government to
                    publish its official records”. In commenting on the specific points made by
                    Osborne, Noble’s memorandum adopted a line of argument that became the
                    “classical” statement of the position of the Historical Division’s historians on
                    this issue.</p>
                <p>Noble denied that the Historical Division was inconsistent in its practice of
                    clearing with foreign governments papers that they had originated and not
                    clearing with those governments records made by American diplomatic officials of
                    conversations with foreign government officials. Noble insisted that these two
                    types of documents fell into entirely different categories. The former
                    represented official government statements for which the originating government
                    must assume responsibility. Therefore, to obtain clearance from that government
                    was entirely proper. An American official’s record of a conversation with a
                    foreign official, however, was “our own document for which the other government
                    need assume no responsibility.” Moreover, the foreign official might have been
                    speaking on his own rather than representing an official government point of
                    view. It could also be said, if the issue was raised, that the report was merely
                    “the interpretation of the American officer reporting.”</p>
                <p>Noble believed that the concern seemed to be exaggerated that foreign officials
                    would not talk freely “for fear (that) a report of the conversation may be
                    published some fifteen or more years hence.” Even if that danger existed it
                    seemed doubtful, however, that a foreign government clearance would be the
                    remedy because permission to print would be requested not from the individual
                    whose conversation was reported but from officials of the foreign office of the
                    country concerned at the time of clearance. To put the report in the hands of a
                    foreign office official might be as damaging as to publish it in FRUS, where at
                    least it would be presented in a proper context. Noble adduced arguments that
                    were of a practical nature but that also involved principles. Foreign government
                    clearance of American parts of conversations would often put the American side
                    in the dilemma of presenting for clearance small items of conversation out of
                    context or of presenting the entire document containing the reported statements
                    as well as additional comments by the reporting American official. This in
                    effect “would often give a right of censorship to the foreign government over
                    the entire document” in a case where the real objection might be to the American
                    comment rather than to the reported statement of the foreign official. This
                    would not have to be stated by the foreign government objecting to the
                    clearance.</p>
                <p>Noble also took issue with the suggestion in the ARA memorandum that if a foreign
                    government objected to a document submitted for clearance on the grounds that it
                    had no record of the conversation or that its own record of it differed “we
                    should have to inform it that we could not defer publication for these reasons.”
                    He felt that such a course would not be practical and that submitting a document
                    to a foreign government and then publishing it over its objections would cause
                    far more resentment than publishing it without asking for clearance.
                    Furthermore, it seemed doubtful that publication of an American report of a
                    conversation with a foreign official without obtaining clearance would
                    necessarily be contrary to the wishes of the foreign government. There was a
                    real difference between giving consent to publication and having no objection to
                    publication done on the responsibility of another government. Moreover, timid
                    officials of foreign governments would probably hesitate to give approval to
                    publication “in the vague fear that there might be some repercussions for which
                    they would be held responsible.”</p>
                <p>Noble conceded that there might be exceptions to this long-standing rule that
                    U.S. reports of conversations with foreign officials would normally not be
                    submitted to foreign governments for clearance. He mentioned in this connection
                    “significant and apparently damaging quoted passages from statements of foreign
                    officials.” A distinction could appropriately be drawn between documents
                    reporting conversations in direct quotations and others merely reporting the
                    substance of conversations. The former might be submitted for clearance, but not
                    the latter, which merely paraphrased the substance of the conversation as
                    interpreted by the writer. In exceptional cases even paraphrased reports might
                    be submitted for foreign government clearance, for instance, if they represented
                    agreed minutes of conference discussions. There might be other cases where
                    “shrewd judgment” might require such reports to be submitted for clearance or
                    for information. Finally, Noble stressed that no hard and fast line could be
                    drawn in cases of this kind, and that “tough-minded judgment” had to be
                    exercised.</p>
                <p>In summary, a general requirement that all documents reporting conversations with
                    foreign officials had to be submitted to foreign government for clearance would
                    not only be contrary to long-established practice but frequently cause
                    “unnecessary embarrassments” in our relations with such governments and would
                    also “vastly complicate” the editing and publishing of FRUS.</p>
                <p>In forwarding his memorandum to Osborne, Noble expressed the hope for an early
                    discussion of this matter with him. He took the opportunity to invite Osborne or
                    any other representative of the ARA Bureau to attend the forthcoming meeting of
                    the Advisory Committee on Foreign Relations, where the matter would be
                        discussed.<note n="12" place="end" xml:id="fn12">Memorandum by Noble (HD) to
                        Osborne (CMA), November 4, 1958, with attached Memorandum from Noble to
                        Osborne, “Clearance with Foreign Governments of Reports of Conversations
                        with Foreign Officials prior to publication “Foreign Relations of the United
                        States”, Nov. 3, official use only.</note> The Advisory Committee, however,
                    in its session of November 7, 1958, dealt only briefly with the subject; it had
                    been arranged beforehand that no decisions relating to this subject would be
                    taken at the meeting. The principal objective seemed to have been to acquaint
                    the Committee members with the position taken by the Historical Division on the
                    matter. It was somewhat surprising that several Department officers representing
                    geographic and functional bureaus were quite sceptical as to the wisdom of
                    submitting memoranda of conversations to foreign governments for clearance and
                    that their expressed views were not greatly different from the HD position.<note
                        n="13" place="end" xml:id="fn13">Extracts from the Minutes of the Second
                        Annual Session, Advisory Committee on the “Foreign Relations of the United
                        States,” November 7, 1958.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Failure to Resolve the Conflict</hi></p>
                <p>On January 21, 1959, a meeting was held in the office of Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Public Affairs Edwin Kretzmann. Osborne and T.R. Martin
                    represented the views of the Office of Caribbean and Mexican Affairs and
                    reiterated the arguments set forth in Osborne’s memorandum of September 22,
                    1958. Kretzmann supported the position argued in Noble’s memorandum of November
                    3, 1958. No progress was made toward an agreement on these issues. At the
                    conclusion of the meeting Kretzmann directed Noble to prepare a memorandum
                    setting forth once more the objections to foreign government clearance of U.S.
                    memoranda of conversations with foreign officials. Such a memorandum would be
                    sent to CMA after approval by Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
                    Andrew Berding. If CMA did not agree, “the material would be referred to higher
                    authority for further decision.”<note n="14" place="end" xml:id="fn14"
                        >Memorandum by Perkins (HD) of Conversation among Kretzmann (P), Noble (HD),
                        Perkins (HD), Osborne (CMA), T.R. Martin (CMA), and Lee (ARA), Jan. 21,
                        1959.</note> Noble submitted the requested memorandum on January 29.
                    Essentially, this paper reaffirmed in an abbreviated version the position
                    spelled out in great detail in Noble’s earlier memorandum of November 3, 1958.
                    The memorandum of January 29 cautioned, in addition, against submitting papers
                    to foreign governments of countries “where the traditions are against the
                    regular and systematic publication of diplomatic papers” and expressed doubts
                    that the possibility of publishing certain remarks after 15 years could prevent
                    a foreign official “from making an honest presentation of his Government’s
                        case.”<note n="15" place="end" xml:id="fn15">Memorandum by Noble (HD) to
                        Kretzmann (P), “Clearance by Foreign Governments of Records of Conversations
                        by American Diplomatic Officials with Foreign Government Officials prior to
                        Publication of ‘Foreign Relations of the United States,’” Jan. 29,
                        1959.</note></p>
                <p>ARA considered Kretzmann’s position a rejection of its own proposal and refrained
                    from appealing the decision because it was not in a position “to prove its
                    contention that the publication of such material was harmful.” This fact emerges
                    from a memorandum of December 4, 1961, sent to Deputy Under Secretary for
                    Political Affairs U. Alexis Johnson by Robert Woodward, Assistant Secretary of
                    State for Inter-American Affairs, discussed below.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Resumption and Resolution of the Controversy: The Mexican
                        Case, 1961–1962</hi></p>
                <p>The memorandum of December 4, 1961, represented a renewed attempt of the Bureau
                    of Inter-American Affairs to change the Department’s policy of not submitting
                    U.S. memoranda of conversations with foreign government officials to the foreign
                    governments for clearance prior to publication in FRUS. In resuming the
                    argument, Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs Robert
                    Woodward reviewed the history of the controversy and explained, as noted above,
                    why ARA had not continued the argument in 1959. Woodward then indicated that his
                    Bureau had decided to raise the issue again as a result of a recent despatch by
                    Ambassador Thomas C. Mann in Mexico, reporting statements by high Mexican
                    Government officials “that the biggest single obstacle to a confidential
                    exchange of classified information is the Department’s publication <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>.” Reporting these
                    Mexican concerns Ambassador Mann had added the comment that the Department’s
                    failure to respect the confidence of Mexican Government officials “for a period
                    of longer than ten or fifteen years” was a “serious determent” to a frank and
                    free exchange of information on matters of importance to the United States. In
                    the Ambassador’s view the United States paid a “high cost” for a service that
                    enabled historians to have early access to classified information.<note n="16"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn16">From Mexico City, despatch 386, Sept. 27, 1961,
                        Confidential.</note></p>
                <p>Thus, Assistant Secretary Woodward’s memorandum of December 1961 used Ambassador
                    Mann’s recently expressed concerns, based on talks with Mexican Government
                    officials, to buttress ARA’s long-held position that publication of reports of
                    conversations with foreign government officials without prior foreign government
                    clearance was harmful. In the light of Mann’s despatch, Woodward stated, “we can
                    no longer accept Mr. Kretzmann’s decision without further consideration.” Citing
                    that despatch and reiterating the arguments that ARA had employed in the
                    1957–1959 exchanges with the Bureau of Public Affairs and the Historical
                    Division, Woodward now recommended to Deputy Under Secretary Johnson that the
                    Department adopt the policy “that no document that purports to be the record of
                    a conversation with a foreign official of a friendly government shall be
                    published without consultation with that government.”<note n="17" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn17">Memorandum by Woodward (ARA) to Johnson (G), “Publication of
                        Certain Records in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                            States</hi>,” Dec. 4, 1961, confidential.</note></p>
                <p>On January 3, 1962, Roger W. Tubby, Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                    Affairs, addressed a memorandum to U. Alexis Johnson that rejected the arguments
                    and recommendations put forth in Woodward’s paper of December 4, 1961. Tubby’s
                    memorandum represented a thorough presentation of the case of the Department’s
                    historians against the ARA proposal. G. Bernard Noble, Director of the
                    Historical Office and E. R. Perkins, Editor of FRUS, drafted the memorandum,
                    which went over much of the ground taken in Noble’s paper of November 3, 1958.
                    The argument was refined and brought up to date.</p>
                <p>Tubby’s memorandum emphasized at the outset that existing procedures assured “a
                    conservative clearance policy” applied by reviewing officers who would be most
                    unlikely to clear anything “that would give legitimate offense.” The memorandum
                    noted in this context that complaints, which were “very seldom raised,” tended
                    to be quite general in nature and failed to cite specific cases alleged to have
                    given offense. This was also true of Ambassador Mann’s despatch of September 27,
                    1961, cited in Woodward’s memorandum.</p>
                <p>The principal thrust of Tubby’s memorandum, however, was directed against the
                    whole concept of “consultation” with foreign governments prior to the
                    publication of memoranda of conversations by American officials with foreign
                    officials as recommended by the ARA Bureau. This concept was rejected for the
                    following reasons:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Consultations of the kind proposed would give foreign governments “a
                        veto on the publication of reports made by our officials.” The United States
                        could scarcely publish a memorandum of conversation submitted to another
                        government if that government had disapproved it. To give foreign
                        governments control over the publication of reports concerning them “could
                        seriously threaten the integrity of our diplomatic record.”</item>
                    <item>2. Tubby’s memorandum rejected ARA’s argument that if foreign governments
                        were consulted on the publication of documents which they had originated,
                        they should also be consulted on documents reporting conversations with
                        their officials. There was an essential difference between these two kinds
                        of papers inasmuch as the foreign government was assumed to take full
                        responsibility with respect to papers it had originated while publication of
                        reports by American officials on conversations were “our responsibility”
                        rather than a responsibility shared with a foreign government.</item>
                    <item>3. Consultation as proposed by ARA would rarely be a reliable check on the
                        accuracy of the reports considering that the latter dealt with events
                        “occurring approximately 20 (not 10 or 15) years previously.” The officials
                        who had participated in the conversations could rarely have been the ones
                        consulted and their record, if made, would doubtless differ in emphasis from
                        the American record. Frequently, the foreign government would have no record
                        of the conversation at all. Thus, the foreign government’s response would
                        not be based on the accuracy of the report but on its reaction “to the
                        report’s political tone.”</item>
                    <item>4. A foreign government might have no objection if the United States
                        published memoranda of conversations on its own responsibility, but it might
                        object “to assuming a share of the responsibility for something whose
                        accuracy or validity it could not check.”</item>
                    <item>5. The procedure of consultation proposed by ARA was given a trial in the
                        1930s but was quickly abandoned when one government refused agreement for
                        the publication of nine memoranda of conversations on the ground that it had
                        no record of such conversations.</item>
                    <item>6. The majority of reports of conversations with foreign officials also
                        contained comments of the reporting officers that the Department would not
                        wish to submit to foreign governments. Thus the choice would be either to
                        submit extracts of documents that could arouse suspicion or entire
                        documents. The latter course would give foreign officials an opportunity to
                        note publication in FRUS on the basis of the comments by American
                        officials.</item>
                </list>
                <p>These were the principal arguments presented in Assistant Secretary Tubby’s
                    memorandum of December 4. Other arguments dealt with the delay in the clearance
                    process as a result of a greatly increased number of documents submitted and of
                    greatly increased chances of disagreements.</p>
                <p>Summarizing the argument, Tubby’s memorandum took the position that the present
                    practice of not clearing memoranda of conversations with foreign officials was
                    sound and ought to be continued for the following reasons:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. The danger of a threat to the integrity of the American diplomatic
                        record because of the failure of some foreign governments to cooperate owing
                        to lack of records and inability to make comparisons, domestic political
                        considerations, or unwillingness to share in the responsibility for
                        publishing such reports.</item>
                    <item>2. Embarrassment to American relations with other powers, arising out of
                        delays in their clearance action, or because of arguments as to the accuracy
                        of the reports of conversations, or the effect of the veto by such powers on
                        publications by the Department of State.</item>
                    <item>3. The fact that the lag of publication behind currency had now reached
                        approximately 20 years, thus serving to reduce further any anxieties over
                        possible abuses.</item>
                    <item>4. The “overwhelmingly satisfactory and very seldom challenged experience
                        of the last century, and the absence of any specific cases of abuse as of
                        the present.”<note n="18" place="end" xml:id="fn18">Memorandum by Tubby (P)
                            to Johnson (G), “Proposed Consultation with Foreign Governments prior to
                            publication of Memoranda of Conversations with Foreign Officials.
                            Memorandum of Woodward, ARA, December 4, 1961,” Jan. 3,
                        1962.</note></item>
                </list>
                <p>On July 20, 1962, John C. Crimmins, Director of the Office of Caribbean and
                    Mexican Affairs, stated in a memorandum addressed to T. R. Martin of the Bureau
                    of Inter-American Affairs that “after careful study of the P (Tubby) memorandum,
                    meetings with officers of the Historical Office, and consultations with all the
                    ARA Office Directors,” he had come to the conclusion “that the weight of the
                    argument is in favor of the P position.” Crimmins therefore recommended that
                    Deputy Under Secretary Johnson be advised that ARA “was withdrawing its
                    memorandum of December 4, 1961.” All ARA Office Directors had concurred in this
                    recommendation. The same day Martin indicated in a memorandum to Johnson that
                    ARA wished to withdraw the recommendation of December 4, 1961, that no record of
                    a conversation with a foreign official of a friendly government should be
                    published without consultation with that government. Martin added the comment
                    that “the case developed by P is persuasive.”<note n="19" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn19">Memorandum by Crimmins (CMA) to Martin (ARA), “ARA Memorandum
                        to Mr. Johnson on Historical Office Difference of Opinion on the Publication
                        in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> of Records of Conversations with
                        Foreign Governments,” July 20, 1962, confidential; memorandum by Martin
                        (ARA) to Johnson (G), “Publication of Certain Records in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>,” July 20, 1962,
                        confidential.</note></p>
                <p>On July 31, 1962, Mark Lissfelt, staff assistant to the Deputy Under Secretary
                    for Political Affairs, informed Robert Manning, who had succeeded Roger Tubby as
                    Assistant Secretary of Public Affairs in April 1962, that the Deputy Under
                    Secretary “concurs in Mr. Martin’s recommendation that the case developed by P
                    is persuasive and therefore agrees to the withdrawal of the ARA recommendation
                    presented in ARA’s December 4, 1961, memorandum.”<note n="20" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn20">Memorandum by Lissfelt (G) to Manning (P) and Martin (ARA),
                        “Publication of Certain Records in <hi rend="italic">The Foreign Relations
                            of the United States</hi>,” July 31, 1962, Unclassified with
                        confidential attachment.</note> This appears to have been the end of the
                    efforts of officials of the ARA Bureau and the Office of Mexican Affairs to
                    change the Department’s policy of not submitting American memoranda of
                    conversations with foreign officials to foreign governments for clearance prior
                    to publication in FRUS.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="underline">The Challenge of the Executive Order</hi></p>
                <p>The resolution of the “Mexican Case” in 1962 had reaffirmed the traditional
                    policy of clearing foreign-originated documents with foreign governments, but
                    not American reports of conversations with foreign officials prior to
                    publication in FRUS. There is no evidence that this policy was challenged over
                    the next 16 years. There were always instances when Department officers before
                    clearing a U.S. document for publication in FRUS informally consulted foreign
                    government representatives, either in Washington or at a post, if they were
                    particularly concerned about a foreign government’s reaction. Such informal
                    consultation, however, did not imply that the approval of a foreign government
                    was requested but rather that the reviewing desk or bureau officers were seeking
                    additional information, enabling them to judge the sensitivity or releasability
                    of a given document.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">The Treatment of Unpublished Foreign Government
                        Documents</hi></p>
                <p>So far, the discussion of policies relating to the release of documents
                    originated by foreign governments or of interest to them has involved only those
                    which were to be published in FRUS. Indeed, for many years publication in FRUS
                    was the principal channel for release of any foreign policy documents from the
                    files of the Department of State, whatever the origin of the document. The only
                    other method of release was through special access to records by selected
                    scholars under tight control by the Department of State. Under these procedures
                    sensitive documents of any kind could easily be denied to the individual
                    researcher who had been granted access. This was particularly true in the case
                    of documents of a recent date. Following the establishment of the National
                    Archives in 1936, however, the Department began to transfer its older records to
                    the custody of that institution. The records prior to a specific date (at first,
                    1906) were considered to be generally open to the public and subject only to a
                    few restrictions on certain categories such as records relating to citizenship,
                    unsettled claims, and Foreign Service inspection. It should be noted that there
                    were no restrictions on documents received from foreign governments as far as
                    the “open” records were concerned. Records dated later than the open period
                    could likewise be made available to certain qualified researchers subject to
                    specific rules and restrictions. Regulations issued by the Department in 1938
                    and 1939 generally stipulated that files that could not be made public without
                    the disclosure of confidences reposed in the Department or without adversely
                    affecting the public interest should not be made available to researchers.
                    Moreover, papers received from a foreign government that had not been released
                    for publication should not be made available to outside researchers without the
                    consent of the concerned government.<note n="21" place="end" xml:id="fn21"
                        >Departmental Orders 751, Apr. 5, 1938, and 796, June 19, 1939 (Files;
                        “Access to Records-Basic File” in AGK Safe.)</note></p>
                <p>As more Department of State files were transferred to the National Archives, the
                    open period was extended beyond 1906 as was the subsequent period eventually
                    designated as “restricted” or “limited-access” period in which certain qualified
                    researchers were permitted to examine records under Department of State
                    procedures. As the opening dates for these periods advanced, the types of
                    restrictions remained essentially the same. Thus, only a few categories of
                    records of the kind mentioned above were restricted in the open period. Foreign
                    government records were not among them. The restricted type of access to records
                    beyond the open period granted to certain qualified researchers excluded
                    unpublished papers received from a foreign government unless that government
                    gave permission.</p>
                <p>By 1948 the Department had begun to distinguish between an “open” period that
                    extended through 1923, a “restricted” period that extended from January 1, 1923,
                    to January 1, 1933, and a “closed” period after January 1, 1933. Department of
                    State regulation 420.1 of March 12, 1948, made it clear that the records through
                    December 31, 1922, were open for inspection by the general public at the
                    National Archives subject to the regulations of that institution and to certain
                    restrictions on “records relating to the citizenship of individuals, unsettled
                    claims, and foreign service inspection and personnel records.” Again there was
                    no mention of restrictions on foreign government records in the open period.
                    Access to records of the restricted period, however, was granted only to certain
                    persons such as lawyers, journalists and scholars, subject to a number of
                    restrictions including one on unpublished papers received from a foreign
                    government. Such papers could be made available to researchers only with the
                    consent of the concerned government. If the Department agreed to request such
                    consent, the interested researchers had to meet the cost of communicating with
                    the foreign government.<note n="22" place="end" xml:id="fn22">Department of
                        State Regulation 420.1, Mar. 12, 1948.</note> The provisions with regard to
                    access to records and the pertinent restrictions generally continued as the
                    beginning dates of the open, restricted, and closed periods were gradually
                    advanced.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Restrictions on Foreign Classified Documents</hi></p>
                <p>In December 1957 the National Archives requested Department of State
                    authorization to declassify State documents prior to January 1, 1930. Although
                    the pre–1930 records had been open to researchers in the National Archives since
                    1956, the Archives needed declassification authority to be able to make copies
                    of previously security-classified items and not to have to place such items into
                    security units in the Archives. In a letter of January 8, 1958, the Department
                    provided the requested authorization for declassification of its pre–1930
                    records in the National Archives with the exception of the few previously
                    mentioned restricted categories and two new categories of papers, namely (1)
                    “files relating to the issuance and refusal of visas or permits to enter the
                    United States” and (2) “classified records originating in other Federal agencies
                    and furnished to the Department of State for its information.”<note n="23"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn23">Letter, Anderson (Division of Records Management)
                        to Lokke, (National Archives), Jan. 8, 1958.</note> On October 16, 1961,
                    however, the Department informed the National Archives that the 1958
                    authorization had not been intended “to include classified records originating
                    in foreign governments or international organizations and conferences of which
                    copies have been provided to the Department and are incorporated in its files.”
                    The Department therefore requested that records of this kind should be added to
                    the exceptions listed in the letter of January 1958.<note n="24" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn24">Letter, Simon (Division of Records Management) to Rhoads
                        (National Archives), Oct. 16, 1961.</note></p>
                <p>Henceforth classified foreign documents were included among the restricted
                    categories of records listed in special “Restrictions Statements” periodically
                    sent to the National Archives to regulate access to records in the custody of
                    that agency that had been originated by the Department of State or were under
                    its control. In 1963 “intelligence and counter-intelligence” documents were
                    added to the restricted categories, and in 1964 the restrictions were extended
                    to records “relating to the investigation of persons or groups of persons by
                    investigative authorities of the United States or foreign governments.”<note
                        n="25" place="end" xml:id="fn25">Letter, Simon, (Division of Records
                        Management) to Grover (National Archives), May 20, 1964.</note> Restrictions
                    on these last two categories of records were for 75 years while classified
                    foreign government documents were restricted for 50 years, the minimum time span
                    within which other democratic nations closed their diplomatic papers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Executive Order 11652 and the 30-Year Limit on
                        Classification</hi></p>
                <p>Between 1964 and 1972 several developments occurred that were bound to affect the
                    status of foreign government documents.</p>
                <p>In 1966 the Department of State opened its records up to 30 years. In subsequent
                    years the Department, without changing the basic principle of a 30-year rule,
                    advanced the open period ahead of 30 years whenever FRUS had completed coverage
                    of the documentation for a single year. Great Britain, for its part abandoned
                    the 50-year rule for the opening of its records by proceeding first to a 40-year
                    rule and, in 1968, to a 30-year rule for the opening of Foreign Office and
                    Cabinet records. In 1967 the Congress of the United States passed the Freedom of
                    Information Act (FOIA), enabling any member of the public to request the review
                    of documents of any age for declassification and release. Although nine specific
                    categories of records were exempted from automatic release under FOIA, foreign
                    government documents were not specifically listed as an exempted category. The
                    first exemption, however, covered documents that were “to be kept secret in the
                    interest of national defense and foreign policy” and were “properly classified”
                    pursuant to an executive order. Thus, while the basic protection for classified
                    documents, whether U.S. originated or foreign-originated, was provided by
                    executive orders on the classification and declassification of national security
                    information, their “proper classification” might be challenged under the FOIA
                    procedures, especially after that statute was revised and strengthened in
                    1974.</p>
                <p>In March 1972 President Nixon issued Executive Order 11652, a revision of earlier
                    Executive Orders on the classification and declassification of national security
                    information issued by President Eisenhower in 1953 and by President Kennedy in
                    1961. The provisions relating to foreign government information in E.O. 11652
                    were bound to create certain ambiguities. Section 4(C) of E.O. 11652, following
                    precedents set in the earlier Executive Orders of Presidents Eisenhower and
                    Kennedy, stipulated that classified information or material furnished to the
                    United States by a foreign government or international organization should be
                    assured a degree of protection required by the Government or international
                    organization that had furnished the information or material. On the other hand,
                    Section 5(E) (1) of E.O. 11652 provided that all classified information or
                    material should become automatically declassified 30 years after the date of
                    original classification “except for such specifically identified information or
                    material which the head of the originating department personally determines in
                    writing at the time to require continued protection because such protection is
                    essential to the national security or disclosure would place a person in
                    immediate jeopardy.”<note n="26" place="end" xml:id="fn26">Executive Order
                        11652, Mar. 8, 1972.</note></p>
                <p>Thus, while E.O. 11652 did not exempt foreign classified documents as such from
                    automatic declassification unless the two criteria cited above were met, the
                    order did require that foreign government information or material should be
                    assured the same degree of protection as that provided by the government or the
                    international organization that had furnished the information or material. The
                    question as to whether 4(C) or Section 5(E)(1) should prevail was never resolved
                    despite extensive discussions of this issue in the Interagency Classification
                    Review Committee (ICRC) that had been established to ensure compliance with the
                    Executive Order.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Establishment of a 30-Year Rule for State Department
                        Documents</hi></p>
                <p>By the early 1970s when E.O. 11652 entered into force, the National Archives and
                    Records Service (NARS) had in its custody large amounts of documents received
                    from the Department of State that, unless declassified earlier, were subject to
                    systematic declassification after 30 years under Section 5(E)(1) of that
                    Executive Order. Since by that time the bulk of the Department’s foreign policy
                    records 30 years old and even less than 30 years old had been declassified
                    following the release of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes of
                    World War II and the early postwar years, the remaining classified items were
                    those covered by special restrictions, including foreign government documents.
                    Some of the reviewing officers were inclined to base their decisions on Section
                    5(E) (1) of the Executive Order and to treat foreign-originated documents no
                    differently than U.S. originated records subject to systematic declassification
                    review at 30 years. Other officers, however, were mindful of Section 4(C) of
                    E.O. 11652 and therefore doubted the Department’s authority to release foreign
                    documents not yet declassified or released by the originating government or
                    international organization.</p>
                <p>In this situation the Historical Office took an initiative by addressing to the
                    Chairman of the Department’s Council on Classification Policy (CCP) a memorandum
                    reviewing the problem of the declassification of 30-year old foreign government
                    documents, especially in view of the ambiguities in Executive Order 11652.
                    According to this memorandum the Department’s adoption of a 30-year rule in 1966
                    and the <hi rend="underline">de facto</hi> opening of records ahead of 30 years
                    parallel to the publication of FRUS, recent British and Canadian policies of
                    opening records after 30 years, and the great variations in the relevant
                    practices of governments throughout the world made it advisable to reconsider
                    the Department’s policy of not opening foreign records in files in its custody
                    or under its control until they were 50 years old.<note n="27" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn27">The Department periodically made inquiries to foreign
                        governments about their policies and practices on the release of diplomatic
                        documents and access. The results of these surveys were eventually
                        coordinated and published by the Historical Office. The most recent survey
                        was issued in October 1976 as a Historical Study under the title “Public
                        Availability of Diplomatic Archives.”</note> Moreover, the Department had
                    learnt that the governments of Britain and Canada regularly declassified foreign
                    records along with their own documents after 30 years unless they fell within
                    privileged or specially restricted categories that were exempted from the
                    automatic declassification of their own records. In these circumstances adoption
                    of 30-year rule for the declassification of foreign classified records by the
                    United States would prevent “our falling back behind the British and Canadians
                    with regard to an important aspect of our declassification policy.” The
                    Historical Office therefore proposed that a recommendation be put before the CCP
                    “that all classified records in the Department’s files or in the custody of NARS
                    be declassified after 30 years unless they fall in categories that would be
                    exempted from declassification if they were American records.”<note n="28"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn28">Memorandum by Aandahl (PA/HO) to Reinhardt (PA),
                        “Declassification of Foreign Documents 30 Years Old,” Feb. 2, 1976. A brief,
                        informal proposal along similar lines had been addressed to Assistant
                        Secretary of State for Public Affairs Carol Laise by William Franklin,
                        Director of the Historical Office in September 1974.</note></p>
                <p>The recommendation by the Historical Office was adopted by the CCP with the
                    proviso that the recommended policy might later be changed in accordance with a
                    new executive order then under discussion. Before new guidelines providing for
                    the declassification of foreign documents 30 years old were sent to the National
                    Archives NARS suggested addition of a clause exempting from automatic
                    declassification also documents “known to be exempted from declassification
                    under guidelines currently shared between the United States and the government
                    or international organization which furnished the information.” Department of
                    State guidelines with this additional clause were issued to the NARS staff on
                    August 6, 1976.<note n="29" place="end" xml:id="fn29">Memorandum by Deutrich
                        (National Archives) to various NARS Divisions, Review for Declassification
                        of 30–year old foreign classified information, Aug. 6, 1976.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Executive Order 12065 and the Concept of “Foreign Government
                        Information</hi>”</p>
                <p>As noted above, the Department’s Council on Classification Policy had approved
                    the recommended policy of declassifying foreign classified records 30 years old
                    on the understanding that this policy might be superseded by a new Executive
                    Order. Drafting of such an order had begun in response to a NSC directive (NSSM
                    229). Although an interagency task force charged with drafting the new Order
                    held a number of meetings in the early part of 1976, its work came to a halt by
                    the middle of that year, perhaps as a result of White House preoccupation with
                    the 1976 Presidential election. No revision of E.O. 11652 had been provided by
                    the time President Ford left office.</p>
                <p>After the Carter Administration came to office in January 1977, a full revision
                    of Executive Order 11652 was undertaken in response to Presidential Review
                    Memorandum (PRM) 29 of June 1, 1977. Work was completed a little over a year
                    later when President Carter signed Executive Order 12065 (June 28, 1978). The
                    Order went into effect on December 1, 1978.</p>
                <p>E.O. 12065 represented a new approach to the problem of foreign classified
                    records inasmuch as it proceeded from a broad concept of “Foreign Government
                    Information” in contrast to E.O. 11652 which, like earlier Executive Orders, had
                    referred to “classified information or material furnished to the United States
                    by a foreign government or international organization.” The concept of foreign
                    government information was defined in the new Executive Order as information
                    “that has been provided to the United States in confidence by, or produced by
                    the United States pursuant to a joint written arrangement requiring
                    confidentiality with, a foreign government or international organization of
                    governments.” Foreign government information thus defined was one of the seven
                    categories requiring original or continued classification. While E.O. 12065
                    generally represented a forward step in the direction of openness, especially by
                    providing for systematic declassification review of all classified records 20
                    years old, foreign government information was exempted from this systematic
                    review at 20 years. Such information, unless declassified earlier, was to be
                    reviewed systematically for declassification 30 years from the date of
                    origination with guidelines developed by agency heads “in consultation with the
                    Archivist of the United States and, where appropriate, with the foreign
                    government or international organization concerned.”<note n="30" place="end"
                        xml:id="fn30">Executive Order 12065, June 28, 1978, Section 3 and Section
                        6–103.</note></p>
                <p>The new definition of foreign government information in E.O. 12065 covered those
                    foreign-originated documents that traditionally had been treated differently
                    from American documents. Unless cleared for publication or declassified by the
                    foreign government such documents were restricted until they had reached a
                    certain age, e.g., the 50-year limit prior to 1976 and the 30-year limit
                    thereafter. But the scope of the definition in E.O. 12065 could also be extended
                    to cover oral communications by foreign government representatives in
                    conversations and contacts with American officials. In the implementation of the
                    Executive Order and in the process of drafting declassification guidelines the
                    idea gained ground throughout the executive branch that oral information
                    supplied by foreign government officials and reflected in American documents
                    should make these documents subject to treatment as foreign documents so that
                    they might either be withheld from systematic declassification review for 30
                    years or released and published only with the approval of the foreign government
                    concerned. Thus, the old controversy that had been in the center of the “Mexican
                    case” in the period 1957–1962 and that appeared to have been settled at the time
                    was revived when certain bureaus and the new Classification/Declassification
                    Center (A/CDC) in the Department of State began to challenge the procedures for
                    the clearance of FRUS volumes that had been confirmed by that settlement.</p>
                <p>The willingness of Department of State officials to treat oral information given
                    to the United States in confidence as foreign government information stemmed in
                    large part from representations by certain foreign governments, especially from
                    Commonwealth countries, that began when E.O. 12065 was still being drafted and
                    continued after it had entered into force. In a note of January 5, 1979, the
                    Canadian Government reminded the Department of State “that the Canadian
                    Government considers that all information provided orally or in writing to the
                    United States Government in expressed or implicit confidence by the Government
                    of Canada or its officials is entitled to the full protection afforded to
                    foreign government information as stipulated by the Executive Order, unless the
                    contrary has been explicitly agreed to by the Government of Canada and its
                    officials.” Canada also expected that its agreement would be obtained “prior to
                    the declassification or release of any such Canadian Government information
                    provided to the United States Government.” Other Commonwealth countries made
                    similar representations in the period since issuance of the order. An Australian
                    note of February 15, 1980, which referred at some length to E.O. 12065,
                    emphasized Australia’s “understanding that the United States will continue to
                    ensure that information whether provided in writing or orally to the United
                    States in expressed or implied confidence will be afforded protection from
                    unauthorized or inadvertent release or de-classification.”<note n="31"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn31">Note No. 4 from the Embassy of Canada, Jan. 5,
                        1979; Note No. 77 from the Embassy of Australia, Feb. 15, 1980.</note>
                    Although the Canadian and Australian demarches appear to have been prompted by
                    concern over the release of relatively recent documents (e.g., release of the
                    “diplomatic volumes” of the Pentagon Papers) there was a tendency in the bureaus
                    and the CDC to apply the broader interpretation of the foreign government
                    information provisions of E.O. 12065 also to older records slated for
                    publication in FRUS. (The order did not withhold all release of foreign
                    government information to thirty years. It simply postponed systematic
                    declassification review for thirty years.)</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs and the Office of the Historian could not help being
                    concerned that too broad an interpretation of foreign government information and
                    of the provisions for declassifying such information might indeed greatly hamper
                    declassification and clearance for publication of American documents containing
                    information thus defined, especially reports of conversations with foreign
                    officials. The CCP assigned to PA/HO the task of preparing draft guidelines for
                    the systematic declassification review of Department of State records
                    transferred to the National Archives. A great effort was made to ensure that
                    American records containing certain kinds of orally conveyed foreign government
                    information would not automatically be exempted from systematic declassification
                    review at 20 years. After long and difficult discussions with the principal
                    geographic bureaus and with the Office of the Legal Adviser agreement was
                    eventually reached on a set of guidelines. While these did not fully meet the
                    requirements of the Bureau of Public Affairs and the Office of the Historian,
                    they provided for declassification at 20 years of certain types of oral foreign
                    government information incorporated in American documents. Under these “general”
                    guidelines for systematic review of Department of State records classified U.S.
                    documents containing oral information given by foreign government officials in
                    the expectation, express or implied, that the information is to be kept in
                    confidence should be declassified if it was determined at the time of the review
                    that the information was no longer sensitive, “although the source of such
                    information may require continued protection.” If only a portion of the
                    information required continued protection, the guidelines provided that “that
                    information shall be released on demand with appropriate deletions.”<note n="32"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn32">Guidelines for Systematic Declassification Review
                        of Department of State records (Communicated to the Archivist of the United
                        States, June 1979).</note></p>
                <p>Despite those provisions in the “general” guidelines allowing for some
                    flexibility in the declassification of foreign government information orally
                    transmitted, the net effect of E.O. 12065 has been to encourage those who wish
                    to blur or even obliterate the distinction between foreign government documents
                    and U.S. documents reflecting oral information obtained in conversations with
                    foreign officials. This traditional distinction until recently could be
                    maintained in the publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and in
                    the declassification of State records in the National Archives, despite earlier
                    challenges. The Classification/ Declassification Center in particular appears to
                    be inclined to adopt a broad interpretation of foreign government information
                    such as is currently favored by some foreign governments, especially those of
                    the Commonwealth countries. On December 3, 1980, Thomas M. Tracy, Assistant
                    Secretary for Administration, who oversees the Classification/Declassification
                    Center, addressed a memorandum to William J. Dyess, Assistant Secretary for
                    Public Affairs, specifying recent approaches by friendly foreign governments on
                    the question noting that the references were not strictly to FRUS documents, but
                    to foreign government information, suggesting that “there is little basis for
                    treating FRUS materials differently from other documents being reviewed for
                        declassification.”<note n="33" place="end" xml:id="fn33">Memorandum,
                        “Foreign Government Concerns About Information Provided in Confidence to the
                        United States,” Tracy to Dyess, December 3, 1980.</note> In commenting on
                    this assertion, David F. Trask, the Historian, affirmed on December 8, 1980,
                    that a distinction was warranted in the case of FRUS materials because (1) it is
                    uniformly older than 20 years, thus susceptible to special treatment under the
                    general guidelines now operative at Archives, (2) its presentation is required
                    for comprehensiveness under the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    mandate, and (3) it is presented in a historical context that tends to minimize
                    any possible damage that might be caused by other forms of release.<note n="34"
                        place="end" xml:id="fn34">Memorandum, “HO Views on Mr. Tracy’s Memorandum
                        dated December 3, 1980,” Trask to Dyess, December 8, 1980.</note> Most
                    recently CDC has insisted in a revision of the Department regulations governing
                    acquisition of clearances of foreign documents that U.S. documents reporting
                    conversations with foreign government officials be considered for submission to
                    foreign governments, for comments if not approval. It reserves to itself the
                    determination of whether material “containing foreign government information
                    should be the subject of communication with the foreign government which
                    provided the information, and undertakes such communication if and when deemed
                        appropriate.”<note n="35" place="end" xml:id="fn35">FAM 247.2, Office of
                        Systematic Review (A/CDC/SR), January 13, 1981.</note> The broad
                    interpretation of foreign government information reflected in recent CDC actions
                    threatens to remove from the systematic declassification review of classified
                    American records a large body of material put back for review at 30 years as
                    foreign government information. Finally, this interpretation will strengthen
                    already existing tendencies among Department officials to push publication of
                    FRUS permanently back to a 30-year line.<note n="36" place="end" xml:id="fn36"
                        >At this writing a review of E.O. 12065 is underway. Its principal outcome
                        may be postponement of all forms of systematic declassification review to
                        thirty years.</note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
