<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From N. Stephen Kane Through Paul Claussen and
                    William Slany to David Trask, March 1981</title>
                <title type="short">Kane to Trask, 1981</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1981-03-18">March 18, 1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1981-03-18-kane-guatemala-appeal.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 125 KB, 3pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, FRUS Clearance Files, 1961-1963 (Lot File 04 D 114), Box 3,
                    1952-1954, Vol. IV, American Republics Clearance Folder. Extra copies were sent
                    to John Glennon and Charles Sampson.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn91">Footnote 91</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From N. Stephen Kane (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Compiler) Through
                    Paul Claussen (Chief of the Western Hemisphere, African, and Middle Eastern
                    Division) and William Slany (General Editor of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) to
                    David Trask (Director of the Historian's Office)</head>
                <dateline>March 18, 1981</dateline>
                <p>Subject: “Fast track” publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    1952-1954, IV (“The American Republics”)</p>
                <p>Issue</p>
                <p>Should HO go forward with publication of the subject volume before 1) receiving a
                    written response from the CIA regarding declassification of a supplementary
                    package of editorial notes based on CIA cables, and 2) appealing NSC deletions
                    of material which has already appeared almost verbatim in previously published
                    volumes?</p>
                <p>Discussion</p>
                <p>The recent decision to go forward with “fast track” publication of the subject
                    volume raises a number of important questions relating to the future of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is the preeminent publication of its kind anywhere in the
                    world. It vividly demonstrates the United States Government's commitment to the
                    principle that an informed public is essential to the democratic process. Its
                    credibility as an accurate historical record of United States foreign relations
                    is widely accepted, and its objectivity is praised by scholars and practitioners
                    alike. The status accorded to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is the
                    result of the traditionally conscientious efforts of those who compile the
                    series to document all significant aspects of United States relations with other
                    countries. In the 1970's, these efforts extended to well-known covert episodes,
                    in spite of the enormous difficulties encountered by HO historians in securing
                    access to and declassification of the necessary papers. In the absence of a
                    high-level policy decision prohibiting coverage of covert activities, HO has an
                    obligation, consonant with its original mandate, to make the effort, and to
                    account for its failure, if necessary. If HO permits silence to substitute for
                    substance, and gaps in the record for accountability, the series' reputation as
                    a credible and objective official documentary publication will not endure.</p>
                <p>In any declassification controversy, there is a point at which HO must opt to cut
                    its losses, but I regard the decision to go forward with publication in this
                    case as premature for the following reasons:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>it puts the onus for failure to publish the record of, or to account for,
                        a well-known covert episode squarely on the Department of State and the
                        Office of the Historian, thereby seriously eroding the credibility of the
                        series;</item>
                    <item>it radically changes the nature of HO's mission, in spite of its current
                        mandate, without the sanction of higher levels in the Department of State or
                        the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation;</item>
                    <item>it imposes a form of self-censorship on the series, and suggests that
                        there is compelling logic to move the threshold of self-censorship from the
                        declassification to the collection phase of the production process;</item>
                    <item>it eliminates the possibility of testing the CIA's claim that there is a
                        distinction between policy and operations, and that the former may be
                        releasable;</item>
                    <item>it forecloses an appeal to the NSC on deletions of materials appearing
                        almost verbatim in previously published volumes, thereby encouraging the NSC
                        to widen this practice;</item>
                    <item>it establishes a strong negative precedent for other <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in progress, thereby jeopardizing a
                        substantial aggregate of documentation; and,</item>
                    <item>it weakens the position of the Department of State in dealing with the
                        anticipated negative reaction of the consuming public.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Recommendation</p>
                <p>In view of the foregoing, I recommend that we reconsider the decision to publish
                    the subject volume at this time, and instead adopt the following series of
                    steps:</p>
                <p>1) defer publication until we receive a definitive written decision from the CIA
                    on the supplementary editorial notes at issue and have an opportunity to appeal
                    certain NSC deletions, or until the volume is thirty years old, whichever comes
                    first;</p>
                <p>2) select another volume for rapid processing in its place, one free of major
                    declassification problems, possibly <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    1955-1957, III (“The American Republics”);</p>
                <p>3) if the CIA decision on the editorial notes is negative, insert a meaningful
                    disclaimer at the front of the Guatemala compilation to account for the lack of
                    coverage, as a countervailing precedent against further loss of similar
                    materials in other volumes; and,</p>
                <p>4) initiate the appropriate process at higher levels in the Department to
                    redefine the official mandate of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series and the principles guiding its compilation in accordance with current
                    realities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
