<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Francis Terry McNamara and David Trask to
                    William Dyess, March 1981</title>
                <title type="short">McNamara and Trask to Dyess, 1981</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-16">December 16, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1981-03-13">March 13, 1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1981-03-13-mcnamara-and-trask-to-dyess.pdf">PDF</ref>, 110 KB,
                    4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Paul Claussen Files, 1972-2005 (Lot File 08 D 437), Box 7, Chron
                    File March 1981. The document bears Francis Terry McNamara’s initials, but not
                    David Trask’s. A copy was sent to David Trask.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn76">Footnotes 76</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn77">77</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From Francis Terry McNamara (Deputy Assistant Secretary of State
                    for Public Affairs) and David Trask (Director of the Historian’s Office) to
                    William J. Dyess (Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs)</head>
                <dateline>March 13, 1981</dateline>
                <p>Subject: “To Fresh Woods and Pastures New”</p>
                <p rend="underline">The Problem</p>
                <p>We believe that the time has come for us to reassess our goals in regards to the
                    Historian’s Office. For the past <hi rend="underline">two</hi> years all efforts
                    have been bent towards reaching a twenty-year line in the publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) by
                    1986. The outcome of these extensive endeavors has been to demonstrate that HO
                    can readily attain a twenty-year line in preparation of manuscripts but that it
                    cannot achieve a twenty-year line in conversion of manuscripts into published
                    books.</p>
                <p>Attempts to speed compilation and to reduce costs have been effective, but a
                    breakdown in the delivery of central services, of which difficulties with
                    declassification constitute only one dimension, have precluded maintenance of
                    the desired schedule of publication. Even if declassification difficulties were
                    to disappear overnight, publication cannot be hastened materially until a whole
                    range of improvements are made in the delivery of needed central services, for
                    example, services that emanate from the Government Printing Office (GPO) and the
                    Foreign Affairs Information Center (A/FAIM).</p>
                <p>Moreover, delays in publication have contributed to a budgetary crisis of unknown
                    but significant proportions. The cost of publication has marched well beyond the
                    assumptions made when funds were allocated for outstanding unpublished volumes
                    (about twenty covering 1950-1954 and about 13 covering 1955-1957).</p>
                <p rend="underline">Options Opened to Us</p>
                <p>What is to be done? There follows a brief exposition of three options.</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>One would be to maintain the present objectives, seeking to attain the
                        twenty-year line by 1986.</item>
                    <item>Another would be to maintain the present objectives, seeking to attain the
                        twenty-year line by 1986, mobilizing a whole range of new resources and
                        seeking much-improved delivery of central services.</item>
                    <item>A third would be to retain the goal of a twenty-year line but to accept
                        some delay in reaching it, holding for the moment the present gap of 26-30
                        years while engaging in certain compensatory activities to mitigate the
                        credibility gap and expand the policy oriented research program.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Discussion</p>
                <p>There is no need to indicate the requirements of option #1 since it represents
                    merely the maintenance of the <hi rend="underline">status quo</hi>.</p>
                <p>Further, there is no need to restate the requirements of option #2, since it is
                    the course of action that has been recommended in the recent past.</p>
                <p>If both options #1 and #2 prove unacceptable or unattainable, the only logical
                    alternative is to accept a hold-the line policy with compensatory activities.
                    There follows a brief outline of the measures that could be adopted along this
                    line with some of their advantages and disadvantages.</p>
                <p>1. HO could divert about half of its personnel to policy-related historical
                    research, greatly enlarging its output in this area. An early increase in the
                    volume of such activity is entirely consistent with the present effort to
                    upgrade the Department’s role in the making of overall national policy.
                    Policy-related historical research of the highest quality is an indispensable
                    element in the policy process, and no other organization in the Department is
                    qualified to provide it.</p>
                <p>2. HO could use the other half of its personnel to sustain the publication of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series at its present level and
                    plan for a renewed burst of compiling in two or three years when
                    declassification has overtaken compiling. To accomplish even this limited
                    objective the Department must improve its provision of needed central services.
                    But no truly extraordinary effort would be necessary, and upgrading could
                    proceed at a measured pace.</p>
                <p>A schedule for work on the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series would
                    rest on twin pillars: first; priority to publication of volumes for the period
                    1950-1957 already compiled. Second, adjustment of the schedule for compilation
                    of volumes covering the period 1958-1963 to the pace of declassification
                    activity. HO would thus reduce its huge backlog of unpublished manuscripts and
                    work toward the ideal of processing manuscripts through publication only after
                    completing the task of declassification. Phases in this process would be: (a)
                    publication of volumes covering 1950- 1954 that are undergoing declassification
                    re-review at the present time; (b) publication of volumes in the triennium
                    1955-1957, now all but completed in manuscript form; (c) preparation of large
                    collections of documents that might be included in the volumes covering the two
                    triennia 1958-60 and 1961-63 for submission to the
                    Classification/Declassification Center and other declassification authorities;
                    (d) compilation, editing, and publication of the triennial sets for 1958-1960
                    and 1961-1963. HO would seek at all times to accelerate movement toward a
                    twenty-year line, but it should not anticipate significant gains for several
                    years.</p>
                <p>3. HO could resume the provision of a service to its user population that would
                    compensate to some extent for the failure to attain the twenty-year line at an
                    early date, namely, publication of the “Current Documents” series. This series
                    was suspended after publication of the volume for 1967 because of budgetary
                    considerations. Given new capabilities, it seems entirely feasible to resume
                    this activity on a much-improved basis at greatly reduced cost. Modern modes of
                    publication involving use of word-processing equipment, electronic typesetters,
                    and microform allow for this outcome. The new “Current Documents” would include
                    important other-agency information and unpublished information of importance as
                    well as the types of information included in the old series.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Conclusions</p>
                <p>To summarize, this approach would involve increasing HO’s policy-related research
                    and resuming publication of “Current Documents” in compensation for accepting a
                    temporary hesitation in the early achievement by the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series of a twenty-year line.</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>The disadvantage of this approach is that it probably could, if
                        misunderstood, arouse considerable anxiety among the user population.</item>
                    <item>The advantage of this approach is that it would reduce the gap between
                        announced intentions and actual accomplishments, compensating for some
                        slowness in delivery of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                        by enhancing the volume of policy-related research and resuming publication
                        of “Current Documents.”</item>
                </list>
                <p>With the establishment of a central declassification office, it makes little
                    sense for HO to work on documents prior to their declassification. In the
                    abstract, it might seem that this practice could afford a useful head-start in
                    compiling volumes. Hard experience over the past two years, however, has proven
                    otherwise. Interminable battles over declassification have resulted in a virtual
                    standstill in publication, a lowering of morale in HO and the creation of an
                    skepticism among important users of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Moreover, many
                    of the cost benefits to be realized from the application of new word processing
                    techniques have been jeopardized by delays ascribable to classification
                    problems.</p>
                <p>We are convinced that substantial savings in time and money can be realized by
                    working only with declassified documents. As a start, editing and printing might
                    be contracted out to low bidders, getting away from the need to use costly GPO
                    classified facilities. Expensive excisions from nearly completed volumes could
                    be eliminated. The interminable, rancorous arguments between equally dedicated
                    historians and declassifiers could be greatly reduced. Finally, on the positive
                    side, the historians could be of help in providing historic perspective to
                    illuminate some of the murkier problems for the Department’s policy makers.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Recommendation</p>
                <p>We propose that you approve option #3, since it is clearly preferable to the
                    other options in the existing circumstances. If you take this step, one that we
                    deem fully within your authority as the Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                    Affairs, we will proceed to develop detailed plans for putting the three
                    principal recommendations of option #3 into effect at the earliest convenient
                    moment.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
