<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Briefing Memorandum From Thomas Tracy Through Richard Kennedy
                    to Walter Stoessel with Attached Iran Guidelines, April 1981</title>
                <title type="short">Tracy to Stoessel, 1981</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2019-06-20">June 20, 2019</date>
                <date type="created" when="1981-04-02">April 2, 1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1981-04-02-tracy-to-stoessel-with-attached-guidelines.pdf"
                    >PDF</ref>, 183 KB, 5pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Central Foreign Policy Files, 1981
                    P-Reels, P810069-1517 through 1521. Tracy’s memorandum to Stoessel received
                    concurrences from Peter Constable (NEA) and, in draft, from JoAnn Dolan (L/ECP),
                    James Roche (S/P), Raymond Seitz (S/S), and Elijah Kelly (S/S-I). The document
                    bears a stamp indicating that Amb. Stoessel saw the memorandum on April 4. The
                    attached declassification review guidelines were drafted by Henry Precht
                    (NEA/IRN) and George Sherman (NEA/P).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn74">Footnote 74</ref></p>
            <div type="document" xml:id="memorandum">
                <head>Briefing Memorandum From Thomas Tracy (Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Administration) Through Richard Kennedy (Under Secretary of State for
                    Management) to Walter Stoessel (Under Secretary of State for Political
                    Affairs)</head>
                <dateline>April 2, 1981</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Freedom of Information Requests on Iran</p>
                <p>The past two years, and especially the hostage period, have presented unique
                    problems with regard to FOI requests relating to Iran. This was one of the
                    several aspects of the Iran situation in which Mr. Newsom was directly involved.
                    Clearly, some of the political and strategic elements of the problem continue.
                    Given the interest of your office in the past, S/S has suggested that we provide
                    the following brief summary of where we stand and how we got there; and to seek
                    your approval to proceed in a more normal fashion now that our people are
                    free.</p>
                <p>Beginning with the first overt action against Embassy Tehran in February 1979,
                    the need was recognized for special care in releasing information relating to
                    Iran in response to FOI and similar public requests. At the same time there was
                    an upsurge in the number of such requests. Many came from journalists. Others
                    came from American companies contemplating litigation or claims against the
                    Iranian Government. Much information on Iran, including some which originated
                    many years earlier, was highly sensitive in these circumstances, reflecting, for
                    example, close US relations with the late Shah and his officials.</p>
                <p>After the seizure of the Embassy personnel as hostages, we in practice stopped
                    releasing any information on Iran through the FOI process. We reasoned that
                    almost any official acknowledgement of past US actions in or relating to Iran
                    might in some way be twisted or distorted to the disadvantage of the hostages.
                    FOI requesters affected by this practice were informally notified and appeared
                    to accept the rationale.</p>
                <p>The only real exception concerned a request from <hi rend="italic">Newsweek</hi>.
                    After the appearance of a series of <hi rend="italic">New Yorker</hi> articles
                    which indicated that the author had privileged access to Department information,
                        <hi rend="italic">Newsweek</hi> threatened to take the Department to court
                    if its pending FOI request was not processed.</p>
                <p>The request concerned the decision to admit that Shah to the United States. CDC,
                    working with L, S/S, and the Iran Working Group, reviewed relevant documents,
                    including Mr. Newsom’s files. With Mr. Christopher’s approval, we released a
                    small number of documents whose contents were already in the public domain.</p>
                <p>Since the release of the hostages, NEA, CDC, and L have agreed that the
                    Department must move on the backlog of over 50 Iran FOI cases. These include
                    requests concerning the negotiations leading to the release of the hostages
                    which will incorporate Mr. Christopher’s files; requests for extensive
                    historical material on U.S. relations with Iran compiled by S/P for the White
                    House in September (the “White Paper”), and background documents relevant
                    thereto; and requests relating to sizeable claims by American corporations
                    against Iran. Some of these last will almost surely result in law suits for
                    reasons other than our responses to the requester. They also include <hi
                        rend="italic">Newsweek’s</hi> appeal of the documents denied in its request
                    mentioned above. (The <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> has a similar
                    request on record but has not pressed us.)</p>
                <p>On the advice of L, CDC has started reviewing these pending cases, beginning with
                    the earliest. New guidance was sought and received from NEA (copy attached).
                    Retired FSO Charles Naas, now on CDC rolls, heads the Iran FOI review team. He
                    was nominated by NEA for this responsibility and has extensive experience in
                    Iran affairs.</p>
                <p>We propose to follow the new NEA guidelines but in every other respect to review
                    FOI cases on Iran henceforth as we do all other FOI requests, which will include
                    consulting with NEA whenever we are in doubt. This will include starting to
                    review two <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes (1951 and 1952-54) on Iran which
                    have been held in abeyance. NEA, L, and S/P agree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="document" xml:id="attachment">
                <head>Memorandum From Peter Constable (Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                    Eastern Affairs) to Clayton McManaway (Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Classification/Declassification Center)</head>
                <dateline>February 10, 1981</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Iran and Freedom of Information</p>
                <p>Ref: Your Memorandum of Feb. 3, 1981</p>
                <p>We agree with your memorandum that with the release of the hostages we should take
                    a fresh look at Iran FOI material. While we can obviously be more liberal than
                    our previously very restrictive guidelines, there remain areas of great
                    sensitivity. We hope that your staff can continue to work closely with NEA/IRN
                    in those sensitive areas.</p>
                <p>We suggest that recently retired FSO-1 Charles W. Naas be assigned prime
                    responsibility for reviewing all Iran materials. Mr. Naas was deeply involved in
                    Iranian affairs as Country Director and DCM from summer 1974 to summer 1979.</p>
                <p>In our view there are four general guidelines that apply to all Iran
                    materials:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>No release of documents that would reveal intelligence sources, methods,
                        plans, or operations;</item>
                    <item>No release of material that would place in personal jeopardy any American
                        or any friendly Iranian or other national;</item>
                    <item>A willingness to release documents that illustrate the broad outlines of
                        US policy towards Iran at the particular time;</item>
                    <item>No release of documents that would seriously complicate efforts to create
                        a new relationship with Iran in the future. We would anticipate that in this
                        crucial area, we would exempt from release material which would compromise
                        the conduct of national defense or foreign policy, as spelled out in FOI
                        regulations.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In addition, we would like to suggest the following considerations for the
                    specific periods under review:</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">1951-1955 Documents for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and
                        FOI</hi> - A simplified and distorted version of the events of this period
                    has become political dogma in Iran and elsewhere. The release of the full
                    diplomatic record would help to provide a better balance in accounts of our
                    role. For that balance, however, it will be essential to cover our dealings with
                    the British. To exclude the story of US-British cooperation on Iran will not
                    give a true picture of US decisions. We suggest that the Department consult with
                    the FCO to work out practical arrangements for possible release of documents
                    from this record.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">1956-February 1979</hi> - Within the general guidelines, we
                    believe we could release much economic, consular, and routine political
                    reporting. There would seem to be very few documents of this sort from this
                    period what could not be released in connection with litigation, but that, as on
                    other subjects, would be decided within the guidelines noted above.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">February 1979-November 1979</hi> - Many of the documents
                    held in Embassy Tehran files prior to November 4, 1979, can be considered
                    compromised. Through checking this carefully and keeping in mind the general
                    guidelines, many of these documents could be released.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">November 1979-January 1981</hi> - Much, but by no means all,
                    of the diplomatic record for this period has been discussed. We recommend
                    release of documents that conform to the general guidelines and that might help
                    to clarify public understanding of the diplomatic activity to free the
                    hostages.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
