<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1982</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1982</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-05-05">May 5, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1982-11-05">November 5, 1982</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1982-11-05-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 255 KB, 14pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, 1982—Report, Minutes, Correspondence. The
                    classified annex referenced in the afternoon session has not been
                located.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn79">Footnote 79</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1982 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 5, 1982</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Gary R. Hess, Department of History, Bowling Green State University,
                        Bowling Green, OH 43403</item>
                    <item>Dr. John L. Gaddis, Department of History, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
                        45701</item>
                    <item>Dr. Ernest R. May, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard
                        University, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Richard N. Rosecrance, Center for International Studies, Cornell
                        University, Ithaca, New York 14853</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Gaddis Smith, Department of History, Yale University, New Haven,
                        Connecticut 06520</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Seymour J. Rubin, Executive Vice President &amp; Executive Director,
                        The American Society of International Law, 2223 Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.,
                        Washington, D.C. 20008</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>The Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John H. Kelly, Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Acting Deputy Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Acting General Editor of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>)</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring, Acting Adviser on Research</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Carol A. Becker</item>
                    <item>Bret D. Bellamy</item>
                    <item>Evan M. Duncan</item>
                    <item>Suzanne E. Coffman</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Kay K. Herring</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>David S. Painter</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Classification/Declassification Center (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>Laurence G. Pickering, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs and Information and Management Center (A/FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Frank M. Machak, Chief, Information Services Division (PS)</item>
                    <item>John F. Ellsworth, Chief Editing Branch</item>
                    <item>Margie R. Wilber, Chief, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                    <item>Rita M. Baker, Deputy Chief, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                    <item>Vicki L. Ettleman</item>
                </list>
                <p>The National Archives and Records Service (NARS):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Diplomatic Records Division</item>
                    <item>Edwin A. Thompson, Chief, Records Declassification Division</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Arthur G. Kogan, retired</item>
                    <item>Beverly Zweiben, Bureau of International Organization Affairs, Department
                        of State</item>
                    <item>Lisle A. Rose, Bureau of Oceans and International Environmental and
                        Scientific Affairs</item>
                    <item>Daniel Helmsteder, President, Scholarly Resources, Inc.</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Morning Session</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Slany called the meeting to order at 9:18 A.M. He introduced Mr. Kelly, who
                    welcomed the Advisory Committee on behalf of John Hughes, Assistant Secretary
                    for Public Affairs and Department Spokesman, who could not be present because he
                    was on Capitol Hill with the Secretary of State, George Shultz, that
                    morning.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kelly said that the Committee played a vital role in providing advice and
                    support to the Office of the Historian, especially for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. He stated that the Department had a
                    commitment to the prompt and efficient publication of the series, always
                    balancing scholarly integrity and quick disclosure against the needs of
                    continued security. He welcomed the Committee’s candid discussion and solicited
                    their advice.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany distributed a revised agenda for the meeting. He regretted that time
                    had not permitted arrangements for the attendance of records personnel from
                    other foreign affairs agencies, but he solicited suggestions from the Committee
                    as to who they might like to have attend next year. He noted that the morning
                    session was open to the public, but that the afternoon session was closed so
                    that classified information could be discussed. Mr. Slany called upon the
                    Committee to elect a chairman. Mr. May nominated Mr. Hess, which was seconded by
                    Mr. Smith. Mr. Rubin moved that the nominations be closed. Mr. Hess was chosen
                    by acclamation.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Historian</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany made an oral report of the activities of the Office to supplement the
                    written report on the subject that had been mailed to the Committee members
                    earlier. He noted that several leadership positions in the Office had been
                    filled on an acting basis pending permanent assignments which must be made under
                    the mechanism approved by the Office of Personnel Management.</p>
                <p>Although the Office had been given budgetary support by the Bureau of Public
                    Affairs and the Department itself, costs in the Office had been lower than in
                    the past because only two volumes in the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series had
                    been published in the last year. During the coming fiscal year, Mr. Slany
                    reported that the size of the Office staff would be reduced from 35 to 29
                    professional and support members. The staff cuts were not unique to the Bureau.
                    The lost positions were earmarked by Management Operations as “declassification”
                    positions because so much of the declassification function had been lost to the
                    CDC several years ago. These lost positions would in no way affect the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Mr. Rubin asked if the loss
                    would affect the declassification that the Office still engages in. Mr. Slany
                    said that it would not. Mr. Slany then added that the Office was still able to
                    hire selectively, having acquired two new historians in the past year, David
                    Painter and Janet Heininger, whom he introduced.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that eight volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series were declassified but not yet published. Although the declassification
                    process has operated much more smoothly in the last year, the printing process
                    at the GPO has not. Some volumes now take longer than one year at GPO. The major
                    problem is one of technology; fifteen to twenty <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes were prepared on lead plates for the linotype process. GPO plans to
                    phase out its linotype operation in the next year. Some of the volumes, those
                    that cannot possibly be declassified by the time the linotype process is no
                    longer available, are already being converted to magnetic tape for GPO’s
                    photocomposition process. Mr. Smith asked if optical scanning might be able to
                    convert the galleys to magnetic tape without retyping. Mr. Slany responded that
                    the Office had tried that, but the optical scanning technology was still not
                    able to handle the type face used in the series. In order to publish the volumes
                    in the quickest fashion possible after declassification, the Office is now
                    exploring the possibility of requesting a waiver from the requirement to publish
                    through GPO, which would necessitate the approval of the Joint Committee on
                    Printing of the U.S. Congress. Waivers such as this are difficult to obtain, he
                    added, but they had been acquired in the past by the National Archives, the
                    Center of Military History, and for the history of the Atomic Energy Commission.
                    Mr. Rosecrance asked how those agencies had acquired waivers. Mr. Slany said
                    that they had been acquired long ago, but that recent waivers had been awarded
                    on the grounds that GPO could not meet deadlines, which was certainly applicable
                    for our series. To Mr. Smith’s question as to why reduced cost would not be a
                    strong argument for a waiver, he replied that the State Department had never
                    been able to get a full breakdown of GPO’s costs on an item by item basis. There
                    was reason to suspect that some of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes “carried” less prestigious publications printed by GPO for other
                    agencies. Mr. Slany estimated that a private publisher might be able to produce
                    a volume for one half of the GPO cost of about $150,000 per volume. Mr. Gaddis
                    asked if the Office had already been in contact with a private publisher, to
                    which Mr. Slany answered that some companies seemed interested. He added that
                    the request for a waiver at a time when GPO was trying to modernize would be
                    resisted strongly. With a waiver, however, a commercial or university press
                    would be able to produce the series faster, more economically, and with a larger
                    press run to include a paperback edition. Mr. Rubin suggested that perhaps a
                    good strategy would be to ask for a waiver just for the backlogged volumes still
                    in lead galleys rather than for the whole series. Mr. Slany agreed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then pointed out because all the 1955-57 volumes in the series would be
                    published using the photocomposition technology, it would be very likely that
                    some of those volumes would appear before the 1952-54 volumes had all appeared.
                    Mr. Gaddis remarked that precedents already existed for publishing <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes out of sequence. Mr. Smith asked if the lead
                    plates themselves could be photoprinted. Mr. Slany replied that the galleys had
                    to be altered prior to printing to account for declassification decisions, and
                    thus photoprinting would not be possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany concluded this section of his oral report by stating that there was
                    certainly no guarantee, given the GPO problems, that any more volumes would be
                    published in 1983 than had been published in 1982.</p>
                <p>The problems associated with publishing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, however, are not being allowed to interfere with the
                    earliest access by the public to the records on which the series is based. He
                    pointed with pride to the arrangements that had been made by the Department of
                    State and the National Archives whereby the Department has provided a subvention
                    which supports the work of 22 archivists at NARS who are working on applying the
                    CDC’s guidelines to the 1950-54 record bloc. Very shortly a portion of that
                    record bloc will be opened. Mr. Pickering estimated that by the end of the next
                    fiscal year the Department will have committed $460,000 to this effort. Mr.
                    Slany expected that the whole record bloc will have been opened by 1986 or
                    sooner. The records relating to Europe are proving to be the most sensitive to
                    declassify and will probably be the last to be released. The CDC meantime is
                    working now on guidelines for the 1955-59 record bloc.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany announced that, to supplement this effort, a joint project of the
                    Historical Office and the CDC was underway to microfiche and then publish
                    separately high-level files of a multi-topical and multinational nature that are
                    not easily covered by the CDC’s review guidelines. The microfiche publication
                    would include the Department’s publication <hi rend="italic">Current Economic
                        Developments</hi>, the Top Secret Daily Summaries, White House summaries,
                    memoranda of the Secretary of State, and conference files prepared by the
                    Executive Secretariat. The microfiche would be distributed to depository
                    libraries around the country and the world. Mr. Sampson, who heads this project,
                    added that the microfiche publication must make clear what portion of the files
                    the user is getting. When asked by Mr. Gaddis if all these files were from the
                    1950-54 period, Mr. Sampson replied that some of the files begin in 1945. Mr.
                    Gaddis asked about the integrity of the files; Mr. Slany responded that this
                    Office’s concern for file integrity was another motive for the project. Mr.
                    Sampson noted that the historians had come across many damaged files with
                    missing documents and missing pages from documents, estimating that one percent
                    to five percent of the files are degraded by each handling of them. Mr. May
                    asked if these files would be sanitized or appear in full. Mr. Sampson answered
                    that less than one-half of one percent were being withheld. Mr. Slany said that
                    the Office would prepare essays to accompany the fiche, explaining what the
                    documents were and what portion they represented. There would be no editing of
                    the documents to be microfiched. Because these documents are easily declassified
                    in that they mention very few names, their review does not interfere with the
                    CDC’s regular declassification schedule for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance asked when all these documents might be available to the public,
                    noting that the British were far ahead of us in releasing their documents for
                    the early 1950s. Mr. Slany said that the thirty-year line was certainly not
                    possible for some records, but he commented that, based on the observations of
                    several members of the staff who had actually visited the Public Records Office
                    in the last year, the British were withholding many sensitive files as well. Mr.
                    Gaddis asked if the Office plans any retrospective volumes to pick up
                    documentation not available at the time of publication of the volumes in the
                    series. Mr. Slany and Mr. Petersen agreed that the Office was very interested in
                    publishing retrospective volumes, having already partially compiled one such
                    volume made up of intelligence and national security documents declassified at
                    the Truman Library subsequent to publication of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes for the time period.</p>
                <p>The meeting then adjourned for a short break for 15 minutes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">User Survey</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany reported that the results of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> User Survey, prepared by the Office and conducted in
                    September 1982, were very encouraging. Both the size of the response and the
                    number of people who took the time to add comments indicated considerable
                    support for the series outside the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon reported on the Survey in detail. Of the 1593 questionnaires that
                    were sent out (deliberately excluding any past and present Office employees),
                    766 were returned; this represented almost 50%. Both the mailing list of the
                    Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations (SHAFR) and that of the
                    Bureau of Public Affairs were used to determine the mailing list for the Survey.
                    Prior to a comprehensive statistical analysis to be conducted by a data
                    processing firm in Baltimore, Mr. Glennon looked at a sampling of 250 returns to
                    derive some preliminary unofficial statistics. Almost 89% of the respondents
                    said they had used the series in the last three years. 64% preferred to wait for
                    a more comprehensive volume than to receive a more timely but less complete one.
                    Over 90% said the series was vital and that it would be a serious loss if it
                    were discontinued. 41%, however, said that they were not specialists in
                    diplomatic history, indicating a use of the series outside the obvious narrow
                    audience. Interest was strong in possible paperback editions, but the responses
                    were mixed concerning the addition of aids and other features such as purport
                    lists, narrative summaries, and bibliographies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that the Office, in conjunction with the Bureau, had been trying
                    to circulate this Survey ever since 1977, although many of the respondents
                    apparently thought that the timing of the Survey had some significance for the
                    survival of the series and/or the Office. One obvious purpose of the Survey was
                    to let managers in the Department know of the size and breadth of the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> constituency, but the main objective was to improve
                    the utility of the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon continued by saying that over 35% of the respondents wrote comments
                    on the page provided. Microform editions and microform supplements were not
                    enthusiastically welcomed. Mr. Smith asked if any of the respondents had noted
                    the usefulness, as he did, of the series as an undergraduate teaching aid. Mr.
                    Glennon said that they had. Mr. Smith added that the utility of narrative
                    summaries and bibliographies depended on the use to which one put the series in
                    general. He, for one, would hate to see any documents sacrificed to make room
                    for editorial apparatus. Mr. Hess asked if the committee would be provided with
                    copies of the summary data when it was complete. Mr. Slany assured him that they
                    would certainly be sent copies, but not until the full analysis was complete
                    after the first of the year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that before turning to Mr. Glennon for the report on the status of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series he wanted to tell the
                    Committee about the suggestion put forward by the Society for Historians of
                    American Foreign Relations for an internship/fellowship program to be instituted
                    in the Department for post-doctoral students of diplomatic history. The
                    intention would be to assign the fellows not to the Historical Office but to
                    other Bureaus and perhaps even embassies overseas. There might be problems in
                    funding such a program entirely by the Department, but the idea was receiving
                    serious attention in the Office and the Department.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report on the Status of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Series</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon reported on the problems encountered in publication of <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Only two of the projected eight volumes scheduled
                    for publication in 1982 had actually appeared. Various printer errors had to be
                    corrected in Volume III for 1951, including replacement of the title page.
                    Volume V (The Near East and Africa) was scheduled for release by the end of the
                    year. Six cleared volumes were in the pipeline and would probably be released by
                    August 1983.</p>
                <p>An average of 12 months elapsed between clearance and publication, and this
                    figure was likely to increase to 13. China 1949 was exceptional in taking only
                    seven months to publish after clearance. The recent Geneva Conference volume
                    took ten months on “fast track,” while Indochina 1952-54 took sixteen.
                    Declassification was slow, but five volumes had been cleared this year and three
                    more were in the final stage of clearance at NSC. A total of 44 volumes were in
                    the pipeline for the years 1951 through 1958-60. Little except exploration of
                    the Presidential Libraries was planned at this stage for the post-1960 period.
                    While some 1958-60 material had gone to CDC for review, the emphasis was on
                    1951-54. Volumes V and VII for 1951 were scheduled for release by January,
                    agreement with CDC on Volume IV was expected shortly, making publication likely
                    in 1984. Only three out of sixteen volumes for 1952-54 had been published. Five
                    were scheduled for 1983, three were at NSC, and five more were encountering
                    clearance problems and were threatened by GPO’s plans to phase out linotyping.
                    The 1952-54 cycle was unlikely to be completed until 1985, with clearance being
                    slowest on the European and Near East volumes.</p>
                <p>The first of the 1955-57 series might be published in early 1984. Twelve volumes
                    were complete, the CDC had returned preliminary declassification memos on two,
                    and was expected to return memos on two more. Compilation was about half
                    completed for the 1958-60 series, which was expected to comprise 16 volumes.</p>
                <p>The floor was then opened to questions from the committee.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smith, noting that Mr. Glennon’s written report had said that no <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compiling was going on at present, wondered whether
                    this inactivity might eventually erode compilation skills. Mr. Glennon said that
                    compiling still continued on a very small scale, and he did not think the skills
                    would disappear. Mr. Smith imagined that selecting and editing of documents was
                    the most intellectually stimulating part of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> work, not the declassifying and negotiating part. Mr. Slany
                    and Mr. Glennon agreed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance asked about the long delays in clearing European volumes, and was
                    told that political questions were the main reason. Mr. Hess asked how much time
                    was spent in deletions. He was told that declassification was the longest phase
                    of the process. Compilation began in 1974 for the 1952-54 series, while it had
                    begun ten years ago for the 1951 series. Even the binding is taking 5 months
                    instead of the promised 2 1/2 months. Mr. May asked about means of expediting
                    the process, particularly contracting either printing or binding to private
                    firms. Mr. Rubin was particularly interested in this possibility. While it might
                    be difficult to persuade Congress to agree to a waiver, private printing would
                    be in line with the Administration’s search for means of cutting costs and its
                    belief in the virtues of the private sector.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon described possible changes in the series. CDC was reviewing proposed
                    microfiche supplements to two of the 1955-57 volumes. These would include
                    verbatim records, background papers, and other material that could not be
                    conveniently included in the regular volumes. Narrative summaries also seemed
                    worthwhile. Current planning called for summaries and purport lists to be
                    collected and published as a separate volume after a triennial series was
                    completed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon continued that the Office had been working with GPO in designing some
                    format changes for the 1958-60 triennium. The purpose of the possible format
                    changes was to make the pages of the series more readable, less crowded, and
                    more efficiently handled in the new computerized printing technology.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked if name lists now appeared in every volume. Mr. Glennon said
                    that from now on, with few exceptions, each newly published volume would contain
                    a name list.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that not enough volumes had been released as yet in the new
                    triennial format to make a judgment on it. The Office was not rigidly committed
                    to the triennial format. Mr. Pickering pointed out that the triennial style gave
                    added problems to the declassification process because such a long period of
                    time was involved.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon noted that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> received considerable
                    publicity when the Indochina volume was released in August 1982. Extensive
                    coverage was provided in UPI and the <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that 18 to 20 journals regularly got review copies of new
                    volumes. Mr. Glennon noted that private publication might yield more extensive
                    publicity. In the near future, the Foreign Press Center would receive press
                    releases and summaries when new volumes appear. Mr. Smith commented that often
                    he did not receive notice of a volume’s availability until the supply had
                    already been exhausted. Mr. Glennon responded that a commercial publisher would
                    undoubtedly devote more effort to marketing the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked how drafters of documents would be identified. Mr. Glennon said
                    that such details would be indicated in footnotes of future volumes. Mr. Gaddis
                    and Mr. Glennon then discussed the problem of how to judge whether a document
                    reflected the views of its drafter, or those of his superiors.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany commented that the Office was experimenting with microfiche in other
                    contexts before trying to add such supplements to <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>.
                    To interrelate the fiche and the volume line by line with accurate and useful
                    cross-references involved much work and human resources. Long runs of documents,
                    such as verbatim minutes of conferences and negotiations or large bodies of
                    briefing papers seemed more suitable for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> microfiche
                    supplements until techniques and technology were considerably refined and
                    developed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hess noted that the scholarship required to compile a comprehensive
                    collection of important documents of an era on a subject had become increasingly
                    more complex. The important documents were not limited to the Department of
                    State’s files. Presidential libraries and the Freedom of Information offices
                    throughout the foreign affairs community also declassified documents; to keep
                    control of what was available was becoming very complex.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that the Office has begun inventories of those papers available
                    outside the Department official files worth preserving which might not routinely
                    be preserved at the National Archives under current regulations and procedures.
                    Mr. Glennon added that trips to Presidential libraries, begun in 1975, have
                    shown that more and more documents are available there on a declassified basis
                    as the years go by. Mr. Slany observed that FAIM has started to put onto fiche
                    long series of documents frequently requested through Freedom of Information.
                    The Historical Office would inventory such collections and help in their
                    preparation and preservation where necessary.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at noon, to be resumed at 2 P.M. for the closed
                    session.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Afternoon Session (Closed to the
                    Public)</hi></p>
                <p>[Here follow a presentation on foreign government information and related
                    subjects by Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary for
                    Classification/Declassification, and discussion with the Committee. This portion
                    of the minutes is retained in the Office of the Historian as a classified
                    document.]</p>
                <p rend="underline">Policy-Related Research</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany reported that the policy-related research program in the Office had
                    taken the largest segment of the Office’s resources for the last 12 months. The
                    Office had paused in the compilation of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes and
                    had concentrated on contributing historical background to the policy-making
                    process in the Department of State. Moreover, the Office felt a political need
                    to demonstrate to the Department our utility in these times of fiscal austerity.
                    He asked Ms. Noring to distribute a classified list of research projects done by
                    the Office in the past year.</p>
                <p>Although the historians in the Office had many areas of expertise, he went on, in
                    some instances the Office has not been or might not be able to respond to a
                    Department request on particular topics or those with a short time fuse. We
                    solicited Committee opinion on the idea of contracting out some research work
                    for the Department to the academic community. Mr. May asked what exactly did he
                    have in mind. Mr. Slany responded that he envisioned making use of the insight
                    and knowledge of the larger community of scholars for the good of the Department
                    on an as-needed basis when Office resources were unavailable or not suitable for
                    the topic. Mr. Smith asked if clearances would be necessary, to which Mr. Slany
                    responded that they could be arranged. Mr. Rubin said that the Department
                    already makes use of scholars in the international economic field. Mr. Slany
                    added that what he suggests is reaching out, much as the British and French do,
                    to professional expertise outside the government. Mr. Gaddis said the idea is
                    admirable, but real problems arise with clearances and the subsequent
                    restrictions a scholar must place on himself later on. Mr. Rubin said, that from
                    his own experience doing this type of contract work, most of the material is
                    unclassified. Mr. Rosecrance said that an interesting area for outside input
                    might be a comparison of the 1930s with the 1980s on the subject of
                    international economic policy. Even graduate students might be usefully employed
                    on that type of research. Mr. Rubin and Mr. Rosecrance both said that the
                    Department could probably get a lot of research done free.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis returned to the issue of clearance, citing the problems that have
                    arisen on restrictions in the CIA Scholar in Residence Program. Mr. Slany said
                    that a line might be drawn on the necessity for clearances, or that limited
                    access might be arranged <hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hess wondered how the Office selected the projects that were on the
                    list--were they self-initiated, solicited, or did they come through normal
                    channels? Mr. Slany answered that it was a mixture of all three. The Office
                    responds the best it can, and is now engaged in prioritizing a list of suggested
                    projects that we could do, which it will then circulate for Department reaction.
                    Mr. Smith asked if the Office worked on the research alone. Mr. Slany said that,
                    other than going back to the requester for redefinition or arranging access or
                    providing feedback the Office does the work without collaboration.</p>
                <p>Mr. Smith queried whether historical research is produced in other bureaus. Mr.
                    Slany replied that INR, the Department Library, the National Archives, the
                    Office of the Legal Adviser, and the Bureau of Economic and Business Affairs all
                    prepare research papers; the Historical Office prepares only a small percentage
                    of the Department’s research. We must make the Department aware of our skills,
                    he added. Mr. Rubin felt that perhaps the Department did not know of the
                    existence of the Office at all. Mr. Slany said that the Department was most
                    aware of the Office in its role as an advocate for the release of documents and
                    that this reputation worked against the Office in most other contexts.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis, returning to the idea of contract historians, asked if Mr. Slany was
                    thinking of individual academic historians or groups of academic historians. Mr.
                    Slany said he was thinking of both. Mr. Gaddis suggested trying out the idea on
                    an unclassified basis. Mr. Smith said that small research projects might be done
                    on a volunteer basis. Mr. May reminded the Committee that when you set up a
                    board of consultants to whom you grant special access, others without that
                    access become extremely sensitive. Mr. Smith said that access to classified
                    material often helps a researcher to ask the right questions even if he
                    eventually makes no direct use of the classified information. Mr. Gaddis
                    reiterated his support for the idea that thus a broad range of previously
                    untapped expertise can be plugged into.</p>
                <p rend="underline"><hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current
                        Documents</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Slany reported that, despite promises made to the Committee last year,
                    neither Current Documents 1981 or Basic Documents 1977-80 had yet been
                    published. The reasons are twofold: the microfiche supplement to the 1981 volume
                    created technical problems far beyond our expectations, and the private
                    publisher we contracted with has unexpectedly delayed the process. Mr. Claussen
                    was asked to report in more detail.</p>
                <p>Mr. Claussen said that HO has received the page proofs for <hi rend="italic"
                        >Basic Documents</hi> 1977-1980 and that 75% of <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> 1981 has been set. He offered to leave these items and some
                    prototype samples with the Committee. Mr. Claussen described <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> as a “learning experience,” stating that this is the
                    first time HO has used a large team of editors to compile a volume as well as a
                    smaller team of senior editors to review it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Claussen discussed the new technology being explored with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi>: computerized typesetting and microform supplements.
                    The former does not involve a waiver from GPO, but still eases the most
                    labor-intensive part of the publication process. It takes 9 to 10 months to set
                    up, at which point the camera-ready copy goes to GPO. GPO signs the project over
                    to a contractor, but HO will have control of the camera-ready copy. Once the
                    bugs are worked out of the system, a 10-day turn-around time should be
                    possible.</p>
                <p>HO has built a methodology for preparing microform supplements and has identified
                    its pitfalls. The <hi rend="italic">Supplement</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> will have an index and eye-visible document numbers. The
                    printed volume will have cross-references to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Supplement</hi>. The volume is intended to stand by itself.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance asked how it was possible to publish volumes in the manner Mr.
                    Claussen described without getting a waiver from GPO. Mr. Slany replied that we
                    are allowed to present GPO with camera-ready copy. GPO is still the printer.
                    This method may or may not have saved the taxpayers money. He continued that the
                    first part of the <hi rend="italic">Supplement</hi> will contain the full texts
                    of documents extracted in the printed volume and texts of additional documents
                    arranged by subject, while a second microfiche supplement containing the
                    Department’s noon press briefings, materials from the White House Press Office,
                    and Department of Defense briefings will be published later. Mr. Claussen stated
                    that we intend to ask GPO to prepare a paperback version of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Current Documents</hi> to sell at a lesser price. Mr. Gaddis asked if the
                    lessons learned from <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> will be applied to
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Slany said they would.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 3:21 p.m. so that the Committee could hold its private
                    meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
