<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1983</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1983</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-03-10">March 10, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1983-11-10">November 10, 1983</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1983-11-10-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 418 KB, 24pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, Correspondence - 1983 - Meeting.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn95">Footnote 95</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1983 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 10, 1983</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Carol S. Gruber, Department of History, William Paterson College,
                        Wayne, New Jersey 07470</item>
                    <item>Dr. John L. Gaddis, Department of History, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
                        45701</item>
                    <item>Dr. Ernest R. May, John F. Kennedy School of Government, Harvard
                        University, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Gaddis Smith, Department of History, Yale University, New Haven,
                        Connecticut 06520 (Not Present)</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Ole R. Holsti, Department of Political Science, Duke University,
                        Durham, North Carolina 27706</item>
                    <item>Dr. Richard N. Rosecrance, Center for International Studies, Cornell
                        University, Ithaca, New York 14853</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Seymour J. Rubin, Executive Vice President and Executive Director, The
                        American Society of International Law, 2223 Massachusetts Avenue, N.W.,
                        Washington, D.C., 20003</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John T. McCarthy, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Acting Deputy Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Acting General Editor of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS)</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring, Acting Adviser on Research</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Carol A. Becker</item>
                    <item>Bret D. Bellamy</item>
                    <item>Karen L. Bryfogle</item>
                    <item>Suzanne E. Coffman</item>
                    <item>Stephen DeMuth</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Kay K. Herring</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>David S. Painter</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>William Hamilton, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs Information Management Center (A/FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Paul Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division</item>
                    <item>John F. Ellsworth, Chief, Editing Branch</item>
                    <item>Rita M. Baker, Acting Chief, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of Plans and Opinion Analysis (PA/OAP):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane</item>
                    <item>Alvin Richman</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Daniel Helmstadter, President, Scholarly Resources, Inc.</item>
                    <item>Wayne Cole, Professor of History, University of Maryland</item>
                    <item>Page Miller, American Historical Association</item>
                    <item>Cathy A. Caplicki, Sign Language Association</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Morning Session</hi></p>
                <p>Mr. Slany called the meeting to order at 9:14 a.m. He introduced Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary John McCarthy, who welcomed the Advisory Committee. Mr. McCarthy
                    explained that although he had received his B.A. in history, he has been a
                    Foreign Service Officer for some 20 years where his timeframe has become “what
                    happened yesterday”. He was glad to be back today in the company of historians.
                    He stated that the publications of the Office of the Historian were essential
                    and important. Although there were problems of declassification, he felt that
                    personnel necessary to do the job were already in place. He expressed his
                    pleasure that members of the Committee would come to Washington to help with the
                    often controversial yet essential program of the Historical Office. He hoped to
                    spend most of the day at the meeting to hear their views.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said he merely served as the Committee’s executive secretary and thus
                    would turn the meeting over to the members. He quickly ran through the agenda
                    and noted that there would be a coffee break in about an hour. Luncheon would be
                    served for the committee at the Foreign Service Club, and would be hosted by
                    William Schneider, Jr., Under Secretary of State for Security Assistance,
                    Science and Technology.</p>
                <p>He said that operating procedure required that at least a part of the annual
                    meeting be open to the public. The morning session was to be open, but the
                    afternoon session beginning at 2:00 would be closed so that classified material
                    could be discussed.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that the first order of business would be for the Advisory
                    Committee members to elect a chairperson. Mr. Gaddis and Ms. Gruber nominated
                    Mr. May. After Mr. Holsti seconded the motion, members elected Mr. May by
                    acclamation.</p>
                <p>Mr. May asked The Historian to present his report.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then suggested that a number of important issues which had been raised
                    in briefing materials sent in advance to the members might be discussed early in
                    the meeting: the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Users’ survey, <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> format (both appearance and structure
                    of volumes, including the proposed Vietnam project) and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> production process. As the annual rate of
                    publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> has slowed down in the
                    last five to eight years, the series is slipping further and further from
                    currency. However, with patient negotiation within the Department, he believes
                    the Office will be able to make progress. Problems in the publication process
                    presently affect the series as never before primarily because technology has
                    switched from linotype to computerized photocomposition. Having already prepared
                    an enormous backlog of volumes (most of which had not yet been cleared for
                    publication), we believe it would be unwise to continue to compile additional
                    volumes at a rapid rate. Under the circumstances, it is preferable to be very
                    selective. He pointed to the Vietnam project as an example. Through the FOI
                    procedures much of the Vietnam material has already been declassified on a
                    helter-skelter basis. The available record should be gathered and combined with
                    the remainder of the basic historical material in its proper historical context.
                    He said the Office of the Historian was also examining other topics such as the
                    US-USSR conflict over Cuba in the early 1960’s, material which many people are
                    also requesting under FOI.</p>
                <p>The Office is also exploring other projects, for example, <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Foreign Policy: Current Documents</hi>. These volumes bring
                    together many documents, all of which have already been available, and when
                    published, put more of the foreign affairs record into the public domain. In
                    addition, other records can be published on microfilm, which will further widen
                    access to diplomatic records.</p>
                <p>He said that policy-supportive historical research has been given some priority
                    within the Office of the Historian. The Department needs historical insight and
                    advice. The Office of the Historian can either provide it itself or reach those
                    in the academic community who can provide it. After more than a year, the Office
                    has established a system of priority topics. Some research has taken the form of
                    narratives, some has been produced as documentary collections, and some as
                    chronologies. The Office of the Historian has been trying to find a mix which
                    will be useful to policy makers. In addition, the Office has attempted to find
                    the most feasible method to reach out to the academic community for specialized
                    policy studies that cannot be done readily by the staff of 22 historians. The
                    Department needs to be reminded of what the Historical Office can do, because
                    the Office has probably lost some of its Departmental identity in the last
                    decade.</p>
                <p>Whereas historical research studies are regarded as useful tools to policy
                    makers, Office advocacy of liberal disclosure and access policies may threaten
                    policy makers and make their work more difficult.</p>
                <p>The Office feels responsible for keeping the Department and the academic
                    community aware of access policies in other governments. Mr. Petersen is
                    directing a project to canvas foreign ministries around the world regarding
                    their own policies on access to diplomatic records.</p>
                <p>We are trying to work within the Department of State to identify important
                    records--especially lot files--to preserve for historical research.
                    Record-keeping in the Department needs all the help it can get, and we are
                    trying to provide our expertise and help to maintain records properly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany continued that the Office has become an advocate of good
                    records-keeping despite the irritation it may cause elsewhere in the Department.
                    The problem is more difficult with the more recent records being kept on
                    computer tape and microfilm. The Office must help to work out how these tapes
                    can be accessed at NARS and how they can be used by diplomatic historians.
                    Historical records must be permanent, accessible, and free from tampering and
                    loss. Some of the Office staff would have to work on this.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany noted that Mr. McCarthy and the Bureau of Public Affairs have supported
                    the Office financially and in other ways. Mr. Slany said that while there had
                    been some shrinkage in the staff, the Office of the Historian will be recruiting
                    new members. There are still limits on recruiting. Under OPM regulations, the
                    Office provides position descriptions, while OPM provides registers of
                    “qualified” applicants.</p>
                <p>In response to Mr. May’s query as to what steps the Office of the Historian was
                    taking in helping to preserve the historical record, Mr. Slany replied that the
                    Office was trying to have an input into the Foreign Affairs Information System
                    (FAIS). Mr. May asked Mr. Slany to say more about keeping the historical record
                    straight. Mr. Slany replied that cables are now kept on line in the computer for
                    about six months and then are dumped off onto tapes and microfiche. This process
                    has been trimmed and adjusted frequently since the early 1970’s. The difficulty
                    for the Office has been in figuring out all these changes and gaining access to
                    the records. There is a fear that perhaps the computerized information may be
                    lost or that the programmers who have hand-crafted the software might someday
                    disappear. The Office has attempted to participate in various committees to give
                    advice on how records can best be preserved. Lot files are another problem. How
                    can powerful, important Bureaus of the Department be persuaded to incorporate
                    their records into a computerized system? The Office seeks to hire an expert on
                    machine-readable records.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then mentioned that the Office might begin to prepare a nucleus of
                    highly classified current records on certain important subjects which could be
                    provided instantly to policy makers on request. The Department would have to
                    feel comfortable that the records would be safe in historians’ hands. The idea
                    is to capture those documents of transcendent importance on the computer soon
                    after the events, not 25 years later. When the records are on paper the problem
                    is the time involved in trying to locate them (whether in Bureau offices or
                    FAIM), negotiating access to them, and then ensuring that they are not screened
                    or destroyed--actions which would compromise the historical record.</p>
                <p>Mr. May asked whether the Office planned to do this independently or through the
                    Executive Secretariat. Mr. Slany replied that he did not envisage the Office
                    doing this independently, but that there is a bureaucratic problem in getting
                    Office input into the area of records keeping. Right now the Office was only
                    beginning to edge into the door. When Mr. May asked where the responsibility for
                    records keeping rests now, Mr. Slany said that it rests in the Executive
                    Secretariat which has its own computer system (SADI) and also in FAIM. We have
                    worked with FAIM in pointing out that the Secretary of State’s records, for
                    example, should be preserved separately and not carted off to private
                    depositories.</p>
                <p>Mr. McCarthy noted that the Office of the Historian has recently “insinuated”
                    itself in several bureau staff meetings. Office members find out what is going
                    on in the bureaus in this fashion and can help out the bureaus when they begin
                    to ask what has happened on given issues in the past.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked for information on the prospect of getting a private publishing
                    firm to publish the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Mr. Slany
                    said that Publishing Services may also want to comment on difficulties over the
                    past year in working on acquiring a GPO waiver. He said that the current
                    Authorization Act for State, Justice, and Commerce includes a requirement that
                    the Historian of the Department of State report to the two committees on the
                    delay in publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    resulting both from declassification and publication problems. It has not been
                    entirely resolved what steps we can take, but he knows that the Joint Committee
                    on Printing (JCP) is receptive to suggestions.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington said the JCP will listen to a case for change if we can make it.
                    But a strong case, especially evidence that the Government Printing Office (GPO)
                    is slow and costly, is needed to get an exemption from the GPO under Title 44 of
                    the US Code. It is a serious matter, and we do not have agreement within the
                    Department yet. We have different responsibilities. There have been delays in
                    both Publishing Services and also in the GPO where subcontracting is often
                    involved. We have two options, one of which is a partial exemption which would
                    entail having direct typesetting done by outside contractors. However he does
                    not have the authority to act independently in this. He agrees with Mr. Slany
                    that there are two aspects: first, the transition from hot type to a mix of new
                    technologies, and second, the need to get attitudes and priorities changed at
                    the GPO and elsewhere regarding the still unresolved question as to whether or
                    not volumes are finally declassified when they go to typesetting. He said Mr.
                    Slany was correct in his time frame of 17-18 months for release after
                    declassification. Mr. Washington said he was willing to go along to get a waiver
                    from the JCP, but we would have to make the case first.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis said he was puzzled. Weren’t the volumes declassified before they were
                    sent to the printer?</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington replied no, the last two volumes had to be purged of classified
                    material. It slows the system to have to “cut and paste.” He said that
                    $100,00[0] per volume was much too high, that $30,000-$50,000 should be the
                    range. GPO prices were almost twice as high for the entire production as
                    commercial publishing would be.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked how that affected the cost to the purchaser.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington replied that GPO set the price too high. He said he had questioned
                    the GPO pricing format, and that GPO was thinking about letting the agencies
                    come in and negotiate.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked about paperback editions. Mr. Slany said that GPO has told us
                    that the price differential from hard cover may not be very large.</p>
                <p>When Mr. Gaddis then asked whether the new production technologies for the
                    1955-1957 series might not solve many of these production problems, Mr. Glennon
                    responded, “We would hope so.” Mr. Slany remarked that we have been too
                    optimistic in the past.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rubin noted that his own experience with delays in American Society of
                    International Law (ASIL) publications suggested that the Office’s optimism
                    should be restrained. Mr. Rubin added that he was also surprised that galleys
                    rather than manuscript were reviewed for declassification and wanted further
                    explanation of the declassification process, including reactions to the problems
                    mentioned in Ian Black’s recent article in the <hi rend="italic">Washington
                        Post</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany replied that it was easier for reviewers to read galleys or page proofs
                    than photocopies of the actual documents. Galleys also look more authoritative.
                    He commented further that the Office tried to explain to the CDC why documents
                    should be declassified, such as showing that the information already is in the
                    public domain. Our role now, however, is much more difficult because many more
                    people and agencies are involved in the declassification process. We are ground
                    between competing forces. The declassification process is now institutionalized.
                    However, he believed Ian Black’s article to be too pessimistic. He said we must
                    realize that the system we have was unavoidable -- that we couldn’t go back to
                    the procedures of ten to fifteen years ago. If no one advocated freer access
                    within the government, then the outside community questions us. Conversely,
                    advocating freer access causes Department insiders to question us.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked if the Office of the Historian operated as an alien presence
                    within the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany replied that it was alien only in the sense that the study of history
                    lies outside the daily operational scope of the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis inquired whether Mr. Slany was talking only of President Reagan’s
                    recent Executive Order or more generally. Mr. Slany said the historical
                    record is not always favorable to the Department, yet it is the Office’s task to
                    bring this information to light. The Department must be informed where the
                    smoking guns are. Whether or not it could be published, the Historical Office
                    was responsible for compiling a complete, accurate foreign affairs record. The
                    Department needed such a record, even if its sensitivity in places prevented
                    full disclosure.</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant McCarthy responded that the size and the importance of the U.S.
                    government in the period currently being declassified was a new phenomenon, and
                    that this added to the problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis then wondered whether the declassification problems have taken a
                    quantum jump over the last year or whether the process has been more gradual.
                    Mr. Slany said it has been gradual, and our task is to educate the
                    reviewers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rubin then cited AHA Executive Secretary Gammon’s comments in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Washington Post</hi> article on growing difficulties in
                    declassification. Mr. Rubin stated that resolutions passed by the ASIL annual
                    meetings had endorsed faster publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> until last year when there was no such resolution because he
                    believed that progress had been made and one was no longer necessary. From his
                    own experience in the Department of State, he believes there is
                    overclassification of documents, and then cited a recent example of denial of
                    publication of a document by the Legal Adviser’s Office, even though the
                    information had been published in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis remarked that the tone of this year’s report by the Historian was much
                    less optimistic than last year’s. Then there were more problems with GPO than
                    with declassification, but this does not appear to be true this year. Mr.
                    Glennon replied that the two problems are somewhat interrelated. Last year at
                    this time six volumes had been declassified, and in the past it was reasonable
                    to assume that they would all be published in a year. But only three have been
                    printed, and three more will not come out until 1984. Two more have been
                    declassified, so five are in the publisher’s pipeline. Declassification is still
                    slow. There is much more cooperation today and we are doing much better, but we
                    still are not at the pace we desire. There are over 60 volumes in the pipeline,
                    including the 1958-1960 and Vietnam volumes now being compiled. Three volumes in
                    linotype this year cost well over $100,000 per volume. The lag time is now 19
                    months; one volume declassified in November 1981 has still not been published.
                    This is a difficult transition period.</p>
                <p>Mr. May thought that the declassification problems might well increase with
                    documents in the mid-1950’s and beyond.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany raised the question of what constitutes an adequate record for
                    publication. Should we go forward even for the early 1950’s when there are some
                    key missing documents? What is a reasonable level of documentation, one that can
                    still justify publication? This is an agonizing problem. We cannot be
                    intransigent with the CDC. We have to work with them. Some portion of the
                    compiled record will probably always be denied declassification at 25 or 30
                    years. The Historical Office has no clear measure of what an “adequate” level of
                    documents may be. Mr. Gaddis remarked that the user survey is clear on this; a
                    majority preferred later publication of a fuller record.</p>
                <p>Is it likely, Mr. Gaddis continued, that there will be a shift in the future to
                    jump ahead to more easily declassified areas, such as in the Vietnam volumes?
                    Mr. Slany responded that the record is compromised to some extent if we do not
                    proceed across the board. This problem has been argued within the Office, but we
                    do not want to compile in a helter-skelter fashion. Mr. Gaddis surmised that the
                    Office might want the Advisory Committee’s advice on the matter.</p>
                <p>The Advisory Committee meeting then adjourned at 10:33 a.m. for a short
                    break.</p>
                <p rend="underline">User Survey</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon reported on the results of the user survey. (Messrs. Richman and
                    Kane, of the Office of Plans and Opinion Analysis, had worked on the survey, and
                    joined the meeting at this point.) He noted that the Committee had received
                    copies of the report.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon addressed first the selection of the audience for the user survey.
                    The Office of the Historian did a study of citations in scholarly journals to
                    identify the authors of works on <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>-related topics since 1861. The citation study determined that
                    these authors were primarily SHAFR members, with a few OAH and AHA members also.
                    The Office of Plans and Opinion Analysis then proceeded to make a composite
                    mailing list of over 1600 names composed of 733 SHAFR members and 873 persons on
                    PA’s list of individuals interested in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon characterized the response to the survey as “excellent.” Of the 1606
                    persons surveyed, 49% completed and returned the survey. Normally, twenty
                    percent is considered a good response to an unsolicited survey. Mr. Glennon
                    outlined the four categories of questions on the survey: (1) use of the series,
                    (2) access to the series, (3) <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> content,
                    and (4) demographics, or user profile.</p>
                <p>The users’ profile revealed that 82% of the users are Ph.D.s , that 90% consider
                    themselves “historians,” and that 63% classify themselves diplomatic historians.
                    Mr. Glennon commented that this latter figure was surprisingly low--less than
                    two-thirds of the sample.</p>
                <p>The survey revealed that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is a
                    heavily-used and highly valued commodity. Seventy-seven percent of the
                    respondents found the series “vital” to their research, while 18% characterized
                    it as “very useful,” a total of 95%. Ninety-six percent felt that the study of
                    diplomatic history would suffer without <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi>. Ninety-three of the respondents used the series as a research
                    tool, while 70% used it as a teaching aid.</p>
                <p>The questions on access to the series yielded surprising results. 78% of the
                    respondents had “convenient” access to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.
                    80% used library copies, and 53% said they would be interested in buying
                    paperback copies if they were available. Mr. Glennon commented that the
                    Historical Office has made no decisions yet on the feasibility of providing <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in paperback. GPO does not
                    recommend binding the volumes in paper because of their generally heavy
                    use--most <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes are sent to libraries. Further,
                    GPO cannot promise greatly reduced prices for paperback volumes; the estimates
                    they are quoting are only a few dollars cheaper than hardbound copies. Mr.
                    Glennon continued that Paul Washington of Publishing Services had questioned
                    GPO’s estimates and was investigating them further. In the end, binding the
                    volumes in paper might not be feasible, for “<hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is not a mass sale item.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon ended his presentation with a discussion of the questions on
                    editorial features. These questions addressed the series’ comprehensiveness as
                    well as its presentation. 57% of the respondents favored thorough documentation
                    of events. 64% favored later publication of a more complete record rather than
                    earlier publication of less comprehensive volumes. Mr. Glennon specified that
                    the survey did not ask whether the respondents preferred a 20-year versus a
                    30-year line for publication of documents; after much discussion in The Office
                    of the Historian and OAP, it was decided that the survey could not present this
                    question adequately. The question on comprehensiveness was viewed as a way to
                    get around this problem. Regarding “editorial innovations,” which Mr. Glennon
                    defined as items such as methodological statements and identification lists, the
                    response was very favorable at 77%. The Office intends to include methodological
                    statements in all <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes beginning
                    with the Vietnam volumes now in preparation.</p>
                <p>On the question of microform supplements to the series, 99% of the respondents
                    stated that they had used microform and about one-third found it “physically
                    uncomfortable” to use. Organization by subject parallel to that of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes was generally favored. Mr.
                    Glennon stated that the Historical Office was grappling with the question of
                    microform and intended to pursue it. The Office of the Historian was unsure
                    about pegging microform publications directly to the volumes because of
                    cross-referencing and clearance problems. Instead, the Historical Office is
                    considering microform publication of special collections not available anywhere
                    else which would provide a significant amount of material to scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked what kind of “special material.” Mr. Glennon responded that
                    certain lot files were one such group. He defined the difference between the lot
                    files and the central files, citing the Secretariat’s conference files and NSC
                    files as examples of the latter. He stated also that The Office of the Historian
                    could “contrive” lot files, giving as an example the materials used in the
                    preparation of the 1955-57 volume on China relating to the Wang-Johnson
                    discussions--full texts of telegrams giving nearly verbatim records of meetings,
                    correspondence. This package would be given to the CDC for clearance and would
                    receive a lot file number. Once it had been declassified, it would be eligible
                    for microform publication. It would not be a part of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, but would be useful to the scholar.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany added that A/CDC has declassified a number of bodies of documents from
                    the late 1940’s and early 1950’s including the Daily Summaries, Secretary’s
                    Memoranda of Conversation, and <hi rend="italic">Current Economic
                        Developments</hi>. The Office of the Historian wants to get this
                    documentation into the public domain before new events require that it be
                    reclassified, as has sometimes happened with <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. He concluded that the Office is thinking of microform
                    supplements in terms of “unique” bodies of documents particularly useful for
                    study of diplomatic history.</p>
                <p>Returning to the issue of publishing early with an incomplete record or
                    publishing later with a more complete record, Mr. Slany stated that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is intended to be the best, most
                    comprehensive record of American diplomatic history. A/CDC and others are
                    obliged to withhold sensitive materials after the Office of the Historian has
                    collected the best, fullest record for use within the Department. When material
                    is not declassified, has the Historical Office already done its job by making it
                    available to the Department, or must the Office struggle within its own
                    bureaucracy to assure release? Mr. Slany solicited the Committee’s advice and
                    guidance.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance asked whether a 35-year declassification line might persuade the
                    government to open the entire record. Slany responded that there was no reason
                    to be sanguine that the effect would be an improvement. Mr. Rosecrance commented
                    that even the British had once had a 50-year line and then had published
                    everything. Mr. Slany responded that there were bodies of U.S records that would
                    have to be protected much longer than 50 years. Mr. Gaddis added that the
                    British had never let everything out.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Holsti, Mr. Slany noted that the Office of the
                    Historian presently considered each volume on its own merits in considering
                    whether the record was complete enough to publish, and he pointed to the
                    forthcoming volume dealing with Latin America, 1952-1954, in which Guatemala
                    posed a particular problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked if the question of withholding materials would be addressed in
                    the methodological statement. Mr. Slany answered that the Office of the
                    Historian would try, but that we could not point to any specific agency as being
                    responsible for not releasing the documents. Mr. Holsti then inquired whether
                    the Office could point to where the record as presented in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> is complete and where it is less so. Mr. Gaddis
                    added that in using files at NARS, he had found helpful the sheets noting where
                    a classified document had been withdrawn, and that he wondered if a comparable
                    procedure would be useful in the printed volumes. Mr. Slany asked the Committee
                    to take up this matter in its report. He stated further that such a procedure
                    had been contemplated for volumes soon to be published. A/CDC and other
                    Department units opposed procedures that might single-out still classified
                    documents and stimulate FOI requests. The Historical Office was eager to include
                    such information for the sake of an accurate record that did not dangerously
                    distort through omission. Mr. Gaddis suggested that perhaps a summary which did
                    not refer to specific documents but which identified the more heavily sanitized
                    areas could be used. Mr. Glennon responded that this had been tried, but that
                    summaries had to be cleared in the Department, too. Ms. Gruber asked if the
                    Historical Office had tried to substitute other materials for withheld
                    documents, and whether this effort had been satisfactory. Mr. Slany answered
                    that it had not.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon elaborated that there were two kinds of “No” from CDC: “No” meaning
                    “not now,” and “No” meaning “not ever.” Guatemala, he continued, was a “not
                    ever”; the Historical Office did the best it could. In other cases, (for
                    example, China,) CDC instructed the Office to wait for the demise of Mao and
                    Chou En-lai. We delayed the volume’s release, and got the documents
                    declassified. Mr. Gaddis asked if a distinction between the two kinds of “No”
                    would provide the guidelines the Office is seeking. Mr. Rubin stated that it
                    would in the easy cases, but that in the more difficult cases the question
                    should be whether the omission of material distorts what is printed. Mr. Gaddis
                    wondered if the Historical Office could somehow indicate the “no, never”
                    decisions--it would be a clue to researchers that a significant body of
                    documentation is missing. Mr. Glennon answered that this in effect was being
                    done already in the summaries of the volumes’ contents. If they are read
                    carefully, one can see that the Historical Office has tried to indicate such
                    omissions. But the summaries still have to be cleared.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked if “No, never” is inflexible. Mr. Glennon answered that “never”
                    is firm enough, defining it as our “working lifetime.” Mr. Slany added that
                    another prickly issue was that the delay of publication could cause more
                    documents to be withheld, rather than released.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance raised the question of the integrity of the series. Using the
                    Freedom of Information Act, someone could obtain the sanitized material and
                    undercut the volume by producing a more complete work. He asked if FOIA differed
                    from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> declassification, noting that some
                    historians got “amazing” material declassified through the former. Mr. Slany
                    stated that the broader criteria for declassification used by the Systematic
                    Review (SR) staff of A/CDC produced a far greater volume of cleared papers than
                    the Mandatory Review (MR) staff were able to clear for occasional FOI
                    requests.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked if SR and MR used the same reviewers. Mr. Slany said no, but
                    added that [William] Hamilton’s people [SR] were sympathetically disposed toward
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, and were probably more
                    knowledgeable on special historical topics. It is always possible that someone
                    may get documents not in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, but then the
                    Office of the Historian may not have sought out certain types of documents. One
                    of the reasons for a methodological statement is to give the scholar an idea of
                    which sources were used and which were not. The Office of the Historian
                    annotates the volumes to make the context of the published documents perfectly
                    clear.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rubin commented that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> takes a broad
                    look at an issue, while FOIA deals with particular sets of documents. The
                    scholar spends more time on a particular, narrower subject and thus comes up
                    with a larger number of documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance stated that there was an argument here for “conspiracy,” a
                    partnership between the different types of reviewers. Mr. Slany suggested that
                    he might wish to address this comment to Ambassador Burke during the afternoon
                    session.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis commented that in his field, no one regards <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> as the definitive work. It is, however, an excellent overview
                    and a guide to the National Archives. It helps the scholar focus his topic and
                    to determine where he needs to go with it. Mr. Rubin added that the scholar has
                    different reasons for going to the Archives than does the Historical Office.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that the Historical Office hoped to make <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> more useable and more accessible to its usership.
                    Two types of changes were being considered: format and altered mode of
                    presentation. Our goal in changing the physical appearance was to make the
                    volumes both more useful and easier to produce. Mr. Slany felt that the proposed
                    format, samples of which were provided to the Committee members, achieved this.
                    The switch from annual to triennial volumes was made because the former
                    organization multiplied preparation and publication problems. Mr. Slany
                    commented that he knew the Committee and other <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> users had not seen enough of the new triennial volumes either
                    to condemn or to endorse the change.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked whether smaller volumes within the triennial cycle could
                    facilitate the publication process. Mr. Slany noted that this approach accorded
                    with the Historical Office’s present thinking. Arranging the foreign policy
                    record in smaller volumes allowed for working with CDC to identify those
                    compilations which could be published earlier, and those which had to be delayed
                    because of clearance problems. This approach would be applied across the board
                    with the 1955-1957 triennium.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon noted that the existence of parts and appendices can cause confusion
                    when trying to amass a complete set of the series. Although the 1955-57 volumes
                    have now been split, it is too late to do this with the 1952-54 volumes, as some
                    are already out. Mr. Glennon commented that the new organization would make
                    things easier all around: production of the volumes, cost, uniformity in size,
                    less hold-up in publication, no proliferation of parts. He felt that
                    reformatting the pages would make them look cleaner. There would be no physical
                    change in the trim size of the volumes. Mr. Gaddis inquired whether the document
                    file numbers would still be included. Mr. Glennon replied that they would.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Documenting the Vietnam War in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Series</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon observed that the first step for the Vietnam volumes was achieved
                    with publication of the two-part volume on Indochina for 1952-1954. The
                    1955-1957 and 1958-1960 volumes, which were compiled earlier, are being expanded
                    and are near completion. Four volumes are planned for the period 1961-1963: one
                    covering 1961, one covering 1962, and two covering 1963. Six historians, the
                    General Editor, and a research assistant are working on the Vietnam series. The
                    compilation schedule established for the volumes is being met. Taking up each of
                    the projected volumes individually, Mr. Glennon noted that the 1955-1957 volume
                    is presently being reviewed, and will be finished this month. CDC review of this
                    volume is in hand and is favorable. Clearance of the volume rests with the NSC.
                    The 1958-1960 volume will be completed and reviewed by February 1984.
                    Compilation of the 1961-1963 volumes will be complete by April; review will be
                    complete by summer. CDC has promised expedited review. Mr. Glennon projected
                    publication of the Vietnam volumes to begin in 1985, and to be complete in
                    1986.</p>
                <p>Looking ahead, Mr. Glennon stated that the Office plan called for taking the
                    series through the 1960’s but he noted that the focus would be solely on
                    Vietnam, not the entire Indochina area. This was being done because Vietnam
                    constituted a “window” in declassification which had to be exploited before it
                    closed because of international developments which might have the effect of
                    “resensitizing” some of the documentation. Turning to the Johnson period,
                    Glennon noted that we confront “a bit of a problem” in that the Johnson Library
                    has not processed material beyond 1965 as yet. In the long range, the Historical
                    Office intends to push the series through 1975, although there are no current
                    plans for preparation of volumes for the Nixon period.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked whether the materials used in compiling the series would include
                    domestic developments bearing on Vietnam policy. Mr. Glennon assured her that
                    such material would be included, especially in the Johnson period.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked the Committee to consider the Vietnam volumes in the context of
                    the entire series and to provide guidance on the question of scope. As presently
                    evolving, the Vietnam series could involve a great number of volumes, which
                    would tax the resources of the Office and the declassification resources of the
                    Department. Would the committee prefer a more limited series, in terms of scope,
                    which could be published earlier? Mr. Rosecrance asked whether we couldn’t do
                    both - publish substantial volumes as well as an overview. Slany said we could
                    do so. Ms. Gruber asked about the prospects for additional staff to work on the
                    series. Mr. Slany said that the Committee could make such a suggestion.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance asked about the sources used for the project. He noted that during
                    the Kissinger period, off-the-record telephone conversations and back-channel
                    contacts were used. Would the compilers have access to White House and NSC
                    documents? Would there be a full reading? Mr. Mabon replied that for 1955-60 the
                    telcons were well known. There was already access to microfilmed, expurgated
                    versions, to which the Historical Office hoped to add. Mr. Sampson added that
                    the Kennedy tapes are not yet fully transcribed, but that the Historical Office
                    was going to request this. He continued that the compilers had seen most of the
                    material at the Kennedy Library, although some collections, like the Robert
                    Kennedy papers, are still closed. The record appears fairly complete; the
                    Historical Office will know more about this at the end of the compiling for the
                    1963 volume.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany returned to the question of the desirability of pursuing the
                    publication of a Vietnam series which would be reduced in scope, in order to
                    take advantage of the “window” of declassification before it closed. Mr. Slany
                    commented that the Historical Office may be able to “strike a deal” with the NSC
                    and the White House. By opting for an early but abbreviated sub-series, the
                    Historical Office may be able to receive maximum access if declassification
                    delays publication of a larger more comprehensive series of volumes. The Office
                    of the Historian may be able to “defeat the FOI route” by opening material in
                    “one fell swoop.” He then said that he was concerned about the concentration on
                    the 1962-63 period. When, he asked, will compilers reach 1969?</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis reflected on the academic community’s reaction to the project. He
                    stated that he could see the bureaucratic reasons for the project, but he felt
                    some concern about the diversion of resources from the rest of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He could see the project’s
                    raising some concern in the profession, which would “welcome [the project’s]
                    depth,” but question its priority. Mr. Gaddis then asked how the Historical
                    Office’s Vietnam project differed from the Center for Military History’s Vietnam
                    projects. Mr. Slany requested that the question be deferred until after
                    lunch.</p>
                <p>Before closing the session, Mr. May expressed his own misgivings. Our
                    understanding of history is shaped by documentary evidence, he stated. We
                    already have a distorted view of Southeast Asia, and he fears that the Vietnam
                    project may assist this distorted view.</p>
                <p>The session adjourned at 12:05 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Afternoon Session (Closed to the
                    Public)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Declassification</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke said that he would continue the topic of discussion introduced
                    at lunch. He stated that he had not prepared formal remarks on A/CDC since the
                    relationship to the Historical Office was essentially the same as in the
                    previous year’s report. The Ambassador stated that he did however wish to draw
                    the Committee’s attention to the activities of the CDC in the field of mandatory
                    review requests. He stated that no document is exempt from mandatory review
                    (which is primarily generated by FOI requests) but that many documents in the
                    mandatory review process are referrals from the Presidential Libraries and are
                    additional to FOIA cases. (He circulated recently declassified samples.)
                    Statistics indicate that in a recent period 1100 mandatory review cases were
                    received from Presidential libraries of which 467 were cleared for
                    declassification, 451 were cleared in sanitized form, and 77 were denied
                    clearances.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke then drew the Committee’s attention to the recent report of the
                    Information Security Oversight Office (ISOO) which contained statistics on
                    declassification by departments, and noted that copies of the report were
                    available.</p>
                <p>Next, Ambassador Burke explained that NSDD 84 of March 11, 1983, should be seen
                    as an effort by the administration to control leaks. Administratively, there are
                    two new forms for employees to sign--a general non-disclosure form and a form
                    for people who have access to Special Compartmented Information (SCI). The focus
                    of concern is on pre-publication review of writings by present and former
                    officials of the U.S. Government. The SCI Information form is narrowly focused
                    to three inter-related categories of information which trigger the need for
                    pre-publication review. He noted that a Department of Justice official has
                    stated that the sole purpose of the form is to allow the deletion of classified
                    information. The government, he said, has no intention of deleting or censoring
                    views and opinions which it does not like, even if they might have an adverse
                    impact on U.S. foreign policy. In fact, the new form is not as restrictive as
                    the old one.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador reiterated that A/CDC operates only within the confines of its
                    charter and that the relationship between PA/HO and A/CDC is stable. He also
                    stated that he does not perceive the declassification of documents for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to be appreciably slower now than it
                    was under previous systems. As a corollary he stated that the declassification
                    of record blocks by NARS under Department of State funding is proceeding on the
                    timetable agreed upon by the Archivist and the Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance inquired if it would be possible for the Advisory Committee to see
                    the A/CDC guidelines for declassification in order to make recommendations. In
                    particular, he wanted to see the guidelines for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. Ambassador Burke replied that the guidelines, which are
                    written for the NARS reviewers and not for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, are classified, but that he would take the question of
                    making them available under advisement. He explained that the guidelines were
                    drawn up with a specific period in mind, in this case the 1950-54 period, and
                    that they were extremely detailed as to what events in which countries were
                    still considered sensitive.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked if there is any coordination between the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> process and the NARS process. He noted from personal
                    experience that in some cases documents actually published in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> were not available at NARS. This, he felt, was a
                    result of a lack of communication between the two processes. As an example, he
                    mentioned the Policy Planning staff papers, many of which were published in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, but not available at NARS. Ambassador
                    Burke indicated that the state of the art does not yet allow for perfect
                    comparison of declassification records between the agencies and hopes it will
                    improve. Mr. Slany felt that this topic was related to a question that Mr.
                    Rosecrance asked in the morning session which had been deferred to the afternoon
                    session so that Ambassador Burke might answer. He asked the Ambassador if the
                    difference in declassification decisions between the Department and NARS (or
                    current DOS standards and hypothetical future DOS standards) or through court
                    decisions on FOIA might result in release of previously classified documents
                    which might reflect adversely on the integrity of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. The Ambassador replied that even internally it happens that
                    there are discrepancies in declassification between Systematic Review (which
                    includes FRUS review) and Mandatory Review. In his opinion Systematic Review
                    (with 12-14 people) declassifies more freely than Mandatory Review (with 30 to
                    40 people) because the SR reviewers represent longevity and experience in
                    subject areas rather than in the random topics that must be declassified under
                    pressure in Mandatory Review. He explained the administrative and funding
                    reasons for maintaining distance between the two units and stated that he
                    believes that the best solution may be a computerized data base for use by both
                    units. The Ambassador stated CDC’s strong desire for such an activity but noted
                    the absence of funding for clerical support made even rudimentary assistance
                    difficult and precluded preparing a comprehensive data base at present.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany mentioned that the Historical Office often had been of assistance to
                    the Mandatory Review Section of CDC by pointing out that documents involved in
                    certain FOIA requests had already been declassified by SR.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis observed that there were two different models of declassification--the
                    U.S. model and the British model. The British model had a strict 30-year rule
                    with certain categories exempt from declassification. He asked which model, in
                    the Department’s opinion, would result in the release of more documents?</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke felt that it would differ on a case-by-case basis. The problem
                    is that the new executive order does not even provide for SR. The Department has
                    continued SR, but it is not obliged to do so. Other agencies do not feel any
                    obligation to conduct SR. There is no systematic release of documents by the
                    Department of Defense, for example. Moreover, legislation pending in Congress
                    would exempt CIA operational files from FOIA. The Department is concentrating
                    its efforts on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, while trying to get
                    other agencies’ documents on a case-by- case basis. His opinion is that the
                    Department of State would be amenable to a timetable of declassification, with
                    the caveat that such a timetable would probably result in much later release
                    than is accomplished by the present system of release via <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>. The Ambassador suspects the problem of resources
                    for declassification is government-wide and under an automatic declassification
                    system might become a greater problem. A/CDC feels that good relations with
                    other agency counterparts is an effective support that might be damaged under
                    other declassification systems.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany added that the existing system had not been fully explored. Without
                    A/CDC, top policymakers would most likely “take fright” and withhold even more
                    documents. In fact, “if there were no A/CDC, we would have to create one.” The
                    key issue is that there is a need for a Department organization, other than the
                    Historical Office, that has the confidence of the top policymakers to carry out
                    declassification of official records. He said that the question of the
                    advisability of a year cut-off system would be clearer later when the existing
                    system had been more fully explored. At present there is a need for better
                    coordination between the Office of the Historian and A/CDC. In addition, the
                    whole operation could do with a “sense of urgency” about its work. Therefore, he
                    was reluctant to speculate on a year when everything would become right. Our
                    efforts, he concluded, would be better spent trying to figure out how to do
                    better what we are already doing.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that A/CDC attempts to speed the system and reduce denials
                    by maintaining informal communication between Systematic Review and Mandatory
                    Review, but he is careful to stress the separation between the two in order to
                    prevent diversion of SR staff (which legally might happen under the new
                    directive.) At present, the Department is “robbing Peter to pay Paul” by using
                    MR resources to pay for SR.</p>
                <p>In addition, CDC is being “whipsawed right and left” on “surprise” FOIA cases. At
                    present, there are 55-60 law suits pending against the department on FOIA. He
                    cited the case backlog in MR as both a threat to SR and a symptom of the total
                    review problem. The instigation of discovery cases by law firms creates huge
                    search costs and review backlogs. He noted that the Hotel and Restaurant Workers
                    Union had sued the Department of Justice to obtain all USG documents relating to
                    political asylum on behalf of Salvadoran illegal immigrants. In this instance,
                    the Department had released around 1,100 documents and withheld 623. This
                    particular action had cost the department in excess of $14,000 in search and
                    review time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany explained that the problem that the Office of the Historian foresaw in
                    regard to a time line for declassification was that of a “credible record.” Will
                    it be possible in all cases, he asked, to get a credible record out within the
                    time frame? This put the Historical Office in the position of having to
                    “anguish” over deciding to publish with the documents available at the time or
                    waiting in hopes of getting out a fuller record. The important question was how
                    comprehensive did the record have to be to be credible? Setting a time line did
                    not solve this problem. The problem of getting the important documents
                    declassified would still remain.</p>
                <p>Mr. May, however, pointed out that the point of having a time line is that it
                    should facilitate declassification decisions.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon replied that the guidelines for declassification would still have to
                    be very specific. Moreover, there are many problems which CDC cannot address, in
                    particular the question of materials from other agencies. Some State Department
                    documents from the compilation must also be referred to them for clearance. For
                    example, there are 4 volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> at the
                    NSC at the present. In his opinion, so long as the Office continues to use other
                    agency material to present a complete historical record, these non-State
                    Department declassification blocks will remain a problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. May felt that the question of State Department documents and other agencies’
                    documents were separable questions. Mr. Slany explained that the Office had some
                    anxiety that separating release of documents from the series would reduce the
                    utility of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon noted that in the case of records for the 1950-1954 period, there
                    were instances, (for example Latin America) in which records were available at
                    NARS but not yet through <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany added that the HO staff was anxious about being able to put together a
                    full record, not just a State Department record. In addition, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> was an important “vehicle for public disclosure,”
                    and Mr. May agreed with this proposition.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rosecrance observed that the State Department should play a leading role in
                    releasing documents. It was the agency most concerned with the foreign affairs
                    record. It had control over its own documents, so it might be possible to go
                    with State Department records alone on a time line. If DOD and other agencies
                    refused to go along, the publication of State Department records might have a
                    “salutary influence” in stimulating them to release their records as well.
                    Ambassador Burke was skeptical that this would actually pressure other agencies,
                    since there was no precedent in other agencies for documentary publication, but
                    only for official histories.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis expressed his concern that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    not lose its “breadth.” Mr. May repeated his observation that the problem of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> should be separated from the question
                    of the release of documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis agreed that the key objective was to facilitate the release of
                    records. He felt that another way to accomplish this would be to set limits on
                    the time other agencies had to review documents State wanted to release. If they
                    failed to meet the deadline, the documents should be published. Ambassador Burke
                    pointed out that in “practical bureaucratic terms” the State Department had no
                    way to force NSC, CIA or DOD to cooperate. They were our peers, and would not
                    accept taskings from State on this matter. He also expressed concern over
                    publishing State Department documents only. As matters stood, the other agencies
                    had no obligation to publish anything. The Defense Department, he believed,
                    would merely continue with its “in-house” histories. The other departments did
                    not have a traditional commitment to release documentary collections. Ambassador
                    Burke expressed his strong conviction that documentary collections were much
                    more valuable to scholars than such publications as DOD’s in-house histories.
                    Mr. Slany noted, in this regard, that other agencies’ declassification efforts
                    were geared to the State Department effort and were, in a sense, dependent on
                    it.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke concluded that we were “stuck” with the present format. The fact
                    that the NSC role had increased so dramatically in importance from the 1950’s
                    on, for example, means that the release of State Department records by
                    themselves offered only an incomplete picture of foreign policy making.</p>
                <p>Mr. May then asked if the problem of getting documents out was getting greater
                    over time as the number of documents and countries was increasing. Ambassador
                    Burke noted that while the number of countries did increase greatly from 1960
                    on, not all countries were equally important. Mr. May continued by observing
                    that one function of A/CDC was to assure that country desks were comfortable
                    with the release of the documents. The simple fact that there were more
                    countries after 1960 seemed to him to indicate an increase in CDC’s work load.
                    Ambassador Burke, however, explained that the A/CDC reviewers were very
                    persuasive with the desk officers. Often they had more experience with the
                    countries in question than the desk officers. In the final analysis the
                    reviewers themselves determined what they released. Therefore, he felt that the
                    problem of the proliferation of countries was a “manageable burden.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Hamilton noted that as far as the NARS project was concerned, the desks and
                    bureaus were not involved. They had seen the guidelines, but documents were not
                    necessarily referred to bureaus. In fact, very few went to the bureaus. In
                    response to a question by Mr. Rosecrance, Mr. Hamilton confirmed that the
                    bureaus therefore did not have a “veto” over the release of documents for
                    accessioning at NARS.</p>
                <p>In regard to work load, Mr. Hamilton observed that the real problem was not so
                    much the increase in the number of countries as the great increase in
                    communications capacity. There were more foreign affairs documents on more
                    subjects; more “paper” in general. Who was to decide which documents were worth
                    keeping? He had no doubt that many documents were an encumbrance and that it was
                    a poor use of resources to review and store them. But historians understandably
                    do not want to delegate the authority to identify and dispose of them. Mr. May
                    noted that the operational result was the same--it was getting more difficult to
                    deal with the increasing volume of documents.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke suggested that the obvious solution was “to put more men on the
                    job.” He would like to find more efficient means to deal with the problem.
                    A/CDC, he noted, had discussed the problem with FAIM, and is awaiting
                    recommendations. A possible solution might be to link NARS with A/CDC via a
                    computer link. As documents are reviewed and released they could become
                    available in digital form at NARS. Recent documents were of course already in
                    digital form.</p>
                <p>Mr. May indicated that he appreciated the validity of Ambassador Burke’s interest
                    in a data-link for digital records, but that his present concern is with the
                    paper record for the 1950’s and 1960’s. Mr. Slany explained that the problem is
                    a managerial compromise based on limited resources. He constantly must juggle
                    conflicting tasks and priorities. These choices expose the Office to the
                    criticism of failing to provide a complete record. He perceives Ambassador
                    Burke’s concern to represent the fact that he also knows his resources must be
                    divided between preservation and current release.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked whether a time line for release would free resources in both
                    offices to devote to the problems just elucidated. Mr. Slany responded that it
                    would change the agenda for the offices, but he questioned whether the
                    Historical Office staff or the Committee could accept the categories of
                    exemption and their impact upon the comprehensiveness of the official record. He
                    also noted that the recent history of changes in Executives Orders was not
                    auspicious.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rubin suggested that the Department consider adopting a process under which
                    everything would be released after 30 years unless specific steps were taken in
                    specific instances to withhold documents. In other words, to reverse the
                    priority of the existing system. Under this new system, affirmative action would
                    be required to keep documents classified rather than to release documents as
                    under the existing system. Paraphrasing Mr. Johnson, he said that he felt that
                    the process of deciding which documents to keep classified would “focus the
                    mind” of the classifiers.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke pointed out that the FOIA process worked that way. The Department
                    has to defend its decision to withhold a document under FOIA. This focuses the
                    attention of the reviewer and results in more documents being released. He
                    suggested that something along the line of Mr. Rubin’s idea might work in
                    conjunction with the 25-year line being proposed by Senator Mathias. On the
                    other hand, it would only work with a small number of documents since it would
                    require senior people to review the documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. May asked how hard it was to identify sensitive documents? Ambassador Burke
                    replied that it was amazing to him how much was released under Presidential
                    library referrals. The problem, in fact, was how to make these documents
                    available to all scholars on a systematic basis.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Other Matters</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked what percentage of the studies in the policy-related research
                    program of the Historical Office were classified?</p>
                <p>Ms. Noring explained that answering in terms of the percentage of reports would
                    be deceiving. While the list of classified studies was only one-third as long as
                    the list of unclassified studies, the story in terms of resources devoted to the
                    studies was quite different. In terms of resources, the split was somewhere
                    around 60 percent for unclassified and 40 percent for classified, and could be
                    as high as 50-50. Many of the classified projects were such things as
                    negotiating histories which, by their nature, took more time.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee’s Private Meeting</p>
                <p>The meeting was adjourned at 3:30 p.m. The Committee met privately to prepare
                    its report.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
