<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From Charles Flowerree to Stephen Gomersall, January
                    1983</title>
                <title type="short">Flowerree to Gomersall, 1983</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2019-06-20">June 20, 2019</date>
                <date type="created" when="1983-01-11">January 11, 1983</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1983-01-11-flowerree-to-gomersall.pdf">PDF</ref>, 99 KB, 1p.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD–WX–595: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, FRUS
                    Clearance Files, 1945–1957 (96 D 068), Box 6, FRUS, 1952–1954, Vol. X, Iran
                    (clearance folder). Posted from an unsigned copy.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn81">Footnote 81</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From Charles Flowerree (Director of Systematic Review) to Stephen
                    Gomersall (First Secretary of the British Embassy)</head>
                <dateline>January 11, 1983</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Gomersall:</p>
                <p>Last year you very kindly undertook to obtain your Government’s views on a
                    collection of documents pertaining to the Buraimi dispute of 1953-1955. Now we
                    are working on another series of documents dealing with the Iranian crisis of
                    1951 to 1954. Because of the intimacy of US-UK liaison in this affair and
                    because of the possible sensitivity of some aspects of it from the British point
                    of view, we would like to have the UK reaction before proceeding to publication.
                    Therefore, we would like to follow the same procedure as was followed in the
                    case of Buraimi.</p>
                <p>The attached collection of 139 documents includes a number of British documents
                    or extracts from them. Other report US-UK conversations or deal with subjects of
                    interest to the UK. In a number of cases certain paragraphs or clauses have been
                    bracketed and marked for excision. This means that from our point of view the
                    document would be releasable after the indicated excisions have been made. In a
                    very few cases, a document is marked “Deny”. This means that the document will
                    not be published and it is included in this collection only for your information
                    and as a means of suggesting the margins of our criteria. One document, not
                    included, is a British memorandum of September 2, 1953, entitled “Persia, Review
                    of the Recent Crisis.” This document you have already indicated to me is
                    releasable with indicated excisions.</p>
                <p>The documents are serially numbered in the upper left hand corner on the first
                    page of each one. I have enclosed a list of documents by number. I would
                    appreciate it if you would obtain the views of your Government regarding any
                    parts of these documents which it considers sensitive. If you require any
                    further clarification please let me know.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <p>Charles C. Flowerree</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
