<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1984</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1984</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-03-10">March 10, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1984-11-09">November 9, 1984</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1984-11-09-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 411 KB, 19pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, Report-1984-Minutes.
                Confidential.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn113">Footnote 113</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1984 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 9, 1984</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. John L. Gaddis, Department of History, Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
                        45701</item>
                    <item>Dr. Carol S. Gruber, Department of History, William Paterson College,
                        Wayne, New Jersey 07470</item>
                    <item>Dr. Warren F. Kuehl (Chairman), Department of History, University of
                        Akron, Akron, Ohio 44325</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Ole R. Holsti, Department of Political Science, Duke University,
                        Durham, North Carolina 27706</item>
                    <item>Dr. Deborah W. Larson, Department of Political Science, Columbia
                        University, 420 West 118th Street, New York, New York 10027</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. John Lawrence Hargrove, Executive Vice President and Executive
                        Director, The American Society of International Law, 2223 Massachusetts
                        Avenue, N.W., Washington, D.C., 20008</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present:</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John T. McCarthy, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Acting Deputy Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Acting General Editor of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS)</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Larry Adamczyk</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Carol A. Becker</item>
                    <item>Bret D. Bellamy</item>
                    <item>Suzanne E. Coffman</item>

                    <item>Evan M. Duncan</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Nancy L. Golden</item>
                    <item>Stuart Kennedy</item>
                    <item>Kay K. Herring</item>
                    <item>Bettye C. Johnson</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>

                    <item>James E. Miller</item>

                    <item>David S. Painter</item>
                    <item>Deborah Peabody</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Vera Smith</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                    <item>James White</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>Henry Bardach, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs Information Management Center (A/FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Paul Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division</item>
                    <item>Vicki L. Ettleman, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                    <item>Leo P. Masciana, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Legislative and Diplomatic Branch, National
                        Archives and Records Administration (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Edwin A. Thompson, Project Director, Records Declassification Division,
                        NARA</item>
                    <item>Page Miller, American Historical Association</item>
                    <item>Beverly Zweiben, Office of Human Rights Affairs, Bureau of International
                        Organization Affairs</item>
                    <item>Stanley Shaloff, Office of Analysis for Africa, Bureau of Intelligence and
                        Research</item>
                    <item>N. Stephen Kane, Office of Opinion Analysis and Plans[, Bureau of Public
                        Affairs]</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany convened the meeting at 9:15 a.m. and introduced Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary McCarthy, who welcomed the committee members on behalf of Assistant
                    Secretary Hughes.</p>
                <p>Mr. McCarthy stated that Mr. Hughes was very sorry he could not be present and
                    outlined the busy schedule of the Department Spokesman. Noting that he had
                    majored in history as an undergraduate, Mr. McCarthy expressed his own interest
                    in the committee’s proceedings. He stated that a lot of progress has been made
                    since last year in thinking through the process of producing the series and what
                    can be done about the very legitimate problems and questions raised by the
                    committee in last year’s report and over the past few years.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Election of Chairman</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that the committee’s first order of business was usually to
                    elect a chairman. Ms. Gruber commented that the committee’s usual practice of
                    selecting a chairman who was serving his last year on the committee meant that
                    the previous year’s chairman was never present to follow up on the previous
                    year’s report. She noted that last year’s chairman Ernest May was no longer on
                    the committee to follow up on the 1983 committee’s excellent report. She
                    nominated Warren Kuehl, a new committee member. Mr. Gaddis and Mr. Holsti
                    seconded the nomination, and Mr. Kuehl was elected by acclamation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl invited Mr. Slany to present his report.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Historian</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that HO has been busy with the staff study and the report to
                    Congress. One is an attempt to find solutions to problems laid out in the other.
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> as it has evolved in the last 20
                    years has probably gone as far as it can in its present structure and with its
                    present objectives. We need to reconcile what we can do in HO with what the rest
                    of the government can do. We have allowed the emergence of a publication which
                    is not at all like what it once was. We have two objectives: publishing the most
                    important documents and serving as a guide to unpublished diplomatic records.
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> can’t publish all the documents
                    anyone would like to have in writing diplomatic history. We shouldn’t be an
                    obstacle to making the record available to the public. The body of documentation
                    needs to be defined differently than it was by Secretary Kellogg in 1925.</p>
                <p>He stated that we have several alternatives. We can serve as a guide to the
                    records that are available, including those outside the DOS. We fulfill an
                    important function in helping to identify significant records and ensuring their
                    preservation so that they can be made available eventually, even if not
                    immediately.</p>
                <p>He called attention to a number of problems:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>The immense quantity of records from recent years. The amount of records
                        on Vietnam alone is staggering. This necessitates setting priorities.</item>
                    <item>The problem of foreign government information. The U.S. has to be
                        sensitive to the concerns of other foreign governments. U.S. documents are
                        riddled with information from foreign sources. If we attempt to make use of
                        this information as if it came from American sources, we have a problem. We
                        need to understand what the academic community thinks should be in the
                        foreign policy record. We may need to be more self-denying. This issue has
                        changed totally in recent years: in the past, we merely had to clear foreign
                        government documents or texts of documents.</item>
                    <item>The problem of other-agency documents. We don’t have full access to other
                        agency documents. The Inter-agency Access Agreement doesn’t apply to all
                        documents in which diplomatic historians have an interest.</item>
                </list>
                <p>He continued: We are in a quandary. We need the advice of the academic community
                    as to whether we should continue publishing even if the record is not complete.
                    We face this problem constantly. It hinges on other-agency records; the
                    Department of State is becoming more efficient at dealing with declassification,
                    but we don’t have control of other agencies. In the Department we have more or
                    less solved the procedural problems of declassification. Scholars may have more
                    access to records at the National Archives than in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. We are faced with the problem of whether to publish the
                    incomplete record. We wonder whether or not we have the support of scholars.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis commented that the committee could not deal with these almost “cosmic”
                    questions in one annual session. He asked Mr. Slany to elaborate on his
                    suggestion of bringing academic historians into a closer relationship with
                    HO.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is the only
                    government publication without outside editorial advice. He stated that we need
                    to combine the staff’s expertise with the thinking of outside professionals. He
                    suggested an editorial board which would discuss general questions of
                    organization of the volumes with the staff and would also advise the staff on
                    questions of whether or not to proceed with publication. We are more inclined to
                    wait for something positive to happen than to make disagreeable decisions.
                    Rumors of problem volumes get out and produce skewed discussion.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked Mr. Slany what he envisioned as to the frequency of the board’s
                    meetings and the level of detail which it might address. Would the board meet
                    2-3 times a year or would it be more active? Mr. Slany said he thought the board
                    would meet several times a year and have additional access to materials.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked Mr. Slany what relationship he envisioned between the board and
                    the Advisory Committee. Mr. Slany replied that HO would want the committee’s
                    advice on the selection of the board.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked Mr. Slany what relationship he envisioned between the board and
                    any prospective consultants. Mr. Slany replied that the consultants would advise
                    HO during the compiling stage. The board would advise in the planning stage and
                    in the post-compiling stage. For example, we are now planning volumes on the
                    Kennedy years. An editorial board could advise us on this.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl stated that he could see the value of bringing in outside historians
                    with experience in working in a particular time period in designing the volumes.
                    He inquired about the selection process: to what extent does HO feel the
                    academic community looking over its shoulder during this process? Mr. Slany
                    replied that the involvement of the academic community would strengthen HO in
                    dealing with other agencies and help us determine on which issues to fight.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis suggested that we might be proliferating advisory committees and
                    suggested that restructuring the advisory committee with more frequent meetings
                    might serve the same purposes. Mr. Slany referred the question of the
                    feasibility of this to Mr. Petersen, who stated that there was no obstacle;
                    several DOS advisory committees meet 2-3 times a year.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis raised the question of the committee’s structure. Mr. Slany stated
                    that this was a matter for the committee to consider. Mr. Gaddis stated that he
                    thought SHAFR should be represented. Mr. Slany noted that this was a timely
                    suggestion, since it was time to renew the committee’s charter. Mr. Petersen
                    said the charter provides that the committee shall meet annually in November but
                    may meet more frequently. Mr. Slany raised the problem of funds. Mr. McCarthy
                    suggested the possibility of enlarging the committee and establishing working
                    groups. Ms. Gruber noted that this was a good time to consider the committee’s
                    structure.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany turned to the publishing problem. He introduced Paul Washington of PS
                    and noted that he had been helpful in the series’ transition from linotype to
                    electronic printing. He stated that the GPO has caused more problems than it has
                    solved. HO has raised the question of an exemption from GPO with the Joint
                    Committee on Printing. A private publisher might be able to make the series more
                    widely available and keep the volumes in print longer. The volumes are often in
                    print for less time than it takes to prepare them. They are reference tools and
                    should be available for a decade or so. The GPO is not attuned to a unique
                    publication like <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. The committee might
                    wish to consider how a university press might be more helpful. Mr. Washington
                    stated that the Department plans to approach some university presses, but hasn’t
                    done so yet.</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti wondered if the cost would be greater with a private publisher. Mr.
                    Washington stated that a small subvention might be necessary. The Department
                    would have to make certain that a university press did not raise the price of
                    the volumes unduly. He referred to the special printing of volumes for Congress.
                    He stated that the current upfront costs for printing and binding were
                    $45,000-$75,000 per volume. The Department would hope to obtain 2500 volumes at
                    no greater cost than this. He thought a university press could expand sales of
                    the volumes. In order to do this, the price should be no higher than current
                    prices and maybe a little lower. We would need to find a university press and go
                    to the Joint Committee. He thought there would be no problem in getting a
                    waiver.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove inquired whether the subvention would not be a matter for
                    negotiation. Mr. Washington replied that in his experience no one did something
                    for nothing. Mr. Slany noted that the Department would pay for the volumes sent
                    to depository libraries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked if there was any mechanism for ensuring that full sets of
                    volumes go overseas. He had just visited a number of universities and libraries
                    in China where only a few volumes were available. Mr. Slany replied that we had
                    made a few volumes available on an ad hoc basis. Mr. Glennon stated that we had
                    a distribution list of 115 and that approximately 24 of these went overseas. Mr.
                    Gustafson of NARS noted that the AHA had asked for donations from members and
                    that Fredrick Aandahl, a former Acting Director of HO, had donated his
                    collection for China. Mrs. Becker noted that the LC has an exchange program.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis stated that the committee might make a recommendation on this and
                    asked for suggestions on what could be done. Mrs. Becker stated that HO has a
                    list of suggestions on how people can obtain earlier volumes or reprints which
                    we send to anyone who inquires. Mr. Gaddis stated that he was interested in how
                    the current volumes could be made more readily available.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington stated that we are interested in creating a larger market by
                    advertising the volumes. He noted that direct overseas sales have been very low.
                    For the first time, the Department is making an effort at marketing the
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gustafson suggested facetiously that one way to increase sales would be to
                    include more controversial documents. He asked why the volumes go out of print
                    so quickly. Mr. Washington stated that the problem was storage costs. GPO looks
                    at the sales records and is reluctant to print more volumes. We can do so in
                    some cases, such as the 1951 Korea volume, but only with difficulty. He noted
                    that we have some volumes at the Department which are unavailable at GPO.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked if there could be a mechanism through which an individual could
                    subscribe to the series. He asked facetiously if the Department had considered
                    having a sale of the volumes it had on hand. Mr. Kuehl stated that a consortium
                    of university presses might be willing to handle distribution of the
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>The committee adjourned for a short break.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany discussed further the size of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes. He pointed out that the Senate Foreign Relations committee had
                    previously enjoined the Office not to change the size of the volumes. Now, it
                    was a major operation to continue to publish books the same size as those of the
                    last few years. There were several difficulties with continuing in the same
                    mode. First of all, money was a problem. The Office could ask the Department for
                    publishing funds incrementally as the volumes came out, but it would be
                    difficult to request the enormous outlay that would be necessary to bring the
                    series to the thirty-year line. There was also the problem of the capability of
                    the Presidential Libraries. HO research teams selecting large numbers of
                    documents to be copied would occupy an archival staff for months, displacing the
                    needs of private scholars. Even before making a Library trip, HO needed to go to
                    other government agencies for permission to view and copy their documents. The
                    total effort took much time, for which more resources were required.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that he would ask advice from the projected new editorial board
                    on how to be more selective in choosing documents for publication. He added that
                    it was impossible for the volumes to meet everyone’s expectations. In response
                    to Ms. Gruber’s question as to whether the editorial board could deal with the
                    size issue, Mr. Slany stated that the editorial apparatus needed to be more
                    defined. He added that a volume’s size depended largely on the significance of
                    the events at issue. In some cases they could be treated with fewer documents
                    and greater narrative summary. Other topics that were more intrinsically
                    important needed greater documentary coverage. He reiterated that the Office
                    needed clear direction from the Advisory Committee on this issue.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked how the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes might
                    alert the reader that the documentary record was not complete. He pointed out
                    that the Archives system was to insert a pink slip to indicate that certain
                    documents had not yet been declassified. Mr. Glennon replied that the volumes
                    often could not specify which documents had been excluded because that
                    information itself was classified.</p>
                <p>Returning to the problem of volume size, Mr. Kuehl asked whether microfiche
                    supplements could be used for large quantities of documents that could not be
                    printed in a scaled-down series. Mr. Slany replied that the Office had made only
                    limited headway on processing a microfiche supplement because of lack of
                    technical skill. He also mentioned the concern of both the HO staff and the
                    professional community that too great an emphasis on microfiche publication
                    could lead to a diminution of the commitment to the printed series. He added
                    that if the Advisory Committee and the academic profession wanted the staff to
                    concentrate more efforts on microfiche, they needed to offer specific
                    encouragement.</p>
                <p>Ms. Larson asked whether HO had regular access to the documents of other
                    government agencies. Mr. Slany replied that the Office had worked on this
                    without too much progress. As time has passed, the terms of access have become
                    more confined. Presently, HO access was not as great as it was five or ten years
                    ago. He stated that the Department must convince agencies that the collection of
                    documents for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series needs a
                    special arrangement apart from private or FOI efforts. He suggested that the
                    Advisory Committee might want to deal with this problem.</p>
                <p>In response to Mr. Holsti’s question of what allies the Office could count on to
                    gain greater access to the documents of other agencies, Mr. Slany stated that
                    Alan Thompson of the Archives was a help to the Office. Mr. Thompson stated that
                    he certainly wanted to think that he was an ally. He added that he hoped to be
                    more personally active with other agencies in making their record available but
                    was not certain how successful he would be. Mr. Gaddis interjected that the
                    obvious answer to the issue of other agency access was the issuance of a new
                    Presidential directive reinforcing the previous Nixon and Kennedy executive
                    orders. He then inquired about the prospects of Secretary Shultz’ approval of
                    the Staff Study. Mr. Slany responded that the study would be approved but
                    expressed doubt that a new directive would contain the necessary sense of
                    urgency to make a real difference. He added that if it simply urged other
                    agencies to be more cooperative with the State Department, it would be hard to
                    say whether it would have any beneficial effect. Mr. Kuehl stated that before
                    the Advisory Committee made specific recommendations, it would have to determine
                    whether a new Presidential order would help or hurt.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked how much of staff time had been devoted to policy related
                    research and whether the production of classified studies was greater than that
                    of unclassified ones. Mr. Claussen replied that he had no up to date figures but
                    estimated that staff participation varied from 30 to 75 · percent, sometimes 95
                    percent in the case of a rush project. Mr. Slany stated that although some of
                    the studies were unclassified, the Office might not necessarily have authority
                    to release them. He pointed out by way of example that the Office-wide
                    organizational history of the State Department had a very limited circulation.
                    Mr. Claussen pointed out that policy related research often proved valuable for
                    future <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compilations.</p>
                <p>In connection with the issue of doing current work of utility to future <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes, Mr. Slany indicated that he has
                    contemplated proposing current computerized compilation of documents for use by
                    the Secretary of State or leading policy makers. One advantage of instituting an
                    ongoing, up-to-date collection program would be that the Office could secure
                    important documents before they were lost or destroyed. To Mr. Gaddis’s question
                    of whether such a program would take more staff time that the traditional method
                    of collecting at the time of compilation, Mr. Slany replied that the Department
                    hierarchy would have to acknowledge that such an effort would be useful and be
                    prepared to supply the necessary resources. He stressed, however, that more than
                    resources, the Office mainly required for the Secretary of State to be convinced
                    that an HO collection effort would be a good thing. Mr. Kuehl agreed that the
                    Office needed to keep up with the contemporary record and indicated that the
                    Advisory Committee might recommend that it embark on such a collection effort.
                    Mr. Slany responded that such a recommendation would be welcome. He added that
                    the Department needed advice on how best to preserve the record and warned that
                    the computerized post-1974 record was in far greater danger of being lost than
                    the earlier paper files. He expressed hope that the Advisory Committee report
                    would enable the Office to reach the people who made the key decisions involving
                    record preservation.</p>
                <p>In response to Mr. Kuehl’s question as to whether each agency had its own system
                    of organizing its records on computers, Mr. Thompson said that common standards
                    had not been worked out. He added that the Archives was vitally concerned about
                    the problem. Mr. Slany stated that a committee of representatives from each
                    agency was currently discussing the issue of organizing computerized records but
                    could not agree on methods to get systems to relate to one another.</p>
                <p>On a new topic Mr. Kuehl asked whether there had been any clarification on the
                    issue of foreign originated information. Mr. Slany responded that the
                    Classification/Declassification Center considered whether to allow the inclusion
                    of such material on a case by case basis. He added that the Department of State
                    took the view that a document’s sensitivity rather than its origin dictated
                    whether it had to be withheld or not. He suggested that Mr. Kuehl question Mr.
                    Burke on the issue during the closed session later in the day.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Response by the Department to the Advisory Committee Report for
                    1983.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany stated that the Office had completed its staff study, which was
                    undertaken after the Secretary of State had read the Committee’s 1983 report and
                    had indicated his willingness to entertain its recommendations. The staff study
                    had been submitted to Secretary Shultz in October and had received his informal
                    approval. Mr. Slany said that the central purpose of the study was to outline
                    the measures needed to maintain a 30-year line. He pointed out that the National
                    Archives was now releasing documents ahead of their publication in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes whereas in the past the
                    documents had appeared in the volumes before they were generally available to
                    the public.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked whether there was any assurance that a 30-year line was indeed
                    feasible. He noted Mr. Slany’s remarks about the need for greater selectivity
                    and restraint in compiling the volumes in order to speed publication but
                    wondered whether the Department was disposed to grant the Office additional
                    resources to meet its goals. Mr. Slany replied that the Office needed to
                    identify the resources required to meet its targets in the forthcoming budget.
                    He added that there was no imminent problem of resources for HO because of the
                    number of volumes still in the pipeline. In fact he had held back on further
                    compiling pending decisions on the shape of future volumes. On the issue of
                    whether, by endorsing the 30-year line, the Secretary of State would commit
                    himself to adding the necessary resources, Mr. Slany stated that it was not
                    clear what additional discussion on the issue would be necessary. He emphasized
                    that the Office must be prudent and should not ask for more than it could
                    efficiently use.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked about the likelihood of future cooperation with the other
                    government agencies. Mr. Slany stated that such cooperation was rational and in
                    the interest of other agencies. He believed that they would prefer to have HO
                    compile a record of value than to allow it to dribble out in bits and pieces.
                    The key was to convince them that HO could produce it efficiently. Ms. Gruber
                    then asked how disclosure would serve NSC’s interest. Mr. Slany responded that
                    the NSC released information through the Freedom of Information Act. HO needed
                    to persuade NSC officials that their FOI declassification effort would be
                    facilitated by the regular publication of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked whether, in light of what had been said, the 30-year was a
                    meaningful publication goal. Mr. Slany stressed that the immediate problem was
                    to publish the backlog of volumes now in the pipeline. The longer range problem
                    was that the other agencies would not have adequate resources to declassify
                    documents as the volumes grew in size. He stated that if the backlog could not
                    be eliminated, the prospect of a 40-year line was great, since the sense of
                    urgency that other agencies might have to cooperate declassifying the volumes
                    would diminish.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked whether the Office might consider publishing (he used figure of
                    98%) readily clearable material now and then publishing the remaining documents
                    on microfiche later when they became available. Mr. Slany replied that this
                    raised the need to examine the volumes on a case by case basis. If the Office
                    could decide that 35 out of 40 volumes could be published now with the
                    understanding that other documents would be added later, that would speed the
                    publishing process. However, other agency clearances might still be a
                    bottleneck. Academicians’ views were also important and there might be
                    suspicions in the historical profession that the Office had been remiss in not
                    insisting strongly enough that certain documents be included in the volumes. Mr.
                    Gaddis suggested that the Office publish supplementary volumes periodically
                    containing previously withheld documents. Mr. Slany explained that the Office
                    had planned to publish a volume on intelligence activities covering an extended
                    period, so far without much success. He also noted that a variety of papers had
                    come into the Office’s possession, some declassified, after the appropriate
                    volume has already been released. He concluded that even after 30 years the
                    possibility of producing a definitive record was remote. Mr. Gaddis expressed
                    the belief that HO’s concern about the profession’s reaction to an incomplete
                    volume could be alleviated if the omitted documents (2 percent) could be
                    included later. Mr. Slany responded that HO historians generally feel that those
                    documents were often the most important part of the volume and added that the
                    staff naturally had a proprietary interest in publishing as complete a volume as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked how the reader would know whether specific documents had been
                    omitted from a volume because of clearance problems. Mr. Glennon replied that in
                    the case of the 1952-1954 Guatemala compilation, HO indicated where the records
                    could be found. However, it was impossible to tell the reader that we wanted to
                    print certain specific documents but could not because declassification was
                    refused. In the preface to the 1955-1957 volume on Vietnam, the Office had
                    attempted to clarify the ellipses occurring in the text, explaining that
                    material had been omitted for a variety of reasons including its failure to be
                    declassified. He continued that the sticking point for the series was in its
                    attempt to be comprehensive. Our inclusion of other agency documents in the
                    volumes required their declassification before publication. NSC has proved to be
                    the greatest bottleneck. He explained that of the 15 volumes on which CDC had
                    completed its review, 6 had been reviewed by the Department of Defense and only
                    2 by the NSC. Then after volumes are finally cleared by all interested agencies,
                    they must wait another year or more for GPO to publish them. Mr. Gaddis inquired
                    why omitted documents could not be identified to readers who at some later date
                    could submit FOI requests. He noted that the pink slip in Archival collections
                    provided this information to researchers, but that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    did not do the same for its readers. Mr. Glennon responded that the Office was
                    not always permitted to inform the reader of the documents which had not been
                    cleared.</p>
                <p>Ms. Larson pointed out the danger of relying on a supplementary volume to include
                    withheld documents from previously published volumes. She expressed concern that
                    general knowledge that such a volume would follow could possibly remove pressure
                    from other agencies to clear material for the regular volumes. She believed that
                    difficult clearance decisions would be routinely postponed until the preparation
                    of the supplementary volume, reducing even further the value and
                    comprehensiveness of the regular volumes. Mr. Kuehl pointed out that the if the
                    uncleared documents could be identified in the regular volumes, then interested
                    scholars could apply pressure for their eventual release. Mr. Holsti asked
                    whether the 2 percent figure so far used to approximate the percentage of
                    documents omitted from the average <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volume was a scientific estimate or just pulled out of the air. Mr. Glennon
                    replied that the highest figure on an <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> manuscript was
                    about 18 percent, levied on the prospective 1952-1954 volume on Eastern Europe.
                    The Office was still withholding the volume in an attempt to reduce the number
                    of deletions, but he confessed that it was a continuing dilemma to decide how
                    long to struggle to include presently sensitive material. He added that the
                    highest percentage of withheld material for any volume which HO has approved for
                    publication was 10 percent, namely the China section of the 1951 volume on Korea
                    and China. Mr. Slany added that HO compilers do not perform any screening
                    function. In fact they would probably subvert CDC’s responsibility if they did,
                    because unless CDC is aware of potentially sensitive material, it would not be
                    able to write declassification guidelines for it.</p>
                <p>Chairman Kuehl adjourned the meeting at noon, to reconvene in closed session at 2
                    p.m., following the Committee’s luncheon with Ambassador Ronald I. Spiers, Under
                    Secretary for Management.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">AFTERNOON SESSION (CLOSED TO THE PUBLIC)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Status of Declassification</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that CDC has had good working relations with the
                    Historical Office. Although differences have arisen over documents or individual
                    volumes, controversies have been resolved amicably and he looked forward to
                    continuing this relationship in the future.</p>
                <p>Burke said that the situation in his Center has remained stable for the last two
                    or three years. Systematic Review has declassified 56,000 pages this year which
                    represents over 92% of the pages examined and is close to the percentage of
                    release of the last few years. That figure does not involve FRUS, microfiche, or
                    material from the Archives. The volume of material released has also remained
                    approximately at the level of the last few years.</p>
                <p>The one new development in FOIA has been the increase in the requests from the
                    media. In 1982 such requests represented 8% of the total, whereas in 1983 they
                    rose to 20% and in 1984 to 25%. The pattern has been that these requests come
                    largely from a few people and that one journalist has currently over 300
                    requests in the Department. The key problem for FOIA will be how to handle this
                    increased number of requests and what priority, if any, to give them. He said
                    that there have been recent legislative attempts to amend the FOIA but that none
                    has yet passed. He stated that one new set of amendments to be introduced early
                    in the year by Congressman English will establish a “fast track” for media and
                    other professionals or organizations which have time sensitive needs. He argued
                    that this amendment would present real problems and put strains on CDC’s
                    resources and would be equally difficult for other Agencies. Ambassador Burke
                    urged the Advisory Committee to follow the progress of these proposed amendments
                    and perhaps testify before Congress urging the need to make the FOIA process
                    equal and fair. He also stated that a bill passed in the last Congress had
                    exempted CIA operational files from FOIA. While the Department had not played a
                    role in the bill’s passage, Sam Gammon of the AHA, had lobbied against it. He
                    said he hoped this legislation would not adversely affect HO’s ability to get
                    access to CIA files.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that the last Congress had also passed legislation
                    removing the National Archives from GSA control. The Department still cooperates
                    with NARA and supplies 2/3 of the budgetary support for the team that is
                    declassifying DOS documents.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke wished to call the Committee’s attention to the problem of
                    preserving future files. As we move into the high tech era, there is a need to
                    focus on the problem of long term preservation of the permanent files of the
                    Department. If the current trend continues, what exactly is it that we will turn
                    over to the National Archives. Wang’s President, An Wang, with whom Ambassador
                    Burke recently talked, had no answer to this problem. Wang’s floppy disks
                    deteriorate in time and documents on them may become unreadable. Ambassador
                    Burke noted that the Office of Technology Assessment is doing a staff study of
                    records keeping in the government and they are meeting with other agencies, as
                    they had with the Department to gather information on this problem. He fears
                    that the report, which is due to come out late next summer, may only state that
                    the problem exists without offering solutions. He stated that the Library of
                    Congress is doing the best research so far on this problem and has been focusing
                    on optical disks that can survive for 100 years and hold about 1 million
                    documents. He wished to commend them for their work in this area.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke also drew the Committee’s attention to the report of the
                    Congressional Conference Committee which had worked on the bill granting
                    autonomy to the National Archives. The report stressed that the Conferees were
                    “sensitive to the preservation of documents produced by electrical impulse,”
                    which had increased the agencies’ ability to produce documents, but impeded
                    their ability to preserve and store these records. The report stated they wished
                    to “insure the new technology preserves the documents.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Holsti asked whether the proposed FOIA amendment proposed any other
                    restrictions on FOIA inquiries. Ambassador Burke replied that the amendment
                    draft he had seen did not. He said that the present FOIA allowed anyone in the
                    world to request any information on any subject except CIA operational matters.
                    Ms. Gruber asked if the amendment would jeopardize the academic community.
                    Ambassador Burke replied that as the proposed amendment now reads, any
                    journalist or representative of a journal or newspaper could request priority
                    treatment. When Ms. Gruber asked about how resources would be allocated to
                    handle the fast track, Ambassador Burke replied it would be up to CDC to
                    establish procedures depending on the form of the amendment as passed. Some have
                    suggested three tracks be established. When Mr. Kuehl asked if journalists were
                    better lobbyists than scholars, Ambassador Burke replied that scholars should
                    lobby to protect their interests. He added that a new development in the
                    question of priorities was the problem of dealing with documents requested under
                    discovery in cases such as the current lawsuit where a former Israeli Government
                    official, Ariel Sharon, was suing <hi rend="italic">Time Magazine</hi>. In such
                    cases documents must be produced under a deadline set by the judge.</p>
                <p>Ms. Larson asked about the sensitivity of the documents contained in FRUS
                    1952-1954 volume VII on Central Europe and when it would be released. Mr.
                    Bardach said that this volume covered a period of the emerging normalization of
                    relations between the U.S. and Germany and included important communications
                    between the U.S. and the USSR as well as between the U.S. and Adenauer. It was
                    also a time when the Four Power Austrian Treaty was being discussed. The NSC has
                    had some reservations about releasing the volume because of the sensitivity of
                    some of the documents contained therein. However, the Department believes that
                    these concerns can be resolved, and that there is much interest in moving Volume
                    VII along since, among other things, 1985 is the 40th anniversary of VE day, as
                    well as the 30th anniversary of U.S. resumption of diplomatic relations with
                    Germany. He said there would be great interest in the volume in Europe as well.
                    When Ms. Larson asked if any additional material would be cut out, Mr. Bardach
                    replied that he believed it might well be published as it was, since it had
                    already been cleared by the Department of State and several documents contained
                    in the volume had been cleared with the FRG.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis inquired concerning FRUS 1952-1954 volume X on Iran. Mr. Glennon said
                    he is currently going through it. When Mr. Gaddis asked if it would go the way
                    of the Guatemalan volume, Mr. Glennon replied one would find more in it than in
                    the Guatemalan volume but not everything a historian would want. He is planning
                    to draft a response to CDC and ask for reconsideration of some documents. The
                    volume should be ready for the NSC in early 1985.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked what would be the role of the Editorial Board at this stage of
                    the declassification process. Mr. Slany said we “crave some sort of judgment”
                    and perhaps the Editorial Board could help us make the best possible decision
                    at this juncture. He said the deletions in this volume were made largely because
                    of information obtained from Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl suggested that the Committee could make broad recommendations.
                    Ambassador Burke replied that the Committee could make recommendations on
                    changes in organization of the volumes and subjects treated. The CDC would like
                    more resources devoted to the production of volumes and possibly outside
                    publication of the volumes. He said we need to persuade the seventh floor of the
                    importance of FRUS which he believes is the single most important government
                    publication of its kind. When Mr. Kuehl asked if HO needed more resources,
                    Ambassador Burke replied he was talking about the Systematic Review Staff of
                    A/CDC which reviews the FRUS volumes as a primary responsibility, but which
                    occasionally must be diverted to help with FOIA work.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl interjected that it seemed scholarly organizations should do more
                    lobbying.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked if the staff study was signed and accepted, and if it resulted
                    in a Presidential order, what could the Committee do to insure that follow-up
                    occurred? Ambassador Burke replied that the statement should have teeth and be
                    issued with some fanfare. It should be delivered to the agencies with an
                    implementing directive in order to make maximum impact, since government studies
                    usually have a half-life of a few years. When Mr. Kuehl asked what kind of teeth
                    could they put in it, Ambassador Burke replied that the statement should be
                    drafted along the lines of the Nixon directive -- a strong, clear statement from
                    the President to the heads of all departments and agencies with an involvement
                    in the topics covered in the FRUS series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked what was the reason for optimism since the administration had a
                    reputation for not favoring openness? Ambassador Burke said that, despite inside
                    media comment to the contrary, the current administration had had no inhibiting
                    effect on the Department’s declassification efforts under mandatory or
                    systematic review and he cited the declassification and release of former
                    Secretary Haig’s memoirs to support his statement. He said the new executive
                    order also had not had an inhibiting effect. Mr. Slany stated that his feeling
                    of optimism was related to the reception given the FRUS volumes by this
                    Administration. He said the volumes have the qualities of being orderly and rich
                    in information and, because they are historical, this way of releasing
                    information may be more attractive to the White House than other ways.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said there was a perception that there was a small group of people
                    obstructing the publication of the volumes. This is not the case. Its just hard
                    to bring all the declassification groups together since there is no umbrella
                    organization covering all the other agencies. Ambassador Burke added that the
                    problem of dealing with the other agencies is that none of them have an
                    equivalent of CDC. If we could get a directive to underline the importance of
                    the series, it might help.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl wondered how the Advisory Committee Reports were viewed by the other
                    agencies. Burke replied that only one report -- the one that preceded his
                    arrival at CDC -- was considered hostile. All the others had been viewed
                    favorably and Ernest May’s report of last year had gotten a lot of attention on
                    the seventh floor.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Preparing the Vietnam Record</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked about the merits of the two options HO was considering in their
                    publication of the Vietnam volumes: publishing shorter volumes faster or larger
                    volumes more slowly. Mr. Slany stated that HO was proceeding on the assumption
                    that we should get the documents to the public as soon as possible, while debate
                    was still going on in the scholarly community. First, if the HO contribution is
                    delayed, its impact will be lessened. Second, CDC has offered us faster
                    clearance now. Third, the capacity of the National Archives and Presidential
                    Libraries to work with us would be short-circuited by too extensive coverage. We
                    want to match their facilities available now with our plans. He said he could
                    envisage an arrangement whereby we would be allowed to have access to certain
                    additional portions of the Presidential Library holdings.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked if consultants could help with the Vietnam volumes. He said the
                    Committee suffered from a lack of information. Mr. Slany said we needed
                    consultants to advise us.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis said he wished to counter HO’s desire to publish shorter volumes
                    faster by arguing first, that the users survey favored the delay and publication
                    of more complete FRUS volumes; second, that Vietnam is neither an unknown or an
                    undocumented issue; and third, that there is a question about how much new
                    information HO volumes would add to the story. Mr. Glennon replied that the user
                    survey statistics were 64% to 36%. He said there would be five volumes for the
                    period 1955-1963. The real problem for the 1965 volumes is that the presidential
                    libraries haven’t processed the documents as yet and the Nixon library does not
                    yet exist. The problem of gaining access to presidential materials after 1965 is
                    the same for all post-1965 volumes, including those on Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked whether HO would publish supplements to accelerated volumes. Mr.
                    Glennon replied we might use the model of the First World War supplement. He
                    added that the 1961-1963 volumes on Vietnam are completed and in CDC.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis wished to know if the Vietnam volumes included material only on
                    Vietnam or did they also include material on Laos and Cambodia. Mr. Glennon
                    replied that the volumes included only materials on Vietnam because it was the
                    only way to keep them a reasonable size and because of the question of
                    clearance. Cambodia and Laos would pose problems in clearance whereas most of
                    the Vietnam documents would not. There were differing views, however, and some
                    people in CDC had urged the greater Southeast Asia approach. Cambodia and Laos
                    would be in the regular FRUS volumes. When Mr. Holsti asked how much delay there
                    would be if HO waited to include Laos and Cambodia, Mr. Glennon replied there
                    would be a major delay. Mr. Slany said HO had its best and most experienced
                    historians working on the Vietnam volumes. There were problems that would have
                    to be met whichever approach was taken.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked if HO was locked into the print format. Could some supplemental
                    documents be issued later as microfiche? Mr. Slany stated HO was not locked into
                    any format, but the scale of the project, not how it was produced, was the
                    factor since all documents had to be cleared by CDC which gave them special,
                    accelerated treatment. HO’s goal was to try to get all documents into the public
                    domain whether on microfiche or in printed FRUS volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Other Topics</p>
                <p>Mr. Gaddis asked about plans for other special volumes. Mr. Slany said that EUR
                    was not enthusiastic about the idea of special volumes on U.S. relations with
                    the Soviet Union. Mr. Claussen said HO was trying to produce a series of
                    unclassified documents on Central America. Mr. Slany said HO’s problem was to
                    decide what we could and should do.</p>
                <p>Ms. Gruber asked about the utility of the oral history program. Had the
                    interviews complemented or contradicted the written records? Mr. Mabon replied
                    that the interviews his group had conducted were of substantial value in a few
                    instances but that memories varied greatly. He replied affirmatively when Ms.
                    Gruber asked if they checked memories against the written record. In response to
                    her query, Mr. Mabon replied that oral histories were cleared and handled the
                    same way that other documents were. He hoped that CDC would declassify these
                    interviews and make them available to the public. He added that in some
                    instances the person may want confidentiality preserved for a number of
                    years.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kuehl asked Mr. Slany to comment on his optimistic statement in his report
                    about the exchange fellowship program. Mr. Slany said the concept was widely
                    supported in the Department and he hoped soon to be able to bring scholars into
                    the Department soon as well as to expand the program eventually to send them
                    overseas.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee’s Private Meeting</p>
                <p>The meeting was adjourned at 3:45 p.m. The Committee met privately to undertake
                    the preparation of its report.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
