<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Henry Bardach to William Slany, August
                    1984</title>
                <title type="short">Bardach to Slany, 1984</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2019-06-20">June 20, 2019</date>
                <date type="created" when="1984-08-10">August 10, 1984</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1984-08-10-bardach-to-slany.pdf">PDF</ref>, 43 KB, 1p.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, Record Group
                    59, Entry UD–WX–595: Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian, FRUS
                    Clearance Files, 1945–1957 (96 D 068), Box 6, FRUS, 1952–1954, Vol. X, Iran
                    (clearance folder). Tabs A, B, and C are present, but not posted. An unknown
                    hand indicates distribution to John Glennon and Paul Claussen.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn84">Footnote 84</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From Henry Bardach (Director of Systematic Review) to William Slany
                    (Director of the Historian’s Office)</head>
                <dateline>August 10, 1984</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Preliminary Review of Volume X, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                    the United States</hi>, 1951-1954, “Iran”</p>
                <p>1. The Classification/Declassification Center has completed its preliminary
                    review of this volume. Coordination with the United Kingdom has been completed
                    and is taken into account in this summary of results. Coordination with other
                    agencies, excepting CIA, has been initiated as indicated. The results of
                    inter-agency coordination will be relayed to HO as received. At that time
                    clearance will be sought from NSC. When final approval has been obtained
                    authorization to publish will be communicated to HO.</p>
                <p>2. As a result of this review all documents proposed for publication in Volume X
                    have been cleared for declassification with the exception of the following
                    documents which must be denied (TAB A), or withheld pending clearance with other
                    agencies (TAB B), or excised (TAB C). Copies of all excised pages are enclosed
                    at TAB D.</p>
                <p>3. It is requested that HO prepare a complete set of the Volume X documents to be
                    forwarded by A/CDC/SR to CIA for review.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
