<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1985</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1985</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-03-10">March 10, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1985-11-08">November 8, 1985</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1985-11-08-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 382 KB, 21pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 4, Minutes 1985.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 9, <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn102">Footnotes 102</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-9#fn117">117</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1985 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 8, 1985</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Robert Dallek, Department of History, University of California, Los
                        Angeles, California 90024</item>
                    <item>Dr. Carol S. Gruber, Department of History, William Paterson College,
                        Wayne, New Jersey 07470</item>
                    <item>Dr. Warren F. Kuehl (Chair), Department of History, University of Akron,
                        Akron, Ohio 44325</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Ole R. Holsti, Department of Political Science, Duke University,
                        Durham, North Carolina 27706</item>
                    <item>Dr. Deborah W. Larson, Department of Political Science, Columbia
                        University, 420 West 118th Street, New York, New York 10027</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. John Lawrence Hargrove, Executive Vice President and Executive
                        Director, The American Society of International Law, 2223 Massachusetts
                        Avenue, N.W., Washington, D.C., 20008</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bradford Perkins, Department of History, University of Michigan, Ann
                        Arbor, Michigan 48109</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present:</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Bernard Kalb, Assistant Secretary and Spokesman</item>
                    <item>George B. High, Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Deputy Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Foreign Relations Division Chief</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen, Policy Studies Division Chief</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson, Operations Staff Chief</item>
                    <item>Carol A. Becker, Information Staff Chief and Assistant to the
                        Historian</item>
                    <item>David H. Herschler, Assistant to the Historian for Records Policy</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Suzanne E. Coffman</item>
                    <item>Karen Collias</item>
                    <item>William Deary</item>
                    <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Nancy Golden</item>
                    <item>Kay Herring</item>
                    <item>Nina D. Howland</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>David S. Painter</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>Dwight Ambach, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs Information Management Center (A/FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Paul Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division</item>
                    <item>George Mattis, Assistant to Mr. Washington</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker, Documentary Editing Section Chief</item>
                    <item>Vicki Futscher, Documentary Editing Section</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Diplomatic Branch, National Archives and
                        Records Administration (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Edwin A. Thompson, Project Director, Records Declassification Division,
                        NARA</item>
                    <item>_____ Hopper, Scholarly Resources, Inc.</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Morning Session</hi></p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl convened the meeting at 9:08 a.m. and welcomed Prof. Dallek and Prof.
                    Perkins as new members of the committee. Prof. Kuehl commented that Prof.
                    Perkins’ presence was especially noteworthy since his father Dexter Perkins had
                    served on the original advisory committee.</p>
                <p>Prof. Holsti moved the reelection of Prof. Kuehl as committee chairman. Prof.
                    Gruber seconded the motion and Prof. Kuehl was reelected unanimously.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany introduced the others present and explained the use of PA/HO staff as
                    note-takers, adding that under the present system of note-taking, the minutes
                    would be less detailed than during the 1960’s, when a Court Reporter was
                    employed.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl introduced Mr. High while awaiting Mr. Kalb’s arrival. After a
                    moment’s delay, Mr. Kalb entered and apologized for his late arrival, remarking
                    that in this respect he was somewhat like the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. He extended a cordial welcome to the committee on
                    behalf of the bureau. He remarked that his battle to move the bureaucracy to
                    clear daily press guidances made him sympathize with the effort to clear 25 to
                    28 year old documents. He noted that as a journalist he had found the series
                    useful, and he congratulated the committee on its efforts to accelerate the
                    clearance process. He stated that he looked forward to his afternoon meeting
                    with the committee, and then excused himself from the proceedings.</p>
                <p>Mr. High stated that he was new to his job, and that he was present as an
                    observer, to learn. He noted that he had been in the management field for
                    several years and had rarely come upon more difficult and yet fascinating
                    managerial problems than those posed by the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. While he was discouraged that the harder we worked at
                    the problem, the further behind we seem to get, he was satisfied that the
                    program was being well-managed. He welcomed the advice of the committee.
                    Although the problem was serious, he was encouraged by the positive response of
                    the Secretary to the work of the historians, and he hoped for increased support
                    from the bureau and the “seventh floor.”</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of the Historian</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that his comments would supplement rather than duplicate the
                    status report contained in the committee’s briefing package. He invited
                    self-introduction of the PA/HO staff and others present. He referred to the
                    staff study, which called for the acceleration of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series to a 30-year line within five to six years. The staff
                    study is being used by PA/HO as a guide in the management of resources and in
                    setting deadlines. One result was the chart in the briefing package showing
                    workflow plans and deadlines in the publishing of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>He stated that the presidential directive had gone to the White House, and he was
                    confident that it would be signed, perhaps today. He remarked that the
                    presidential directive probably will be the most important thing that has
                    happened to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in ten years. It
                    will produce a more effective clearance process; it will enable the Department
                    to take the lead in publishing the foreign affairs record; and it will provide
                    PA/HO with improved procedures and the leverage to ensure that the process moved
                    forward. He added that Mr. High planned--as an early follow-up to issuance of
                    the presidential directive--to convene a meeting of high-level State, DOD, CIA,
                    NSC, and other agency officials to develop steps to achieve a 30-year line.</p>
                <p rend="underline">CIA Documents</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl commented that the inclusion of CIA documents in the series was
                    encouraging. Mr. Slany said that the Central Intelligence Agency had made an
                    arrangement with the Senate that exempted CIA operational records from
                    declassification in return for which the Agency had agreed to declassify older
                    non-operational records of historical interest. It had enlarged its historical
                    staff enabling it to accelerate declassification of records and accession by
                    NARA. PA/HO can gain enhanced access to Agency records in exchange for
                    publishing some of the more important records in supplemental volumes to the
                    series. He stressed that the supplementary volumes would not be allowed to delay
                    publication of the series, but the important documents should be published in
                    the supplements.</p>
                <p>Mr. Petersen said that two supplementary volumes, currently being blocked out,
                    would cover intelligence organizational development from 1945 to 1950, the
                    establishment of intelligence within the NSC system, and intelligence estimates
                    of the Soviet Union from 1945 to 1954. The precise terms of reference of both
                    intelligence volumes have to be negotiated with the CIA before PA/HO actually
                    undertakes the projects. Mr. Slany added that these supplements would provide an
                    opportunity to deal with important intelligence records that could not be
                    published in the earlier <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Microform Supplements</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that printed supplements were only one limited line of
                    development. He then elaborated on proposed microform supplements to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, to include: the NSC meetings
                    from 1947 to 1954, meetings with heads of state of the Soviet Union and other
                    major powers, the internal publication <hi rend="italic">Current Economic
                        Developments</hi>, top secret daily summaries, the Secretary’s memoranda of
                    conversations, and memoranda of conversations of the Secretary with the
                    President for the late 1940s and early 1950s. Mr. Slany reiterated that the
                    proposed supplements were intended to enhance, and would not delay, the printed
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Since it is beyond the
                    Historical Office’s ability to include all important documents in printed
                    volumes, the microform supplements would truly help. He added that the
                    publication schedule for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> calls for
                    50-60 print volumes, covering the period through 1960, to be published between
                    now and 1990, which in itself seems impossible. The level of documentation in
                    print volumes has been greatly scaled down from that of the volumes covering the
                    early 1950’s.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl stated that the committee had not taken an official position
                    regarding the microfiche supplements. SHAFR has been skeptical. He urged that
                    the committee discuss the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon explained that the first of the microfiche supplements, targeted for
                    publication in 1986 with the related print volumes on China (1955-57, II and
                    III), contained a verbatim record of the Wang-Johnson talks. The print volumes
                    would contain only summaries of the talks. The microfiche supplement would
                    contain 30 fiche, or 3000 pages.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins observed that there was outside concern that the supplements would
                    delay publication of the print volumes and that there may not be adequate
                    resources to compile the next three-year series. Mr. Slany stated that full-time
                    compiling for the 1960’s would begin around 1987. Most of the current compiling
                    was for the Vietnam volumes and to a lesser extent the 1958-60 series. The
                    supplements should not require an extensive compilation effort, if the process
                    can be perfected. We need to explore the methods for publishing bodies of
                    records on microfiche. It may be necessary in FY 88 to buttress resources for
                    compilation, but such a request would be neither necessary nor advisable at
                    present.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson found annotation useful that indicated who saw daily summaries and
                    the Secretary’s staff committee minutes, and she asked whether this annotation
                    would be left out of microform supplements. She also expressed concern that some
                    important documents would be omitted from the printed volumes if published in
                    the microfiche supplements.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek wanted to be assured that access to declassified or newly discovered
                    material not published in the early volumes would not be delayed because they
                    were to be published on microfiche by the Department of State. Mr. Slany stated
                    that publication of the microfiche would in no way keep the documents out of the
                    public domain.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek asked if an index of open materials could be published in
                    cooperation with the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations. Mr.
                    Thompson stated that the National Archives prepares a quarterly report on the
                    opening of records, including declassified records. This report is sent to 200
                    journals for widespread dissemination.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that the Office had decided that it would be most useful for the
                    microform publications to be packaged and shelved in libraries with the print
                    volumes. Ms. Becker showed a mock-up of a microfiche container made by GPO that
                    resembled, and could be shelved with, the print volumes. Inside the container
                    would be a vinyl folder, containing the fiche on one side and a printed guide on
                    the other. She related that she had seen in person what had happened at the
                    Library of Congress to the first PA/HO microfiche publication, <hi rend="italic"
                        >American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1981, Supplement</hi>--the
                    fiche were stored in a drawer while the paper guide to the fiche was stored next
                    to the print volume on the shelf--in other words, the wrong two parts were
                    together. The new packaging, which has been approved in theory by GPO and by the
                    Depository Library Council, is now in the final design stages.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Relation of Microform Publication to NARA</p>
                <p>In response to Prof. Larson’s previous concern, Mr. Sampson asserted that
                    multi-subject memoranda likely will not be omitted from the printed <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, if they are important. Where
                    document extracts appear in the print volume and the full texts appear as a
                    unique block in the microfiche publication, there will be a footnote in the
                    print volume, if possible. As to the daily summaries, he stated that an
                    annotated set likely will appear in the microfiche publications.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson inquired if the paper copy would be available at the National
                    Archives. Mr. Gustafson responded that it is National Archives policy not to
                    make available to researchers the paper original if a document has been
                    microfilmed, although there are a few exceptions to this rule. He emphasized
                    that National Archives microfilm publications duplicate exactly the paper
                    original. Prof. Larson stated that often several copies of a document existed,
                    some containing historically important marginal writing. Mr. Gustafson agreed,
                    emphasizing the importance of selecting the proper copy of a document to be
                    filmed or, for that matter, transferred to the National Archives. Prof. Larson
                    suggested that criteria be developed for the selection and filming of records on
                    microfiche.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gustafson questioned the publication of documents in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> microfiche supplements that to a substantial extent
                    may have been filmed by the National Archives, or are planned to be filmed by
                    NARA when they have been declassified. Mr. Slany stated that PA/HO is trying to
                    avoid duplicating the microfilm publications of the National Archives. The
                    purpose of the Historical Office microfiche publications is to make available
                    some documents that cannot be transferred to the National Archives at an early
                    date, and to provide the full texts of important documents that have been
                    published in part in print. Mr. Gustafson acknowledged that these were useful
                    objectives, and agreed that the PA/HO microfiche program might speed the
                    declassification of documents. He added later that he thought the program should
                    be pursued because of the new packaging plan for the fiche, and because the
                    GPO’s readiness to distribute copies to depository libraries would allow the
                    Department program to go beyond what the National Archives was able to do with
                    its microform publications.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Guidelines for Microfiche Decisions</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl inquired if the Historical Office used a systematic list of
                    guidelines to determine what to publish in microform. Mr. Slany stated that this
                    had been discussed in committee meetings within the office. Mr. Glennon
                    mentioned that there were internal office memoranda concerning this matter. He
                    added that the 1965 Vietnam volume would include a microfiche supplement in
                    order to keep the print volume to 1000-1200 pages. The volume would
                    cross-reference documents published in the microfiche with a brief summary in
                    the print volume. Prof. Kuehl said that perhaps the term “supplement” had been
                    applied too loosely; it sounded like not all the Historical Office microfiche
                    publications would be true supplements. Mr. Slany responded that the term would
                    be applied across the board to ensure that the microfiche publications were
                    linked to and shelved with the printed <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes in libraries. Prof. Kuehl asked for assurance to the scholarly community
                    regarding the nature of the microfiche supplements. Can the Department provide a
                    statement and work with the National Archives? Mr. Slany responded that he would
                    give the committee a document detailing the microfiche program, and coordinate
                    the microfiche publications with the National Archives.</p>
                <p>In response to Prof. Perkins’ expression of surprise at the size of the compiled
                    volumes, Mr. Slany explained that in the late 1970’s a Senate Foreign Relations
                    Committee report on a Department of State authorization bill had contained
                    language admonishing the Department to consult with the Senate and House
                    Committees before specific page cuts were made in the size of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Mr. Glennon remarked that
                    although there are many volumes in the offing, the problems thus far have not
                    been in the compiling, but in the declassification and publication processes.
                    Mr. Slany asserted that what is needed is support and understanding from the
                    committee for the necessity to provide at least part of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series to the public in a form other than paper. Mr.
                    Gustafson suggested that future status reports on the series should indicate the
                    average number of pages per printed volume for the time period, and that the
                    microfiche supplements should contain true supplemental material and not replace
                    the printed volumes. This should alleviate concerns from the scholarly
                    community.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Paper Guides to Microfiche Publications</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl inquired about the cost of the printed guide to the microfiche
                    supplement to <hi rend="italic">Current Documents</hi>. Mr. Patterson stated
                    that the guide was produced on the WANG equipment in-house, and sent out for
                    preparation of camera-ready copy and printing. The cost of the guide was part of
                    the total cost of the microfiche package, and thus was difficult to determine.
                    Prof. Kuehl asked how distribution of this printed guide-type of publication,
                    which he considered to be valuable even without the accompanying fiche, can be
                    extended, perhaps even to the entire SHAFR membership. Mr. Slany asserted that
                    if it is a small size guide, it can easily be disseminated to large numbers of
                    scholars. Mr. Mabon remarked that the guide to the 1955-1957 China supplement
                    will be similar to the printed guide to the <hi rend="italic">Current
                        Documents</hi> supplement.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Reviews of Microfiche Publications</p>
                <p>In regard to the China microfiche supplement, Prof. Kuehl suggested that someone
                    should review the publication in the SHAFR <hi rend="italic">Newsletter</hi> to
                    publicize it more widely. As the first non-print supplement to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, it is imperative that the
                    publication be reviewed by the scholarly community. Mr. Slany thought this was
                    an excellent idea. It would provide feedback for the next committee meeting.
                    Prof. Kuehl stated that the reviewer should be a respected scholar and asked the
                    committee for nominees. There was no immediate response from the committee, but
                    Prof. Kuehl indicated that the reviewer should be someone well versed in
                    Sino-American relations.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked the committee to note items in the status report regarding
                    declassification issues that would be discussed in the afternoon session. Prof.
                    Dallek remarked that at some point Prof. Larson’s letter should come before the
                    committee. Prof. Kuehl indicated that it would come up during the afternoon
                    session.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson complimented the Historical Office on the 1952-1954 <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on national security. She
                    asserted that the volume may change the historical impression of Eisenhower. She
                    thought the volumes were thorough and not much was omitted. Prof. Larson then
                    inquired about the distribution of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes to the overseas posts. Mr. Slany responded that Mr. Paul Washington of
                    the Department’s Publication Services Division could discuss that later in the
                    meeting.</p>
                <p rend="underline">The Presidential Directive</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber inquired what clear guidelines or mechanisms for action would derive
                    from the presidential directive. Mr. Slany stated that the mechanism will allow
                    for the Secretary of State to convene meetings of other agency officials to
                    discuss the Historical Office access to documents, and ask agencies to give
                    priority to the Historical Office requests for records. The directive should
                    give the Department authority to coordinate the declassification process, and
                    this would allow for an integrated, rather than an <hi rend="underline">ad
                        hoc</hi>, approach to declassification and access to other agency
                    records.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber inquired whether these interagency meetings would discuss
                    substantive criteria for declassification as well as procedural questions. Mr.
                    Thompson responded that he thought, with luck, both could be discussed, but Mr.
                    Ambach thought the meetings would deal mainly with procedural questions.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asserted that the resolution of substantive declassification questions
                    would have to be done on a case-by-case basis. There was no sense of purpose
                    held in common among the agencies, and it was difficult for the Department to
                    convince other agencies of the importance of this work. He thought that the
                    meetings would help create a common purpose and may lead to a greater sense of
                    urgency on the part of other agencies. He added that procedures can be improved
                    through these meetings.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins inquired whether the NSC had any structure to deal with the
                    historical perspective. Mr. Slany responded that they have a sense of history,
                    but declassifying our volumes is a low priority. Ms. Coffman, who has been
                    assigned to the NSC from the Historical Office on detail, remarked that Bromley
                    Smith, a former Executive Secretary of the NSC, has been commissioned by the NSC
                    to write a history of it. She asserted that Brenda Reger’s staff of four was
                    diligent about keeping up with what had been compiled, what needs to be
                    reviewed, and what has been released. The NSC staff maintains internal checks to
                    ensure it is not denying access to documents that have been released. The staff
                    also sends copies of released documents to the presidential libraries.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson asserted that the problem of lack of agency cooperation is
                    demonstrated in the chart provided in the briefing package. She inquired whether
                    this remained a problem and, if so, whether the problem was more stringent
                    declassification criteria in other agencies or lack of resources. She was
                    concerned about the continuing delays. Mr. Slany asserted that agencies
                    sometimes are not aware of the importance of getting clearances, and this will
                    be remedied in the presidential directive. He indicated that this could be
                    discussed further in the afternoon session.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson inquired what indication there was that the presidential directive
                    would be effective. Mr. Mabon stated that if the directive were followed up
                    properly there would be an across-the-board impact. Prof. Gruber commented that
                    the directive would serve mainly as a procedural tool, and Mr. Slany concurred.
                    Prof. Larson stated that the general perception in the presidential libraries
                    was that President Reagan was not eager to release information. She could not
                    see how the directive would have a beneficial impact if the president’s attitude
                    was well known.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ambach responded to the question of resources by stating that this was a
                    considerable problem. He asserted that in his opinion the principal anticipated
                    benefit of the presidential directive would be to focus on the resource
                    problem.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins inquired whether future status charts could indicate the dates when
                    clearance action was requested from agencies. Prof. Dallek agreed that this
                    would be useful. The chart could then be sent to agencies, and would clearly
                    indicate which agencies are holding up the process.</p>
                <p>The committee took a brief recess at 10:40 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Special Volumes and Policy Research</p>
                <p>Chairman Kuehl reconvened the meeting at 11:05 a.m. and asked what criteria the
                    Office used in engaging in “special publications”, as described on page 7 of the
                    Status Report. Specifically, he questioned the appropriateness of <hi
                        rend="italic">Documents on Germany</hi>--were there not more recent topics
                    more worthy of the Historical Office’s resources? Mr. Slany assured Prof. Kuehl
                    that the resources used to produce <hi rend="italic">Documents on Germany</hi>
                    came from outside the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> staff and did not
                    subtract from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> production. Such special
                    publications quite often were prepared in response to policy-makers needs and
                    were done for public affairs reasons.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber asked whether the agenda for policy research was set outside the
                    office. Mr. Claussen responded that the Historical Office worked with the rest
                    of the bureaucracy, and the policy research agenda was a compromise. We did not
                    do everything we were asked to do, nor did we self-generate all research. Mr.
                    Claussen added that <hi rend="italic">Documents on Germany</hi> was fully funded
                    outside the Office. It was a useful guide requested by an interagency committee
                    on the 40th anniversary of the end of World War II. The committee thought that
                    the previous publication on Germany needed updating and reprinting. Mr. Claussen
                    noted that research studies were often generated along similar lines.</p>
                <p>Prof. Holsti asked if policy research diverted resources from production of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Mr. Slany pointed out that the
                    Historical Office assigned policy research to units in the office which were not
                    involved in producing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. He added that it
                    was important bureaucratically for the office to have contacts with the rest of
                    the Department of State beyond nagging them to release 30-year old
                    documents.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber asked how many policy research projects were classified. When Mr.
                    Slany responded that most of them were classified, she asked did they not then
                    add to the amount of classified material which eventually had to be reviewed for
                    release? Mr. Claussen stated that policy studies were usually classified by
                    derivation (based on the classification of the sources used in preparing the
                    study). Indeed, he believed that they expedited declassification because the
                    studies were easier to declassify than the raw documents themselves. Mr. Slany
                    added that policy studies captured and saved documentation which might otherwise
                    be lost. Prof. Holsti asked whether the Historical Office deliberately initiated
                    research in some areas in order to capture the present for future historians, to
                    which Mr. Slany answered yes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Marketing and Distribution of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Volumes</p>
                <p>Paul Washington presented a report on his efforts in the past year to convince
                    GPO that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is a unique series and has to
                    have special attention. In effect, GPO has been asked to allow longer press runs
                    for the series, to increase the shelf life of the sales copies, and to keep the
                    sales price down. He believes he has been half successful in his efforts.</p>
                <p>In addition, Mr. Washington outlined the steps which GPO and his office are
                    taking to improve sales promotion. The Department of State press release on the
                    publication of a volume is now turned into a one-page ad for journals and used
                    in radio advertisements. Special promotional flyers mailed out by GPO in other
                    book orders are now prepared for new volumes; each of these flyers contains an
                    order form with a “tracer number” on it that can be tracked to measure its sales
                    effectiveness. Forty-nine new orders can be traced to this new promotional
                    activity. In response to Prof. Larson’s query, Mr. Washington explained that
                    copies of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes are indeed sent to
                    U.S. posts abroad, but said that he did not know exactly how volumes are plugged
                    into the USIA distribution system.</p>
                <p>Prof. Holsti asked if the emphasis on GPO doing a better job meant that the
                    search for a private publisher of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>--a
                    topic of much discussion at last year’s advisory committee--had been abandoned?
                    Mr. Washington responded that although GPO is under new direction and can
                    probably now do a better job than in the past, the Department is still pursuing
                    a “direct deal” contract with a private publisher.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked about the size of the print run at GPO, and Prof. Gruber
                    asked what percent of the print run goes to libraries. Mr. Washington responded
                    that approximately 2000-2500 copies are printed, one thousand of which are
                    distributed to the depository libraries, 350 are bought back by the Department,
                    and about 825 are eventually sold (the sales figure is a 10% increase over the
                    last 10-15 years.) The decision of how many copies to print rests with GPO.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson remarked that the “best seller” volumes for 1952-1954--National
                    Security, Korea, and Indochina--were quickly sold out, and she thought there
                    should be some way to produce a second run of them. Mr. Washington replied that
                    GPO based its print runs on average sales of the volumes in the past and had no
                    way to determine what would be a big seller. Some volumes never come close to
                    selling out. He confirmed, however, that the Department of State would press GPO
                    to rerun out-of-print volumes for which there is continuing interest, and to
                    make more of an effort to base print runs on subject content rather than on
                    previous overall series sales statistics.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked how many volumes were bought by individuals and how many by
                    institutions. Mr. Washington did not have the hard figures, but he guessed it
                    ran about 60% to institutions (not counting the depository libraries which get
                    the volumes free) and the rest to individuals.</p>
                <p>Prof. Holsti asked who gets the money for volumes sold. Mr. Washington responded
                    that the money goes to Treasury and then back to GPO to reduce their production
                    costs. Mr. Slany added that the Department must convince GPO that if they
                    publicize the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes more, they will
                    sell more, and they will make more money.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber asked how the market for the volumes can be expanded. Mr. Slany
                    answered that it is difficult to publicize the volumes because they come out so
                    sporadically. Mr. Washington agreed that this is precisely the problem he faces.
                    He cannot predict and plan for a certain number of volumes to be produced each
                    year. Mr. Slany pointed out the sad fact that by the time scholarly journals get
                    around to reviewing a <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume, they are
                    often out of print. He added that some journals do not review them at all. Prof.
                    Larson asked whether it would be possible to put advertisements in academic
                    journals, for example, in <hi rend="italic">World Politics</hi>. Mr. Washington
                    replied that the Department’s Office of the Legal Adviser has frowned on use of
                    government funds for advertising.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gustafson noted that, as explained in a Department handout giving sources for
                    both print and microform editions of out-of-print <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> is
                    published as a House document and then microfiched by CIS for sales purposes. He
                    asked when this started. Ms. Becker explained that the series has been a House
                    document for a long time, but that only recently has CIS been filming and
                    offering the volumes as part of its microfiche sales program.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. Hargrove, Mr. Washington described the
                    depository library system. Mr. Slany added that a major research university,
                    even if it was a depository library, usually bought additional copies of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl summed up the discussion of marketing and distribution of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> by stating that the day’s report gave
                    him encouragement. Last year’s advisory committee report had recommended an
                    improved effort in this area and it seemed to have been followed.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Records Management Issues</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then suggested that the committee turn its attention to the Historical
                    Office’s response to last year’s report. The Office has tried harder to be
                    involved in Department of State records maintenance, even though that function
                    is the responsibility of another bureau. As a reflection of his concern, the
                    Office has now hired a records historian, David Herschler. Slany stated that
                    Department records were being lost, not intentionally, but because of the vast
                    volume of records being created. It is the Historical Office’s mission to remind
                    the Department of State to keep and maintain its historically valuable papers.
                    He stated again that this was one of the important side effects of the Office’s
                    policy studies program.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked if the Department of State had any policy about logging or
                    summarizing telephone calls. Mr. High answered that while officers were
                    encouraged to write memoranda of important calls, time constraints often
                    prevented it from being done.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson returned to her fear, expressed earlier in the meeting, that the
                    Department of State was losing valuable annotation contained on multiple copies
                    of documents. Mr. Claussen assured her that Secretary Shultz’s staff is very
                    conscientious about indicating what he sees. Nina Noring added that each
                    administration has different record-keeping practices. Mr. Washington, who had
                    helped to set up the SADI system on the Seventh Floor, reported that SADI only
                    tracked correspondence, action memos, and special summaries, not who saw what.
                    William Deary stated that documents that he had worked with had control numbers
                    on them indicating which official they went to. He stated that it would be
                    impossible to save all annotated copies of documents. Milton Gustafson added
                    that it was a problem of technology. Once copying machines became widely used in
                    government, there was no way any longer to account for all copies. The Archives
                    tries to accession only one copy, and that copy may not be the one with the most
                    historically significant annotation.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked what the Advisory Committee could do to help save electronic
                    records beyond its previous recommendations that they must be identified as
                    important records, saved, and eventually made available to the public? Prof.
                    Perkins noted that the Advisory Committee had little experience with this issue,
                    and that the Historical Office had better expertise. He hoped it would use that
                    knowledge to assure better records management and preservation. Mr. Slany
                    admitted that the Historical Office had to shoulder its share of the
                    responsibility. It had been remiss in the past, but it was doing a better job
                    now by becoming more involved.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned for lunch at 11:57 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Working Luncheon</hi></p>
                <p>The Committee held a working lunch in the Department which was also attended by
                    Mr. High, Mr. Slany, Mr. Petersen, Mr. Glennon, and Mrs. Becker. The major topic
                    of discussion was the organization and functions of an editorial board as well
                    as the use of academic consultants for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. The discussion elicited the expression of a wide
                    variety of views on the feasibility of such a proposal, first suggested at last
                    year’s meeting and outlined in some detail in a draft paper prepared for the
                    Committee by Mr. Slany.</p>
                <p>A number of options for the use of an editorial board and consultants were
                    explored. Mr. Slany underscored the necessity for working more closely with
                    academic experts and enlisting the support of the scholarly community for
                    difficult editorial decisions concerning the series. These ranged from
                    organization of material and selection of topics to the inclusion of particular
                    documents. Mr. Slany reminded the Committee that it had given less attention to
                    the substantive contents of volumes in recent years as it became more concerned
                    with general publication policies for the series. Avenues discussed by the
                    Committee included: appointment of a board by the Advisory Committee; the
                    Committee constituting a board from its own membership; and the Committee itself
                    assuming the duties of an editorial board. It was the sense of the Committee
                    that it should exercise direction over whatever new unit was established. Mr.
                    High reminded the Committee and the Historical Office about the budgetary
                    constraints that existed on new activity.</p>
                <p>During the course of the discussion, the concept of a senior private historian
                    playing a role in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> clearance process
                    was mentioned. This suggestion reemerged at the Committee’s afternoon
                    session.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Afternoon Session</hi></p>
                <p rend="center">(Closed to the Public)</p>
                <p rend="underline">Declassification Questions</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl called the session to order at 2:15 p.m. Ambassador Burke joined the
                    committee at the conference table. Prof. Kuehl led off with a series of
                    questions:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>why has the series slipped to 34 years behind currency in the recent
                        publication of 1951, Volume IV?</item>
                    <item>can the committee do anything to help with the implementation of the
                        presidential directive?</item>
                    <item>how can a 30 year line be established if much of the documentation at the
                        Johnson Library has not been processed yet, and if the Nixon Library has not
                        yet been established because of the court case?</item>
                </list>
                <p>Prof. Larson asked another set of questions:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>is it true that the Executive Order of 1982 allows already declassified
                        material to be reclassified?</item>
                    <item>is the delay in NSC clearance of the 1952-54 volume on Germany and Austria
                        the result of NSC “censorship”?</item>
                    <item>why has there been no the Historical Office-CDC agreement on the 1952-54
                        volume on the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe?</item>
                </list>
                <p>Prof. Gruber asked:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>what are the categories of classification?</item>
                    <item>are there written guidelines that the CDC reviewers follow for <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> declassification?</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador Burke responded by giving a brief history of the various executive
                    orders dealing with declassification since the first one under Truman, and then
                    gave a general description of how the CDC operates in clearing <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes under the current Executive Order. He said
                    that there are only three levels of classification: Top Secret, Secret, and
                    Confidential. He pointed out that declassification often involved other agencies
                    such as the Department of Defense. If a document was purely of State Department
                    origin, declassification could be decided by CDC without referral to another
                    agency. After looking at the document, however, the CDC reviewer might decide to
                    consult the desk or office from which the document originated.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins commented that this sounded as if each case was decided on an <hi
                        rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> basis and asked again if there were any
                    guidelines for declassification.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke replied that there were informal guidelines but not necessarily
                    written ones to cover every case. He pointed out that CDC reviewers are experts
                    in their individual areas and that CDC depends upon their judgment.</p>
                <p>Prof. Holsti asked whether the recent executive orders on declassification
                    differed significantly. Ambassador Burke said that there were not any
                    significant differences. Some criteria for classification have been added
                    through the years, but the thrust has not changed dramatically. Reclassification
                    was done only if the material in question was recoverable, i.e. if it had not
                    already been copied and distributed. He agreed that the recent executive order
                    was more stringent than its predecessors in this regard, but he pointed out that
                    it had been drafted not by the White House but by the Information Security
                    Oversight Office (ISOO). It reflected the experience of many officials from
                    different agencies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Thompson said he could recall only three or four attempts to reclassify
                    documents, and only one case where it was accomplished. He said that processing
                    was going on in all the Presidential libraries. The Nixon material was a special
                    case, because access was not yet regularized. He felt, however, that the Nixon
                    material would be available in time for the Historical Office to compile volumes
                    and adhere to the 30-year line.</p>
                <p>Mr. Glennon said that the Historical Office was examining ways to speed up the
                    processing of Vietnam material at the Johnson Library, which now was processed
                    only through 1965. In the meantime, we were considering the possibility of
                    gathering Vietnam documentation from other sources and saving the Johnson
                    Library research for last.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Prof. Kuehl, the Ambassador said he did not
                    anticipate any major declassification problems with the Vietnam volumes, given
                    the quantity of documentation that has already been declassified.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ambach pointed out that the absence of agreement between declassifiers and
                    historians did not mean that matters were necessarily at an impasse. In some
                    cases, the two offices were in the process of working out an agreement. Prof.
                    Perkins commented that 16 volumes in this category, however, was a very large
                    number.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson asked whether the delay in releasing the 1952-54 Germany volume was
                    due to the sensitivity of U.S. relations with West Germany. Mr. Ambach answered
                    that this was a tough volume to clear and noted that there was a conflict
                    between the Department’s desire to publish and the NSC concern about still
                    sensitive issues. He added that clearance also required resources.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek asked what the Advisory Committee could do that would be
                    constructive to help get the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    out and maybe even reach the 30-year line. Prof. Gruber asked specifically
                    whether a committee recommendation that more resources be added to the CDC or
                    NSC would be helpful. The Ambassador said that in surveying the status report,
                    it seemed that only 3 volumes fell beyond the 30-year line. All the rest were in
                    the 1955-57 triennium. Most of the delays in this group were due to the GPO.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson asked whether the Department felt it had to wait 30 years before a
                    volume could be published. Ambassador Burke answered that 30 years was a goal
                    and he was reasonably hopeful it could be attained. He mentioned in particular
                    the problems posed for clearance by long-lived foreign officials who were active
                    in the 1950’s and are still active.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked whether the CDC could clear the 27 volumes for the 1955-1957
                    triennium in a two-year period of time so as to reach the 30-year line. The
                    Ambassador replied that it was feasible, and that Under Secretary of State
                    Spiers was committed to supporting the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series with resources. In reply to Prof. Gruber’s question, he said that a
                    recommendation by the committee for more resources for the CDC would be
                    helpful.</p>
                <p>In further response to Prof. Perkins’ question, Mr. Ambach said that clearance
                    time for a volume averaged six months in CDC, but the time to clear with other
                    agencies varied considerably from volume to volume. Ambassador Burke expressed
                    his belief that the new presidential directive would encourage other agencies to
                    respond more quickly.</p>
                <p>Prof. Gruber asked whether the new presidential directive would encourage the NSC
                    to clear more material for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Ambassador
                    Burke answered that on a close call, it might make a difference with the NSC,
                    but in general it was unlikely to have much effect with that agency.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked what Secretary Shultz meant by the word “disclosure” in his
                    reply to last year’s committee report? He used the word in referring to the
                    process whereby documents are released to the public after thirty years.
                    Ambassador Burke answered that the word referred to the transfer of records to
                    the Archives where they become fully accessible. Mr. Slany said that the word
                    “disclosure” appears in the new presidential directive as well, and means that
                    its purpose not only is to facilitate publication of the partial record in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series but also to provide access
                    to the full record at NARA.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Scholarly Community Involvement with Declassification
                    Process</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek suggested there might be a way for the scholarly community to figure
                    in the declassification process on particularly important disagreements between
                    the Historical Office and the declassification staff. In reply to the
                    Ambassador’s comment that his official position wouldn’t let him recommend
                    circumventing the system, Dallek said that he was not advocating a lobbying
                    effort. He proposed that a scholar with an excellent reputation be cleared to
                    become part of the process. Although this would not resolve all the problems, it
                    would open up the process more and might reduce some of the suspicion that
                    exists in the scholarly community.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson said that many people felt that the declassification decisions were
                    made arbitrarily, especially in the apparent absence of written criteria. At the
                    Eisenhower Library, she frequently saw withdrawal slips and was told by library
                    staff that these were Churchill-Eisenhower communications that were routinely
                    removed because of the provisions of the executive order. She asked whether it
                    was true that anything written by a foreign leader automatically retained its
                    classification. Entire folders at the Eisenhower Library were pink-sheeted. She
                    specifically mentioned the Churchill-Eisenhower correspondence on trade
                    issues.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke said that her general impression was not valid. Many
                    communications from foreign leaders, including Churchill, had been declassified.
                    At David Painter’s suggestion, Burke briefly defined “foreign government
                    information” for declassification purposes. He said that, as distinct from
                    “foreign government documents” which are those documents authored by foreign
                    governments, “foreign government information” is information contained in U.S.
                    documents that was obtained from foreign governments. Permission is requested
                    from friendly governments before publishing foreign government documents or
                    foreign government information of a sensitive nature. Foreign government
                    information is not withheld or cleared simply because it is foreign.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke asked Prof. Dallek whether the procedure he had suggested might
                    not lead to the outside scholar being coopted. Nevertheless, Ambassador Burke
                    said he would be willing to try it if the right person could be found--someone
                    who was willing to devote the time needed to review the documents. In response
                    to Prof. Gruber’s question as to how he envisioned the process working,
                    Ambassador Burke said that one possibility was for the outside scholar to be
                    given a position in the Historical Office or Classification/Declassification
                    Center. A key question would be how this person was to be recruited.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek remarked that the selection should probably be handled by the
                    organizations represented on the committee. It would have to be a person in whom
                    the academic community had the highest confidence.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl suggested that a retired distinguished historian, like Richard
                    Leopold, would be ideal.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove questioned whether the participation of an outside scholar in the
                    process would be that helpful. He asked whether there was not something
                    structurally deficient about the declassification system. How much of the
                    backlog in publishing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes was due
                    to a lack of means for resolving disputes, and how much was due to other
                    factors? He said that the committee needed more information about how the
                    process worked.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that they had to be practical concerning the operation of
                    the government and inter-agency disputes. He noted that there are fiefdoms
                    within the government and that, if an agency felt strongly about a particular
                    document, it could stop it from being released. He pointed out that there was no
                    oversight agency with the power to monitor the declassification process except
                    the NSC and the President. He said that they could use more resources. He
                    suggested that a representative of the historical profession would function best
                    in an ombudsman capacity. He or she could not become involved in each individual
                    dispute. Ambassador Burke noted again that he was in favor of the Presidential
                    Directive because it would reinforce the primacy of publication of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and would help with other agencies in
                    declassification disputes.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked whether Ambassador Burke himself had the power to arbitrate a
                    simple case, such as a dispute between the historians and the declassification
                    reviewers. Ambassador Burke responded that in almost all cases the decision of
                    the bureau would be final. Prof. Perkins emphasized whether he had the <hi
                        rend="underline">power</hi> to act in such cases. Ambassador Burke replied
                    that he did, but that this was not a common occurrence.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove asked whether declassification disputes were ever taken to the NSC
                    for resolution. Mr. Slany replied that the NSC only wanted to see documents upon
                    which agreement had been reached by all other agencies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove asked whether a review group at a sub-cabinet level could not be
                    created. Prof. Dallek said this idea was consistent with his suggestion about an
                    ombudsman, and that it would be more practical to start with an individual. At
                    some later point a group might be created.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany commented that the Historical Office had not pushed some disputes to an
                    early resolution in the hope that delay might ultimately help clearance. He
                    noted that an early enforced decision might be negative and/or leave no
                    possibility for appeal. He pointed to the danger of a conflict resolution
                    procedure that worked well but resulted in many documents being left out. It
                    would be possible to have <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    published in 20 years but without much in them. He stated that the atmosphere
                    concerning disclosure of information had changed in the last ten years and that
                    a new Executive Order might prove even more restrictive. He commented that those
                    who wanted to protect information from disclosure could do it more effectively
                    than ever. This was why the Historical Office viewed with skepticism involvement
                    in the hasty resolution of declassification disputes. Slany noted that the
                    Historical Office was working more cooperatively with CDC than ever before and
                    was finding more ways within the system to resolve disputes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">How the Declassification Review Process Works</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that in the end it has to be the Department’s action
                    officers who retain ultimate decision. They are the ones who are aware of
                    whether a delicate negotiation is in progress that would be jeopardized by the
                    publication of the material in question.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove said there was a built-in bias in the system favoring continued
                    classification. An action officer’s career might be damaged by disclosure, but
                    never by recommending continued classification. The risks to a person’s career
                    would be reduced by having a higher organ of resolution. Ambassador Burke said
                    decisions were made not only to protect careers. There were real issues at
                    stake, particularly current negotiations. Prof. Perkins said it was obviously a
                    question of degree. Some disclosures would only cause a ripple of trouble, not
                    an explosion. He agreed with Mr. Hargrove that the desk officer was not the most
                    dispassionate person.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke pointed out that the declassification reviewer often has
                    considerable influence on the desk officer. The reviewer is often someone who
                    had first-hand experience with the material in question and who has the broader
                    historical perspective that the desk officer lacks.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl said that the Advisory Committee did not know enough about the
                    clearance process. He could not understand how the Presidential Directive would
                    accelerate the process. How would the Presidential Directive help in the dispute
                    over specific issues concerning the 1952-1954 volumes? Ambassador Burke stated
                    that it would speed up the process. It would give the Department the power to go
                    to other agencies and use the Presidential Directive to say this should be
                    released.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked Ambassador Burke whether he could prepare a paper describing
                    the functions of the Classification/Declassification Center and whether this
                    paper could be given to the scholarly community. Ambassador Burke asked that the
                    Committee, outside the terms of its formal report, tell him what sort of paper
                    it would like.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked what priority clearing <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes had for a desk officer. Ambassador Burke responded
                    that it used to be very low but noted that now the declassification reviewers
                    approach desk officers directly as needed. He also commented that, if the
                    documents in question happened to be related to a declassifier’s experience in
                    the Foreign Service, the officer was generally more eager to clear them.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins expressed the feeling that the retired Foreign Service Officers
                    serving as declassifiers were most likely concerned with protecting U.S.
                    policy-makers. Ambassador Burke said it was just the opposite. The reviewers
                    feel that generally the documents reveal a good record and are anxious to get it
                    out. There has been no case where a bad policy had been covered up. Prof.
                    Perkins said he was happy to receive these assurances, but he wanted only to
                    mention that this view did persist in the academic community. The Ambassador
                    said he was aware of this, and that he had heard similar sentiments voiced.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked what was the main concern at CDC. Was it sensitivity--the
                    impact of the release of historical records on policies today? Ambassador Burke
                    agreed that this was the principal consideration.</p>
                <p rend="underline">New DOS-NARA Agreement</p>
                <p>Ambassador Burke stated that last week Under Secretary Spiers had concluded a new
                    agreement with the National Archives to help support declassification of State
                    Department records for the 1955-1959 period. This renews the previous subsidy,
                    which had been for the 1950-1954 record block. Mr. Thompson said that for this
                    block, NARA will pay a larger percentage than it had for the 1950-1954 block. He
                    said that NARA’s review of the 1955-1959 block will begin in March 1986 and will
                    be completed in four years.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee’s Private Meeting</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl adjourned the meeting at 3:55 p.m. The committee met privately to
                    prepare its report.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
