<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1986</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1986</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-02-24">February 24, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1986-11-06">November 6, 1986</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1986-11-06-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 326 KB, 21pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 5, Advisory Committee Minutes - 1986. Drafted
                    by Historian William Z. Slany, Deputy Historian Neal H. Petersen, and Assistant
                    to the Historian and Information Staff Chief Carol A. Becker (PA/HO). A record
                    of the classified briefing on declassification procedures, mentioned at the
                    close of the Thursday afternoon session, has not been located.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn19">Footnote 19</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1986 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 6-7, 1986</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Robert Dallek, Department of History, University of California, Los
                        Angeles, California 90024</item>
                    <item>Dr. Blanche Wiesen Cook, Department of History, John Jay College, CUNY,
                        New York, New York 10036</item>
                    <item>Dr. Warren F. Kuehl, Department of History, University of Akron, Akron,
                        Ohio 44325</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Michel Oksenberg, Center for Chinese Studies, Lane Hall, University of
                        Michigan, Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109</item>
                    <item>Dr. Deborah W. Larson, Department of Political Science, Columbia
                        University, New York, New York 10027</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. John Lawrence Hargrove, Executive Vice President and Executive
                        Director, The American Society of International Law, 2223 Massachusetts
                        Avenue, N.W., Washington, D.C., 20008</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bradford Perkins, Department of History, University of Michigan, Ann
                        Arbor, Michigan 48109</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Warren I. Cohen, Department of History, Michigan State University,
                        East Lansing, Michigan 48824</item>
                    <item>Dr. Michael H. Hunt, Department of History, University of North Carolina,
                        Chapel Hill, North Carolina 27514</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Other Persons Present:</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George B. High, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(Both days):</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Neal H. Petersen, Deputy Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Foreign Relations Division Chief</item>
                    <item>Carol A. Becker, Assistant to the Historian and Information Staff
                        Chief</item>
                    <item>Mitchell Stewart, Management Advisor</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>(Friday only):</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen, Policy Studies Division Chief</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson, Operations Staff Chief</item>
                    <item>David H. Herschler, Records Historian</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler</item>
                    <item>Suzanne E. Coffman</item>
                    <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>Nancy Golden</item>
                    <item>Katherine Hagedorn</item>
                    <item>Kay Herring</item>
                    <item>Nina D. Howland</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Ronald D. Landa</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>Neal O’Loughlin</item>
                    <item>David S. Painter</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC): (Thursday session)</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ambassador John R. Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Classification/Declassification</item>
                    <item>Dwight Ambach, Director, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                    <item>Benjamin Fleck</item>
                    <item>Charles Floweree</item>
                    <item>William Galloway</item>
                    <item>Sidney Sober</item>
                </list>
                <p>Foreign Affairs Information Management Center (A/FAIM):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Paul Washington, Chief, Publishing Services Division</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker, Documentary Editing Section Chief</item>
                </list>
                <p>Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief, Diplomatic Branch, NARA</item>
                    <item>Edwin A. Thompson, Project Director, Records Declassification Division,
                        NARA</item>
                    <item>David Langbart, Records Appraisal Division, NARA</item>
                    <item>Kenneth McDonald, Chief Historian, CIA</item>
                    <item>Chief, Classification Review Division, CIA</item>
                    <item>Mary McAuliffe, Historian, CIA</item>
                    <item>James Gardner, American Historical Association</item>
                </list>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Omitted here is a list of abbreviations.</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Thursday Morning Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p>The meeting was convened at 10:30 a.m. Deputy Assistant Secretary High welcomed
                    the Committee to the Department, observed the Department’s concern over the
                    effort to accelerate the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, and
                    wished the Committee well in its deliberations. The Committee elected Prof. Brad
                    Perkins by acclamation to be Chairman.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Opening Statement by The Historian</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked the Committee to consider and make recommendations to the
                    Department on two major issues this year: 1) the need to limit the size of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in order to stretch
                    available resources to meet the targets of the acceleration program; and 2) the
                    need for expert academic critical evaluation of the contents of volumes before
                    publication to assure that the numerous if smaller volumes published under the
                    acceleration plan contain the essential historical record.</p>
                <p>Consideration of these two related issues ought to be carried on bearing in mind
                    the three positive factors and three negative factors. On the positive side:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(1) The first year of the acceleration plan has been successful and
                        publication and declassification of the increased number of volumes is on
                        schedule;</item>
                    <item>(2) The Department’s leadership is aware and concerned about the delays in
                        publishing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and supports
                        the efforts of all involved to speed up the process;</item>
                    <item>(3) The process of declassifying the volumes in the series is working
                        well.</item>
                </list>
                <p>On the down side, however, there are an equal number of negative factors:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(1) General budget reduction efforts of the government as a whole and the
                        sharp cuts in the State Department’s budget in particular have a very direct
                        and serious impact upon the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> program
                        and will require broad cost cutting measures if the acceleration schedule is
                        to be achieved.</item>
                    <item>(2) In the last ten years the Historian’s Office has carried out a major
                        modernization and improvement in the preparation of the series volumes
                        including greatly expanding the sources used in the compiling, expanding the
                        annotational apparatus, and revising the format of the volumes; the
                        Committee and the public, however, has thus far seen few of these new
                        volumes (more than 40 in number have been compiled and fewer than 10
                        published) and cannot make much of a judgment about the new editing
                        procedures and how far they go toward reducing the need for oversized
                        books;</item>
                    <item>(3) while the declassification procedures have been essentially perfected
                        and are functioning well, the substantive evaluation of the impact of
                        declassification review upon the quality of the published historical record
                        has to be continuously critically reviewed; the staff of the Historian’s
                        Office is inevitably placed in an adversarial position toward the
                        Department’s declassifiers and obliged to advocate the maximum disclosure of
                        historical records and information.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Slany concluded by again emphasizing the need for Advisory Committee advice
                    and counsel on structure and scope of an accelerated series that provides for
                    over 50 volumes over the next four years as well as for guidance on how to
                    institute a more systematic critique of that many volumes in advance of their
                    publication. The review and critique that was most needed would evaluate the
                    structure of individual volumes, the selection of documents, and the impact upon
                    the accuracy of the record of deletions in the declassification process. In the
                    discussion that followed the Committee commented upon the merits and dangers of
                    the trade-off between earlier publication of the record and more selective
                    volumes in the series that were smaller than those of recent years. The
                    committee explored the concern of the academic profession over the endorsement
                    of a Department policy to publish less of the official record. There seemed to
                    be general willingness on the Committee’s part to acknowledge the need for
                    economies in producing the accelerated series, but members were eager to explore
                    all aspects of the matter.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Statement on Budgetary Considerations by Mitchell Stewart</p>
                <p>Three factors are at work:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1) The accelerated publishing schedule will create a large increase in
                        funding requirements. The Department has already acted to reduce sharply the
                        printing and binding costs of each volume by concluding a long-term contract
                        with a commercial printing firm. Under this new printing contract, each
                        800-page volume costs the DOS $28,000. This figure is far lower than any GPO
                        cost for any previous volume and is generally regarded as genuinely
                        economical. It includes technical editing, proofreading, index, composition,
                        printing and binding.</item>
                    <item>2) There is a tradeoff between volume size and cost. Each additional page
                        above 800 (which has been determined to be the optimum size to declassify,
                        edit, index, and produce) has a dollar cost associated with it.</item>
                    <item>3) Marketing realities matter. Of a complete press run of about 3000
                        copies, the first 300 copies (paid for by the Department at a cost of
                        $28,000) are given away by HO; the next 1030 copies (at a marginal cost of
                        $4.00 per volume) are given away by the Congress to the depository
                        libraries; the next 1000 copies (again at a marginal cost of $4.00 each) are
                        paid for by the Congress and are given away as House Documents. Thus, only
                        about 800 are sales items at GPO for which marketing techniques will make
                        any difference at all.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Upon conclusion of this presentation, several committee members inquired about
                    the relative advantage of publishing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes at a university press. Members of the Historian’s
                    Office explained that the Department was obliged by law to publish its volumes
                    only through the Government Printing Office. A waiver from this legal
                    requirement could only be obtained from Congress, and it was extremely difficult
                    to obtain. The extended term printing contract for the volumes was the best that
                    could be done, but the Department would continue to pursue such a waiver. The
                    university press route remained a possibility in the future. The great advantage
                    of a university press might not be in its cost per item but in its far superior
                    merchandising mechanisms. On the other hand, the GPO distribution system, which
                    provides free of charge copies of each <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume to
                    over 1000 depository libraries, retains an undeniable advantage.</p>
                <p>Committee members inquired about the possibility of publishing some list of the
                    documents omitted from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes because
                    of declassification problems. Such a list of documents could help scholars who
                    might wish to carry on research beyond the printed texts. Reductions in the
                    number of documents printed in the series would make such lists even more
                    useful. Mr. Slany said that to some extent this was already being done, but in
                    the form of references to individual documents in footnotes. In cases where
                    whole documents had been deleted by the CDC, a precise list of still classified
                    papers would become grist for FOIA requests. The CDC would obviously find such a
                    list undesirable. Slany assured the Committee that the Historian’s Office would
                    explore the inclusion in future <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes of calendars
                    or lists of papers not selected for publication but of importance to the study
                    of the subject being documented.</p>
                <p>There was a discussion of the relationship of the publication of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes and the systematic
                    declassification of Department records and their opening to scholars and the
                    public. Strictly speaking the opening of the Department’s files for scholars’
                    access and the publication of the selected record in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> volumes are separate and distinct operations. In practice, the
                    preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes is the
                    essential first step in the CDC’s work in systematically reviewing the files for
                    declassification. Slany observed that the contribution of the historians in
                    selecting a sample of the most representative documents and files for any given
                    time period is the key to the CDC processing of the whole of the Department
                    records before they are acquired by the National Archives. From the Department’s
                    point of view the actual publication of the volumes in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series is not necessary for the completion of the
                    declassification of all the records and their opening at the National Archives.
                    Slany further observed that budget reductions being experienced by the
                    Department made the status of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series precarious
                    for the reason that opening of the files could go forward even if no volumes
                    were published. That was why it is urgent to devise a publication scheme and
                    scope that continues to be reasonable to meet the most urgent Department
                    obligations to the historical community.</p>
                <p>The Committee turned to a discussion of the functions and role of a possible
                    editorial board. Attention was given to the utility of a pre-publication review
                    of the volumes. Slany reminded the Committee that more than 50 volumes would, if
                    the schedule were adhered to, be published in the next four years. Neither the
                    Office nor the Department wanted to wait for several years to discover that the
                    volumes were flawed in some serious way as to negate the whole expensive effort
                    of bringing out the volumes in the face of so many constraints. Slany was
                    willing for the Committee to provide the names of particularly qualified
                    scholars who could review the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes after they had
                    been declassified but before they were set in print and published.</p>
                <p>The idea of an editorial board as a subcommittee of the Advisory Committee was
                    examined and generally supported. The editorial board or members of the
                    Committee might serve as brokers between the Department and the academic
                    community in identifying qualified specialists who would review individual
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>Further Committee discussion revolved around two overlapping themes -- the need
                    for the Committee or its editorial board to review and evaluate the contents of
                    the slimmer <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in manuscript
                    before and apart from any declassification review (and whether this review
                    required access to the larger body of classified records from which the
                    manuscript compilations were derived) and the second theme of the need for the
                    Committee and board to review the deletions made during the declassification
                    process to determine the accuracy of the remaining record to the published. The
                    Committee did not come to a clear conclusion in the exchanges on these subjects,
                    but it appeared to be inclined to wish to investigate both. Committee members
                    also raised the question of whether the Department and other agencies prepared
                    and exchanged lists of documents declassified under the FOIA process and the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> declassification procedures. Mr. Slany informed the
                    Committee that, at the request of the A/CDC, the Historian’s Office had proposed
                    a quarterly Departmental publication of lists of Department documents
                    declassified and released under the FOIA. This publication, which could be used
                    by the public to identify and get access to copies of released documents, could
                    be fairly easily and economically prepared. The decision on going ahead with
                    this project rested elsewhere in the Department.</p>
                <p>The Committee also wanted to know more about the microform supplements. Mr. Slany
                    had reported earlier that microform supplements would be resorted to for
                    publication of some documents not included in the accelerated <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He thought that the size of the supplements
                    would vary but would probably be in the ratio of three microformed pages of
                    manuscript for every page of manuscript that went into the print volumes. The
                    documents included in supplements would not be those denied publication for
                    reasons of classification, but those not included in print volumes because of
                    their secondary importance and their size. Mr. Glennon explained that several
                    different designs for microform supplements were being used. First, there were
                    those special internal serial documents like <hi rend="italic">Current Economic
                        Developments</hi>, the Top Secret Summaries, the Wang-Johnson talks, and
                    other collections of the same sort. Such serials would be included as
                    supplements but without much, if any, annotational connection to the printed
                    volumes in the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series. Second, there were
                    collections of documents that related to a particular volume, on particular
                    countries or topics (such as Burma or Nepal), that were too large to include in
                    the print volume but could be published as supplements and linked in some
                    general annotational way. Thirdly, there were supplements composed of individual
                    documents that were not important enough to include in the printed volumes but
                    which would be carefully linked to the documents in the printed text with
                    annotational apparatus. The Historian’s Office was pursuing all three
                    tracks.</p>
                <p>The Committee had lunch with Ambassador Gerald Helman on the 8th Floor of the
                    Department. Ambassador Helman is Deputy to Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs Michael Armacost.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Thursday Afternoon Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p>The meeting reconvened at 2 p.m. Chairman Perkins returned the discussion to Mr.
                    Slany’s presentation on reduction of the size of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes for 1958-1960 and said that the proposal represented a 40% cut. Prof.
                    Oksenberg suggested that the volumes contain a guide to what is left out for
                    reasons of space and clearance. Prof. Perkins said that there were problems
                    connected with specifying what was not in the volumes. Prof. Cohen said that
                    this step was essential. Prof. Larson said that smaller volumes would
                    necessitate a more systematic approach to inclusion of materials; inclusion
                    should be based on a hierarchy of importance, with White House material first.
                    Mr. Slany noted that more White House documents were being included, and that
                    there was a top-down approach. However, the principles of inclusion that date
                    back to Secretary Kellogg should be examined and revised. Mr. Glennon added that
                    there was much more White House documentation beginning with the Eisenhower
                    years. This also pertained to the Vietnam volumes of the Kennedy and Johnson
                    period.</p>
                <p>Prof. Oksenberg observed that in the briefing material <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> had been described in four different ways: l) history of the
                    conduct of American diplomacy 2) record of the conduct of foreign relations 3)
                    the official diplomatic record, and 4) (implicitly) a guide to illuminate the
                    foreign policy decision-making process. If one definition were chosen, that
                    might point the way on categories of inclusion. Prof. Dallek recounted the
                    evolution of the series from the 1930’s when it relied almost exclusively on
                    State documents to its present form. He thought emphasis should continue to be
                    placed on the decision-making process and highest-level papers.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Pre-Publication Review of Volumes</p>
                <p>Prof. Hunt said that he was reluctant to approve smaller volumes without
                    Committee consideration of contents. The Committee had to see what was left out
                    for reasons of national security and for size reduction. Prof. Dallek said an
                    editorial board should be an arm of the Advisory Committee and not a 30-person
                    board. Oksenberg and Cook supported this idea. Prof. Perkins cited the
                    possibility of establishing an editorial board as a subcommittee of the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>There ensued general discussion of the feasibility of review prior to publication
                    of the volumes. Mr. Slany referred to CDC reluctance, but noted that in the past
                    the Committee had seen volumes before publication. The concepts of
                    pre-declassification review by the committee, post-declassification review, and
                    a combination of the two were considered.</p>
                <p>Prof. Cook referred to the 1952-1954 Guatemala compilation as one that fell short
                    of being comprehensive; even some declassified documents were not included. Mr.
                    Slany said that HO had been unable to use some declassified documents in the
                    case of Guatemala and in other instances. Prof. Dallek observed that if Vietnam
                    coverage were severely curtailed by declassification review, it could cause
                    major credibility problems with the profession.</p>
                <p>Prof. Oksenberg suggested a review similar to that obtained by a university
                    press, that is, review by a scholar and another knowledgeable person prior to
                    publication of a book. Prof. Dallek suggested that the Committee might serve as
                    a clearing house for appropriate readers. Mr. Petersen observed that publication
                    produced by military historical offices were often reviewed by advisory
                    committees after declassification and before release. Prof. Hunt said the
                    Committee could start up immediately in this fashion. Mr. Slany cautioned that
                    the CDC was sensitive to the possibility of pre-publication leakage even though
                    this had never taken place.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl referred to the report of last year’s Committee subcommittee on the
                    editorial board question which had recommended that the board be composed of
                    Committee members. Chairman Perkins said that the committee report would ask for
                    review of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> manuscript in the future. Prof. Hunt
                    agreed that the board should be composed of Committee members. Prof. Dallek
                    added that the committee could also arrange for outside readers as the subject
                    matter indicated. Mr. Glennon suggested a two-step approach; for now, it would
                    be easier to arrange for the Committee to review volumes after declassification
                    but before publication; subsequently, permission should be sought for Committee
                    examination of volumes as compiled and to see all documents excised and denied.
                    Prof. Oksenberg felt that the Department would agree to Committee access to all
                    documents chosen for a volume, but would not permit examination of
                    declassification decisions.</p>
                <p>[At this point, Ambassador John Burke, Deputy Assistant Secretary (CDC) and
                    members of his staff discussed the declassification process with the Advisory
                    Committee until the session adjourned at 5:30 p.m. The proceedings of that
                    discussion have been classified SECRET and are thus not included in these
                    minutes.]</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Morning Session (Open)</hi></p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins formally convened the meeting at 9:13 a.m., and asked Mr. Slany to
                    make his presentation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that there were three main issues to discuss: the structure of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series both in terms of physical
                    size and of content, the role of microform supplements, and distribution and
                    marketing. He referred the committee to Tab 7 of their briefing material, which
                    set out publication plans and Tables of Contents for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes in the 1955-57 and 1958-60 periods. He noted that only 17 volumes for
                    the 1958-1960 triennium were planned, which was a reduction from 1955-1957. The
                    committee could help us determine if this framework best served the interests of
                    scholars. In addition, he pointed out that the numbering of the volumes had
                    become arbitrary. Starting with 1955-57, they are now numbered and printed as
                    cleared and published. This step will not allow the continuation of the
                    numbering pattern of previous years.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked if reducing the size of the volumes by 40% and introducing
                    microfiche supplements will produce savings. Mr. Slany replied that reductions
                    were the only way the series could be produced at all in the light of dwindling
                    resources.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked by what standards would the future volumes be organized. Mr.
                    Slany replied that it would depend on personnel and financial resources and the
                    number of pages that could be printed, edited, and cleared. Other agencies had
                    less resources for clearing documents; their declassification activities are not
                    centralized in every case as they are in the State Department. In a February
                    meeting the State Department approached all the clearing agencies and filled
                    them in on the requirements for meeting a 30 year line by 1990. All the agencies
                    indicated their willingness to try very hard to meet the schedule for the 50
                    streamlined print volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Microfiche Supplements</p>
                <p>Prof. Hunt asked what percentage of the cuts from the volume will be restored by
                    the microfiche. Mr. Slany estimated that the supplements will include about 3
                    times as many documents as the printed volume and that the total documentation
                    released should be 2 to 3 times as great as in a printed volume. The documents
                    selected for microform publication, however, also require declassification,
                    which adds substantially to the clearance burden.</p>
                <p>Prof. Hunt asked how material for the microform supplements would be selected.
                    Mr. Glennon replied that there were several modes: special documentary
                    collections tied only indirectly to specific volumes of the series; documents,
                    or even collections of documents for whole countries, of lesser importance; and
                    collections of documents that were closely tied by annotation to the texts of
                    the printed volumes. He said that HO hoped to use the third mode most
                    frequently.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany explained that at least one State Department internal publication will
                    come out in microform very soon. This publication--Current Economic
                    Developments--is one example of a publication not connected to any specific
                    volume. He noted that it had an elaborate index and was an excellent guide to
                    the major issues of U.S. foreign economic policy during the period of its
                    internal publication, 1945-1954.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked what the time frame for volumes and microform publications
                    would be. Mr. Slany replied that ideally supplements would appear at the same
                    time as the printed volumes to which they were related. Prof. Perkins asked if
                    both groups of documents went simultaneously for clearance. Mr. Slany replied
                    that in some cases the bodies of documents went to A/CDC as a single very large
                    sample. However, for budgetary reasons CDC presently could review only those
                    documents proposed for publication in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes. The
                    intention had been for the Historical Office to give CDC a larger sample with
                    which to write their guidelines and to make a final selection for <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> only after declassification. Prof. Perkins asked if
                    this method actually expedited <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes. Mr. Slany
                    replied that dealing with a larger sample facilitated NARA declassification work
                    rather than <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked if documents declassified in later years but relevant to the
                    subject of a particular fiche supplement would be considered for publication as
                    additions later on. Mr. Slany said this was a question for the committee’s
                    consideration. If the fiche trailed the volumes, it might be possible. However,
                    a definitive supplement would limit ability to publish these later documents. He
                    added that the final decision on when to publish the fiche had not been made. He
                    also noted that a number of problems with the format in which they would be
                    released had to be resolved. Prof. Kuehl stressed that updating fiche was
                    easy--simply add a suffix to the old number on the new fiche card to indicate
                    where the new material should be filed.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Transfer of Records and Preparation of Guidelines</p>
                <p>Prof. Cohen repeated Prof. Perkins’ question about whether review of the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes by the CDC delayed the opening of documents
                    at NARA. Mr. Slany indicated that publication of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and
                    opening of the complete files were not absolutely linked. The real issue in
                    opening files at NARA was the elasticity of CDC resources.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked whether the word “disclosure” had ever been defined. Mr. Slany
                    said that it meant opening all records to researchers. HO’s goal was to bring
                    its activities as close as possible to the 30-year line for both publications
                    and for opening Department files at the Archives.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked whether there had been a decision to “decouple” <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publication from opening the files. Mr. Slany
                    replied that these were separate lines of activities. Alan Thompson said that
                    NARA did in fact accept uncleared records, with guidance for their subsequent
                    clearance coming from CDC and HO. In reply to a question from Prof. Cohen, Mr.
                    Thompson said that historical perspectives and relations with the country in
                    question determined what documents were or were not sensitive. Guidelines for
                    1955-59 are being based on the experience gained with the 1950-54 files. The
                    guidelines are classified, but CDC bases them on criteria from the country
                    desks. They are written in narrative style and are quite specific as to what has
                    to be withheld. Ambassador John Burke was the only person whom Mr. Thompson
                    could cite as their author.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek asked whether <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publication and NARA file
                    openings were simultaneous. Mr. Thompson replied that there had been no linkage
                    between the two for the past 10 years. Mr. Slany added that, as a matter of
                    fact, NARA records could be opened more or less on schedule even if the
                    Department decided not to finance the publication of any more <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> volumes. PA/HO still would have the responsibility, however, to
                    collect the documents to initiate the preparation of guidelines for the
                    declassification process. By identifying leading policy issues, <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publication helped NARA to develop its own
                    declassification guidelines.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Declassification Procedures</p>
                <p>Prof. Cook inquired about pre-CDC clearance procedures. Mr. Slany replied that
                    before the CDC was created in 1978 documents had to be reviewed by overburdened
                    geographic bureaus. Other agencies and governments still had to consulted, but
                    HO itself coordinated the review process. The sharp increase in FOIA requests in
                    the late 70’s made bureau review impossible. “If CDC did not exist, it would
                    have to be invented.”</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson then asked whether documents were transferred to NARA incrementally
                    before there was a CDC. Mr. Slany said this was the case, and the bureaus had to
                    be asked to agree to their transfer. Milton Gustafson then explained that prior
                    to 1975, State records were released to NARA one year at a time. The Freedom of
                    Information Act amendments in the late 70s, however, no longer permitted records
                    to be withheld just because 25 or 30 years had not yet elapsed, obliging NARA to
                    turn to multi-year blocks. Mr. Thompson said that NARA expected to release all
                    1959 records by 1991, some of them next summer.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson expressed concern at the delay in releasing records, noting that the
                    British had already released records relating to the Suez Crisis. Mr. Thompson
                    said that some State records on Suez would be available in January; he said
                    we’re ahead in some areas and behind in others, and NARA would be delighted to
                    go faster if it had the resources.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked how CDC decided to allocate its resources. Mr. Slany replied
                    that HO provided lists to the CDC showing the volumes in the order necessary to
                    meet the publication schedule. Mr. Thompson added that <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> got priority for CDC review. Mr. Gustafson noted that NARA needed
                    a better record of documents declassified through publication in <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. It was embarrassing to have a researcher make an
                    FOI request only to be told months later that the documents desired had been or
                    were about to be published.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany said that CDC had a less than perfect record of what documents it had
                    declassified since its beginnings in 1979. There was no stamp on documents
                    indicating whether or not they had been previously declassified or withheld.
                    HO’s word processing system was currently being used to try to devise a list of
                    documents cleared wholly or in part. Mr. Hargrove asked whether there was any
                    means of keeping track of which documents were not cleared the first time
                    around, so that they could be added to the database. Mrs. Carol Becker replied
                    that HO was compiling lists of documents that it had selected for publication,
                    and that the lists would later indicate whether or not the individual documents
                    had been cleared.</p>
                <p>Prof. Cook asked whether other agencies were working toward the same time
                    schedule as State. Mr. Thompson replied that, theoretically, NARA would like to
                    review all Federal records at 30 years, regardless of origin. In practice,
                    resources were limited and only a State subvention to NARA was expediting the
                    opening of State’s records. Of other agencies, only AID was making a similar
                    joint effort. By way of contrast, one more year would still be needed to clear
                    the last records of the OSS, which closed down in 1945. There had been no
                    cooperation from the FBI concerning its records.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Electronic Records</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl then asked what would happen when existing computer technology became
                    obsolete. Mr. Slany said that HO had not formulated any rules, but that a
                    Department task force was studying the preservation and control of electronic
                    records. David Herschler qualified this observation. A working group had been
                    established with two people from HO on it, but there had been only one meeting
                    and that was 8 or 9 months ago.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked about the life expectancy of diskettes. Mr. Herschler replied
                    that diskettes were not an acceptable storage mode. Nine-track magnetic tape,
                    however, was acceptable. The life span of laser disks was not certain, but
                    appeared to be at least 15 to 20 years.</p>
                <p>Prof. Oksenberg pointed out that preservation of electronic records could be the
                    most urgent issue of all before the committee. Mrs. Becker suggested that all
                    new members of the committee be sent copies of Mr. Herschler’s 1985 report on
                    the subject.</p>
                <p>Mr. Herschler then pointed out that the Department’s electronic records were far
                    from complete. Office lot files are not part of the automated files, but
                    supplement them. Lot files are “computerized” only if created on a word
                    processor. Prof. Dallek asked whether memcons were in lot files or computerized
                    in the central files. Mr. Herschler explained that they were only on paper. FAIM
                    did not always regularly microfilm them for inclusion in its system. Mrs. Becker
                    explained that since 1973 (when the Department’s automated system went into
                    effect), the Department’s practice was to have 2 official record copies, one on
                    film and one on tape. Records of the Secretary of State were in custody of the
                    Executive Secretary, and were stored on a separate computerized system (SADI)
                    with its own index.</p>
                <p>Prof. Oksenberg asked whether State studied how other agencies kept their
                    records. Mr. Herschler replied that every agency had some electronic records,
                    but none was wholly paperless. There was no coordinated interagency policy on
                    electronic records.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany then interrupted the session for a coffee break at 10:15 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="underline"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Supplementary Volumes
                    on Intelligence</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany resumed the session by introducing the subject of retrospective
                    supplements to printed volumes in the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series. A
                    previous Committee had suggested preparation of a supplement on post-World War
                    II intelligence and foreign policy development which would incorporate
                    disclosures made since the volumes in this area were published. The Office of
                    the Historian was considering such a project, perhaps comprising one printed
                    volume and one microfiche supplement. He asked Kenneth McDonald, the CIA
                    Historian, to discuss this proposal further.</p>
                <p>Mr. McDonald noted that the idea had originated three years earlier, when he and
                    Mr. Petersen had participated on a SHAFR panel on intelligence. In 1983 the CIA
                    was beginning to release OSS operational records and was also negotiating with
                    Congress on the Freedom of Information Act. He pointed out that in the
                    bargaining which culminated in the recent legislation that exempted the CIA from
                    some aspects of FOIA, an agreement had been reached to review some older CIA
                    records for possible release. The concept of supplementary intelligence-related
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publications was given impetus by this
                    agreement. The Agency now has a classification review staff which is currently
                    working on the records of the Office of the Director of Central Intelligence
                    from the late 1940s. Mr. McDonald commented that the Department’s requirement
                    for records from 1945-1950 thus coincides with the work of the CIA
                    declassification staff, and will result in State historians being given good
                    access to CIA records of the period. He is not sure, however, how much of this
                    material can be declassified.</p>
                <p>He then introduced the Chief of the Classification Review Division (CRD) who
                    described the historical review program. It has started reviewing records from
                    the Office of the Director of Central Intelligence, as well as some records from
                    the Special Services Unit (which superseded OSS) and records of the U-2
                    incident. The staff has processed about 135 feet of records. Review must now be
                    coordinated with other agencies. About l foot of records has completed the
                    entire process. The next group of records to be examined will be finished
                    intelligence, which the CIA hopes will help with the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> supplements.</p>
                <p>Mr. McDonald observed that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    represents the U.S. Government’s accountability for its foreign policy. The CIA
                    recognizes this. While the British have never released any intelligence records
                    at all, the CIA is committed to releasing its records. The Agency works under
                    the same NARA rules as other executive agencies, using the same procedures.</p>
                <p>Prof. Hunt asked if finished intelligence will deal with covert intelligence. The
                    CRD chief said that operational records relating to sources and methods are
                    exempted from consideration by his staff under the new Congressional directive.
                    The committee pressed to get an appreciation of where the cut-off line existed
                    in determining what constituted operational information. Both Prof. Perkins and
                    Prof. Cook used CIA activities in Italy during the first decade after WW II as
                    an example of covert operations which were well known, historically significant,
                    and could be documented without compromising CIA methods or sources. Both Mr.
                    Macdonald and the CRD chief indicated that it was altogether unlikely that the
                    CIA would officially confirm the existence of covert operations, despite
                    widespread knowledge of the existence and impact of such operations.</p>
                <p>This, the CRD chief stated again, is the central issue. The CIA works for the
                    President under Congressional oversight. It has orders from both the Congress
                    and the President to protect sources and methods. If he were to look at these
                    records to see if they could be released, he would ask the following questions:
                    Who ordered the activities? Who was used? Where did the money come from? How did
                    it get there? The Agency would probably not reveal this. Where, he asked, should
                    they draw the line? Just admitting that this activity occurred would not, he
                    felt, be enough. There was no real answer, but he would probably be inclined to
                    “cut it off early.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany observed that these issues were worth consideration by the Committee.
                    Perhaps the Committee could explore how the Office of the Historian could work
                    with the CIA to bring material on intelligence formulation to light and could
                    confirm that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was a useful vehicle
                    for disclosure.</p>
                <p>Prof. Dallek stated that although it was fine to publish a retrospective volume
                    and that its publication would represent some progress, there should be no
                    illusions about the volume’s reception; some scholars would “savage” it,
                    scoffing at how little was being released compared to what was already widely
                    known. He worried about creating cynicism, about creating a sense of a gap
                    between U.S. rhetoric and action. He was not, however, insensitive to the
                    Office’s and the CIA’s dilemma. The volume would produce an angry reaction, but
                    he favored publishing it.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked for a concrete indication of what was being considered for
                    publication. Mr. Petersen responded that one volume relating to the
                    organizational development of the intelligence community from the Second World
                    War to 1950, and a second volume largely relating to finished intelligence
                    concerning the Soviet Union are being prepared. Prof. Perkins asked what was the
                    proportion of previously released documents to never released documents in the
                    proposed supplement? Mr. Petersen responded that probably less than 25% of the
                    volume on organization of intelligence would comprise CIA material. The second
                    volume would have a larger percentage. Mr. Petersen added that there was also
                    the CIA report to every NSC meeting on the world situation, as well as Director
                    of Central Intelligence memoranda to the President. Although much of this
                    material has been declassified, it will be published in a coherent way for the
                    first time. To avoid disappointment, he recommended defining the terms of
                    reference for the supplements very carefully and then sticking to them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany suggested that the committee might want to nominate a reviewer or two
                    for these volumes before publication. Prof. Dallek felt that such a review might
                    serve to help preserve the credibility of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    series.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl observed that most important to him was the question of the budget
                    trade-off in preparing a supplement. The Office was proposing two additional
                    volumes at the same time it was reducing the size of the regular series. Mr.
                    Slany responded that one or two volumes could be added over four or five years
                    without a change in the schedule for the regular series. Three or four volumes,
                    however, would tip the balance. This was less a problem for printing and
                    publication than it was for declassification. The Committee’s recommendations
                    would be useful to us in setting our priorities.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked whether a new policy of supplementing the series was being
                    established. Both Prof. Hunt and Prof. Cook stated they would need to see the
                    material involved before making a recommendation. Prof. Cook also asked for more
                    guidance. She was worried about creating a dual system rather than being
                    vigorous about a 30-year rule and accountability, even though she realized some
                    issues won’t wind down after 30 years. Prof. Larson said that political
                    scientists would find such volumes very useful, even if they contained nothing
                    more than finished intelligence.</p>
                <p>Prof. Oksenberg wondered whether the retrospective supplement might encourage
                    people not to declassify things now--to delay release--because they knew there
                    would be a supplement to the volumes they review now. Was there any validity to
                    this argument? He offered the observation that Mr. McDonald had neglected to
                    mention the very important CIA dealings with other intelligence communities,
                    either overt or covert--would it be useful to delay publication until liaison
                    relationships could be included? Mr. McDonald responded that the area of liaison
                    arrangements was extremely sensitive. The British do not admit the existence of
                    intelligence organizations for 30 years, even if commonly known. For the United
                    States to acknowledge the existence of these organizations could endanger
                    current liaison arrangements. Therefore release of this information was
                    unlikely. The CRD chief confirmed that the United States cannot unilaterally
                    declassify that material, noting that most countries do not require their
                    intelligence services to release information.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Distribution of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Volumes</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked Paul Washington, Director of Publishing Services, to comment on
                    production and distribution of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Mr. Washington noted
                    that the primary issues considered by the committee last year in his area
                    included technical editing resources and costs and the possibility of
                    privatizing the publication of the series. Mr. Washington indicated that the
                    focus of concern had changed somewhat over the course of the past year, and that
                    he had both good and bad news to convey to the committee. The good news was that
                    the Department now had the editorial resources to handle anything. Moreover,
                    Amtech Information Services has received a multiyear contract to publish the
                    volumes, eliminating the need to take bids for every volume. The new printing
                    arrangements seemed to be working well. There was more good news in the cost
                    figures for the most recent volumes published. Costs have dropped under new
                    printing procedures from a high of $175,000 per volume to controlled costs of
                    $35,000 - $45,000 per volume. Improved marketing developments were on the way;
                    the Superintendent of Documents was happy to consider increased sales of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. In the area of distribution,
                    USIA has agreed to update stocks of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes at posts
                    abroad to enhance visibility and sales. On the down side, because
                    declassification had slowed down recently, there is not much technical editing
                    or Amtech printing work to do; the editing staff has been diverted to other
                    areas.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked what the variation in sales between a popular and unpopular
                    volume were. Mr. Washington noted that a popular volume, 1952-1954, XIV, has
                    sold 173 copies this year. In response to Prof. Cook’s query about the
                    possibility of reprinting out of print volumes, Mr. Washington explained that
                    the plates for printing the volumes are destroyed because of storage problems.
                    Mr. Slany commented that the Committee had to remember that “popular” and
                    “unpopular” were relative terms--even popular <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes had a small market.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson remarked that sometimes by the time many scholars learn the volumes
                    are out, they are out of print. Mr. Washington responded that GPO produces a
                    monthly catalogue of available items available to all who request being placed
                    on their mailing list. Ms. Becker noted that press releases on each volume are
                    sent to journals and individual historians, and that each of these press
                    releases has an order blank with price information on the back. Ms. Herring
                    urged the committee members to encourage their colleagues to reply to the
                    Department’s annual questionnaire asking if they wish to remain on the mailing
                    list. Regulations require that the list be purged and updated annually, and
                    individuals not responding to the questionnaire are automatically taken off the
                    mailing list.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany noted that the Department intends to produce a catalogue of Department
                    publications. Mr. Washington stated that GPO, because of the unpredictability of
                    publication schedules, has been so far reluctant to offer standing subscription
                    orders for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Prof. Larson suggested advertising in a professional journal. Prof. Kuehl
                    strongly urged that the Department advertise the volumes, particularly in <hi
                        rend="italic">Diplomatic History</hi>.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins asked what the average size of a press run was. Mr. Washington
                    replied between 1,500 to 3,000 copies. Of these, GPO tries to sell between 800
                    and 1000. A large number of unsold volumes, he observed, are taking up space on
                    GPO shelves. These volumes are expensive to warehouse, and GPO doesn’t want them
                    around too long.</p>
                <p>Prof. Kuehl asked for cost projections over the next few years in order to assess
                    the question of the necessity of smaller volumes. Washington projected fairly
                    stable costs of $35,000 - $45,000 per volume, with a possible variation of 6% up
                    and as much as 10-12% down. Included in that figure are printing and binding
                    costs of about $20,000. per volume and editing costs of about $24,000. per
                    volume.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hargrove recalled last year’s discussion of privatizing publication of the
                    series. He applauded the printing contract which had been let, and asked if any
                    consideration had been given to letting a similar contract to a private firm to
                    promote marketing of the series on a commission basis. Washington indicated that
                    he was receptive to the idea, but he noted that the GPO had its own marketing
                    staff which would feel threatened by any such suggestion.</p>
                <p>At this point, Mr. Perkins noted it was time to break for lunch. The session then
                    recessed at 12 noon.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Afternoon Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p>The meeting resumed shortly after 2 P.M. Mr. Slany asked Mrs. Becker to explain
                    to the committee the status of the microfiche supplement program.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Microfiche Supplements</p>
                <p>Mrs. Becker began by tracing for the new members on the committee the Office’s
                    previous experience in publishing in microfiche--the supplement to the 1981 <hi
                        rend="italic">Current Documents</hi> volume. With the help of a consultant,
                    first we developed an excellent set of specifications for archival microfiche.
                    Our first publication consisting of 150 microfiches was accompanied by a
                    pamphlet and packaged in a Tyvec floppy bag for mailing. In early 1985, Mrs.
                    Becker and Mr. Glennon went to the Library of Congress to see what had happened
                    to the publication in their Government Documents Collection. They discovered
                    that the fiche had been put in a microfiche drawer in order by Superintendent of
                    Documents (SUDOCS) Number on one side of a large room. The pamphlet, on the
                    other hand, had been shelved with the book collection (right next to the printed
                    volume for 1981) on the other side of the room. Result: the wrong two parts were
                    together. This situation undoubtedly was replicated in most of the government
                    collections across the country, because libraries have to protect microfiche
                    from light and dust, but put all printed material on open shelves. In other
                    libraries, moreover, the fiche and the print volumes might be in separate rooms
                    or on separate floors in libraries, rather than on opposite sides of one
                    room.</p>
                <p>After exploring many different options for ensuring that publications that are
                    split in libraries are properly crossreferenced both on the shelf and in
                    catalogs, the Office and the GPO jointly came up with the idea of a box that
                    solved many problems: 1) it looked like a volume in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> series and could be shelved like one in the proper sequence; 2)
                    it would afford light and dust protection for the fiche; 3) it would keep the
                    fiche and the pamphlet together in a vinyl folder inside the box; 4) it was
                    enthusiastically endorsed by the Government Depository Librarians Council in the
                    fall of 1985 as a way to allow libraries to keep the series together in a
                    responsible manner. A prototype of the box was produced by GPO, which Mrs.
                    Becker showed to the committee and then passed around for closer inspection.</p>
                <p>A long contract-writing period began in the fall of 1985, just before the 1985
                    Advisory Committee meeting (at which meeting we reported that our hopes were
                    high for a solution to the shelving dilemma.) The contract had to cover four
                    different products: a box that resembled a book; a vinyl folder to hold the
                    fiche and the pamphlet; the pamphlet; and the fiche. The contract was put out
                    for bids in August; there were no bidders. The contract was put out again in
                    September; there was one bidder. At a meeting at GPO earlier in November, the
                    State Department rejected the bid on the grounds of cost. The State Department’s
                    costs would be over $20,000. (the price of a print volume), and the sales price
                    would have to be $50. to $60. to permit GPO Marketing to cover their costs. The
                    GPO suggested that the contract be amended to allow a longer time schedule for
                    production, which they predicted would lower the costs somewhat.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany asked the committee for their advice - should we continue to pursue the
                    box idea despite the high cost? Should we redesign the box so that it would be
                    much larger and much cheaper, to hold all the supplements together, rather than
                    in individual boxes? Should we abandon the box idea altogether and concentrate
                    on getting our microfiche publications out to the scholars as soon as possible
                    (since two fiche publications are completed now and ready to be contracted
                    out--the Wang-Johnson talks to supplement the 1955-57 China volume published
                    last summer, and the <hi rend="italic">Current Economic Developments</hi>
                    series)?</p>
                <p>Prof. Cook strongly supported continuing to try to produce a box. Prof. Oksenberg
                    was anxious to see documentation on the Wang-Johnson talks. Prof. Hunt favored
                    producing a large box to house all microfiche supplements to the series. If the
                    box had to be abandoned because of cost, Prof. Kuehl favored giving each fiche
                    supplement a volume number, so that librarians and users would be forced to
                    account for missing numbers, and thus would go to the catalog which would give
                    the correct classification number and location for the missing “volume.”</p>
                <p>The committee promised to recommend action in its report.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins adjourned the meeting at about 3 P.M. The committee then met in
                    private session to consider its recommendations and report.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
