<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, December
                    1988</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, December 1988</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-02-24">February 24, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1988-12-08">December 8, 1988</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1988-12-08-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 450 KB, 25pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 5, 1988-Minutes of the Advisory Comm. Drafted
                    on December 20 and revised on December 30, 1988. Cleared by Acting Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Public Affairs George High and Director for Systematic
                    Review (A/CDC) Richard Morefield.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn59">Footnote 59</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the December 1988 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical
                    Diplomatic Documentation</head>
                <dateline>December 8-9, 1988</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Robert Dallek, Department of History, University of California at Los
                        Angeles</item>
                    <item>Dr. Blanche Wiesen Cook, Professor of History, John Jay College, CUNY, New
                        York City</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Political Science Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Michel Oksenberg, Center for Chinese Studies, University of
                        Michigan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bradford Perkins, Department of History, University of Michigan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Warren I. Cohen, Department of History, Michigan State
                        University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Michael H. Hunt, Department of History, University of North
                        Carolina</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Thursday Morning Session (Open)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Warren I. Cohen (Chairman)</item>
                    <item>Professor Blanche Wiesen Cook</item>
                    <item>Professor Robert Dallek</item>
                    <item>Professor Michael H. Hunt</item>
                    <item>Professor Bradford Perkins</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George B. High, Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Chief, Foreign Relations Division</item>
                    <item>Rita M. Baker</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Evan M. Duncan</item>
                    <item>Vicki E. Futscher</item>
                    <item>Nancy L. Golden</item>
                    <item>David H. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Nina D. Howland</item>
                    <item>Sherri Jennings</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Nina J. Noring</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>William F. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Sherrill B. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>H. Eugene Bovis, Acting Director</item>
                    <item>Mr. Richard Morefield, Chief, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of the Assistant Secretary of State for Management Policy
                    (M/MP):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Susan T. Tait</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George C. Chalou, External Affairs Staff, National Archives and Records
                        Administration (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Milton O. Gustafson, Chief Civil Reference Branch, NARA</item>
                    <item>Mr. David A. Langbart, Records Appraisal Division, NARA</item>
                    <item>Page Putnam Miller, Executive Director, National Coordinating Committee
                        for the Promotion of History</item>
                    <item>Jeanne Schauble, Records Declassification Division, NARA</item>
                </list>
                <p>The public session of the meeting was opened at 9:22 a.m. by William Z. Slany,
                    The Historian of the Department. He turned over the direction of the meeting to
                    the new chairman, Professor Cohen, who accepted the position and invited Acting
                    Assistant Secretary of State George High to address the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Remarks by Acting Assistant Secretary High</p>
                <p>Mr. High welcomed the Committee on behalf of Assistant Secretary Charles Redman,
                    who was traveling with the Secretary of State in Brussels. Mr. High noted that
                    the Committee met at a time of transition for the Department and the Bureau, but
                    he assured Committee members that the work of the Historian’s Office would not
                    be affected by the change in leadership. PA/HO’s program will, however, continue
                    to be impacted by budget constraints and the large amounts of documentation to
                    be examined for inclusion in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. He acknowledged past chairman Professor Perkins’ leadership,
                    perseverance, and dedication, and he welcomed Professor Cohen as chairman of the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>Turning to a review of developments of the last year, Mr. High noted that the
                    series was short of the accelerated schedule because of delays in
                    declassification at the National Security Council. The schedule was to bring
                    publication of the series to a 30-year line by 1990. He anticipated that the
                    series would not complete the Eisenhower administration until 1992. The good
                    news, he noted; was that PA/HO had virtually completed the compilation of the
                    documents for the Eisenhower era, A/CDC has completed declassification for all
                    volumes for 1989 and several for 1990, and volumes were now being returned from
                    the NSC at a rate of about one a month. Most importantly, the commitment of
                    PA/HO and A/CDC to support accelerated publication of the series has not
                    faltered. The news on the budget front was still generally bad, but there was a
                    widespread feeling in the Department that the cuts in the foreign relations
                    budget had bottomed out. The PA budget has supported the accelerated PA/HO
                    publication program throughout the budgetary problems, and would continue to do
                    so. Mr. High added that the microfiche publication program initiated by PA/HO
                    should offset the slimmer print volumes in the Foreign Relations series.</p>
                <p>Mr. High informed the Committee that its charter had been renewed by the
                    Department for 2 years, without substantive change. The Department was examining
                    the possibility of broadening the Committee to include representatives from the
                    American Economics Association, the Society of American Archivists, and the
                    International Studies Association.</p>
                <p>Mr. High reported that the Department had considered the Committee’s Annual
                    Report. During the first 6 or 7 months of this year there had been an ongoing
                    dialog between the Committee Chairman and Assistant Secretary Redman which
                    focused on two issues of pressing importance to the Committee: access to
                    classified materials which have been denied publication and access to the
                    guidelines prepared by A/CDC for the National Archives declassification review
                    of Department of State files. Mr. High told the Committee that the Department
                    had considered the Committee’s views and concerns on these issues carefully and
                    had reached decisions: The Department will continue the briefings of the
                    Committee by A/CDC reviewers on specific <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes. The Department will solicit advice from the
                    Committee on which volumes to review, but cannot guarantee that the Committee’s
                    requests will be honored in every instance. The Department has also decided that
                    it cannot make available to the Committee the A/CDC guidelines. These guidelines
                    are viewed in the Department as an internal management tool; they outline
                    specific topics which must be reviewed by the Department prior to any
                    declassification or release action. They are the responsibility of A/CDC and are
                    outside the purview of the Advisory Committee and the process of publishing the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Access to classified
                    information within the government is based on the principle of “need to know”,
                    and the Committee, whose advisory role is focused on the content and direction
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and the work of the
                    Historian’s Office, is not deemed to have a need to know that would authorize
                    access to the guidelines prepared by A/CDC.</p>
                <p>Mr. High observed that in June Assistant Secretary Redman had shown Professors
                    Perkins and Cohen the general guidelines to the National Archives and a
                    country-specific guideline so they could see what they looked like and report
                    back to the Committee. This was a one-time effort to demonstrate what the
                    guidelines were about and to show that they did not affect the selection of
                    material for the series.</p>
                <p>Mr. High went on to say that the Department had looked at this issue closely over
                    a substantial period of time. The decisions set out in the Redman meeting in
                    June represented a considered decision by Department leadership. The Department
                    considers the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series a thoroughly
                    professional work and that declassification decisions are made in a fully
                    professional manner. The PA Bureau and the Historian’s Office stand behind the
                    volumes and the declassification work. Mr. High noted that he was not aware of
                    any concern within the Historian’s Office about what is being withheld from
                    publication. The Advisory Committee, then, has several insights into the
                    declassification process: one is the professionalism of the Department’s staffs,
                    another is the annual briefing given to the Committee by A/CDC on
                    declassification. We hope that individually and cumulatively these briefings
                    will be a very substantial answer to the concerns the Committee has
                    expressed.</p>
                <p>Mr. High concluded with the basic message from the Department to the Committee:
                    We have heard your concerns, we have attempted to address them, we have gone as
                    far as we can. It is now time to move on to the rest of a pressing agenda
                    relating to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He added that
                    the Department needed the Committee’s advice on a variety of issues. Among these
                    issues were the question of the utility of microfiche publications, the future
                    and structure of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, the
                    efficacy of pre-publication professional review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes, and the question of access to unprocessed materials
                    at Presidential libraries.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt initiated the Committee’s response by asking for a copy of the
                    Committee’s current charter, and he asked for some clarification, which was
                    provided, of the June meeting with Mr. Redman. Professor Perkins observed that
                    the professional organizations represented by the Committee would not accept
                    that its advisory charter was limited to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Professor Cook added that she understood from past
                    Committee chairman Betty Unterberger that the existing charter had established
                    an advisory role for the Committee that extended to State Department records
                    retired to the National Archives as well as an oversight responsibility for the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Mr. High responded that the
                    Department viewed Committee members as advisers to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and the Office of the Historian, not to the
                    declassification staff and the declassification program.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen cited the two areas of non-agreement between the Committee and
                    the Department: the restriction of the purview of the Committee to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and access to the guidelines for
                    NARA declassification review. While not abandoning these issues, he noted that
                    the Committee was prepared to set them aside to concentrate on the pressing
                    issues confronting the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series as it
                    moves into the 1960’s. He noted in passing that the Committee had asked that a
                    volume dealing with relations with the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe be
                    included in the declassification briefing, and the volume was not included in
                    the briefing list. He concluded, however, that he and the Committee felt a new
                    spirit of cooperation on all issues, and they were generally encouraged.</p>
                <p>Professor Cook stated that the Committee was interested in problems relating to
                    the preservation and disposition of State Department documentation at the
                    Archives, not just declassification. Dr. Slany assured her that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> process was archival in its
                    implications, and PA/HO had an equal interest in the integrity of the files.
                    Professor Hunt pointed to Mr. High’s statement regarding the professional
                    standards maintained by the series, and noted that it was the Committee’s
                    purpose to support and attest to those standards. Professor Cohen noted that in
                    the past the Committee had not received sufficient information to provide advice
                    to the scholarly community on the integrity of the series. The A/CDC briefings
                    will provide information about an area which in the past has concerned the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany stated that the issue of records policy is so important that PA/HO may
                    need to focus resources on records issues and work still more closely with
                    A/CDC, A/FAIM, NARA, and others to achieve more comprehensive planning,
                    especially for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Someone in
                    the Office of the Historian might be assigned responsibility to coordinate such
                    planning with regard to the documentation involved and the structure of the
                    volumes. Professor Perkins asked about the kind of planning which underlies the
                    volumes now. Dr. Slany stated that there is no formal structure; planning is
                    guided by past experience and the availability of documents in the Department.
                    Professor Cohen noted that an annual meeting did not allow the Committee to have
                    the impact it wants especially in the planning process; a continuing dialog was
                    needed.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report by The Historian</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany referred to his written report on the future of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series circulated to the Committee in advance of the
                    meeting. He foresaw the expanded scope and altered contents of the future
                    volumes that will be used by all levels of readers. It would not be possible to
                    include complete documentation on important diplomatic developments, but it
                    would be possible to present information on how and where such developments
                    could be researched. A volume could include some documents, some explanatory
                    material, and some apparatus to point toward further research. In essence, the
                    object was to provide a true documentary history. Biographical information and
                    an explanation of the structure of the Department at the time could be included.
                    Dr. Slany stated “we need a great deal of interaction with the scholarly
                    community and the teaching fraternity” to help decide the future structure of
                    the volumes. He added that the options remain open; we may have some combination
                    of printed volumes supplemented with microfiche. Dr. Slany noted,
                    parenthetically, that the sales of PA/HO’s microfiche publications have been
                    unexpectedly good. Professor Hunt asked about attempting to survey microfiche
                    users, and the Committee concluded that it would be difficult to do.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins commented on the Historian’s written report. He was encouraged
                    by the beginning of work on an oral history program and the collection of
                    historical data on U.S. consuls. He had two requests: (1) a chart showing where
                    each volume is in the clearance/publication process such as the Committee was
                    given previously, and (2) a statement of the percentage of material deleted in
                    the various volumes. He wondered how confident we were that we could reach the
                    30-year line by 1992; he recognized that we had been held up by NSC delays in
                    declassification. Dr. Slany said the NSC was currently returning one volume a
                    month. He thought there was a reasonable prospect that we could hold to the
                    schedule.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins asked if faster NSC declassification meant that less material
                    was declassified. Dr. Glennon said the problem with the NSC had not been one of
                    withholding material but of delay. Dr. Slany added that in some cases the NSC
                    declassified more than other agencies.</p>
                <p>Professor Cook asked whether PA/HO had a problem of access at the Eisenhower
                    Library. Dr. Slany said no, except for a few things which were not available or
                    not processed at the time when we did our research.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen asked where the resources were coming from for new projects such
                    as oral history and the project on consuls, when resources for <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> were declining. Dr. Slany assured him that these
                    projects would not be done at the expense of the series; they would attract
                    money and interest on their own merits.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins asked who would do the interviews for oral history. Dr. Slany
                    indicated that the interviewers would be Foreign Service officers who could
                    establish rapport and gain the confidence of the interviewees. Professor Dallek
                    pointed out the great range of quality in oral history interviews; it was
                    crucial to combine the documentary record with the interview in order to provide
                    a context. Dr. Slany stated that PA/HO would provide background material and
                    training for the interviewers and noted how important it was that the
                    interviewee have confidence in the interviewer. Professor Hunt asked what would
                    be done with the record of the interview. Dr. Slany replied that the interview
                    record would be a classified document under the control of the relevant bureau
                    where the information could be used. Professor Hunt questioned whether under
                    these circumstances an interview would be likely to elicit comments that were
                    not already part of the official record. Professor Dallek asked what kind of
                    restrictions would be placed on access to the interview records. Dr. Herschler
                    replied that they would be official records, subject to the FOIA. Dr. Slany
                    added that the records of interviews would become part of the Department’s
                    historical records and eventually be included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    Series</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen stated that the Committee would now turn to the question of the
                    future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Professor Hunt
                    noted that he had just read the 1961 Vietnam volume, which was excellent. He
                    assumed it would be a model for the future of the series. The White House
                    documents in the volume underlined the importance of that material and the fact
                    that the White House had become the focus of policymaking. Professor Perkins
                    asked if that was a universal truth; Dr. Slany replied that it depended on the
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek pointed out the danger of becoming focused entirely on White
                    House documents. He suggested breaking away from the geographic organization of
                    the series and organizing it around important issues or episodes in Presidential
                    administrations and including in it State Department, White House, and
                    other-agency documentation. Planning the volumes would be very important, and
                    the Committee’s advice and that of area specialists would be valuable.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek also cautioned regarding the use of historical narratives, which
                    were bound to be colored by the author’s viewpoint. PA/HO should be the
                    presenter of the record rather than the interpreter of it. Inclusion of
                    guidances or “signposts” to groups of records would be valuable, however.
                    Professor Perkins agreed that the inclusion of narratives would be a very
                    “dubious experiment.” Interpretation should be avoided, and a cursory narrative
                    would not be useful. A statement of the major issues with respect to a
                    particular country in a given time period with a guide to the files would be
                    acceptable. Dr. Slany pointed out that we already did some of that in the
                    editorial notes in already-published volumes and in summary accounts of the
                    contents of volumes prepared at the time they are released.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt pointed out that the 1961 Vietnam volume included some synopses of
                    this nature. Professor Cohen asked if that volume represented what Dr. Slany had
                    in mind. Dr. Slany replied that the Vietnam volume had a broader range of
                    documents than previous volumes. Professor Hunt acknowledged that Vietnam was a
                    special case but thought the series should continue its fundamental geographic
                    organization. He suggested, as an example, a Latin America volume focusing on
                    the Alliance for Progress with bibliographic guidance on bilateral relations
                    with countries of the area. Professor Dallek observed that documentation was
                    often geared to crises, which have ramifications in other areas. The volumes
                    would therefore need guides to other sources of material. Professor Hunt pointed
                    out that the national security volume provided some overview. Professor Perkins
                    observed that some of these questions could not be answered in principle but
                    only in detail.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by Professor Cohen, Drs. Slany and Glennon stated that
                    including brief synopses with bibliographic guidance would not inherently
                    increase clearance problems. Professor Dallek concluded that a consensus
                    regarding the topics to be included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes was necessary prior to compilation.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt raised the question of the audience of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. Professor Cohen pointed out that the volumes
                    were an important research tool for students and that, for that purpose,
                    documents were more important than bibliographical guidance to files in the
                    Archives. Professor Perkins asked how PA/HO viewed its audience. Dr. Slany
                    listed Department officials, scholars, students, and readers in countries
                    outside the United States that have no foreign affairs documentary publications.
                    Professor Cohen noted that the volumes were very important in countries such as
                    China. Professor Cook pointed out that journalists constituted another
                    audience.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek suggested publishing the bibliographical material in microfiche.
                    Dr. Slany replied that such material would not constitute more than 10 percent
                    of a volume; microfiche would be reserved for additional documentation. Dr.
                    Smith interjected that an integrated print and microfiche publication opened up
                    opportunities for compilers to include more documents. Professor Dallek
                    supported this, suggesting placing documentation on minor countries in the
                    fiche. Dr. Glennon said we were already doing this.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins stressed the importance of printing substantial collections of
                    documents on major subjects, even though this raised difficult choices in
                    selecting the topics. He preferred printing “thick documentation” on subjects
                    such as the Cuban missile crisis and consigning some subjects to the fiche
                    rather than printing shallow documentation on everything.</p>
                <p>There was further discussion of the question of the organization of the volumes
                    and of the projected list of volumes for 1961-1963. Dr. Mabon pointed out that
                    some volumes were structured around issues more than would appear from the brief
                    list of volume titles. The Southeast Asia volume, for example, would focus
                    largely on the Laos crisis, but the organizational details could only be worked
                    out in the course of research on the volume.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt stated that the key questions were: what did the President decide,
                    on the basis of what information did he make the decision, and what impact did
                    those decisions have. He thought the volumes should not merely document the
                    Presidential decisions but include the input preceding the decisions and the
                    effects they had. He thought that rather than publishing bibliographical
                    information in microfiche, it would be better to include more documents in
                    microfiche.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek inquired about records of the FBI and the Department of Justice;
                    would bibliographical material regarding these, for example, be included? George
                    Chalou of NARA pointed out that NARA had a 2-volume guide to FBI records and
                    that some of those records were being transferred to the Archives. The
                    suggestion was made for a separate volume with bibliographical material, but Dr.
                    Glennon thought such a volume could be held up in clearance because of a handful
                    of sensitive files. Both Professors Hunt and Cohen preferred to integrate the
                    bibliographic information into the documents in the volume.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 11:45 a.m. for lunch.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Thursday Luncheon Meeting</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p>Committee members:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Cohen, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Professor Cook</item>
                    <item>Professor Dallek</item>
                    <item>Professor Hunt</item>
                    <item>Professor Perkins</item>
                </list>
                <p>Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                </list>
                <p>National Archives and Records Administration:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Langbart</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Advisory Committee held a working luncheon meeting at the Garden Restaurant,
                    12:15 - 1:30 p.m.</p>
                <p>At this meeting, Mr. Langbart, an officer of the Records Appraisal and
                    Disposition Division of the National Archives and Records Administration,
                    briefed the Committee on the status of efforts to identify, appraise, and
                    preserve the decentralized records of the Department of State.</p>
                <p>Mr. Langbart outlined his responsibilities as a records appraiser and the
                    regulations governing the authorities and duties of the National Archives and
                    the Department in the disposition of Department records. He also briefly
                    described the organizational units within NARA concerned with Department
                    records, including the Washington National Records Center and the archival
                    custodial unit holding accessioned Department records. He then delineated the
                    emergence of Department lot files (that is, special, decentralized retired
                    office or bureau records) and their relationship to the Central Foreign Policy
                    File in the period since World War II. He described the efforts made, often
                    unsuccessful, to manage the lot file system in the Department and the pressure
                    which the vast increase in paper documentation placed on recordkeepers in the
                    Department. This pressure required some restraints on the growth of lot files
                    and led to their screening (and sometimes destruction), at times at the
                    unfortunate expense of unique and important sources.</p>
                <p>Mr. Langbart pointed out that through the cooperative efforts of the Historian’s
                    Office, NARA, and the Department records managers (A/FAIM), certain categories
                    of lot files that may be archival and may constitute unique, substantive,
                    self-contained collections of documents relating to significant offices,
                    functions, people, and events will be exempt from the screening process and
                    preserved intact until they can be properly reviewed by Department historians
                    and appraised by NARA. Such categories of records include the non-housekeeping
                    files of the Department’s principals controlled by the Executive Secretariat;
                    records of the Policy Planning Staff; records of bureau and office chiefs;
                    records of inter- and intra-departmental committees, working groups, and task
                    forces; records of individuals and offices concerning specific, substantive,
                    unique functions, events, or issues; crisis files; non-housekeeping records of
                    the Bureau of Intelligence and Research; and other specialized collections.</p>
                <p>The presentation emphasized the need for continued cooperation between the
                    National Archives and the Department to ensure the proper identification,
                    preservation, and accessioning of the Department’s diverse files if researchers
                    in the future will have access to a comprehensive and accurate historical
                    record.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Thursday Afternoon Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Cohen (Chairman)</item>
                    <item>Professor Cook</item>
                    <item>Professor Dallek</item>
                    <item>Professor Hunt</item>
                    <item>Professor Perkins</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present:</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA)</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. High, Acting Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon, Chief, Foreign Relations Division Chief</item>
                    <item>Ms. Baker</item>
                    <item>Ms. Futscher</item>
                    <item>Ms. Golden</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Dr. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Dr. Noring</item>
                    <item>Dr. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sanford</item>
                    <item>Dr. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Dr. Smith</item>
                    <item>Dr. Wells</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bovis, Acting Director</item>
                    <item>Mr. Morefield, Chief, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                    <item>Mr. Charles Flowerree</item>
                    <item>Mr. Sidney Sober</item>
                    <item>Mr. Theodore Tremblay</item>
                </list>
                <p>Office of the Assistant Secretary of State for Management Policy (M/MP):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ms. Tait</item>
                </list>
                <p>Professor Cohen convened the meeting at 2 p.m. and called on Mr. Morefield to
                    conduct the A/CDC briefing of the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Mr. Morefield’s Comments</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield began by saying that A/CDC was in the process of reorganization.
                    A/CDC’s role began after the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    were compiled by PA/HO historians. A/CDC served as the representative of
                    Department bureaus to obtain clearance of State Department documents and also
                    obtained clearances from other agencies.</p>
                <p>He distributed a List of Executive Orders involved in classification and a
                    Checklist of Exemption Citations.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield mentioned three constant guidelines A/CDC uses:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1) In an open society decisions on access were based on the right to know
                        and the need to know;</item>
                    <item>2) The decision to withhold information included periodic review of those
                        decisions;</item>
                    <item>3) Within the concept of “need to know”, A/CDC must find the person with
                        the authority to declassify the information.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Professor Perkins asked how “need to know” was defined. Mr. Morefield responded
                    that the person who classifies decided who has the “authority” to make the
                    decision; these presumptions can be overcome when circumstances changed. The
                    basic question was, is there now a need to protect? Mr. Morefield asked, based
                    on the list of cleared volumes, which volumes the Committee would like reviewed
                    next year.</p>
                <p>[The classified briefing by A/CDC reviewers followed.]</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen thanked the A/CDC members for their briefing. He remarked that it
                    had been a good discussion which gave the Committee additional insights into
                    A/CDC’s role in the preparation of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Access to Documents in Presidential Libraries</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany opened the discussion, stating that the present slow rate at which the
                    John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson Libraries were processing documents for
                    their respective administrations threatened to delay the accelerated compilation
                    of the post-1960 period. He added that an $18,000 Department subvention in FY
                    1988 to facilitate processing at the Kennedy Library had not yielded results
                    commensurate with the outlay. He said Dr. Stanley Katz, President of the
                    American Council of Learned Societies, had suggested that the Department and the
                    National Archives jointly establish a “Friends of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>” committee to solicit funds from major foundations to enable
                    Presidential libraries to accelerate the opening up of their records to
                    research. Dr. Herschler stated that the job would cost approximately $600,000
                    over 4 or 5 years. Dr. Slany added that, without an improvement, <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compiling could not achieve the 30-year
                    line called for by President Reagan.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Professor Cook about the possibility of sending a
                    State Department historian to research unprocessed materials, Dr. Slany advised
                    her that official historians did not have access to unprocessed material and
                    that the libraries would each need one or two people to work full time to solve
                    the problem. He added that the Archivist of the United States, Don W. Wilson,
                    was aware of the problem and was exploring various solutions. The key to the
                    issue was for the Archivist to find a way to reapportion scarce NARA resources
                    and meet the special needs of the Presidential libraries. Dr. Herschler pointed
                    out that a new archivist at a Presidential library would require a year or more
                    to be fully cleared and trained. Dr. Slany stated that he wished to enlist the
                    Advisory Committee’s advice and support both in its capacity as a committee and
                    through the associations that it represents.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek suggested that members of the Committee talk to people connected
                    with the libraries who he believed would be sympathetic to accelerating records
                    processing. He specifically mentioned Nancy Smith, David Humphrey, and LBJ
                    Library Director Harry Middleton. He added that the pre-Presidential LBJ records
                    were now almost completely available to the public. He asked about the
                    possibility of foundation funds earmarked for the development of oral history
                    being shifted to records processing and declassification. Dr. Slany responded
                    that the Presidential libraries would have to be persuaded that document
                    processing was a higher priority. Professor Hunt suggested that Professor Cohen
                    should express his concern to the libraries on behalf of the Committee.
                    Professor Cook added that the Eisenhower Library was initially slow in
                    processing its records until outside pressure had been brought to bear.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt asked whether the National Archives would suffer if <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> were not published; whether, for
                    example, the possibility of not receiving State Department records as a result
                    of a slowdown would offer an incentive for the Archivist to speed the processing
                    of Presidential library documents. Professor Perkins asked whether people could
                    be moved from the older Presidential libraries where the processing had
                    presumably been done to the more recent ones. Professor Cook expressed doubt
                    that there were people to spare. She noted that the Eleanor Roosevelt papers had
                    still not been processed at the FDR Library.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen then asked for the names of people to contact. Dr. Slany
                    responded that Don Wilson and John Fawcett, Assistant Archivist for Presidential
                    Libraries, were the most important since they determined the apportionment of
                    resources to the Presidential library system. Professor Dallek suggested that
                    prominent scholars of the Kennedy period such as Arthur Schlesinger and Theodore
                    Sorenson, and Senator Ted Kennedy be asked to support the need for accelerated
                    access to materials at the JFK Library.</p>
                <p>Dr. Smith pointed out that part of the problem was the libraries’ difficulty in
                    hiring cleared individuals to process classified materials. He recalled the
                    difficulty experienced at the JFK Library to find someone who was cleared to
                    work on materials requested by PA/HO researchers. Professor Cohen then asked, if
                    this were the case, whether the Advisory Committee could do anything. Dr. Slany
                    emphasized his hope that the Advisory Committee would explain and support the
                    requirements of the Historian’s Office. Perhaps the Department might have to
                    strike a deal whereby PA/HO historians would somehow assist in processing the
                    material in return for access. Dr. Smith stated that access by Department
                    historians to unprocessed materials could significantly assist Library personnel
                    to process documents of special historical interest. He noted that in his last
                    research trip to the JFK Library, he and the archivist had worked together to
                    bring about the processing of a particularly important collection. Dr. Slany
                    stated that it would nevertheless be more effective to provide the Library with
                    the resources it needed to do the job. In response to a suggestion by Professor
                    Cook that a Department historian be assigned to do the processing, Dr. Slany
                    said that such an arrangement might arouse the concerns of other agencies who
                    would discern favoritism and inequity.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins said that the key to progress on the processing issue was to
                    get foundation funding for it. Dr. Slany said that PA/HO and the National
                    Archives were formulating a joint proposal. The Department could not legally
                    accept foundation or private funding, but the National Archives could through
                    its Trust Fund. In any case, any private funding would not be for compiling but
                    for processing files at the Presidential libraries. Professor Cohen concluded by
                    saying that the Advisory Committee would send a letter to Dr. Wilson and asked
                    The Historian to provide necessary information.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report on the U.S. Consular Project</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany explained the U.S. consular project, based on the unique historical
                    consular card file housed in the Historian’s Office, and stated that his
                    ultimate goal was to stimulate and facilitate some serious history of the U.S.
                    consular service and American foreign policy. He said he hoped to find a method
                    to collate the information contained in the card file about where the consular
                    officers served with information about their publications and papers. He wished
                    to explore with the Committee his idea for a conference on consular history.
                    This conference of diplomatic historians and others interested in consular
                    history would be convened to advise him on what should be done with the data on
                    consular officials already obtained by PA/HO and on how best to make it
                    available to researchers.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt asked what was the rationale for spending more money on the
                    consular project and what the cost would be. Dr. Slany replied that the
                    information about consular officials and their posts had been inaccessible in
                    the past since it remained in PA/HO in the form of several thousand 8" x 12"
                    cards. It should, therefore, be made available to researchers in order that more
                    could be learned about those individuals who laid the foundation for U.S.
                    foreign policy. He said it would cost $30-40,000 to put the data already
                    obtained in a database management system. He said a small portion of the work
                    was already done and that he could bring someone in on contract to complete the
                    task.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt reported that one of his Ph.D. students had done his dissertation
                    on U.S. chiefs of diplomatic missions and principal officers at major consular
                    posts during the 1890s. This student had found there was little scholarly
                    interest in consuls per se. Professor Hunt questioned whether a further
                    expenditure of that amount was worth the effort.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany explained that he believed it very important to have insight into
                    another dimension of foreign relations and that there was a need to make the
                    information already collected available to researchers. He said the guide to
                    manuscripts was valuable. When asked about the final product, he said the data
                    about these officials would be available in a digital database.</p>
                <p>Professor Cook said this project was “really important” as it provided “another
                    world view.” While Professor Dallek remarked that some may see it as “quaint,”
                    Professor Perkins said it would be used selectively by area specialists.
                    Professor Cohen stated that it was the consensus of the Committee that this
                    consular project was important and worth considering. Regarding a conference, he
                    said it would be useful to have a broader range of opinion to consider whether
                    the arrangement of the tranche of information presented by PA/HO is useful and
                    suggested directors of graduate schools be invited to the Department for a
                    briefing.</p>
                <p>The session adjourned at 4:30 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Morning Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Cohen (Chairman)</item>
                    <item>Professor Cook</item>
                    <item>Professor Dallek</item>
                    <item>Professor Hunt</item>
                    <item>Professor Michel Oksenberg</item>
                    <item>Professor Perkins</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present:</p>
                <p>Professor J.C. Hurewitz, Columbia University</p>
                <p>Bureau of Public Affairs (PA)</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. High, Acting Assistant Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Office of the Historian (PA/HO):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon, Chief, Foreign Relations Division</item>
                    <item>Ms. Baker</item>
                    <item>Ms. Futscher</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Dr. Howland</item>
                    <item>Dr. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Dr. Noring</item>
                    <item>Dr. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Ms. Robinson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Schwar</item>
                </list>
                <p>Center for Classification/Declassification (A/CDC):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bovis, Acting Director</item>
                    <item>Mr. Morefield, Chief, Office of Systematic Review</item>
                    <item>Mr. Sober</item>
                </list>
                <p>Office of the Assistant Secretary of State for Management Policy (M/MP):</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Ms. Tait</item>
                </list>
                <p>Professor Cohen convened the session at 9:05 a.m., and introduced J.C. Hurewitz,
                    Emeritus Professor of History at Columbia University, to provide a
                    pre-publication review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1955-1957,
                    volumes XIV and XV, Arab-Israeli Dispute through July 1956. (The volumes are
                    scheduled for publication in the spring of 1989.)</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz warmly complimented the editors of the two volumes he had
                    reviewed. He emphasized the accuracy and completeness of the foreign affairs
                    record presented in the volumes and assured the Committee that the American
                    record of the Arab-Israeli dispute was fully and accurately documented. Although
                    he considered himself highly knowledgeable about the events of 1956 and 1957, he
                    had learned many new details in reviewing the volumes and he intended to include
                    some of them in his own current research.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz reminded the Committee that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes under discussion only presented the American role in
                    the Arab-Israeli dispute and the actions of Britain and France against Egypt.
                    This limitation could not be held against the Department or the editors of the
                    series. The editors had done their job well and the results were volumes of
                    solid scholarship. Professor Hurewitz emphasized, however, that serious students
                    and researchers would not be content with the official American view of these
                    events, and they would have to seek the wider historical context elsewhere. It
                    was necessary for the serious scholar to be aware of the broader range of
                    historical events as well as to consult foreign government documents, especially
                    British, but also Israeli and Egyptian sources. U.S. policy was more reactive
                    than it appeared in the two volumes. In reply to Professor Hunt’s question,
                    Professor Hurewitz said that it was not necessary to include or refer to all
                    these materials in the volumes. The job of the editors of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes was to show how the United States got
                    involved in significant events, how U.S. officials saw their responsibilities,
                    and how they carried them out. The volumes could not be faulted in this
                    respect.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz described the three main themes of volume XIV, all of which
                    were related to British initiatives: (1) Alpha, a major U.S.-U.K. peace
                    initiative to resolve the Arab-Israeli dispute; (2) the Soviet-Egyptian arms
                    deal; and (3) the decision to build the Aswan Dam.</p>
                <p> After providing some historical background on these three themes, Professor
                    Hurewitz noted most of this background could not be obtained from the two
                    volumes. Professor Hurewitz emphasized that while the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes made an important contribution, they did not provide
                    the full historical picture, and he cited some recent and forthcoming
                    publications on the Suez question.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz then took up a few specific points. He said the volumes lacked
                    three British memoranda of conversations between Francis Russell and Evelyn
                    Shuckburgh, which were important for an accurate record. These memoranda were
                    available in the Public Record Office and ought to be included, if possible, in
                    the volume. Professor Perkins observed that he thought it was placing too much
                    responsibility on the compilers to have them search foreign materials. Dr. Slany
                    said that in some vital instances, compilers should and did concern themselves
                    with foreign records.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion about the need of the Department to restrain the size
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, and the inability of
                    Department historians to provide complete details on all interesting issues.
                    Microform supplements were being looked to as a means of providing users with
                    more details than could be included in present volumes. Professor Hurewitz made
                    a personal plea that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    continue to provide full coverage of the details relating to major crises in
                    print volumes. He noted the difficulties in using microfiche.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz offered the Committee some personal views on how to enlist
                    wider support for the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Because it was in the U.S. interest to publish this
                    record, he felt that Congress should become involved. Official CIA documentation
                    also should be pursued, in order to counterbalance fragmentary, inaccurate, and
                    often self-serving memoirs.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz suggested that for accuracy the running head for one of the
                    topics be extended beyond the pages it presently covers, and that the title for
                    one of the sections be changed to describe more correctly what occurred. He also
                    noted that the volumes did not contain the first conversation of the Anderson
                    mission and that messages numbered 3-12 were omitted. Dr. Nina Noring pointed
                    out that some of the missing and unaccounted for numbered cable messages dealt
                    with administrative matters (scheduling of planes and meetings) and that the
                    volume did present the complete set of the Anderson discussions. Dr. Slany
                    assured the Committee that the volume would provide editorial explanations that
                    would allay confusion about such omitted documents.</p>
                <p>The Committee posed a number of questions relating to pre-publication review. At
                    what stage would it be useful to have this kind of review? Dr. Slany said that
                    it might be possible to insert it earlier in the process of preparing a volume,
                    but that would require obtaining security clearances. He said that if egregious
                    omissions or errors were found in a volume at pre-publication review, changes
                    could be made. Dr. Hurewitz noted that with computerized printing adjusting a
                    volume was not as difficult as it once was. Mr. Slany pointed out that PA/HO
                    operated on a slim margin, budget-wise.</p>
                <p>Professor Hurewitz also made to the Committee a recommendation that the original
                    document classifications, which had once appeared beneath the heading and were
                    now included in a footnote, be restored. Because the classification said so much
                    about a document, it should be highlighted. Professor Cook felt that prominent
                    identification of the original classification of documents was very
                    important.</p>
                <p>After additional discussion, Professor Cohen noted that there were several stages
                    at which pre-publication review might take place: a general discussion by
                    specialists in the area or topic of issues and subjects prior to undertaking
                    compilation, or the pre-publication review of the completed volume. Neither
                    review would involve classified records or require special security
                    clearances.</p>
                <p>Professor Oksenberg made some observations concerning any pre-publication review
                    process for the series. The earlier an expert entered the process, the more the
                    final product would be trusted among the academic community. There was a danger
                    that the volume as eventually published could become identified with a
                    particular academician and his or her particular conception of the subject
                    matter. This could affect the perceived objectivity of the volume. Professor
                    Dallek expressed some agreement with this formulation. Professor Cohen appeared
                    to see no serious danger in a review process involving outside experts, but
                    noted that another scholar would have given a much different interpretation of
                    the period than had Professor Hurewitz.</p>
                <p>Professor Oksenberg went on to say that Professor Hurewitz had identified an
                    inherent limitation of the series by pointing to the existence of relevant
                    foreign government documents that were not included in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He asked if Professor Hurewitz thought
                    there were any missing, easily declassifiable documents of which he had
                    knowledge, and whether he thought the omission of denied material had resulted
                    in distortion. Professor Hurewitz replied that the questions assumed he had full
                    knowledge, which he didn’t. From what he knew of the subject, he “could live
                    with these two volumes.” He expressed regret that U.S. documentation did not
                    come out on a regular basis compared to the British practice of opening records
                    at the Public Record Office after 30 years. He questioned the need for a
                    triennium and noted that declassification of the first year was held up until
                    declassification of the last year.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen commented that the key point was whether something was hidden. An
                    outsider could not add credibility to the series, but could only determine
                    whether publicly-known things were left out. Professor Cook noted that the
                    Committee had already been told that covert matters were omitted. Professor Hunt
                    asked Professor Hurewitz whether he thought, from his knowledge of public
                    disclosures of U.S. covert activities of the period, that the volumes gave an
                    adequate sense of the CIA role. Professor Hurewitz replied that they did not. He
                    acknowledged and agreed with the CIA desire to protect names and methods, but
                    thought the substance of such material should be included. He used as an example
                    of what he would find interesting a statement by Allen Dulles to the National
                    Security Council that indicated that the Soviet-Egyptian connection on armaments
                    began in March 1955. Professor Hurewitz would like to see the reporting on which
                    Dulles’ statement was based. He was not interested in the names of agents or the
                    methods, but there was information in this area he would be happy to see.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen then raised the question of whether there should be a disclaimer
                    in the volumes, so that students would not be misled that they were getting the
                    whole story. Dr. Slany thought that prefaces to volumes could include a more
                    precise statement on the series. Professor Cook suggested a printed bracketed
                    note at the location of denied documents, indicating an omission. Dr. Slany said
                    that her proposal had been suggested but had proved to be not feasible. Specific
                    disclaimers would be unacceptable to the CIA and other agencies. He noted that
                    bibliographic apparatus in the reshaped <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes of the future would make users more aware of the omissions in the
                    series.</p>
                <p>Professor Oksenberg asked whether PA/HO had ever confronted a situation where the
                    denial of material had created a serious distortion. Dr. Slany replied that this
                    had happened in the case of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952-1954,
                    volume IV, which included documentation on the overthrow of the Arbenz regime in
                    1954 in Guatemala. The Historian’s Office decided, after careful and even
                    painful evaluation of options, to publish the volume because it was more
                    important to publish -- with the incomplete Guatemala story -- rather than keep
                    the entire volume out of the public’s hands. Mr. Sober pointed out publication
                    of the 1952-1954 volume on Iran had been held up due to the current tensions in
                    U.S.-Iranian relations rather than because covert activities were
                    documented.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen explained that the Committee’s meeting with Mr. High had been
                    moved forward and would take place at 11:00 a.m. Further discussion on the
                    future of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, which had been
                    scheduled for the late morning, would take place at lunch.</p>
                <p>The session adjourned at 10:47 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Luncheon Meeting</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <p>Committee members:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Cohen, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Professor Cook</item>
                    <item>Professor Dallek</item>
                    <item>Professor Hunt</item>
                    <item>Professor Oksenberg</item>
                    <item>Professor Perkins</item>
                </list>
                <p>Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Advisory Committee convened its working luncheon meeting at noon in the
                    Department’s Buchanan Dining Room. Discussion at the luncheon centered on the
                    redefinition of the content, scope, and format of the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series for the 1961-1963 triennium.</p>
                <p>Professor Dallek restated his earlier comment that the volume of records,
                    especially the preponderance of key documents at the Presidential libraries and
                    in other collections outside the Department, made necessary the organization of
                    the series around key issues, with the most important documents published in the
                    print volume, other selected documentation published in microfiche, and gaps in
                    the historical record filled by narratives providing a comprehensive guide to
                    the full record.</p>
                <p>Professor Perkins argued that the series would be less useful to readers if the
                    texts of documents in the print volume were replaced by narrative, although he
                    recognized that some narrative or at least bibliographic description would be
                    necessary to compensate for the gaps in documentation. Dr. Slany explained that
                    the narrative summaries and guide to the full record was not meant to replace
                    the texts of documents, but were essential because the series could no longer
                    publish as large a part of the full record as in the past. Professor Cohen
                    expressed agreement with this principle, and this seemed to be the general sense
                    of the Committee. Professor Cohen asked Dr. Slany to prepare a mock-up of what a
                    new-style volume might look like so the Committee might better understand the
                    proposed changes in focus and content.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt again expressed his satisfaction with the Vietnam 1961 volume and
                    thought it might be used in some ways as a prototype for the rest of the
                    triennium, particularly because of the breadth of sources and the expanded
                    bibliographical apparatus. There was some discussion of the role of microfiche
                    for these volumes. While some Committee members seemed willing to accept the use
                    of microfiche to publish larger numbers of documents, there was no clear
                    consensus on how the fiche and print volumes should be organized. Professor Hunt
                    stated that Committee members might be able to provide some direction for the
                    1961-1963 triennium after they had an opportunity to examine a combined print
                    and microfiche volume. Dr. Glennon reported that the 1958-l960 Latin America
                    volume, which was likely to be the first to be cleared, might provide the
                    Committee useful insight.</p>
                <p>Professor Hunt asserted that the current plan for the 1961-1963 triennium
                    reflected a focus on issues, rather than the traditional geographic
                    organization, citing the Berlin Crisis and National Security volumes -- in
                    addition to the Vietnam publication -- as examples. Professor Dallek thought all
                    the volumes ought to focus on issues rather than concentrate on particular
                    issues highlighted within a “geographic” volume. He argued that, in light of the
                    heavy concentration of foreign policy documentation in the White House, the
                    series should reflect not only key international events but also the domestic
                    political factors influencing U.S. foreign policy. Professor Oksenberg cautioned
                    that a radical departure in format of the volumes might have a negative impact
                    on the series’ readership, which for decades had seen the consistent publication
                    of volumes according to geographic orientation, with the exception of “special”
                    volumes, such as the World War II conferences. He wondered if the future
                    compilations in the series could somehow focus on major issues without
                    abandoning the traditional organization of the volumes.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen thought the Committee should provide advice on the issues to be
                    presented in the print volumes. He inquired whether the list of volumes for
                    1961-1963 could be expanded to include a detailed table of contents for each
                    volume which would indicate the topics being documented. On the basis of such
                    information, the Committee could propose areas and topics of emphasis or suggest
                    additional issues. Dr. Glennon said that his staff had prepared a draft which
                    could be made available to the Committee, although it would have to be revised
                    in light of the refocus of the triennium on issues. Dr. Slany said that the
                    Office would prepare this and send it out to the Committee as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>The luncheon meeting adjourned at 1:15, and the participants returned to Room
                    5531 for a brief review of the action items PA/HO and the Committee had agreed
                    to undertake.</p>
                <p>Professor Cohen requested that PA/HO provide him with a list of names and titles
                    of individuals to be contacted by the Committee and their representative
                    organizations to expedite the processing of materials at the Presidential
                    libraries. He also restated his request for the detailed table of contents for
                    the 1961-1963 triennium that had been discussed during the luncheon.</p>
                <p>After brief discussion, the Committee indicated a desire to be briefed by A/CDC
                    at the next Committee meeting on the 1951-1954 Iran and 1955-1957 National
                    Security volumes, as well as the 1955-1957 volume containing the USSR
                    compilation. Professor Cohen thought that he and other Committee members might
                    come to Washington in the spring to continue and expand the dialog with the
                    Historian’s Office and other Department officials, and asked Dr. Slany to
                    provide travel orders and other pertinent information.</p>
                <p>As to the preparation of the Committee report, Professor Cohen said that he
                    expected to have the report written during January and delivered to the
                    Department in February. He requested Committee comments by the end of December.
                    Dr. Slany said that the Minutes of the meeting would be sent to Professor Cohen
                    as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>The meeting of the Advisory Committee was adjourned at 1:45 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
