<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Information Memorandum From C. Edward Dillery to Ronald
                    Spiers, August 1988</title>
                <title type="short">Dillery to Spiers, 1988</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-13">January 13, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1988-08-04">August 4, 1988</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1988-08-04-dillery-to-spiers.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 344 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Management, Under Secretary
                    for Management Files, 1988 (Lot File 90 D 066), Box 6, Sept. 16-20, 1988. The
                    memorandum was drafted by Susan Tait (M/MO) on August 3 and captioned “Not for
                    the System.” The referenced “Mary Ryan’s July 11, 1988 note” to Dillery and the
                    four listed attachments were present, but are not posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn49">Footnote 49</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Information Memorandum From C. Edward Dillery (Deputy Director of Management
                    Operations) to Ronald Spiers (Under Secretary of State for Management)</head>
                <dateline>August 4, 1988</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Historical Advisory Committee (HAC) Terms of Reference (TOR) and Related
                    Problems</p>
                <p>In the wake of Charles Redman’s June 14th meeting with HAC Chairman Perkins,
                    there remain several untied strings:</p>
                <p>1. An answer to your query about the HAC TOR;</p>
                <p>2. Guidelines for amending HAC’s charter prior to a mandatory charter review in
                    late summer;</p>
                <p>3. Emerging problems concerning a HAC member’s security violation, clearances for
                    other HAC members, charges of waste and mismanagement in PA/HO formally filed
                    with the IG, and a letter from the National Coordinating Committee for the
                    Promotion of History to the Chairman of the Senate’s Governmental Affairs
                    Committee complaining about the Department’s handling of classified
                    documents.</p>
                <p rend="underline">The HAC TOR</p>
                <p>The Federal Advisory Committee Act (FACA) sets the general framework for all
                    Federally chartered advisory committees. The key elements are:</p>
                <list rend="bulleted">
                    <item>Committees shall be advisory only.</item>
                    <item>All matters under consideration shall be determined by an officer of the
                        agency involved.</item>
                    <item>Advice and recommendations should not be influenced by any special
                        interest.</item>
                    <item>Membership should be balanced in terms of points of view
                        represented.</item>
                    <item>The committee should be essential to the sponsoring agency’s
                        functions.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The HAC charter states that the committee shall be advisory only. Its purpose is
                    to advise PA/HO on professional problems connected with the FRUS series “and
                    other responsibilities of the Office of the Historian.” The charter also says
                    the committee will keep interested learned societies informed of its activities.
                    Membership is based upon nominations made by the learned societies (charter is
                    at Tab 1).</p>
                <p rend="underline">Charter Issues</p>
                <p>Despite the charter’s statement that its role is advisory only, the HAC, in fact,
                    is a single interest group that has adopted a confrontational posture in its
                    relations with the Department (except for PA/HO). It does advise on
                    administrative matters -- finances, personnel procedures -- but even this does
                    not appear to meet the “professional problems” criteria. If it is, as PA/HO
                    sometimes claims, advising on substantive matters connected with the FRUS
                    series, this is not reflected in the minutes of its meetings, its annual reports
                    or even in PA/HO’s list of committee accomplishments (list is at Tab 2).
                    Instead, it has seized upon the single issue of declassification to the near
                    exclusion of all other subjects.</p>
                <p>In M/MO’s view, the committee as presently constituted strains the bounds of
                    FACA’s balanced membership injunction. All of the members and the professional
                    societies they represent share a strong interest in the earliest and broadest
                    possible access to government documents, and therefore provide no wider
                    perspectives on the validity of classification procedures or practical working
                    experience in handling national security information.</p>
                <p>The public record makes it clear that the committee is a pressure group. Its
                    members come from the “publish or perish” academic environment. Their attacks on
                    A/CDC over the past five years and their stepped up campaign for increased
                    access to classified information presents a clear conflict between their
                    advisory duties and their own professional interests, and put them in an
                    adversarial relationship with those responsible for safe-guarding national
                    security information. A recent security violation by a HAC member up for tenure
                    underscores the seriousness of this conflict.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Charter Amendment</p>
                <p>The committee’s charter faces mandatory biennial review in September. We believe
                    there are two key issues that require revision: the statements on purpose and
                    selection of members.</p>
                <p>The committee’s original purpose -- to review and advise on volumes coming up for
                    publication in the FRUS series -- has been diffused by tacking on a reference to
                    advising on “other responsibilities of the historian.” This has gotten the
                    committee into all kinds of administrative bypaths and led to a virtual
                    obsession with the issue of declassification. Deleting the “other
                    responsibilities” phrase and confining HAC’s function to reviewing FRUS volumes
                    could help get the group back to a more useful role.</p>
                <p>HAC’s charter also charges it with keeping the learned societies informed of its
                    activities. This is another area of conflict because the FACA specifies that
                    advisory committees are established to serve their sponsoring agencies. This
                    part of the charter, as well as PA’s contention that the committee’s PR function
                    is vital to the FRUS program, appears to us to distort the law’s intent. The
                    appearance of such a PR statement in HAC’s charter invites criticism and should
                    be dropped. This reference may also be a major source of the members’ apparent
                    view that HAC does not exist primarily to serve the Department, but vice
                    versa.</p>
                <p>As noted above, HAC is a single interest pressure group at least in part because
                    of the method of selecting committee members. The charter needs to be amended to
                    address effectively the issues of conflicts of interest and unbalanced
                    membership. The members should be chosen directly by senior officers in PA.
                    Nominations from learned societies could be entertained but the responsibility
                    for choosing each member would clearly rest with the Department. Some members
                    should come from non-academic backgrounds, particularly those with military,
                    diplomatic and other professional working experience, to lend balance and
                    promote challenge and debate rather than self-serving unanimity in the HAC
                    meetings.</p>
                <p>The charter amendments would be a first step in returning HAC to a useful,
                    constructive role and ending its confrontation with A/CDC.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Security Issues and Related Problems</p>
                <p>DS believes that the casual name check clearance presently used for HAC members
                    is inadequate. In fact, this procedure has been abolished and a more
                    comprehensive investigation, applicable to all consultants, advisors and
                    contractors, has been substituted in line with E.O. 12356. DS believes HAC
                    members and others similarly affected should execute the form called “Conditions
                    Governing Access to Official Records for Historical Research Purposes” and, in
                    addition, attend a security briefing and execute a non-disclosure agreement.</p>
                <p>While tightened security requirements are obviously needed, this will not get at
                    the HAC members’ (as presently chosen) basic conflict of interests. Another
                    option would give members access only to unclassified documents. Academicians
                    have no special expertise to qualify for second guessing bureau desk officers or
                    CDC professionals. This option would also help to counter the demonstrated
                    pattern of increased access leading to increased demands for still greater
                    access.</p>
                <p>The critical letter (at Tab 3) sent on May 20 by the Director of the National
                    Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of History to the Senate Governmental
                    Affairs Committee may not be an active issue. At the request of committee staff,
                    several A/CDC officers on July 12 presented an unofficial verbal rebuttal to the
                    letter. There is some reason to believe the matter will end here. As an
                    indication of how far the committee is willing to go in confronting the
                    Department, however, the letter is further evidence of the need for a change in
                    management direction.</p>
                <p>Finally, the pending bad news ticker offers so far unsurfaced charges against
                    PA/HO of waste and mismanagement brought formally before the IG (please see Tab
                    4). The case is not among those currently under review nor do we have any
                    indication of early IG attention. We will press the IG for priority
                    consideration of these charges in order to make sure this complex issue does not
                    undercut efforts to correct the HAC’s relationship with the Department.</p>
                <p>Attachments:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Tab 1: HAC Charter</item>
                    <item>Tab 2: PA/HO list of HAC accomplishments</item>
                    <item>Tab 3: Coordinating Committee Letter to Senate</item>
                    <item>Tab 4: WFM charges brought against PA/HO</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
