<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum of Conversation Between Charles Redman and HAC
                    Members, June 1988</title>
                <title type="short">Redman-HAC Meeting, 1988</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-13">January 13, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1988-06-14">June 14, 1988</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1988-06-14-redman-meeting-with-hac-members.pdf">PDF</ref>, 428 KB,
                    5pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 5, Perkins Bradford Meeting-1988. Drafted by
                    William Slany (PA/HO) and cleared by Charles Redman (PA) and George High (PA).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn45">Footnote 45</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum of Conversation Between Charles Redman and HAC Members</head>
                <dateline>June 14, 1988</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documents</p>
                <p>Participants</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Prof. Bradford Perkins, U. of Michigan</item>
                    <item>Prof. Warren Cohen, Michigan State U.</item>
                    <item>Assistant Secretary of State Charles E. Redman</item>
                    <item>Deputy Assistant Secretary of State George B. High</item>
                    <item>The Historian, William Z. Slany</item>
                </list>
                <p>After welcoming Prof. Perkins (Chairman of the Advisory
                    Committee) and Prof. Cohen, Assistant Secretary Redman explained
                    that the Department had carefully studied the issues raised by
                    Perkins in his letter of March 17 on the relationship between
                    declassification procedures and the preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p rend="underline"><hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Volumes to be Reviewed</p>
                <p>Redman first took up the issue of the role of the Advisory
                    Committee in the selection of volumes to be discussed with the
                    Committee by the A/CDC reviewers. The declassification reports
                    to the Committee at its past several meetings had been quite
                    successful, and the Department was prepared to continue with them
                    at future annual meetings. Redman told Perkins and Cohen that
                    the Department welcomed the Committee’s suggestions for the
                    volumes to be discussed upon at future meetings. He explained
                    that a number of considerations would be involved in making the
                    Department’s final selection, but the Committee’s requests would
                    be carefully weighed. He emphasized to Perkins and Cohen that
                    the briefing by the declassification reviewers was the single
                    most important opportunity for the Committee to have a clear view
                    of the rationale for the exclusion of sensitive documents and
                    information. This is the opportunity for the Committee to make
                    judgment whether the procedures for review and declassification
                    of the record printed in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes are
                    comprehensive and credible.</p>
                <p>High added that the process of reporting declassification
                    to the Committee was complicated by limitations upon the
                    availability of A/CDC reviewers as well as by the high cost in
                    scarce resources to A/CDC of preparing carefully for these
                    declassification reviews.</p>
                <p>Before responding to Mr. Redman’s first point, Perkins
                    described the intense pressure that he and other members of the
                    Committee were experiencing from their societies and the academic
                    community to find out much more about the impact of the current
                    declassification procedures upon the compiling of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi> series and the historical documentation available to
                    scholars. Cohen observed that Perkins had a reputation in the
                    academic community as a conservative when it came to challenging
                    the government’s procedures.</p>
                <p>Perkins thought that the Committee would respond favorably
                    to the Assistant Secretary’s proposal about suggesting volumes,
                    but tried to obtain a more precise commitment or agreed
                    undertaking on the number of volumes to be recommended and
                    reported upon. Perkins explained that the Committee wasn’t
                    concerned so much about volumes because they were “interesting”
                    but because the issues involved were so important that the
                    principles of selection and deletion needed close review. The
                    Assistant Secretary saw no point in elaborating detailed
                    procedures or numbers of volumes. He felt that the Department
                    should be allowed to make a good faith effort, and the Committee
                    would make its own judgment after the fact about the way the
                    selection and review process was working. Cohen acknowledged
                    that the Department should have the chance to make a good faith
                    effort, but he feared the tendency would be to choose the least
                    controversial areas like the United Nations, Sweden, and
                    Switzerland. He warned that the first year the Department turns
                    down all volumes requested for a review, there will be a problem.</p>
                <p>Perkins said that the Advisory Committee would be willing
                    to make recommendations of volumes, but its experience with A/CDC
                    raised concerns that the final choices of volumes to be reviewed
                    at annual Committee meetings would be the least significant and
                    least instructive. Perkins did not wish to appear to be
                    micromanaging A/CDC’s declassification decisions, but he knew
                    that there was in the academic community the commonly-held view,
                    which he deplored, that the official record printed in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes was incomplete as a result of extensive
                    clearance denials.</p>
                <p>Redman said he was troubled by the Committee’s skepticism
                    and reaffirmed his conviction that there must be good faith on
                    both sides and that both sides must be acknowledged as fully
                    professional. The Committee’s concerns about the Department’s
                    declassification procedures cannot be allowed to become an
                    investigative effort. He said he hoped we could work together as
                    professionals. Perkins and Cohen agreed that the relationship
                    had to be a positive one to work.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Guidelines for the Archives</p>
                <p>Redman turned to the second issue raised in Perkins March
                    17 letter -- Advisory Committee access to Department “guidelines”
                    prepared for the use of the National Archives and Records
                    Administration. He explained that the “guidelines” are a records
                    management tool intended to accompany the Department’s permanent
                    records when they are transferred to the National Archives. They
                    are not part of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> compiling process and they
                    in no way affect the preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series. They give no authority to declassify. Responsibility
                    for the preparation and administration of these “guidelines”
                    rests exclusively with the geographic bureaus and A/CDC. The
                    “guidelines” are intended for use by junior archivists at the
                    National Archives as they make their page-by-page review of the
                    Department’s permanent records.</p>
                <p>Redman explained that the Department had selected for
                    Chairman Perkins portions from these “guidelines” in order to
                    make more clear how the process works in preparing them and using
                    them. Redman emphasized, however, that this was a one-time-only
                    effort by the Department to demonstrate to the Advisory Committee
                    that the “guidelines” do not affect the selection of documents
                    for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. He then showed Prof. Perkins
                    and Prof. Cohen the current general guidelines for the systematic
                    review of Department records for the 1955-1959 period as well as
                    an example of particular subject or country guidelines -- in this
                    case the guidelines for United States-Austrian relations for
                    1955-1959.</p>
                <p>After scanning the examples of guidelines, Perkins
                    expressed some relief to discover no surprises in the range of
                    issues defined. He wondered whether they ever become more
                    specific. He found the general guidelines so broad as to
                    scarcely warrant being classified, and he wondered whether they
                    couldn’t be downgraded or declassified so that he could share
                    them with the rest of the Committee. Perkins speculated about
                    whether a broader view of the guidelines wouldn’t reveal patterns
                    of declassification denial that would be of importance to the
                    Committee. Perkins also noted that the charter of the Advisory
                    Committee called for it to provide advice on records policy.
                    Redman emphasized that the guidelines were being shared at this
                    time only to demonstrate that they have nothing to do with the
                    preparation of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Redman informed Perkins and Cohen that Prof. Deborah
                    Larsen’s disclosure of classified information obtained at last
                    January’s Advisory Committee meeting to a June 11 session of the
                    Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations undermined
                    the Department’s ability to work with the Advisory Committee in
                    areas that involved the responsible handling of sensitive
                    information and worked against any broadening of Committee access
                    to classified information. Perkins and Cohen recognized the
                    seriousness of this matter.</p>
                <p>Cohen explained that he could, on the basis of Redman’s
                    briefing, explain the general declassification guidelines, but he
                    could not do the same for the country-specific guidelines. The
                    Austrian guidelines were difficult for him to appraise; could he
                    see, at some point, the guidelines on China -- a[n] area where he
                    could make a more informed judgment? The Assistant Secretary
                    responded with an emphatic no; there was no reason for any access
                    to the guidelines. The examples provided today were more than
                    adequate. The guidelines were irrelevant to the compiling of the
                    published record.</p>
                <p>Cohen rejoined that the briefing convinced him that the
                    guidelines were relevant. He thought that in the future the
                    Advisory Committee might usefully see the guidelines for those
                    countries and topics where it was not possible for A/CDC to
                    provide an oral briefing. Cohen sought to draw a distinction
                    between the Advisory Committee’s understanding of and involvement
                    in the declassification process in the pre-A/CDC period (when
                    they were briefed on exclusions) and the present, and he
                    suggested the advantages of the former. Perkins reminded Cohen
                    of the delays experienced in the pre-CDC system and expressed a
                    preference for the current method, but he also indicated that the
                    greater openness of the record to the Committee prior to 1980 was
                    desirable.</p>
                <p>Redman recapitulated that the guidelines issue was, so far
                    as he could determine, a “red herring”. The Committee was
                    bogging itself down in the details of these guidelines when the
                    main issue about the selection of documents and comprehensiveness
                    of the volumes was illuminated by the oral declassification
                    briefings done by A/CDC. The Department is prepared to continue
                    and refine these briefings because it is the method by which the
                    Advisory Committee’s opinion, advice, and evaluation can be
                    obtained about comprehensiveness and selection.</p>
                <p>Redman concluded by stressing his feeling of urgency about
                    getting on with the larger issues of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series, including reaching the 30-year line for publication and
                    refocusing the contents of the series to serve the users better.
                    Perkins responded by agreeing that these larger issues were
                    important, but that the Committee had in the last several years
                    been far more worried about their lack of understanding of the
                    declassification procedures. He told Redman he was still
                    skeptical about the series reaching its ambitious publication
                    goals, despite the Historian’s optimistic appraisals. Perkins
                    also assured Redman that the Committee would be taking up the
                    future scope and shape of the series at its next meeting.</p>
                <p>As the meeting concluded, Perkins expressed appreciation
                    for the meeting with the Assistant Secretary and explained that
                    he would communicate the results to the other members of the
                    Committee. He expected that the Committee would probably respond
                    favorably to the invitation to provide Committee preferences for
                    volumes to be reported upon by A/CDC at forthcoming annual
                    meetings, but he anticipated some difficulty in explaining the
                    Department’s view on the guidelines for Department documents
                    retired to the National Archives. He hoped that he might receive
                    a communication from the Assistant Secretary recapitulating the
                    points made in the meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
