<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Ronald Spiers to Charles Redman, November
                    1988</title>
                <title type="short">Spiers to Redman, 1988</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1988-11-10">November 10, 1988</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1988-11-10-spiers-to-redman.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 138 KB, 1p.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Central Foreign Policy Files, 1989
                    P-Reels, P890058-1591.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn58">Footnote 58</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From Ronald Spiers (Under Secretary of State for Management) to
                    Charles Redman (Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs)</head>
                <dateline>November 10, 1988</dateline>
                <p>Subject: PA Management of the Historical Advisory Committee</p>
                <p>Thank you for your memorandum of November 2 regarding the Historical Advisory
                    Committee (HAC).</p>
                <p>I have accepted your recommendation for the renewal of the HAC charter for two
                    years. My action is based on your undertaking to manage the Committee with more
                    purpose and persistence than has perhaps always been the case in the past. The
                    intemperate and unbalanced report issued by the Committee this year provides
                    ample evidence that the <hi rend="underline">status quo</hi> is unsatisfactory.
                    I will look to your leadership to ensure that the proposed agenda for the
                    December meeting produces a session, and subsequent report, which adequately
                    addresses the subjects on which PA looks to the Committee for advice. I
                    understand that the Committee's February report asked the Historian to prepare a
                    paper for the next meeting describing the problems he faces in shaping the
                    future of the FRUS series; this would appear to provide an excellent opportunity
                    for PA and the Historian to tell the Committee exactly what you want from
                    it.</p>
                <p>I have asked M/MP to continue to monitor your progress with the Committee and to
                    keep me informed. I am prepared to revoke the Committee's charter at any time
                    should its activities pose a burden for the Department as a whole which can no
                    longer be justified by the benefits PA receives from its continued
                    existence.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
