<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1989</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1989</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1989-11-16">November 16, 1989</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1989-11-16-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 1.1 MB, 27pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 5, Advisory Committee
                Minutes—1989-1990.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn92">Footnotes 92</ref>, <ref target="../chapter-10#fn96"
                    >96</ref>, and <ref target="../chapter-10#fn97">97</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1989 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 16-17, 1989</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">American Historical Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Ronald H. Spector, Department of History, University of Alabama</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Organization of American Historians</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Bradford Perkins, Department of History, University of Michigan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Warren I. Cohen, Department of History, Michigan State
                        University</item>
                    <item>Dr. Michael H. Hunt, Department of History, University of North
                        Carolina</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">American Society of International Law</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Stephen T. Zamora, University of Houston Law Center</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">International Studies Association</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Paul M. Kattenburg, Institute of International Studies, University of
                        South Carolina</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Society of American Archivists</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Anne H. Van Camp, Hoover Institution, Stanford, California</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Thursday Morning Session (Open)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Warren Cohen</item>
                    <item>Dr. Bradford Perkins</item>
                    <item>Dr. Michael Hunt</item>
                    <item>Ms. Anne Van Camp</item>
                    <item>Dr. Paul Kattenburg</item>
                    <item>Dr. Stephen Zamora</item>
                    <item>Dr. Ronald Spector</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>G. Alfred Kennedy, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">The Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Chief, Foreign Relations Division</item>
                    <item>Rita M. Baker</item>
                    <item>David H. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>David W. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Elaine M. McDevitt</item>
                    <item>David S. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Charles S. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Louis J. Smith</item>
                    <item>Harriet D. Schwar</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Historical Documents Review Division:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Richard Morefield</item>
                    <item>Mr. Eugene Bovis</item>
                    <item>Mr. William Hamilton</item>
                    <item>Mr. Henry Barduch</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Publishing Services Division:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Paul Washington</item>
                    <item>Ms. Barbara Bacon</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. George C. Chalou, External Affairs, (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Mr. David A. Langbart, Records Appraisal Division, (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Mr. E. Allen Thompson, Records Declassification Division, (NARA)</item>
                    <item>Mr. Jim Gardner, National Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of
                        History</item>
                    <item>Ms. Virginia Saunders, Congressional Printing Management, Government
                        Printing Office</item>
                    <item>Mr. Daniel Helmstadter, <hi rend="underline">Scholarly
                        Resources</hi></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Cohen</hi> opened the meeting by announcing his
                    agreement to serve as chairman of the Committee and he asked Committee members
                    to adopt the agenda, which they did.</p>
                <p>He thanked Mr. Bovis and Mr. Morefield for being cooperative in past
                    misunderstandings regarding the classification/declassification procedures. He
                    also thanked George High (not present) for his past cooperation and support and
                    welcomed Deputy Assistant Secretary Kennedy to his first meeting with the
                    Advisory Committee.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Remarks by Deputy Assistant Secretary Kennedy</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Kennedy</hi> welcomed the members of the Committee and
                    expressed the Department's appreciation to the members. He also welcomed the
                    newest representatives at the meeting (Ms. Van Camp, Dr. Kattenburg, Dr.
                    Spector, and Dr. Zamora).</p>
                <p>Mr. Kennedy discussed the Department's efforts to accelerate the FRUS publication
                    schedules and explained how budget difficulties have hindered this goal. He
                    assured the Committee that the Bureau of Public Affairs is committed to
                    supporting the work of the Committee. He also detailed the new structure of the
                    Bureau and the new role of the Assistant Secretary. While Ms. Tutwiler may not
                    be available for discussions with them, Mr. Kennedy and Ms. Hoggard are
                    interested in working with the Committee. The tradition of strong PA Front
                    Office support will continue.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report of The Historian</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Slany</hi> began the discussion with a review of several
                    points in the report of the Advisory Committee made in March 1989 and a brief
                    summary of what the Department is doing in response to these
                    recommendations.</p>
                <p>Regarding the structural changes in the FRUS series, Dr. Slany commented that
                    there are many options under consideration, especially for those volumes
                    documenting the Kennedy administration. Chapter headings and tables of contents
                    will be given to the Committee for review and recommendation. Also area
                    specialists may be included in the process of planning and review of future
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>Some changes being considered in the series are the addition of a narrative
                    summary, a calender of files, or a bibliographic guide, or a combination of all
                    three, to the documents. Microfiche is being considered to replace as much as
                    50% of the text as budget constraints become more pressing. The British have
                    adopted a similar approach.</p>
                <p>A bibliographical guide in addition to a documentary text would assist in
                    research of related documents at NARA and the Presidential libraries and would
                    encourage the preservation of these documents.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Zamora</hi> initiated a discussion on the problem of the
                    Vietnam volumes. These volumes were projected through 1969. The body of
                    documents, however, was much larger than anticipated and access difficulties to
                    the Johnson papers prevented projection past 1965, funds are being focused on
                    more short term goals. The compilation will include congressional documents and
                    collections of private papers as well as interviews that supplement the
                    documents.</p>
                <p>Budget restrictions have required reductions in volume size. To compensate,
                    scanning and laser disc technology are being considered.</p>
                <p>Discussion next turned to the consideration of a disclaimer in the volumes
                    explaining why some documents or portions of documents were not declassified.
                    FPC argues that even mention of missing documents can be a security risk. The
                    Advisory Committee agreed that a carefully worded general disclaimer will be
                    drafted for further discussion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Slany</hi> turned to the subject of completing 1960
                    documentation by 1990, a goal which will not be reached due to NSC and other
                    delays. 1992 is a more realistic target date. The Committee was asked to review
                    this development and make any recommendations for improvements.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany commented that among the subjects to be covered during the meeting were
                    the expansion the Advisory Committee to include representatives of Federal
                    agencies other than State and other interested disciplines, and preservation of
                    electronic records as well as those subjects mentioned briefly above.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report on the Printing and Distribution of the Foreign Relations
                    Series</p>
                <p>Paul M. Washington, Chief of the Publishing Services Division, Bureau of
                    Administration and Information Management, reported on the printing and
                    distribution of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>In February 1986, the Superintendent of Documents requested guidance from the
                    Depository Library Council to recommend titles for conversion to microfiche in
                    order to achieve Congressionally-mandated cost reductions in the Depository
                    Library Program. Since that time, 20 volumes have been published but not
                    distributed to the libraries because of delays the letting a contract to produce
                    microfiche copies for the depository libraries. GPO estimates that the cost of
                    reprinting the volumes to place them in the depository libraries is $600,000, as
                    compared with $15,000 to publish and distribute the volumes as microfiche. For
                    future volumes, the cost would be $10,000 per volume to place a print copy in
                    1,100 depository libraries, as opposed to $800 per volume for microfiche.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins asked if the copyright law requires GPO to provide copies to the
                    depository libraries. Mr. Washington responded that only the Superintendent of
                    Documents has the authority to determine the distribution of publications to
                    depository libraries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington stated that after all the effort to produce the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, it seemed essential that copies be made
                    available to the depository libraries. He posed three options in this regard:
                    provide Department funds to place print volumes in selected depository libraries
                    (approximately $10,000 per volume); provide a Department contract to prepare
                    microfiche copies of the volume at the time of publication; and award a contract
                    to the National Technical Information Service (NTIS) to produce the backlogged
                    volumes quickly.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hunt observed that the GPO requirement to opt for the low bidder presented a
                    problem with the quality of the contractor. It was a troublesome characteristic
                    of the GPO contracting system. Mr. Washington stated that it was the GPO policy
                    to have one contractor do all the microfiche work.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector asserted that the only viable option should be to go back and print
                    the 20 volumes for distribution to the depository libraries. He argued that the
                    Advisory Committee could go to Congress and request the $600,000, since
                    congressmen can be lobbied over the fact that there were no <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in the various state and university
                    libraries that comprise a large portion of the depository library system.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington thought it would be useful if the Committee would campaign to
                    produce some movement from GPO on this question. To get 20 volumes behind is a
                    major problem. By no longer producing copies for the depository libraries, GPO
                    had reduced the print run for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes from 2,500 to 1,400 copies. Dr. Slany reported that the Department had
                    not been aware of the GPO decision to discontinue distribution of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> print volumes to the depository
                    libraries. Mr. Washington had been effective in persuading the Superintendent of
                    Documents to keep <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in stock for
                    at least 10 years.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hunt inquired whether it would be possible to combine projected sales and
                    depository library distribution in the same print run; the fewer volumes sold,
                    the more available for distribution to the depository libraries. Mr. Washington
                    stated that the GPO handles the two distributions separately from a funding
                    standpoint: the sales program returned money to GPO, while depository library
                    volumes are funded by appropriations. He pointed out that the increasing price
                    of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes may limit sales.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector argued that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes can
                    be marketed more aggressively.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington asserted that the Department was looking into different marketing
                    options, but said the high price of the book and the irregular printing schedule
                    limit marketing options.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany stated that the Department should be in a better position to market the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes than the GPO. West Germany
                    planned to privatize its official publications. The market would control
                    pricing. A comparable publication under this option in West Germany, however,
                    might cost as much as $80.</p>
                <p>Mr. Helmstadter pointed out that the private sector was better positioned to
                    print and market the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes more
                    effectively. He thought that the cost of reprinting the volumes should not
                    exceed $10.00 per volume (or $200,000 total). Marketing of the volumes can be
                    increased dramatically. Given the number of college and university libraries,
                    sales and distribution of the volumes should be more than 2,500.</p>
                <p>Mr. Washington stated that from his perspective, there would be no problem having
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> published by the private sector
                    provided there were no legal impediments caused by the GPO mandate.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen asked Mr. Washington if he would provide a list of key individuals at
                    the Government Printing Office and the Joint Committee on Printing to write to
                    regarding the distribution of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes to the depository libraries. He also requested a brief history of the
                    problem so that the Committee could better formulate its recommendations in its
                    report.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner, representing the National Coordinating Committee for the Promotion
                    of History, asserted that the NCC will look into playing a role in this
                    matter.</p>
                <p>Ms. Saunders, representing the Government Printing Office, noted that the
                    depository libraries can select among the GPO publications. Approximately 1,100
                    of the 1,400 have selected <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. The
                    decision to go to microfiche distribution copies came about because of budget
                    cuts at the GPO.</p>
                <p>Before concluding, Mr. Washington reported that the cost of printing <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had come down to a reasonable level.
                    The Department was particularly pleased with the current contractor, although
                    the existing contract was due to expire at the end of November.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen thanked Mr. Washington for his report, and stated that the matter of
                    the distribution of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to the depository
                    libraries is a high priority for the Committee.</p>
                <p rend="center">Thursday Afternoon Session (Closed)</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Cohen</item>
                    <item>Dr. Hunt</item>
                    <item>Dr. Kattenburg</item>
                    <item>Ms. Van Camp</item>
                    <item>Dr. Perkins</item>
                    <item>Dr. Spector</item>
                    <item>Dr. Zamora</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Ms. Baker</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Dr. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Ms. McDevitt</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Dr. Smith</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Historical Documents Review Division:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Richard Morefield</item>
                    <item>Mr. Charles Flowerree</item>
                    <item>Mr. Theodore Tremblay</item>
                    <item>Mr. William Hamilton</item>
                    <item>Mr. Dwight Ambach</item>
                    <item>Mr. Eugene Bovis</item>
                    <item>Mr. Phillip Valdes</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Report on the Declassification Review of Foreign Relations</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Richard Morefield</hi>, the Director of the Historical
                    Documents Review Division HDR (formerly the Office of Systematic Review,
                    Classification/Declassification Center), explained the recent reorganization of
                    the Bureau of Administration and how his division fits into it. Essentially, HDR
                    has been integrated into the information and management element of the Bureau of
                    Administration and Information Management, the bureau which also handles Freedom
                    of Information, Privacy, and Declassification matters. The same people are doing
                    the same job with the same mandate, but under a different name. The philosophy
                    of the reorganized bureau is that it will be user-driven, service-oriented, and
                    dedicated to using modern technology.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield reviewed the past year's work of HDR and noted that it had been
                    highly successful. Ten volumes had been released, principally for 1955-57. This
                    left four 1955-57 volumes to be cleared, of which three are now at the NSC. The
                    remaining volume is still being considered by the UK. He added that ten volumes
                    are likely for 1990.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield also reported that the NSC logjam was essentially broken, in large
                    part because of the assistance that HDR had provided NSC as well as from an
                    exceptional effort by the NSC itself to clear volumes. Only 6 volumes remained
                    at NSC (of these, 3 had been submitted to them in June 1989).</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield had hoped to be able to announce that the block of 1955-1959 of
                    Department of State records was totally available at the National Archives, but
                    this was not yet the case. He expected the records for this period to be
                    available soon.</p>
                <p>Finally, Mr. Morefield announced that HDR was beginning to examine the problem of
                    multilateral records, such as those of NATO, and to consider how these could be
                    systematically declassified.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield then noted that there were clouds on the horizon: the first being
                    resources available for processing documents under systematic review versus
                    those devoted to the ever increasing number of FOIA requests. In particular, he
                    cited the large number of FOIA requests on the Cuban missile crisis and noted
                    that so far the Department had been willing to provide the resources necessary
                    to deal with large requests, but that this may not always be the case. Secondly,
                    he informed the Committee that the exponential growth of paper in the 1960's
                    might well siphon off resources from review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> documents.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, he noted that the number of agencies needed to clear any given document
                    would continue to increase and this, in turn, would slow down processing.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Spector</hi> asked if it were true that the Department
                    of State did not know what it had released as he had been told by someone
                    outside the Department. He had also been told State had no FOI reading room.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield denied this. There was a reading room and documentation was
                    released on microfilm, not by case, but by subject. The question facing HDR was
                    should this operation be computerized and should material he made available by
                    modem.</p>
                <p>Asked by <hi rend="underline">Dr. Hunt</hi> if FOIA requests threatened to
                    overwhelm the Department, Mr. Morefield answered that it would be more efficient
                    to declassify wholesale, that is, systematically, but that the law was written
                    differently.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hunt inquired if blanket declassification was a possibility. Mr. Morefield
                    responded that the Department was unalterably opposed to automatic
                    declassification.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Dr. Zamora</hi> asked if HDR was operating under a
                    presumption of release or denial. Mr. Morefield answered that there was a
                    definite presumption of release and denials could only be made for a few
                    specific reasons. Dr. Spector pointed out, however, that it had been his
                    experience at the Navy that each new executive order on declassification allowed
                    for more denials and, if declassifiers chose, they need not release
                    anything.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield said that was an attitudinal problem. He believed his system of
                    using retired FSO's with area expertise created an attitude favoring release
                    while still protecting sensitive material. The problem was that most denials
                    were based on current events. If the Department released information given in
                    confidence by a foreign government, it risked not getting that kind of
                    information in the future.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Ted Tremblay</hi> then discussed the declassification of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> 1961-1963, vol. III, Vietnam, 1963. Dr.
                    Glennon noted that the deletions were minor, about 2.5%, and then Mr. Tremblay
                    characterized them and placed them within the context of the volume.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Ted Keefer</hi> pointed out that, perhaps due to modesty,
                    Tremblay was not telling the full story of the declassification of this volume.
                    Initially, CIA had made massive deletions which would have destroyed fully the
                    credibility of the volume. HDR went back to CIA twice and convinced them to
                    restore virtually all their denials and to make only minor excisions. Dr. Keefer
                    noted that Vietnam was unique in that, from a certain point in time, the CIA was
                    prepared to acknowledge its existence in Saigon. Therefore, some headings will
                    be from the Station Chief to the Agency and vice versa. Unfortunately, this
                    situation occurs only in the case of Saigon and only in a specific timeframe,
                    and is not the beginning of a general trend.</p>
                <p>Asked by Dr. Cohen if he was satisfied with the HDR review of the volume, Dr.
                    Keefer replied that he was very pleased and that it represented a success. The
                    only fly in the ointment, and it was a small fly at that, was that we were
                    unable to convince the British, the Canadians, and State's Office of Soviet
                    Affairs to release a British report, a Canadian intermediary exercise, and a
                    discussion between a Soviet Embassy official and a White House aide on Vietnam.
                    While these were only small parts of the volume, they raised issues would impact
                    on the series coverage of Vietnam in the late 1960's.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tremblay recounted the opposition of the British and the Canadians to our
                    releasing their documents. He stated that in the case of the 1961 Vietnam
                    volume, after the death of Gromyko, the Department was prepared to release a
                    disputed conversation but by that time it was too late for inclusion in the
                    volume.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Charles Flowerree</hi> of HDR discussed the declassification
                    of <hi rend="italics">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1955-1957, vol. XIX, National
                    Security Policy. He noted that it was a long time in review, but that in itself
                    had allowed for more to be declassified. He briefly described the
                    declassification results. Of 185 total documents, 12 had been denied, and of
                    those, 9 were National Intelligence Estimates (NIEs) dealing with the way we
                    evaluated Soviet capabilities. That was a stumbling block for CIA. The other 3
                    were JCS analyses of Soviet capabilities which were denied for similar reasons.
                    Mr. Flowerree then described the contents of the volume. Returning to the
                    deletions, Mr. Flowerree described the excisions. [<hi rend="italic">Text not
                        declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Both Dr. Spector and Dr. Perkins asked why the NIEs were denied and Mr. Flowerree
                    explained that methods of assessing Soviet capabilities were still considered
                    sensitive.</p>
                <p>Asked why the volume was so long in review, Mr. Flowerree responded that the
                    problem was with the other agencies and foreign governments and then, as the
                    volume went to NSC, it was delayed by the Iran-Contra roadblock.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hunt asked if the reader would be able to determine from this volume how the
                    Soviet threat was assessed. Mr. Flowerree answered that the specifics would not
                    be there. Even if CIA had cleared the NIEs, the detail would still not be there.
                    Rather one had to use the high-level discussions at the NSC meetings to
                    understand how the Soviet threat was being assessed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Phillip Valdes</hi> then gave an account of the
                    declassification of the USSR compilation in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> 1955-1957, vol. XXIV, Soviet Union and Eastern Mediterranean,
                    which is already published. He described the denials and excisions in the Soviet
                    compilation, which were extensive (10% and 23% respectively). Of the 482
                    documents in the volume, 51 had been denied and 110 excised. He described
                    briefly the contents of the volume and then raised the issues which presented
                    problems. [<hi rend="italic">Text not declassified.</hi>] The Cyprus compilation
                    (206 documents, 16 denied, 52 excised) had problems with documents discussing
                    the division of the island and 3 Greek government documents which the Embassy in
                    Athens refused to ask the Government to clear. The Greek compilation's (50
                    documents, 8 denied and 8 excised) [<hi rend="italic">text not
                    declassified</hi>.] The Turkish compilation (83 documents, 5 denied and 5
                    excised) was essentially a matter of removing material on intelligence
                    operations [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>.] Dr. Glennon observed
                    that the percentage of material denied on this volume was about 6.5%, slightly
                    higher than the general average of 4.5%.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen then asked if he could see the documents which were described in this
                    session, those that were not Top Secret or other-agency documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield replied that the Committee had only Secret clearances, and most of
                    these documents were Top Secret and non-Department of State documents. All the
                    Committee would be able to see were just a few of the least impressive and he
                    was not sanguine that they could see even these.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen stressed that the integrity of the series demanded that the Committee
                    insist on seeing these deletions. Dr. Spector suggested that the Department
                    grant a Top Secret clearance to the Chairman and that he be allowed to see them.
                    Dr. Cohen said that the Advisory Committee had already sent a letter to its
                    constituent bodies saying that the members would be seeing the deletions and he
                    felt access had to be granted in the near future. He stated that he believed
                    this was the bargain that had been struck with the Department.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Report on the Longevity and Preservation of Electronic
                    Records</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant Secretary Robert K. Carr then spoke to the Committee about
                    Department's efforts in the area of information management. Mr. Carr explained
                    that on October 1 the Department had merged six separate offices dealing with
                    information management. A “Foreign Affairs Information System” is being
                    installed throughout the Department. The Under Secretary for Management is
                    anxious to move the Department to a new information environment. We are truly
                    looking toward the day of the “paperless office”. The number of documents is
                    growing and information techniques are changing. Comments which formerly were
                    marginal are being replaced by electronic communication between offices through
                    “electronic mail”.</p>
                <p>Mr. Carr suggested that it is the responsibility of the National Archives to take
                    the lead in developing criteria for how and when the Department should transfer
                    documents. The volume of information continues to grow dramatically. For
                    example, one can look ahead to an era when voice transmissions will be part of
                    the record</p>
                <p>Ms. Van Camp noted that it might well benefit the Committee at some occasion to
                    plan a visit to the Archives to observe first-hand their research efforts in the
                    area of electronic records.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Morning Session</hi> (Closed)</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Cohen</item>
                    <item>Dr. Spector</item>
                    <item>Dr. Zamora</item>
                    <item>Dr. Perkins</item>
                    <item>Dr. Kattenburg</item>
                    <item>Ms. Van Camp</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Professor Bruce Kuniholm, Duke University</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Ms. Baker</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Ms. McDevitt</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Dr. Smith</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Historical Documents Review Division:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Richard Morefield</item>
                    <item>Mr. Eugene Bovis</item>
                    <item>Mr. Henry Bardach</item>
                    <item>Mr. Charles Flowerree</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Evaluation of Foreign Relations, 1952-1954, Volume X, Iran,
                    1951-1954</p>
                <p>At the invitation of the Committee, Professor Bruce Kuniholm of Duke University
                    commented on the recently published volume <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, 1952-1954, vol. X, Iran, 1951-1954. Kuniholm concluded that
                    the publication of what he saw as a seriously misleading account of U.S.
                    relations with Iran at a critical juncture constituted “something like fraud” by
                    the Department of State. The publication of such a volume, Kuniholm felt, called
                    into question the credibility as well as the purpose of the series. He
                    emphasized, however, that in criticizing the volume he was not criticizing the
                    work which went into the compilation of the volume, but rather the political
                    decisions which underlay the removal of documentation essential to a credible
                    account, and the decision to publish what he considered to be a seriously flawed
                    and misleading record of U.S.-Iranian relations.</p>
                <p>Professor Kuniholm reviewed the volume in some detail and elaborated on his
                    criticisms. A reading of the volume, Professor Kuniholm noted, created an
                    impression concerning the overthrow of the Mosadeq government in 1953 which was
                    simplistic and wrong: Mosadeq was anti-British, the British opposed Mosadeq, the
                    British tried to enlist the support of the U.S., to some extent the U.S.
                    supported the British, the British departed, the U.S. tried to patch up the
                    relationship, and in the end Mosadeq was overthrown by a popular uprising.</p>
                <p>Professor Kuniholm argued that the account of the overthrow of the Mosadeq
                    government, to the extent that it was covered in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volume at all, is vastly different from the real story which
                    can be pieced together from memoirs of participants, such as Kermit Roosevelt,
                    and from other available accounts of [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified.</hi>] Professor Kuniholm stressed that, despite all that has
                    been revealed in such accounts, the volume is entirely silent on the CIA's role
                    in the overthrow of Mosadeq. CIA plans and activities leading up to the
                    restoration of the Shah to the throne are totally absent from the volume. He
                    conceded that the volume did include useful information on a number of other
                    issues, and was “good as far as it goes”, but he added that “all the crucial
                    stuff is omitted.”</p>
                <p>Professor Kuniholm raised and dismissed all of the arguments he felt the CIA
                    might have used to justify withholding the missing information. Weighed against
                    those arguments was the public's right to be informed and the importance of an
                    accurate record for analysts inside as well as outside the government. In
                    arguing the importance of an accurate record for internal analysts, he recalled
                    his difficulty in obtaining access to a CIA study of this episode when he was in
                    the Department working on a highly classified study of the background of U.S.
                    policy toward Iran during the hostage crisis. He also noted that Iranian
                    nationalists have reacted to the United States since the overthrow of Mosadeq on
                    the presumption that the CIA was behind the change. It might have been better
                    for U.S.-Iranian relations to have made the actual story available long
                    since.</p>
                <p>The Committee generally applauded and concurred in Professor Kuniholm's
                    assessment of the volume. Chairman Cohen agreed that the volume was badly flawed
                    and he stated that he was concerned about the impact on the series as a whole of
                    publishing obviously misleading accounts. Dr. Perkins seconded those concerns
                    and said that it would be better not to publish a volume that distorts the
                    record to such an extent unless a disclaimer could be included to the effect
                    that the published account did not constitute the entire record. Dr. Kattenburg
                    agreed in general, but played devil's advocate to the extent of wondering
                    whether Roosevelt's published account wasn't self-serving, and the entire
                    episode of the overthrow of Mosadeq largely something engineered by the British.
                    Professor Kuniholm replied that he was certain that the United States was the
                    principal actor. At that point, he was asked what he would have done if faced
                    with the necessity of having to publish an incomplete account. He replied that
                    he would have resigned.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector felt that two issues were raised by Professor Kuniholm's
                    presentation. At one level the volume highlighted the specific problems
                    confronted by the Historian's Office in attempting to present a complete account
                    of U.S. foreign policy. At another and higher level, there was the more serious
                    problem of a government institutionalizing the practice of lying to itself.
                    Drawing on his background in the Navy's historical program, Dr. Spector noted
                    that the case was always made by military historians that detailing mistakes and
                    omissions in an account of a military operation might save some lives if those
                    who studied the record for lessons to be learned actually profited from the
                    lessons of history. He felt that a similar presentation should be made to the
                    officers with substantive responsibilities for declassification of the documents
                    selected for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Misinformation
                    in the record of foreign relations and national security policy can be similarly
                    dangerous, particularly when perpetuated as a basis for analysis.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany expressed appreciation for Professor Kuniholm's presentation and said
                    that HO was aware of the problems raised by the Committee. He noted that HO was
                    still groping for a solution to the problem highlighted in the presentation and
                    perhaps had not made a strong enough case to other agencies on the issue. He
                    indicated that this was one of the problems to be worked out as the office felt
                    its way from the old <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series to the
                    new.</p>
                <p>Dr. Glennon pointed out that the volume does contain some good material and
                    called the Committee's attention to one or two documents. He commented that
                    researchers cannot use the volume alone but must use other sources as well. He
                    said that in terms of pages, HO lost only about 2% of the pages in the volume in
                    the declassification process. With the help of the CIA historian, we were able
                    to get access to about 36 pages, double spaced, of CIA cables that had been
                    retyped by the CIA; they essentially said what Kim Roosevelt said in his book
                    but could not be included in the volume. We had 1,100 pages of good material and
                    were faced with the question of whether to sit on it or publish it. Dr. Perkins
                    pointed out that HO had withheld the 1949 China volume documenting the Chou
                    En-lai demarche for several years. Dr. Glennon replied that we had reason to
                    believe that the China volume would be cleared after the death of Chou and Mao
                    Tse-tung. This had been correct. When they died, the volume was cleared.</p>
                <p>Committee members asked about the volumes concerning Guatemala in 1954 [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified.</hi>] Dr. Glennon thought the Guatemala
                    compilation was far less complete than the Iran volume. Our major problem was
                    one of access. Dr. Glennon, Dr. Schwar, and Dr. Keefer commented [<hi
                        rend="italic">text not declassified.</hi>] Dr. Glennon added that the
                    problem of coverage of covert operations in the series was perhaps more
                    widespread than the Committee realized.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield pointed out that the Iran volume included a great deal of material
                    concerning international economic issues and the involvement of the Seven
                    Sisters in Iran. Professor Kuniholm said the volume included a great deal of
                    good material. He said he could see the dilemma but thought the volume should
                    include a disclaimer.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector thought this was a fundamental decision for the Department: whether
                    or not to claim this is a complete record of U.S. foreign policy. Dr. Perkins
                    pointed out that a disclaimer was a two-edged sword in that it could be used by
                    other agencies as an excuse to deny documents. Dr. Slany raised the possibility
                    of an introduction explaining the circumstances under which a volume was
                    compiled.</p>
                <p>Dr. Zamora asked about review of a volume by an independent scholar. Dr. Slany
                    said there was a plan to have Michel Oksenberg look at a China volume. Dr. Cohen
                    thought there were two problems with involving an academic in the compilation
                    process: (1) they did not have time, and (2) they were concerned about being
                    co-opted. Dr. Spector suggested that an early review of a completed compilation
                    by an outside scholar might serve as an early warning system to indicate the
                    reaction to a volume like this one. Dr. Kattenberg thought this was unnecessary;
                    HO historians could see the problems with such a volume without any outside
                    review. Drs. Slany and Glennon indicated that they had recognized the problems.
                    Dr. Spector noted that most government agencies have a review panel with one
                    outside scholar and one participant in the events.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins asked what HO thought about a disclaimer. Dr. Glennon pointed out
                    that there was a question as to whether we could clear a meaningful disclaimer.
                    Dr. Cohen thought we should not allow publication of another volume like this
                    one without such a disclaimer. Dr. Kattenberg thought we should make clear to
                    the upper echelons that something had to be done along this line. He thought
                    there should be a high-level interagency review of the situation and some sort
                    of interagency cooperation. He mentioned the Center for the Study of
                    Intelligence which has done work in this area.</p>
                <p>Discussion of a possible disclaimer continued, with the committee in general
                    agreement that a disclaimer was necessary, although Dr. Perkins again noted that
                    it was a two-edged sword. Reverting to Dr. Slany's suggestion of an introduction
                    to specific volumes rather than a general disclaimer, Dr. Perkins asked Dr.
                    Slany what he would have said in an introduction to the Iran volume. Dr. Slany
                    replied that he would have said we did not have access to all agency documents.
                    Dr. Cohen thought that was not sufficient; we can not assume everyone has the
                    background to understand the import of such a statement. He thought it was
                    essential to protect the integrity of the volumes.</p>
                <p>Dr. Zamora thought a general disclaimer would be better. Dr. Kattenberg thought
                    an introduction should state how many documents had been denied by each agency.
                    Bruce Kuniholm suggested a bibliographic essay, including not only memoirs but
                    secondary material, such as the article the August 1987 issue of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Middle East Studies</hi>, on such matters as the
                    Iran coup. Mr. Morefield said such an essay might say “Since it is U.S. policy
                    not to discuss these matters, we can neither confirm nor deny these
                    allegations.”</p>
                <p>Dr. Smith pointed out that the CIA has an interest in releasing some documents.
                    When Congress exempted the CIA from the Freedom of Information Act, the CIA
                    agreed to find some vehicle for the systematic release of some of its documents.
                    For this reason, the agency is interested in HO's project for a supplementary
                    intelligence volume. However, this would only include documents concerning
                    intelligence in general. In response to questions from the Committee concerning
                    the supplementary intelligence volume, Dr. Slany said HO may be able to get Tom
                    Thorne, a former Deputy Assistant Secretary in INR, to work on it.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen concluded that the committee had to let the Secretary know that this
                    was a serious problem which was undermining the series. The purpose of the
                    series is to give the American people an accurate record of U.S. foreign policy.
                    It is essential to warn the reader that important aspects are not included. Dr.
                    Cohen asked Committee members to reflect on the problem and to send him their
                    thoughts. It was important to make a thoughtful, concerted approach to the
                    Secretary on the matter, and Dr. Cohen noted that he would be in Washington all
                    winter and could formulate and press such an approach.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Discussion of Revisions of the Charter of the Foreign Relations
                    Series</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany requested the Committee's comments on revision of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> directive, especially in connection with the
                    preparation of volumes for the Kennedy period. Dr. Cohen noted that the
                    directive specified use of other agency documents when necessary and withdrew
                    his previous proposal that the Office consider publication of Department of
                    State documents only.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany said that PA/HO might stop any pretence of publishing the whole record,
                    and concentrate on selected issues. Dr. Perkins said there were really two
                    issues, topicality and comprehensiveness. Dr. Spector recalled that when PA/HO
                    had concentrated exclusively on Vietnam for a few years, it had gotten many
                    complaints from researchers in other areas despite the high quality of the
                    Vietnam volumes. He had liked the approach, but many others had not. Dr. Cohen
                    said that there was a danger that some of the areas on which complete
                    documentation was available, unlike Vietnam, might not be the ones of most
                    central importance. Dr. Perkins argued against starting with the assumption that
                    documentation on some topics was so slim that no volume was possible. It might
                    prove to be the case, but the <hi rend="underline">a priori</hi> assumption
                    should not be made.</p>
                <p>There was general agreement that in the future more selectivity was inevitable.
                    Dr. Zamora wondered if modern computerized systems might not make possible a
                    series with a few book publications, but a great mass of documentation available
                    on line. Dr. Herschler pointed out some of the problems with this approach given
                    the difficulty of compiling documents from other agencies. Dr. Kattenburg said
                    there should be an Executive Order declassifying everything up to 1960, with all
                    the burden of proof to be on the government for continued classification of all
                    subsequent materials.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany said another problem was that many agencies did not properly maintain
                    the record, much less make it accessible. Dr. Spector said that this was
                    properly a job for the Archivist of the United States. The Archivist had never
                    done this before, but the new one seemed disposed to try. In the Department the
                    historians should identify what needed to be kept. Dr. Herschler mentioned that
                    such a provision was already in Departmental regulations. Dr. Spector said,
                    “Make it stronger.” Dr. Cohen discussed an article by Nancy Tucker, which stated
                    that while she was temporarily on the China desk materials of historical value
                    had been routinely destroyed. Dr. Spector suggested that PA/HO see to it that
                    the Inspector General carried out his responsibilities with respect to record
                    retention. Historians should accompany the IG on his inspections. This
                    technique, he recalled, had been valuable when he was at the Naval Historical
                    Center. Also, Congressional scrutiny would help.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany again asked for the Committee's recommendations on selectivity. Dr.
                    Spector said outside advice would help the Office to justify future decisions.
                    Dr. Perkins believed that narratives would be a mistake. Dr. Cohen suggested an
                    introduction which would explain what was included, and why, and what was left
                    out, and why, with archival and bibliographic information on both classes of
                    material. Dr. Kattenburg said it would look “damn silly” for the Department to
                    send readers to secondary sources on matters on which the Department was charged
                    with printing the record. Dr. Cohen said that the Committee would come up with
                    recommendations on the selectivity issue, especially on how to refer to omitted
                    materials.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins wondered if it would be desirable or possible to distinguish between
                    a disclaimer, earlier discussed in connection with the Iran volume, and a
                    description of missing substantive material. Dr. Kattenburg recommended that the
                    disclaimer be as bland and neutral as possible.</p>
                <p>There ensued discussion as to whether advice should be solicited from individuals
                    or groups of experts. Dr. Cohen thought that consultation with individuals
                    should be done if useful, and not for the purpose of a cover to justify anything
                    the Office did. Dr. Slany cautioned that consultation would lengthen the time it
                    would take to prepare the volumes. Dr. Kattenburg emphasized that the compilers,
                    as trained historians, were perfectly capable of utilizing the secondary
                    literature themselves.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion of the possibility of getting a private subsidy to help
                    the series' financial problems. The Department can receive private money. There
                    was general agreement that channeling of funds through a private foundation was
                    preferable because donors would prefer to give to it rather than directly to the
                    government.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Friday Afternoon Session (Closed)</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Cohen</item>
                    <item>Dr. Spector</item>
                    <item>Dr. Zamora</item>
                    <item>Dr. Perkins</item>
                    <item>Dr. Kattenburg</item>
                    <item>Ms. Van Camp</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of the Historian:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Dr. Slany</item>
                    <item>Dr. Glennon</item>
                    <item>Ms. Baker</item>
                    <item>Dr. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Dr. Mabon</item>
                    <item>Ms. McDevitt</item>
                    <item>Dr. Sampson</item>
                    <item>Dr. Schwar</item>
                    <item>Dr. Smith</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Historical Documents Review Division:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Richard Morefield</item>
                    <item>Mr. Henry Bardach</item>
                    <item>Mr. Eugene Bovis</item>
                    <item>Mr. William Hamilton</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">National Archives and Records Administration:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. John Fawcett</item>
                    <item>Dr. George Chalou</item>
                    <item>Ms. Nancy Smith</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Report on Access to Documentation at Presidential Libraries</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett said that the National Archives has been working on procedures to
                    assist the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and has tried to cut
                    out some of the burdensome aspects of the process, but pointed out that this was
                    a complex problem. His office and HO could not solve the declassification
                    problem by themselves. Declassification was an extremely cumbersome, frustrating
                    process, but NARA was attempting to cut some bureaucratic procedures.</p>
                <p>The Department of State had helped NARA to send an additional employee to the
                    Kennedy Library last year but a 3-month detail was not enough to handle the
                    project; such help needs to be long-term. Mr. Fawcett also maintained that the
                    funds for such a long-term project had to be provided by the Department because
                    much of it would aid government historians but would not help the public.</p>
                <p>NARA is also taking other actions to help HO move forward with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>; the Kennedy Library has reassigned an archivist
                    from domestic records to foreign affairs. It has also hired two additional
                    staffers, although they have not yet received their security clearances. The
                    Johnson Library has not filled an oral history vacancy and has transferred the
                    position to declassification/mandatory review (at some cost to its oral history
                    program).</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett said that his main point is that NARA is unhappy with the current
                    situation, despite these cooperative efforts, because it has had a negative
                    effect on public access to the records. Therefore, the same people who do
                    mandatory review have less time to work on public access.</p>
                <p>He stated that NARA knows much more about handling classified material and
                    mandatory review than it did 20 years ago. Without question, in the absence of
                    huge increases in funding and personnel, the most effective way to handle
                    declassification is systematic review from Department of State guidelines. This
                    has worked at the Eisenhower Library, where they have made tremendous progress,
                    and Mr. Fawcett urged that such guidelines be provided at an earlier stage. He
                    also noted that the Department is the only agency that has given NARA guidelines
                    (still incomplete) for the Eisenhower administration.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett has talked to the directors of Ford, Carter, and Reagan Libraries
                    regarding the most effective way of handling classified materials. This would be
                    to process classified material specifically for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> access as the first stage for systematic review/mandatory
                    review, i.e., to sort the files by classification, code word, etc., so that
                    Department of State historians could begin work on them. This would mean that
                    the libraries would not have to do the work over again for mandatory review
                    requests because they would have both the physical arrangement and an
                    intellectual overview of the files.</p>
                <p>He asked HO to develop preliminary priorities for the Ford, Carter, and Reagan
                    administrations. (The Nixon Library is a special case because it has to follow
                    the cumbersome access procedures written into law.) He pointed out that if HO
                    began its research before 20 years have passed, it could start to work with the
                    Department's declassification people earlier. NARA resources could then be
                    devoted to providing public access to those records.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett concluded his report by pointing out that there are problems with
                    limited resources; therefore, the Department and HO have to support additional
                    resources for declassification. If such resources are provided, the Presidential
                    libraries could be more effective.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Discussion With the Advisory Committee</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins commented that this was quite a change from last year, when the
                    Advisory Committee was told that the Kennedy Library had no resources. Dr.
                    Warren Cohen noted that the Committee has continued to receive complaints from
                    researchers.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett replied that, obviously, they have had problems. For years, the
                    Kennedy Library had not directed its resources toward archival processing as
                    much as the other Presidential libraries. Now there is a new director who is
                    concerned about this and is taking steps to improve the situation, but they
                    cannot catch up immediately. In response to Dr. Perkins' query as to whether the
                    new director was a professional archivist, Mr. Fawcett that he was not, but that
                    he had a great interest in the subject as well as an academic background.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett admitted that scholars have had problems. The Kennedy Library is
                    still waiting for the two new staffers to get their clearances, which would
                    improve the situation. (He pointed out, however, that he himself was still
                    waiting for codeword clearance.) He also noted that NARA had to balance
                    mandatory review requests and appeals; Presidential libraries respond wherever
                    there is the greatest pressure.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins asked if the staff at the Presidential libraries ever moved around,
                    to which Mr. Fawcett replied that usually they did not. He noted that the
                    average time of employment at the Roosevelt Library was 18 years.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen argued that Presidential libraries with no declassification work need
                    fewer people and asked whether NARA could transfer people to the Kennedy or
                    Johnson Libraries. Mr. Fawcett replied that they could not move people, although
                    they could shift positions when vacancies occurred and noted that NARA had
                    shifted declassification positions. He also pointed out that these employees
                    have acquired expertise regarding collections, which is necessary for reference
                    work as well as declassification. He added that the workload does not go down
                    when collections are declassified; it shifts from processing to helping
                    researchers. Dr. Perkins asked whether employees need as much skill to do
                    reference work, to which Mr. Fawcett replied that skill consists of knowledge of
                    the records, not of the process.</p>
                <p>Mr. Fawcett noted that one of their biggest problems was getting agencies to
                    follow proper procedures regarding classified material before NARA received it.
                    Agencies at the highest level (such as the National Security Council) often
                    ignored these procedures but NARA could not.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins asked if someone could be detailed on a temporary basis, to which Mr.
                    Fawcett replied that this had happened last year (with Department of State
                    funds) but it was very expensive.</p>
                <p>Regarding the problem of lack of resources, Dr. Spector asked why the
                    Presidential libraries did not say that they could not operate the Carter and
                    Reagan Libraries without more resources. Mr. Fawcett pointed out that the
                    Presidential libraries have only 5% of the total records at NARA and are often
                    regarded as “country clubs” whose resources can be cut. He noted that NARA's top
                    priority is the new building and that the records in Washington and Suitland
                    have to be processed before they can be moved to a new building.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector argued that NARA has an enormous mission with no resources to fill
                    it. To Mr. Fawcett's statement that the budget process has to have priorities,
                    Dr. Spector asked why NARA did not ask for a bigger “pie.” Mr. Fawcett replied
                    that Don Wilson was asking for a bigger pie but that within the pie he had to
                    make choices. Dr. Spector accused NARA of “doing it backwards” and suggested
                    telling Congress how much it needed. Mr. Fawcett answered that NARA <hi
                        rend="underline">did</hi> tell Congress all of its needs, adding that
                    Congress was sympathetic but not always responsive. He pointed out that Don
                    Wilson has had more meetings with the President than all of his predecessors
                    combined, adding that this President is interested in history. He is trying to
                    raise the Archives' budget incrementally, but to push the Presidential libraries
                    angle would jeopardize other priorities.</p>
                <p>Dr. Spector asked why not say, before a new Presidential library opens, that NARA
                    has to have more resources to operate it. Mr. Fawcett replied that, after having
                    to “cannibalize” other libraries to set up the Carter Library, they had asked
                    for money in advance for the Reagan Library and received it. To Dr. Cohen's
                    suggestion that they transfer some of this to the Kennedy Library, Mr. Fawcett
                    responded that NARA had to spend appropriations as Congress intended.</p>
                <p>To Dr. Spector's accusation that Presidential libraries have had a record of
                    “failure” for the last 15 years, Ms. Van Camp commented that every archival
                    institution in the world has a backlog of unprocessed records.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen pointed out that the Committee's concern was getting material out of
                    the Kennedy and Johnson Libraries, adding that he had done well 10 years ago at
                    the Johnson Library, when working on his book. He asked for an estimated
                    timeframe after which the Committee could tell its constituents that there would
                    be no problem at the Kennedy Library. Mr. Fawcett responded that once the two
                    new staffers were on board, the backlog should be cleared quickly.</p>
                <p>Dr. Cohen asked if there were a way that the Advisory Committee could help the
                    Presidential libraries to get the resources they need. Mr. Fawcett said that one
                    big priority was larger appropriations for declassification; he would put the
                    NARA congressional liaison people in touch with the Committee via the
                    Historian's Office.</p>
                <p>Ms. Van Camp asked about getting clearer guidelines, to which Mr. Fawcett
                    responded that there were problems with either himself or Dr. Slany asking for
                    changes in the Executive Order. Therefore, he suggested that the Committee get
                    in touch with Page Miller, who has been working on this issue. Helping Ms.
                    Miller would help the Presidential libraries.</p>
                <p>The 33rd meeting of the Advisory Committee adjourned at 2:45 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
