<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Draft Letter From W. Lee Rawls to Richard Darman, October
                    1990</title>
                <title type="short">Rawls to Darman, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-06">January 6, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-10-25">October 25, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1990-10-25-rawls-to-darman.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 626 KB, 4pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Front Office
                    Files, 1989-1990 (Lot File 93 D 287), Box 1, PA—Foreign Relations Series 1990.
                    This draft letter was attached to an October 24, 1990 Legislative Referral
                    Memorandum on S. 3225 from the Office of Management and Budget to the National
                    Security Council; the Departments of the Treasury, State, Defense, and Energy;
                    the Central Intelligence Agency; and the General Services Administration. Within
                    the Department of State, Will Davis (Bureau of Legislative Affairs) sent this
                    package to the Bureaus of Legislative Affairs, Management, and Public Affairs
                    and the Office of the Legal Adviser for comments on October 25, 1990. Neither
                    the Department’s response to OMB nor the final draft of Rawls’s letter has been
                    located.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn41">Footnote 41</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Draft Letter From W. Lee Rawls (Assistant Attorney General) to Richard G.
                    Darman (Director of the Office of Management and Budget)</head>
                <p>Dear Mr. Darman:</p>
                <p>This letter sets forth the views of the Department of Justice on S. 3225, which
                    amends the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956, as recently passed by
                    the Senate. See 136 Cong. Rec. §16, 299-301 (daily ed. Oct. 19, 1990). We
                    believe that certain provisions of this bill present constitutional
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>Section 47(a) calls for the preparation and publication of “a thorough, accurate,
                    and reliable documentary record of major United States foreign policy decisions
                    and significant United States diplomatic activity.” § 47(a)(1). The publication
                    is to “include all documents needed to provide a comprehensive record of the
                    major foreign policy decisions and actions of the United States Government.” <hi
                        rend="underline">Id</hi>. To assist in the publication project, agencies
                    would be required to carry out a procedure for declassification of documents. If
                    an agency determined that a document could not be declassified because of “a
                    continuing need to protect sources and methods or other national security
                    information,” the agency would be required to attempt to make such deletions as
                    would make the document declassifiable. § 47(b)(3)(A). An Advisory Committee,
                    which would be created under the bill, could direct the agency to prepare a
                    declassified summary of material so excised if the Committee believed that the
                    record would otherwise be misleading or incomplete. If the Advisory Committee
                    disagreed with the agency’s decisions about deletions or the summary, or if the
                    agency refused to prepare a redacted version of the document or the summary, the
                    Advisory Committee would report to Congress, and the agency would be required to
                    respond to the report. The Advisory Committee could also approve the withholding
                    of documents if, by vote of a majority of its members, it determine that
                    continued secrecy was necessary to avoid “imped[ing] current diplomatic
                    negotiations or other ongoing official activities of the United States
                    Government” or to “condense the record and avoid repetition of needless
                    details.” § 47(c)(7). Documents of the Department of State would automatically
                    be declassified 30 years after the events documented unless their release “would
                    compromise weapons technology important to the national defense of the United
                    States or provide access by other nations to sensitive weapons design
                    information relating to United States or foreign military equipment or relating
                    to United States cryptologic systems or codes,” would create a threat of harm to
                    living persons who gave confidential information to the United States, or would
                    “demonstrably impede current diplomatic negotiations or other ongoing official
                    activities of the United States Government.” § 47(e).</p>
                <p>The Advisory Committee would consist of nine “distinguished historians,” of whom
                    not more than two would be employees of the United States. Members would be
                    appointed by the Secretary of State, with the advice of the Assistant Secretary
                    for Public Affairs. The bill would apparently require the Secretary to select at
                    least one member of the committee from each of the lists prepared by six named
                    historical organizations. Members would serve for a term of three years. The
                    Committee would select its own Chairman, who would serve a term of one year. §
                    47(c).</p>
                <p>We have three objections to S. 3225. First, the bill trenches on the President’s
                    constitutional authority to protect state secrets. Second, it intrudes upon the
                    deliberative privilege for communications within the Executive Branch. Third,
                    the bill does not provide for sufficient presidential direction and control over
                    the operations of the Advisory Committee to be created under the bill.</p>
                <p>1. S. 3225 trenches on the President’s constitutional authority both to protect
                    military, diplomatic, and national security secrets and to safeguard the
                    deliberative process within the Executive Branch. The Constitution vests in the
                    President an expansive authority to protect state secrets from disclosure:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">The President, after all, is the “Commander in
                        Chief of the Army and Navy of the United States.” U.S. Const., Art. II, § 2.
                        His authority to ... control access to information bearing on national
                        security ... flows primarily from this constitutional investment of power in
                        the President and exists quite apart from any explicit congressional grant
                        ... . The authority to protect such information falls on the President as
                        head of the Executive Branch and as Commander in Chief.</quote></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Department of the Navy</hi> v. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Egan</hi>, 484 U.S. 518, 527 (1988) (citations omitted). <hi
                        rend="underline">See United States</hi> v. <hi rend="underline">Nixon</hi>,
                    418 U.S. 683, 710 (1974) (“As to these areas of Art. II duties the courts have
                    traditionally shown the utmost deference to Presidential responsibilities.”).
                    Indeed, the President can assert an absolute privilege against forced disclosure
                    of state secrets: “The [state secrets] privilege, it is clear, is absolute. ‘NO
                    competing public or private interest can be advanced to compel disclosure.’” <hi
                        rend="underline">In re United States</hi>, 872 F.2d 472, 476 (D.C. Cir.)
                        (<hi rend="underline">quoting Ellsberg</hi> v. <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mitchell</hi>, 709 F.2d 51, 57 (D.C. Cir. 1983), <hi rend="underline">cert.
                        denied</hi>, 465 U.S. 1038 (1984)). <hi rend="underline">cert.
                        dismissed</hi>, 110 S. Ct. 398 (1989).</p>
                <p>Moreover, as a practical matter, while S. 3225 may be intended to provide for the
                    release only of information other than state secrets, the procedure to be
                    followed under the bill would create a substantial danger that state secrets
                    would be revealed. First, in the discharge of the duties committed to him by the
                    Constitution, the President cannot be bound by Congress’ determination of what
                    constitutes a secret worthy of protection. There may be unforeseen circumstances
                    in which the grounds for continued secrecy laid out in the bill would be
                    insufficient to reach information that the President considered a state secret.
                    Second, the bill would require the Executive branch to make publication
                    determinations about a vast body of material on unreasonably short notice. By
                    its terms, the bill requires the publication of “all documents needed to provide
                    a comprehensive record of the major foreign policy decisions and actions of the
                    United States Government” and the “published record shall omit no facts which
                    were of importance in reaching a decision.” Publication decisions would have to
                    be made within 60 days after submission of the documents for review. §
                    47(b)(3)(A). These requirements place an unreasonable burden on the Executive
                    Branch and creates a substantial likelihood that state secrets will
                    inadvertently be made public.</p>
                <p>2. S. 3225 would also intrude upon the deliberative privilege for communications
                    within the Executive Branch. That privilege rests on “the necessity for
                    protection of the public interest in candid, objective, and even blunt or harsh
                    opinions in Presidential decisionmaking.” <hi rend="underline">United
                        States</hi> v. <hi rend="underline">Nixon</hi>, <hi rend="underline"
                        >supra</hi>, 418 U.S. at 708. As the Supreme Court has recognized, “[a]
                    President and those who assist him must be free to explore alternatives in the
                    process of shaping policies and making decisions and to do so in a way many
                    would be unwilling to express except privately.” <hi rend="underline">Id</hi>.
                    The revelation of such communications, even long after the events, would have a
                    chilling effect on the candor of executive branch officers and employees. If S.
                    3225 were enacted into law, the President’s advisers would be put on notice that
                    their advice will one day become public, and they may be less “candid,
                    objective, and even blunt or harsh” as a result.</p>
                <p>3. The operations of the “Advisory Committee” under the bill would also be
                    unconstitutional because the Committee would not be subject to sufficient
                    presidential direction and control. The President “may properly supervise and
                    guide [officers’] construction of the statutes under which they act in order to
                    secure that unitary and uniform execution of the laws which Article II of the
                    Constitution evidently contemplated in vesting general executive power in the
                    President alone.” <hi rend="underline">Myers</hi> v. <hi rend="underline">United
                        States</hi>, 272 U.S. 52, 135 (1926). In our view, the power to withhold
                    documents from publication would be the “the performance of a significant
                    governmental duty exercised pursuant to a public law.” Buckley v. <hi
                        rend="underline">Valeo</hi>, 424 U.S. 1, 141 (1976). Such duties may be
                    performed only by “Officers of the United States,” appointed in conformity with
                    the Appointments Clause and subject to presidential direction and control. <hi
                        rend="underline">Id</hi>. S. 3225, however, satisfies neither of these
                    requirements. Notwithstanding that the Advisory Committee has a role in
                    decisions affecting the national security, S. 3225 appears to contemplate that
                    the Advisory Committee would operate in a manner bound to frustrate the “unitary
                    and uniform execution of the laws,” because the Committee would report on
                    disputes within the Executive Branch over declassification decisions, and the
                    agencies would then be required to answer the Advisory Committee’s reports.
                    Furthermore, absent review by principal officers, the members of the Advisory
                    Committee would themselves be principal officers for the purposes of the
                    Appointments Clause, and would have to be appointed by the President with the
                    advice and consent of the Senate. <hi rend="underline">See Morrison</hi> v. <hi
                        rend="underline">Olson</hi>, 108 S. Ct. 2597, 2608-2609 (1988). The
                    President has plenary authority to nominate principal officers, subject only to
                    the advice and consent of the Senate, and the Congress can not dictate the
                    qualifications of the persons to be appointed or require them to be chosen from
                    lists provided by specified non-governmental entities. <hi rend="underline">See
                        Public Citizen</hi> v. <hi rend="underline">U.S. Department of Justice</hi>,
                    109 S. Ct. 2558, 2580-2584 (1989) (Kennedy, J., concurring in the judgment).</p>
                <p>Sincerely,<lb/>W. Lee Rawls</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
