<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1990</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-11-15">November 15, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1990-11-15-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 832 KB, 28pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Front Office
                    Files, 1989-1990 (Lot File 93 D 287), Box 1, FRUS—Advisory Committee 1990 Annual
                    Meeting (11/15-16).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn48">Footnote 48</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1990 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation</head>
                <dateline>November 15-16, 1990</dateline>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Participants:</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Advisory Committee</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Richard Cooper</item>
                    <item>Betty Glad</item>
                    <item>Margaret Hermann</item>
                    <item>George Herring</item>
                    <item>Warren Kimball</item>
                    <item>Bradford Perkins</item>
                    <item>Emily Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Ronald Spector</item>
                    <item>Anne Van Camp</item>
                    <item>Stephen Zamora</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</p>
                <list>
                    <item>G. Alfred Kennedy, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="underline">Office of the Historian</hi></item>
                            <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                            <item>David Baehler</item>
                            <item>Rita Baker</item>
                            <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                            <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                            <item>Taylor Fain</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>Nancy Golden</item>
                            <item>David Herschler</item>
                            <item>Nina Howland</item>
                            <item>Ted Keefer</item>
                            <item>David Mabon</item>
                            <item>Elaine McDevitt</item>
                            <item>Jim Miller</item>
                            <item>Nina Noring</item>
                            <item>Althea Robinson</item>
                            <item>Charles Sampson</item>
                            <item>Bill Sanford</item>
                            <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                            <item>Luke Smith</item>
                            <item>Sherrill Wells</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Division of Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification
                    Review</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Henry Bardach</item>
                    <item>Frank Machak</item>
                    <item>Richard Morefield</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Publishing Services Division</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Barbara Bacon</item>
                    <item>Paul Washington</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Bureau of Legislative Affairs</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Gary Chafin</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of the Legal Adviser</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Katherine Skipper</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George Chalou, National Archives</item>
                    <item>Ron Swerczek, National Archives</item>
                    <item>David Langbart, National Archives</item>
                    <item>J. Kenneth McDonald, Central Intelligence Agency</item>
                    <item>Mary McAuliffe, Central Intelligence Agency</item>
                    <item>Paige Miller, National Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of
                        History</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Open Session, November 15, 1990,
                    Morning</hi></p>
                <p>The Open Session of the 1990 meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical
                    Diplomatic Documentation began at 9:05 a.m. Prof. Richard N. Cooper arrived at
                    9:25. Dr. William Z. Slany proposed that a Chairman be selected and an agenda be
                    adopted. Prof. Warren F. Kimball was selected by acclamation as Chairman. The
                    draft agenda circulated earlier by Slany was adopted provisionally.</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs G. Alfred Kennedy was the first
                    speaker. He stated that the Department wants to cooperate with the Committee and
                    feels its work is important. He mentioned the controversy caused by the
                    resignation of former Chairman Warren Cohen, and said that he did not believe
                    that an Act of Congress would be necessary to improve the series; working in
                    concert with the Committee should be sufficient. Kennedy said that Slany would
                    describe in more detail PA's plan. Once the Department agreed to the plan,
                    coordination with other agencies would be possible. Publication of a volume was
                    not enough; it was necessary for scholars to verify its accuracy, completeness,
                    and integrity. HO was being reorganized to concentrate more resources on
                    compilation and publication. Kennedy concluded by saying that he would report on
                    the meeting to Assistant Secretary Tutwiler.</p>
                <p>Kimball then opened the floor to questions.</p>
                <p>Prof. Bradford Perkins said that Warren Cohen had believed that he had reached an
                    agreement with State, and had quit after State had reneged on it. Last year's
                    meeting, incidentally, had been the first at which neither the Assistant
                    Secretary nor the senior DAS had been present. Perkins was skeptical that State
                    could deliver.</p>
                <p>Kennedy replied that nobody had shown him documentary evidence of a
                    State-Committee agreement; perhaps there was a verbal agreement. It was time to
                    put this issue behind us. The Department wants to deliver on the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The absence of senior people
                    did not mean a lack of commitment. Tutwiler was aware of the problem and had
                    brought more senior people into the discussion. Under Secretary Selin said that
                    he looked forward to meeting with the Advisory Committee. Moreover, a year after
                    Cohen's resignation, the Department senior leadership is engaged with the issue.
                    They are moving to reduce tensions within the agency and to convince the
                    Congress that State can fix the problem. He hoped to have a plan ready before
                    Congress took up the legislation again.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether Advisory Committee members could meet with Tutwiler.
                    Kennedy replied that the request was not unreasonable, but any meeting might
                    take place at short notice.</p>
                <p>Prof. Stephen T. Zamora asked whether State was still uncertain about the
                    Advisory Committee's role. Kennedy denied it. Zamora stated that, after only two
                    meetings, he was unclear about his own role. Slany said that part of the problem
                    was the dynamics of changing Committee membership; he looked forward to a still
                    more active Committee in the months to come.</p>
                <p>Prof. Ronald H. Spector asked whether State had a counterproposal to the
                    legislation which spells out the Advisory Committee's role. Kennedy replied that
                    a work plan was being developed and that possibly Congress could be persuaded
                    that legislative action was unnecessary. Slany would describe the committee's
                    role at greater length.</p>
                <p>Slany stated that the Department lacks unanimity on a definition of the
                    Committee's role. The aim was to give it a more specific role in the production
                    of the volumes and to avoid a repeat of the Iran flap.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked if it were true that someone in FPC had said the Advisory Committee
                    had no “need to know.” Kennedy denied that this was now the case.</p>
                <p>Kimball said that access was the key to the Advisory Committee's evaluation
                    sanction. The Secretary can designate a “need, to know” for State's records. If
                    he does, a major problem is solved. Kennedy replied that Baker was unlikely to
                    say anything that explicit, or that “need to know” would ever be complete. State
                    was trying to upgrade the Committee members' clearances, but even then there
                    would be statutory and other limits. Kimball replied that the key matters were
                   “need to know” and level of access. He was stressing the former, and the
                    Committee's need to have a high-level person come out and say that they had it,
                    within statutory limits.</p>
                <p>Perkins said that he understood from FPC that copies of documents stored in PA/HO
                    for the preparation of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> were temporarily
                    downgraded to Secret. Richard Morefield of FPC/HDR replied that documents were
                    downgraded to Secret for handling purposes only.</p>
                <p>Prof. Margaret Hermann, a new member, expressed surprise that access for the
                    Committee was not automatic. Slany replied that State would consider how to
                    grant access and would work with other agencies on specific topics.</p>
                <p>Prof. Betty Glad asked whether there were any proposals to ease access guideline
                    restrictions. Slany replied that there were no new laws or regulations, just
                    procedural changes to facilitate disclosure.</p>
                <p>Hermann asked whether the Advisory Committee could take one volume and see what
                    was excluded so as to get a better feel for the guidelines. Perkins called the
                    guidelines so vague that even the Declaration of Independence could be kept
                    classified. Much depended on individual FPC members. Slany replied that State is
                    considering involving one or more Committee members in the publication cycle for
                    one volume--a “companion editor”--but that it would take awhile to arrange.
                    Slany said that he had made the proposal to the Committee during the past 2
                    years. Participation would require visiting the Department regularly. Kimball
                    then said that a working session would be necessary to discuss such a proposal.
                    Spector said that the Advisory Committee preferred cooperation to another year
                    of “guerrilla warfare,” but that it could not endorse non-formulated
                    proposals.</p>
                <p>Cooper wanted to know: 1) what were the terms of the Committee's mandate and 2)
                    what were State's objections to the legislation? What specific criteria did they
                    oppose?</p>
                <p>Slany replied that he had identified the Committee's major concerns. The
                    Committee had tried to address issues on a case-by-case basis. Documents from
                    other agencies complicated the declassification process. State was now trying to
                    publish 10 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes each year. Cooper
                    said that if the Committee had no access to classified material, how were they
                    to determine why something was excluded, and wondered what their role was. Slany
                    noted that the Advisory Committee had had “episodic” access during the 1950s,
                    60s, and 70s when questions of skewing the record had arisen. The discussion now
                    centered on a broader mandate. Perkins said that, beginning 4 years ago, FPC
                    began to report excisions to them. Slany replied that such a briefing would be
                    held tomorrow.</p>
                <p>Morefield tried to differentiate between declassification guidelines in the
                    Executive order and the guidelines given to the Archives. Perkins asked whether
                    the general guidelines were classified. He had never seen a copy of them, but
                    they had to differ from the Executive order. Both Cooper and Kimball said that
                    the Committee was very much concerned with NARA's declassification guidelines
                    and would like to see a copy of them, while Spector observed that each agency
                    interpreted the Executive order differently and set its own declassification
                    guidelines. Morefield explained that the Executive order required
                    declassification after systematic review, or else for the agency to give
                    instructions to NARA about what topics still needed protection. Kimball wanted
                    more details on the guidelines and said that the matter should be discussed at
                    greater length.</p>
                <p>Zamora reiterated that the Committee lacks a defined role. The legislation gives
                    it one, although perhaps it is too broad. Kimball stated that the Committee
                    should make clear to the Department what its view of its role is. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and the Department faced a
                    crisis of confidence. The Committee should be ready to help the Department but
                    in order to help, it must have confidence in the Department's operations.</p>
                <p>Slany introduced Gary Chafin from the Department's Bureau of Legislative Affairs
                    who discussed State's reaction to the legislation. Chafin reported that the
                    Department had been surprised at the speedy approval of the bill in the Senate
                    after being told to expect no action. The bill will be reintroduced in the 1991
                    session, probably as part of the Department authorization bill. The House took
                    no action on the bill, but the topic would come up next year in some form.</p>
                <p>H Bureau had sent its objections to the House Foreign Affairs Committee (HFAC)
                    and the Senate Foreign Relations Committee (SFRC), but unless State could
                    present an alternative, Congress would be heard from and hearings might be held.
                    State's first objection to the bill was that it derogated from the Executive
                    order and mandated a piecemeal change in government-wide practice. The major
                    effort is to avoid damage from the legislation.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked what damage the Department envisions. Chafin responded that the
                    legislation would derogate from the Executive order. Legislation should not be
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>-specific.</p>
                <p>Cooper then asked whether State considered the bill too broad or too narrow in
                    scope. Chafin replied that the issue should be addressed in a broader way rather
                    than by disrupting government-wide practices.</p>
                <p>Spector commented that no government-wide declassification now existed; the
                    Executive order was interpreted differently by different agencies. Glad noted
                    that specific legislative action might give a push toward a better
                    government-wide system.</p>
                <p>Chafin noted that a second objection to the legislation was the creation of
                    further layers of bureaucracy. The legislation would also abolish the Committee
                    in its present form. Cooper said “it would not be the end of the world.”</p>
                <p>Glad asked if the Department supported any parts of the legislation. Slany
                    responded that while the Department appreciated the generalized sentiment of
                    support for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in the bill, the question
                    was whether the legislation if passed would make coordination and work on the
                    series more effective.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed at 10:30 a.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 15, 1990,
                        Morning</hi></p>
                <p>The Committee reconvened at 10:50 a.m. Kimball announced that the Committee had
                    decided to depart from the agenda in order to hold a closed, Committee-only
                    session from 3:30 p.m. to the end of the afternoon.</p>
                <p>Paul Washington spoke on the distribution of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Beginning in 1986, the Government Printing Office, in
                    the interest of economy, had distributed 23 volumes of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> to 1,100 depository libraries in microfiche form. This
                    distribution had been completed last April. PA/HO had learned of the conversion
                    to microfiche distribution only 2 years ago. If all the depository libraries
                    were to be given hard copies of each of the 23 volumes, the reprints would cost,
                    at an average of $15 apiece, $379,500, or $16,500 a volume. This cost would be
                    spread over the next 5 years. The question was, who would pay? Some of the
                    depository libraries had indicated a preference for fiche because of space
                    limitations, but 2/3 wanted the printed volumes. If GPO obtains the needed
                    funds, these libraries will be resurveyed to see if they still want the paper
                    copies. There was also the question of whether the depository libraries would
                    receive paper copies of future volumes. Some, again for space reasons, did not
                    want to. Washington also handed out a chart showing availability and sales of
                    in-print <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Cooper wondered how
                    the print run of the volumes was determined, and was told that it was determined
                    by the GPO and was often an odd number.</p>
                <p>Prof. George Herring wondered if the Committee should repeat its recommendation
                    of last year, that the libraries should all receive paper copies. Cooper said
                    that maybe the Committee should not make a recommendation on this point, and
                    allow the libraries to make their own decisions on the basis of their individual
                    use patterns and space availability. Kimball thought that users had the right to
                    put their oar in, and that the Committee were users and serious ones at that.
                    Glad pointed out that paper copies were in the interest of students as well as
                    professors, but there should be provision for microfiche at small
                    depositories.</p>
                <p>It gradually developed from the discussion that GPO's present plan was definitely
                    to have some form of a dual hard copy and microfiche distribution system.
                    Washington and Slany pointed out that this was not wasteful because of the
                    comparative inexpensiveness of microfiche.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested making print over-runs available to individuals. Washington said
                    this would reverse a 10-year policy of maintaining an overstock for future
                    generations of scholars.</p>
                <p>Cooper pointed out that printing costs are a function of technology and that
                    print runs of future volumes would no doubt be less expensive. The discussion
                    closed with the Committee reserving for the time being its position on the
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Slany then presented his report on the status of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. He noted that the Office of the Historian had
                    reorganized in order to assign more historians to work as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> compilers. Only a small staff had guided <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> in recent years, but the pace of the
                    series had not suffered because the declassifiers had been clearing out a large
                    backlog of volumes.</p>
                <p>Now the Office was redeploying its professional staff to keep the pipeline full
                    and to keep the scope of the series in rough equity with that of the three
                    previously-prepared triennia. He introduced the Division Chiefs: Charles
                    Sampson, Europe and Canada; Paul Claussen, East Asia and Latin America; Nina
                    Noring, Middle East, Africa, and South Asia; David Mabon, Arms Control and
                    Economics; Sherrill Wells, General and Special Projects. A total of 19 people
                    will give full or part-time attention to compiling and editing material for the
                    Kennedy years.</p>
                <p>A new Deputy Historian/General Editor was being recruited to give substantive and
                    management guidance to the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> program.
                    Slany asked particularly for the Committee's suggestions regarding potential
                    applicants for this position. The new person, he said, would have primary
                    responsibility for the Kennedy and Johnson periods.</p>
                <p>Slany described briefly the proposed tables of contents for the 1961-1963 period,
                    of which the Committee had received a copy. Although constrained by reduced
                    funding, the Office planned to produce 25 volumes plus microform supplements.
                    The Department sought to match the series at the level of completeness reached
                    by the series for the Eisenhower period. He emphasized that the tables were
                    still flexible and open to the Committee's suggestions. He described the work
                    done so far for the triennium: four volumes on Vietnam, two already published
                    and two in the publication process; two volumes on Laos and Western Europe,
                    delivered to the declassifiers last summer; and five more volumes completed or
                    near completion.</p>
                <p>Slany said that the content and scope of the volumes had become an important
                    topic due to a shrinking resources at the Office's disposal. He discussed the
                    ever-increasing necessity to tighten the standards of selection, again stressing
                    the potential helpfulness of the Committee in making suggestions for items to
                    focus on. It might be necessary to contract-out certain volumes to make up for
                    gaps in the Office's expertise. Another possibility was to do the entire 5 years
                    of the Johnson administration as one unit.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked how it was possible to keep the volume sizes the same given the
                    increase in the number of documents available to historians for this time
                    period. Perhaps a different format was needed for the series to reflect
                    this.</p>
                <p>Slany admitted that an ever smaller percentage of available documents were being
                    printed than in earlier decades, and that fewer of these documents were State
                    Department documents.</p>
                <p>Cooper said that the increase in the number of available documents might
                    necessitate a new strategy for compiling <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Slany said the publication might have to move to a more bibliographic function,
                    serving as an archival source and directing scholars to existing documents not
                    contained in the volumes.</p>
                <p>Perkins said that there was a choice between covering all topics in a shallow
                    manner or reverting to a “post-holing” technique of singling out important
                    issues for detailed coverage while acting as a bibliographic source on
                    others.</p>
                <p>Cooper pointed out that what scholars today may single out for detailed coverage
                    may turn out to be of little importance to future scholars.</p>
                <p>Kimball said the Committee might consider asking HO to prepare a study on this
                    issue to generate thinking on future strategies for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Van Camp agreed and emphasized that the issue needed to be considered beyond that
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested that some guidelines on this subject must already exist for some
                    of the Kennedy volumes to have been compiled and asked Slany to share these.
                    Slany replied that no such explicit guidelines existed.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked that the Committee receive a flow chart showing where each of the
                    planned volumes was in the compilation and publication process. HO had furnished
                    such a chart in previous years and it had been very helpful. Rosenberg requested
                    a chart which would show the proportion of denied materials in each volume as
                    published, for the period 1949-1963.</p>
                <p>The Committee discussed the problems and opportunities presented by
                    computerization of records. David Herschler pointed out that a great many
                    documents never made it into the Department's computerized database. David
                    Langbart, the National Archives specialist on retirement of Department of State
                    records, described the special program for the retirement of lot files from the
                    Executive Secretariat, stressing that these were not, even after accessioning,
                    integrated into the Central Files because they had never been meant to be part
                    of them. Preserving these records was vital because they including many items
                    which, “by both accident and intent,” had not been logged into the automated
                    system. Cooper made a distinction between official and unofficial records but
                    was assured by many of those present that this distinction often broke down in
                    practice.</p>
                <p>Kimball inquired whether these problems were a legitimate concern of the
                    Committee. Van Camp disagreed saying that the topic was fundamental to the
                    Committee and to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. If
                    information were not well-managed, the job of compiling and publishing <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would be made more difficult and would
                    affect the manner in which HO functions. Kimball stated that the Committee
                    should therefore have a statement from the Department on just what its records
                    policy was. Van Camp replied that she thought that such a report might be
                    difficult to generate.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed at 12:05 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Luncheon, November 15, 1990<lb/>Buchanan
                        Room</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Present</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Committee members</item>
                    <item>G. Alfred Kennedy</item>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany</item>
                    <item>John Fawcett, National Archives</item>
                    <item>Elaine McDevitt</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Advisory Committee held a working luncheon. John Fawcett, Director of the
                    Office of Presidential Libraries, National Archives and Records Administration,
                    joined the Committee as did Deputy Assistant Secretary Kennedy and Special
                    Assistant Povenmire. In informal discussions during the meal the Committee
                    members reviewed the morning proceedings and Fawcett's efforts to improve the
                    public use of documents at some of the more newly-established Presidential
                    libraries.</p>
                <p>As the meal ended, Under Secretary Selin joined the Committee. The Under
                    Secretary greeted the Committee and expressed his appreciation for its valuable
                    advice to the Department and the Historian. He assured the Committee of the
                    Department's continuing commitment to an accurate and comprehensive <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The Under Secretary personally
                    acknowledged the importance of the Advisory Committee's role in verifying the
                    accuracy of published volumes in the series. He was quite aware that the
                    Committee members could not evaluate the quality of books proposed for
                    publication unless they could themselves see what was deleted during the
                    declassification process. Only that sort of examination could determine whether
                    the printed record was distorted in any important way. He recognized that
                    Committee members' access to classified records was absolutely indispensable for
                    them to do their work.</p>
                <p>Under Secretary Selin understood that the process of providing Committee members
                    with Top Secret clearances was underway. He warned that the process could be
                    lengthy, and the whole Advisory Committee might not have their clearances soon.
                    The Under Secretary reminded the Advisory Committee of the difficulties in
                    expediting clearances. He suggested that the Committee might want to form a
                    subcommittee or working party of those members who were cleared by the spring of
                    1991 in order to get on with the process of reviewing classified records
                    withheld from a volume or volumes proposed by the Department Historian for
                    Committee scrutiny.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Kimball regarding the relative uselessness of
                    security clearances without a “need to know,” Under Secretary Selin assured the
                    Advisory Committee that it would, of course, have such a “need.”</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary took up the question of the pending Congressional bill
                    regarding the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. There were many
                    problems with the existing draft legislation. The Department knew that it had to
                    improve the series and was certain it could do so far better than Congress
                    could. The Department had, however, been slow in bringing before the
                    Congressional committees the Department's views on the legislation and its plans
                    to assure the accuracy and completeness of the published record. The Under
                    Secretary assured the Committee that the Department would have its action plan
                    on the reform of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in the
                    hands of the relevant Congressional committees before Congress convened on
                    January 17, 1991. The Advisory Committee would be consulted and kept informed
                    about the contents of the plan.</p>
                <p>Under Secretary Selin responded to the Advisory Committee members who anticipated
                    they might be involved in the expected Congressional hearings in 1991 regarding
                    the legislation. He acknowledged that the members of the Committee might be
                    asked to comment to the Congress regarding the legislation. The Committee was,
                    however, a creation of the Department, and the Under Secretary could not imagine
                    how the Committee as a whole could possibly take a formal, public position
                    regarding the legislation, especially legislation that the Department
                    opposed.</p>
                <p>Perkins was particularly concerned to know if the Under Secretary understood the
                    importance to the Advisory Committee of access to the Department guidelines for
                    the page-by-page declassification review of Department documentation transferred
                    to the National Archives. The Committee felt strongly that its mandate must not
                    be confined to documents included in particular <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes but must extend to the larger body of Department
                    documentation from which the contents of the printed volumes were drawn. Under
                    Secretary Selin acknowledged that the Committee's access to the Department's
                    relevant systematic review declassification guidelines was necessary to allow it
                    to fully evaluate the accuracy and completeness of the published historical
                    record and other records made accessible to the public at the National
                    Archives.</p>
                <p>Under Secretary Selin concluded his remarks to the Advisory Committee by assuring
                    them of the Department's intention to move quickly to perfect its planning for
                    an improved <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and the hope that
                    the Committee can work with the Department and the Historian in modernizing the
                    publication.</p>
                <p>The luncheon concluded at 1:45 p.m.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Closed Session, November 15, 1990, Afternoon</p>
                <p rend="underline">Others Present</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John Fawcett, National Archives</item>
                    <item>Nancy Smith, National Archives</item>
                    <item>Thomas Thorne, PA/HO</item>
                </list>
                <p>The session reconvened at 2 p.m.</p>
                <p>John Fawcett summarized the Presidential libraries' former procedure of
                    simultaneously processing classified documents for use by PA/HO historians and
                    for the public at large. Because this procedure did not adequately meet PA/HO
                    needs, materials are now partially processed for Department of State historians
                    in order of priority for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Fawcett reported there were over 20 visits by PA/HO historians to the John F.
                    Kennedy Library during 1989. He also reported resources were increased at the
                    Lyndon B. Johnson and Kennedy Libraries to expedite the examination of documents
                    by Department of State historians.</p>
                <p>Slany stated these procedures and additional resources had definitely enhanced
                    research performed by PA/HO historians. He briefly outlined the PA/HO
                    reorganization, and said the reorganization will increase the number of
                    historians performing research at Presidential libraries during 1992 and 1993.
                    Slany indicated he would work out a schedule of visits by PA/HO historians to
                    Presidential libraries that “won't overwhelm everyone,” and that PA/HO
                    historians would only resort to using Presidential libraries for documents not
                    found elsewhere. Fawcett said it would be helpful and essential for the
                    Presidential libraries to have as much advance notification as possible of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> needs.</p>
                <p>Fawcett and his assistant, Nancy Smith, stated that access by PA/HO to documents
                    is typically much easier directly at the agency level than at Presidential
                    libraries because of the NSC's review procedure. As an example, Fawcett outlined
                    the following procedure for historians to gain access to classified NSC and
                    White House documents at Presidential libraries: 1) the NSC is notified PA/HO
                    would like to review a certain file or files, 2) NSC is notified a second time
                    when PA/HO requests a copy of the documents, and 3) NSC is asked to review
                    compilations for declassification.</p>
                <p>Charles Sampson noted, however, that the NSC has never denied PA/HO timely access
                    to documents.</p>
                <p>Fawcett referred to a recent article in the <hi rend="italic">Washington
                        Post</hi> that reported former Secretary of State George Shultz had removed
                    copies of his official papers. Fawcett commented that Secretary Shultz was the
                    first Secretary of State to have implemented a procedure for removing his
                    papers, and that all classified documents are in the Federal Records Center
                    managed by the National Archives in San Bruno, California.</p>
                <p>Sampson, speaking on behalf of PA/HO, expressed appreciation for all the
                    assistance provided by Suzanne Forbes at the Kennedy Library.</p>
                <p>The session adjourned for a break.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 15, 1990,
                        Afternoon</hi></p>
                <p>Thomas Thorne made a presentation on the volume on the relationship between
                    intelligence and U.S. foreign policy that will supplement the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. The project had been started several years
                    ago, interrupted, then resumed in May 1990 on a part-time basis (about 60
                    percent). The majority of the material had been collected before he began work
                    on the project although some collecting is still being done with the aid of the
                    CIA. Compilation and annotation should be completed in early 1991.</p>
                <p>The volume will be a combination fiche and print publication covering the
                    formation of the intelligence community during the period 1945-1950. The project
                    will comprise about 3,400 pages of documents: 2,200 pages of memoranda, reports,
                    minutes; and 1,200 pages of finished intelligence, i.e., estimates, intelligence
                    memoranda to the President which transmitted raw intelligence data (about 1/4 of
                    the 1,200 pp.).</p>
                <p>Thorne explained his standards of selection:</p>
                <p>1) In compiling an institutional history, he sought to cover the main issues and
                    themes of the beginning of the intelligence community: military vs. civilian
                    control, size of the agency, the origins of covert action in the late 1940s, the
                    integration of clandestine intelligence collection, and the development of the
                    evaluative and estimating process.</p>
                <p>2) He also included samples of finished intelligence (to be reproduced in the
                    fiche portion), including estimative material, and interagency intelligence
                    estimates for the period 1946 through mid-1950 until the outbreak of the Korean
                    war.</p>
                <p>In collecting the documentation, Thorne discovered that materials are widely
                    scattered among government agencies and within agencies: Central and lot files
                    of the Department of State, Truman Presidential Library, Military Record Groups
                    at NARA, Bureau of the Budget (especially 1943-1946), and other files at NARA.
                    There are a few record collections that have cumulated material that would be
                    otherwise difficult to locate. He cited the Troy Papers at NARA and the
                    collections at the CIA History staff. Overall, he found CIA records rather
                    difficult to use because he had no direct access to the files but had to go
                    through the History Staff. Nor are there any finding aids that would facilitate
                    research. Recordkeeping in the early years of the Agency was neither regularized
                    nor centralized.</p>
                <p>A “surprising” amount of material has already been declassified except in two
                    categories: covert actions and the origins of clandestine intelligence
                    collection. Thorne was optimistic, however, that the age of the documents and
                    already-released information would help to overcome problems in declassifying
                    these documents.</p>
                <p>J. Kenneth McDonald, Historian of the CIA, characterized the volume on
                    intelligence as a model of collaboration between the Agency and PA/HO. In 1985,
                    the Agency inaugurated its Historical Review Program to review and release
                    records and established an advisory panel of consultants consisting of both
                    government officials and distinguished historians. Under systematic
                    declassification, the CIA has released two histories of the early years of the
                    Agency.</p>
                <p>McDonald cited the two recently-published histories: one by Arthur Darling
                    published in November 1989 covering the 1945-1950 period and one by Ludwell
                    Montague published in September 1990 covering Walter Bedell Smith's tenure as
                    Director of Central Intelligence. The Agency was currently working on
                    declassifying supporting documents for the first history.</p>
                <p>Mary McAuliffe, Deputy Historian of the CIA, reiterated Thorne's statement of the
                    difficulty of using the CIA files. She attributed this difficulty to two
                    factors:</p>
                <p>1) there has been no orderly recordkeeping in the CIA, leading to great
                    difficulties in finding early documents; and</p>
                <p>2) the compartmentalization of the Agency has resulted in each directorate
                    maintaining separate files.</p>
                <p>The CIA History Staff, mostly historians on the staff engaged in writing
                    histories, has made an effort to collect some source documents from around the
                    agency. This cooperative project with Thorne has stimulated more of this effort
                    to collect and identify files within the Agency.</p>
                <p>In response to a question regarding future intelligence volumes for the post-1950
                    period, McDonald said CIA had no plans to produce more special volumes. [The
                    State Department Historical Office, however, will be planning intelligence
                    supplements to span the Eisenhower period.] McAuliffe looked forward to building
                    on the close and productive working relationship the CIA History Staff and the
                    State historians--Bill Deary, Neal Petersen, Ted Keefer, and now Tom Thorne--had
                    developed in working on this volume.</p>
                <p>In regard to including documents on specific covert actions, Thorne noted that
                    the volume was only a broad overview of the subject and contained no details on
                    specific actions. There were, however, specific intelligence estimates on, for
                    example, Soviet military strength, included in the documents that would be
                    reproduced in the microfiche portion of the publication.</p>
                <p>On the issue of State historians' access to CIA records, which Zamora pointed out
                    was a problem identified last year, Slany said that access to CIA records in the
                    files of other government agencies was better, but there are no doubt episodes
                    for which State does not have access to key documentation. McDonald again made
                    his point that the problem is not access but declassification, which the CIA
                    History Staff can facilitate somewhat by acting as a broker with the CIA
                    declassification staff.</p>
                <p>The issue of requesting access to CIA records at the Presidential Libraries or
                    requesting access directly from the CIA was discussed. The intelligence
                    documents at the Libraries were generally quite accessible and allowed the
                    historians a larger selection; the CIA records are dispersed throughout the
                    Agency and are extremely difficult to find or gain access to even for CIA
                    historians. There are few if any finding aids. Nonetheless, as McDonald pointed
                    out, the collaboration between Thorne and McAuliffe should be used as a model
                    for designing future State-CIA cooperative research for <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if there were a position the Committee could take in this issue
                    that could be helpful. Hermann noted it appeared that beyond urging continued
                    close cooperation between the CIA and the State Department, no further Committee
                    statement was necessary.</p>
                <p>McDonald digressed to speak about the legislation and the problems it posed for
                    the agencies in the foreign affairs community. The legislation proposed
                    establishing a “super declassification board,” a panel made up of historians
                    that would determine ultimate declassification. The panel would institute
                    sanctions on the agency involved. McDonald indicated that an
                    Executive/Congressional quarrel was not the best way to solve the
                    declassification impasse. In response to a question, however, McDonald said that
                    the CIA was not working on alternatives to the legislation.</p>
                <p>Slany expressed his and the Office's appreciation for Thorne's contribution to
                    the progress on the important project of an intelligence supplement to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, due largely to Thorne's
                    experience as the former Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research.
                    Hopefully the volume would be published in 1993.</p>
                <p>Cooper asked about the possibility of publishing National Intelligence Estimates
                    which represented finished intelligence stripped of all references to sources
                    and methods. The NIEs were important in the policymaking process. He wondered
                    why it was so difficult to declassify them. McDonald and McAuliffe agreed.</p>
                <p>Morefield and McDonald explained that publishing the NIEs as a series of numbered
                    documents could reveal long-term trends of intelligence collection and methods
                    of analysis and evaluation--the so-called “mosaic argument”.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that the Committee would take the position that inclusion of NIEs
                    would be very valuable to the published record and would urge their
                    declassification.</p>
                <p>McAuliffe briefly summarized the guidelines of declassification of covert actions
                    that the Agency uses: no presence in foreign countries and no activities in
                    foreign countries are acknowledged by the Agency, unless a “window” has been
                    opened by, for example, the assassination of a CIA Station Chief.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 16, 1990,
                        Morning</hi></p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Participants</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Advisory Committee</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Warren Kimball, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Betty Glad</item>
                    <item>George Herring</item>
                    <item>Bradford Perkins</item>
                    <item>Emily Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Ann Van Camp</item>
                    <item>Stephen Zamora</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</p>
                <list>
                    <item>G. Alfred Kennedy, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <item><hi rend="underline">Office of the Historian</hi></item>
                            <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                            <item>PA/HO Staff</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Office of Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification
                    Review</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Richard Morefield</item>
                    <item>Hugh McL. Woodward</item>
                    <item>Philip Valdes</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George Chalou, National Archives</item>
                    <item>Mary McAuliffe, Central Intelligence Agency</item>
                    <item>Kenneth McDonald, Central Intelligence Agency</item>
                    <item>Nancy Smith, National Archives</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Committee convened at 9 a.m. Slany circulated to the members: 1) copies of
                    model pages for a facsimile edition of a <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volume, and 2) copies of a 1988 memorandum outlining various
                    options for the future format of the series.</p>
                <p>Morefield said that he wished to brief the Committee on the work of his unit, the
                    Historical Documents Review Staff of the Division of Freedom of Information,
                    Privacy, and Classification Review (FPC/HDR), prior to the volume briefings to
                    be given by Philip Valdes on the 1955-1957 Eastern European volume, and by Hugh
                    Woodward on the 1958-1960 Cuba volume.</p>
                <p>Morefield explained the relationship of HDR to other elements of the IS
                    bureaucracy. He said that HDR's work fell into three areas: 40 percent of the
                    time was spent reviewing for declassification <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes and other special projects submitted by HO (such as
                    the intelligence volume discussed yesterday or a lot file project on the
                    Secretary of State's Memoranda of Conversation); 40 percent of the time was
                    spent on systematic review of the Department's documents as part of the transfer
                    to the National Archives; and 20 percent of the time went to other agency
                    support. He used this breakdown to underline that HDR could only devote less
                    than half of its time to reviewing <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Morefield emphasized that the production of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes should be viewed as a pipeline. He pointed out that
                    over the last 5 years many volumes had been leaving the pipeline, but few had
                    been entering it. This was not completely HO's fault, but rather reflected the
                    difficulty in gaining access to Kennedy Library documentation. But the paucity
                    of volumes entering the pipeline had created programming problems for HDR which
                    had to properly oversee its budget and inform annuitants whether their services
                    would be required during the coming year. He said that recently HDR and HO had
                    been working toward achieving a schedule that would help address these
                    problems.</p>
                <p>Morefield said that HO had three problems in regard to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series:</p>
                <p>1) How to handle editorially the growing number of issues within increasing space
                    limitations. He expressed concern that if HO did not cover a particular issue
                    for space reasons and did not explain this in a preface, then the reader would
                    presume that the HDR “troglodytes” had rejected it;</p>
                <p>2) How to handle the subject of covert activities when a government-wide decision
                    denies their declassification. Morefield indicated two recently declassified <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes which handled the intelligence
                    question adroitly: the coverage of assassination intrigue by using Church
                    Committee hearings and coverage within the Suez volume of the impact of
                    intelligence on the decisionmaking process; and</p>
                <p>3) How to achieve objectives with declining available resources. HDR, he pointed
                    out, needed to know when <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> manuscript was
                    going to be submitted to HDR because it had to deal with staff and budget
                    limitations.</p>
                <p>Morefield then briefly summarized recent discussions between HO and HDR which had
                    produced a schedule for the submission for review of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes through March 1991. Morefield pointed out that the
                    scheduling question involved the size of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and the need to abide by plans and agreements
                    made.</p>
                <p>Morefield also raised the question of joint planning. In August and September a
                    schedule had been worked out through March 1991. He referred to a 1986
                    memorandum by the declassification leadership that committed the Department to
                    fewer and smaller volumes. According to Morefield, HO had reneged on this, and
                    now FPC will be stretched to the limit to meet demands posed by the documenting
                    of the Kennedy administration.</p>
                <p>Morefield praised the briefing on the intelligence volume given the previous day
                    and said that HO should provide HDR with similar briefings on all volumes. He
                    felt the remark that most of the documents had already been declassified was
                    particularly helpful.</p>
                <p>Morefield described the lengths of time involved in each step of the
                    declassification process. The initial HDR review, during which the HDR reviewer
                    consulted with the appropriate State Department desk, took 6-9 months for an
                    800-page volume. When this was completed, HO could if it wished appeal the
                    results. Simultaneously documents were sent to other government agencies and,
                    when necessary, to foreign governments. This second step took 6-9 months, during
                    which time HDR had no control over the process. Once these reviews were
                    received, documents were then sent once again to the desk and then to NSC.
                    Following NSC review, the volume once more went through the desks. HO could
                    appeal the results when the process was done and this appeal might take a year.
                    The whole declassification process (without the appeals) takes 2 to 2-1/2 years.
                    With publication time included, it is around 3 years if all goes well.</p>
                <p>Perkins recalled that several years ago HO had prepared flow charts for each of
                    the volumes which were quite helpful in determining which component of the
                    process was responsible for delay. He recalled that the last flow chart he had
                    seen showed that the major delay was at the NSC. Morefield replied that by
                    detailing FPC staff to NSC they had resolved this problem. Kimball suggested
                    that HO prepare a type of “buck sheet” (as “flow chart” was an out-of-date
                    concept) that would indicate who was responsible for which deletions.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that 6 to 9 months seemed very long to him; he wondered why it took
                    so long. Morefield replied that some reviewers keep going back to the bureaus to
                    get as much as possible released. He reviewed their efforts with NSC and
                    explained how FPC had cut back on the amount of material sent to other agencies.
                    He raised FPC's brokering of the NIE and SNIE reports with CIA.</p>
                <p>Kimball assumed that the Committee would obtain access to denied and excised
                    documents and stressed the need to know which agency had denied or excised a
                    document. He felt the Committee could not do its job without this access.
                    Morefield stated that access would be a problem and stressed that pointing
                    fingers at other agencies would be counter-productive.</p>
                <p>Kimball replied that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> was authorized by a
                    Presidential directive and Executive order. Morefield noted that nonetheless it
                    was hard to get other agencies to spend money for our programs and that
                    finger-pointing would only make it harder.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if FPC could reverse NSC decisions.</p>
                <p>Morefield indicated that it could not and that in any case it was probably
                    imprudent to do so. He indicated that State had to give consideration to other
                    agency concerns, because if an agency feels it has been hurt by a State release
                    it will not cooperate further. Morefield then went on to describe the INFORM
                    system for tracking declassified documents and making them available to the
                    public. He noted that as soon as a volume was published there were requests for
                    the documents cross-referenced and for those excised as well.</p>
                <p>There followed a brief discussion on the limits on earnings of the FPC staff
                    annuitants.</p>
                <p>Morefield then stressed that clearance of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes was not the top FPC priority. He could juggle the
                    staff within a quarter but had to balance HO demands against those of Archives.
                    FPC could not ignore its mandate to turn over to the Archives State Department
                    files at about the 30-year line. He reiterated that for the past year and a half
                    he had been trying to get a schedule from HO without success and that finally he
                    had given HO the parameters of what FPC could handle: he asked that HO spread
                    out submission of manuscript over a given year and that it not all be on one
                    subject.</p>
                <p>Slany observed that he had given FPC preliminary schedules and that the present
                    one stretched into 1992.</p>
                <p>Van Camp believed a long-range plan would help. She asked how the 30-year line in
                    the proposed legislation would affect FPC. Morefield replied that this would
                    detract from the effort to clear <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes since more time would be needed to do the processing.</p>
                <p>As Morefield concluded his remarks, Kimball brought up a letter from a number of
                    HDR staffers recently published in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Service
                        Journal</hi>. Kimball particularly objected to the statement that the
                    mandate of the Committee did not include declassification. Kimball called this
                   “wrong.” He said it did not reflect the cooperative attitude that the Committee
                    was trying to encourage with the declassification unit and said he was “deeply
                    troubled” by it. Kimball said it reflected an attitude problem in HDR.</p>
                <p>Morefield responded that the Committee and part of the Department had differing
                    views on the Committee's mandate. Morefield said there was not more specificity
                    in the Committee's charter because agreement could not be reached within the
                    State Department.</p>
                <p>Perkins stressed that was old business. The Committee felt strongly that it was
                    advisory on declassification as well since as the volumes became more selective
                    in the face of exponentially growing numbers of records, this function would
                    become even more important. Perkins pointed out that as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> was forced to become more and more selective from
                    the mass of documentation, it was more and more imperative for the Committee to
                    become involved in the general declassification issue.</p>
                <p>The meeting then turned to the declassification briefing of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>, 1955-1957, volume XXV, Eastern Europe. Kimball
                    posed the question of whether in the absence of appropriate access to documents
                    the Committee members wished to hear the briefings at all, as this would be a
                    form of acquiescence in the denial of access. The Committee disagreed and
                    consideration turned to the briefing.</p>
                <p>This portion of the minutes is Confidential and is maintained as a separate
                    document.</p>
                <p>The meeting recessed at 10:30 a.m. for a break.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 16, 1990,
                        Morning</hi></p>
                <p>The Committee reconvened at 10:45 a.m. to hear Frank Sieverts of the Senate
                    Foreign Relations Committee (SFRC) staff and Jim Curry of the Senate Select
                    Committee on Intelligence (SSCI) staff discuss the proposed <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> legislation.</p>
                <p>Sieverts began by explaining the genesis of the bill. The impetus for the
                    legislation came from the extensive public criticism of alleged significant
                    omissions in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952-1954, Iran. This
                    included criticism by all the major historical organizations. This criticism had
                    come to the attention of the SFRC, its Chairman, Senator Claiborne Pell, and its
                    ranking minority member, Senator Jesse Helms. Senators Pell and Helms had found
                    allies in the majority and minority leaders of the SSCI, Senators David Boren
                    and William Cohen.</p>
                <p>When the Senators focused on the problem, they had discovered that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had no legislative mandate: “it exists
                    because it exists”. Sieverts explained that this was reason to worry because the
                    Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> had once existed and is no
                    more. Given the fate of the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, which also lacked a
                    mandate, Sieverts felt that it was important to provide the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series with one.</p>
                <p>Sieverts outlined the history of the bill. It was approved by the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee as an amendment to a Department of State supplemental
                    authorization bill; the Department of State then determined that it did not
                    require the supplemental authorization; the legislation was then introduced as a
                    free-standing bill. It was passed by the Senate in the final days of the last
                    session (thereby constituting an “action of the Senate”), but did not become law
                    because there was no corresponding House of Representatives action.</p>
                <p>Sieverts predicted that in early 1991 the Senate and House bill would be added to
                    a “must” authorization bill for Department of State funding. He expected it to
                    be passed in mid-February and noted that interested parties had until then to
                    make comments and suggestions.</p>
                <p>Sieverts then asked the Advisory Committee for advice regarding the proposed
                    legislation which, he noted, authorizes the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series as a continuing responsibility of the U.S. Government
                    and gives the Advisory Committee <hi rend="underline">legal</hi> status, thereby
                    making both <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and the existence of the
                    Committee a matter of law. The legislation also spells out goals for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>; provides a set of principles for the
                    series; defines the function of the Advisory Committee; and provides for
                    automatic declassification of Department of State documents after 30 years. It
                    also creates a procedure for the inclusion of intelligence materials in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Sieverts explained that the goal of the legislation was to get HO historians
                    fullest access to Department of State and other government agency documents. He
                    said that the SFRC had received wide public support and interest and repeated
                    that he was confident that the legislation would pass. He then asked Jim Curry
                    to discuss the Department of State's response to the proposed legislation, a
                    letter dated October 25 from Assistant Secretary of State for Legislative
                    Affairs Janet Mullins to Dante Fascell, Chairman of the House Committee on
                    Foreign Affairs.</p>
                <p>Curry began by explaining that he too was trained as an historian, with a Ph.D.
                    from the University of Virginia. He pointed out that neither Senator Boren nor
                    Senator Cohen would ever do anything to damage U.S. intelligence equities and
                    noted that they had had extensive discussions with CIA representatives to ensure
                    that the legislation <hi rend="underline">would</hi> protect U.S.
                    intelligence.</p>
                <p>Noting that many documents use code words, Curry declared that the Mullins letter
                    could have used “hyperbole” and “paranoia” as its codewords. He considered the
                    letter a statement of official Department of State opposition to the bill. For
                    example, her letter claims that the legislation derogates from the
                    government-wide system for declassification provided by Executive Order 12356.
                    Curry pointed out, however, that in fact the legislation leaves declassification
                    in the hands of the originating agencies, but requires that those agencies
                    attempt to declassify documents for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> and
                    tries to establish procedures for the submission of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> documents to agencies for declassification. It also calls for
                    unclassified abstracts or summaries of documents that cannot be
                    declassified.</p>
                <p>Curry argued that 30-year-old documents--except those dealing with certain
                    activities--do not need to be remain classified. Embarrassment and stupidity
                    should not be used as grounds for denial. The American people are entitled to
                    know the basis for U.S. foreign policy and 30 years is <hi rend="underline"
                        >not</hi> too short a time. It was not true that U.S. national security
                    would be endangered by the legislation. National security would be protected,
                    but would not be used as an excuse for withholding documents.</p>
                <p>Curry also dealt with the contention that the proposed bill would conflict with
                    the Atomic Energy Act, the National Security Act of 1947, or other legislation.
                    He believed that with reason and responsibility, the material could be
                    released.</p>
                <p>Curry denied the letter's complaint that preparation of unclassified abstracts or
                    summaries of withheld documents under the proposed bill would be a fiscal
                    problem for the Department and said that only a handful of documents would need
                    summarizing. If more resources were required, the Department should ask Congress
                    for the money. He also disagreed with the letter's contention that the Advisory
                    Committee would become a high-level review body, rather than a scholarly
                    advisory body. Some additional work would be required but Curry pointed out that
                    the Committee would be authorized to review <hi rend="underline"
                    >procedures</hi>, which should not take too much more time. Under the
                    legislation, the Committee would have access, would receive a sampling of
                    documents, and would know what had been left out of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked for an explanation of the end of the process if the Advisory
                    Committee did not agree with declassification decisions. Curry responded that
                    the agency would then have to make a case to the SFRC and the HFAC for
                    withholding the document. However, he described this as a “sanity check” and
                    said that the committees would not force an agency to release withheld
                    documents; the originating agency would always have the final say.</p>
                <p>Glad asked whether this would be micromanagement. Curry replied that he hoped
                    not, but noted that sometimes Congress needed to micromanage. She then asked
                    whether dealing with reports on declassification disputes would be a burden for
                    Congress. Curry replied that this procedure was supposed to encourage settlement
                    of differences. Congressional committees get such reports all the time. Also the
                    reports would be used only as a last resort and he did not believe they would be
                    particularly burdensome.</p>
                <p>Zamora commented that the proposed legislation did not seem to change the
                    declassification guidelines, except for the Department of State. He pointed out
                    that the exception no. 3 allowed documents to be withheld if their release would
                    demonstrably impede current diplomatic negotiations or other ongoing official
                    activities of the U.S. Government and said that “other activities” seemed
                    awfully broad. Sieverts explained that some historians wanted to allow only very
                    specific and limited grounds for denial. The drafters had to have guidelines
                    flexible enough to protect national security, but these were not to be used as
                    loopholes to avoid declassification.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked what the differences were between the Senate and House bills.
                    Noting that the legislation would be redrafted in the next session, Sieverts
                    said that there were only minor differences. He explained, for example, that the
                    House bill specified when terms of Committee members were to start and said that
                    the Senate would probably adopt the House language. Perkins noted that the House
                    language also tightened up the date in which the system would go into effect.
                    Sieverts observed that, if anything, the House was more suspicious than the
                    Senate about declassification.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the legislation applied only to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> or did it apply to documents accessioned by the National
                    Archives as well. Sieverts responded that it would certainly apply as well to
                    the documents destined for the Archives because of the provision for automatic
                    declassification after 30 years. Curry added that the Advisory Committee would
                    review Department of State declassification <hi rend="underline"
                    >procedures</hi>, but would only receive a sampling of withheld documents.
                    Committee members would not become declassifiers. Sieverts pointed out that the
                    new automatic declassification process would be simpler than the current system.
                    After 30 years, the burden of proof would be shifted to the agency.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that the Committee was most concerned about the guidelines.</p>
                <p>Sieverts stated that if the bill was adopted the guidelines would be changed and
                    it would make declassification easier. With a tip of the hat to Senator Helms,
                    he suggested that the present system of declassification could be viewed as
                   “Corporate Statism” whereby the government controlled release of historical
                    materials. The bill envisioned a “Free Enterprise” approach in which private
                    scholars would take control. There was general awe that Sieverts had managed to
                    hit the appropriate ideological buttons with that analogy.</p>
                <p>Perkins complained that it was “not quite fair” to assume that the Department
                    declassifiers automatically wanted to keep documents classified and asked
                    whether action by the Department to change its declassification modus operandi
                    would mean that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation would not
                    be needed. Curry said that he agreed that this might have been possible if the
                    Department had cooperated, but pointed out that it had been fighting the
                    legislation “tooth and nail.” Perkins asked if a new law was necessary, to which
                    Curry replied yes.</p>
                <p>Herring commented that the focus of the bill had been on Department of State
                    records and asked what about those of other agencies, noting that such agencies
                    presented an increasing share of policy and declassification problems. Sieverts
                    replied that the origins of the bill had been Department of State problems and
                    concern over material omitted from <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, but
                    agreed that this was just a beginning. He noted that use of the documents of
                    other agencies was a growing problem for historians, even those with access. He
                    pointed out that earlier intelligence documents had been transmitted through the
                    Department of State. This was no longer true, but if historians lacked access to
                    these documents, they would not have a full picture of what happened. The
                    legislation constituted an important step in the right direction. Curry added
                    that release of CIA documents will, of course, be difficult, but he believed
                    that the bill was a major step forward.</p>
                <p>Kimball expressed concern that the proposed language on the content of the series
                    might prevent necessary changes and reforms. He asked what would happen if HO
                    were to claim that because there were too many documents, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> should become a finding aid consisting primarily of
                    indexes and bibliographical information. Would the legislation prevent this?
                    Curry said yes, it would prevent changing the basic format of the series. He
                    argued that this was a good thing because <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> constituted a major resource for historians who cannot come
                    to Washington. Curry noted that he had used <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> as an undergraduate; he argued that the government should
                    continue to publish the series and try to make it as comprehensive as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>Kimball repeated that he was concerned with the practical aspects of producing
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Would the legislation be an
                    obstacle to reforms in 15 years?</p>
                <p>Sieverts suggested that there might be a point at which major changes in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would become necessary. Sieverts
                    thought this would perhaps occur with the Department's 1973 conversion to
                    electronic record-keeping and he saw that as a time to consider changes. Clearly
                    automatic declassification would then be necessary. Sieverts stated that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had a special status and the
                    legislation sought to preserve it.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked what would happen if the Historical Office needed to expand
                    resources to maintain the format? Curry answered that the Department should come
                    to Congress with an appropriation request.</p>
                <p>Van Camp commented that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> might have to be
                    reformed in 2 years, not 15; thus perhaps the legislation was not realistic.
                    Curry asked why it would be necessary or desirable to change <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> to merely an index of documents.</p>
                <p>Kimball retracted that example as too extreme, but wondered again if the
                    Department of State and the Advisory Committee decided to change the format,
                    would the bill impede that? Would reform be possible without a new law? He
                    observed that the legislative process wasn't neat and clean.</p>
                <p>Sieverts stated that the Congress would certainly be prepared to think about
                    change, especially in connection with electronic record-keeping and computerized
                    access. It would be prepared to look at how these developments would affect <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. Curry suggested that if the Department
                    did not work with the Congress it would find that the bill “would be rammed down
                    their throat”. So far, the Department had responded only with a flat “no”.</p>
                <p>Zamora asked whether the Department could forestall the legislation by
                    instituting a new plan. Sieverts replied yes, but argued that <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> needed a legislative mandate; thus, they intended to
                    go forward with the legislation. Important declassification and <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> goals belong in the law. In addition,
                    Curry pointed out this could not be done just by the Department of State.
                    Obviously State cannot force access by other agencies, but the bill can. Van
                    Camp asked how legislation would do this. Curry said that the bill sets it out
                    in law.</p>
                <p>McDonald agreed with the basic intent of the legislation but had some
                    reservations. The provisions for access to CIA material would mean that scores,
                    if not more, people would have access to extraordinarily sensitive material. It
                    was not just the case of compiler and reviewing editor of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi>, but numerous officials in State, CIA, Congress, the
                    Advisory Committee, etc., down the line. It increased the risks of leakage.</p>
                <p>McDonald also observed that the Advisory Committee was now an amateur, temporary
                    body. The law would transform it into a different organization and require it to
                    become more bureaucratic. It might even develop its own staff. He noted that the
                    present system was slow, frustrating, and arcane, but wondered if the new system
                    contemplated under the bill would be any better.</p>
                <p>Kimball said that the question was who watches the watchdogs? McDonald suggested
                    that they might limit complete access to 2-3 Advisory Committee members who
                    would report to the whole Committee. He reminded the Committee that with
                    official access comes responsibilities including an agreement to pre-publication
                    review. Access to Top Secret documents changes what you write. Curry said that
                    the drafters had been as sensitive as possible to the need to protect national
                    security and the CIA's integrity, but noted that these were 30-year-old
                    documents. The bill attempted to protect both national security and the
                    interests of the U.S. public.</p>
                <p>The Committee then heard a declassification briefing of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, 1958-1960, volume VI, Cuba. This portion of the minutes is
                    Confidential and is maintained as a separate document.</p>
                <p>At 12:15 p.m., the meeting adjourned for a working luncheon.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Luncheon, November 16, 1990</hi></p>
                <p rend="underline">Present</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Advisory Committee members</item>
                    <item>Ambassador Roy. R. Rubottom</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany</item>
                    <item>David Herschler</item>
                    <item>David Mabon</item>
                    <item>Elaine McDevitt</item>
                </list>
                <p>During this working luncheon, Ambassador Roy Rubottom reviewed the upcoming <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on Cuba, 1958-1960. Ambassador
                    Rubottom had been Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American American
                    Affairs during this period, and signed many of the documents that appear in the
                    volume.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Rubottom stated that it was important to understand U.S.-Cuba
                    relations in the context of U.S. relations with all of Latin America. The United
                    States followed a three-pronged policy with regard to Castro during this period:
                    probe and test; let Castro's deeds speak for themselves; and rely on
                    international mechanisms, particularly the OAS (which he said was a weak link).
                    He provided a number of interesting anecdotes with regard to his experiences in
                    obtaining information about Castro.</p>
                <p>With regard to the volume on Cuba, Ambassador Rubottom had just a few specific
                    comments:</p>
                <p>l) The book covered the U.S. policy of allowing Castro's deeds to speak for
                    themselves quite well. The NIEs printed in the volume are particularly
                    revealing.</p>
                <p>2) One anecdote concerned a trip by Ambassador Smith to Santiago in which the
                    Batista regime violently suppressed a protest by women. When Smith publicly
                   “deplored” this, he was criticized in the pro-Batista press. According to
                    Rubottom, Smith was never the same. This episode, he suggested, could be
                    included in annotation in the volume.</p>
                <p>3) He could find no mention in the volume of the Advisory Council on Economic
                    Affairs, chaired by Milton Eisenhower, which he thought deserved a citation in
                    an appropriate footnote.</p>
                <p>4) In response to a query by Kimball whether he was “comfortable with the
                    integrity of the volume,” Ambassador Rubottom replied, “I think so”. And in
                    response to a followup question whether there was anything of significance
                    omitted from the volume, Ambassador Rubottom did point out that the extensive
                    and intensive work between the United States and the OAS did not get very
                    thorough treatment in the volume. Mabon noted, however, that this area was
                    covered in the Latin America regional volume.</p>
                <p rend="center"><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 16, 1990,
                        Afternoon</hi></p>
                <p>The Committee reconvened at 2 p.m.</p>
                <p>Slany proposed that in order to allow the Advisory Committee to meet in Executive
                    Session, the planned discussions for the afternoon be removed from the agenda
                    and substituted with written reports to the Committee. These included long-term
                    planning for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series; facsimile
                    publishing (in the event the series should need to be produced in this way in
                    order to meet the cost of publishing 12 volumes each year); a proposed
                    microfiche publication of declassified NSC minutes, agendas, actions, and
                    memoranda of discussion for the years 1947-1953; and an explanation of the steps
                    taken by PA/HO in compiling and publishing the much-criticized volume on Iran,
                    1951-1954.</p>
                <p>With regard to the Iran volume, it would be useful to get the Advisory Committee
                    to recommend steps in dealing with gaps in the record and finding ways to
                    supplement the record with documents now available that were not previously
                    released or seek additional documents from the CIA.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the tranche of documents recently released by Iran is available.
                    McDonald responded that it was available and the CIA had a copy. McAuliffe added
                    that this documentation needs to be assessed to determine if it contains
                    information to supplement the foreign policy record. The Advisory Committee
                    suggested that HO make recommendations regarding the gaps in the Iran volume for
                    the Committee to review and discuss at the next meeting. Slany agreed to
                    this.</p>
                <p>Glad asked McDonald if Jim Curry's earlier statement was correct that the
                    legislation on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> would not affect CIA
                    declassification procedures. McDonald stated that he thought this would be the
                    case because the release of documents would remain within CIA control.
                    Congressional sanction, he said, would likely put more pressure on the agency to
                    release material for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, so to that extent
                    there would be an impact on the CIA. He remained concerned that expanded access
                    to CIA documentation heightened the risk of leaks of the most sensitive
                    information.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the CIA planned to work with Congress to deal with this problem.
                    McDonald stated that he thought the CIA could work with Congress on a practical
                    solution. The Department of Justice, however, had drafted a technical objection
                    to the legislation.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg said the notion that the legislation will result in large numbers of
                    contested documents may not be the case if agency historians and declassifiers
                    would work out conflicts in advance. McDonald responded that there was much to
                    be said for this view. On the whole, he thought, the legislation was like using
                    a 16-inch gun when a rifle was needed. He thought the legislation, as presently
                    laid out, was overkill; the best solution might be to handle the matter
                    administratively.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by Kimball whether Congress should enact legislation
                    authorizing the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and leave the
                    details of implementation to the Executive branch, McDonald stated that the CIA
                    has an advisory committee that functions this way. Accountability can be built
                    into the legislation, he said, without having Congress micromanage its
                    implementation.</p>
                <p>George Chalou of the National Archives pointed out that NARA had been told by
                    Morefield that under the legislation State declassification reviewers would
                    divide Department of State records at NARA into “Department only” and “other
                    agency” groups. NARA has grave reservations about this procedure, he said, as it
                    could result in “alienation” of Department of State historical files, changing
                    the original order of the documents.</p>
                <p>Slany proposed that he report to the Committee by mail on the remaining agenda
                    items (long-term planning for the series, facsimile publications, a proposed
                    microfiche publication on NSC documents, background on the preparation of the
                    Iran volume, and options on following up on the omissions from the Iran volume)
                    and allow the Committee to move into private session.</p>
                <p>Kimball thanked Slany, the PA/HO staff, and other participants in the 2-day
                    meeting. The afternoon session adjourned shortly before 3 p.m., and the Advisory
                    Committee went into executive session.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
