<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From William Webster to David Boren, June 1990</title>
                <title type="short">Webster to Boren, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-01-06">January 6, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-06-23">June 23, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1990-06-23-webster-to-boren.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 350 KB, 2pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Administration, Office of
                    Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification, Historical Documents Review
                    Office Record Files, 1950-1993 (Lot File 95 D 113), Box 2, FRUS Legislation: PL
                    102-138. This copy bears a stamped signature for William H. Webster.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn21">Footnote 21</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From William H. Webster (Director of Central Intelligence) to David L.
                    Boren (Chair of the Senate Select Committee on Intelligence)</head>
                <dateline>June 23, 1990</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Chairman:</p>
                <p>The Senate Committee on Foreign Relations has recently introduced S. 2749, a bill
                    to provide supplemental authorization of appropriations for Fiscal Year 1991 for
                    the Department of State. The bill contains a number of provisions that would
                    govern the writing and publication of the “Foreign Relations of the United
                    States” historical series. We strongly object to the provisions as currently
                    drafted, and we request that your Committee assist us in getting the provisions
                    amended because of their impact on the Intelligence Community.</p>
                <p>If enacted as drafted, the provisions would require that all departments and
                    agencies of the U.S. Government provide to the State Office of the Historian and
                    a “Historians Advisory Committee,” a “full and complete set of the documents and
                    other materials pertinent to the record of the United States foreign policy
                    decisions and actions.” The only grounds for withholding any of such documents
                    from publication would be the compromise of U.S. weapons systems, the disclosure
                    of technical information relating to military equipment or cryptological
                    systems, or the names of living persons who provided confidential information to
                    the· U.S. Government. The bill essentially declassifies everything that does not
                    fall into those categories.</p>
                <p>The bill ignores Executive Order 12356 governing classification of national
                    security information, and in fact narrows greatly the types of information that
                    could be considered as damaging to the United States if disclosed. The bill also
                    ignores the Freedom of Information Act, and indeed is inconsistent with the
                    exemptions of that Act. The “Historians Advisory Committee” may also withhold
                    other documents from publication on certain additional grounds listed in the
                    bill, but those grounds are not related to the protection of intelligence
                    sources or methods. If enacted in its current form, the provision could in
                    effect declassify every Presidential Finding and National Intelligence Estimate
                    by mandating their publication in the historical series.</p>
                <p>At a minimum, we believe that the bill should be amended so that the grounds for
                    withholding documents and information from publication include all of the
                    exemptions contained in the Freedom of Information Act, and the decision on what
                    documents may be provided or published should rest with the departments or
                    agencies providing the documents.</p>
                <p>I am sending an identical letter to Vice Chairman Cohen. I seek your support in
                    amending the bill to meet our serious intelligence concerns.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,<lb/>William H. Webster</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
