<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Memorandum From Kim Hoggard to Ivan Selin, December
                    1990</title>
                <title type="short">Hoggard to Selin, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-12-06">December 6, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1990-12-06-hoggard-to-selin.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 137 KB, 3pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Front Office
                    Files, 1989-1990 (Lot File 93 D 287), Box 1, PA—Foreign Relations Series 1990.
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs Margaret Tutwiler cleared this
                    memorandum. The listed attachments were present, but are not posted.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn49">Footnotes 49</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn50">50</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum From V. Kim Hoggard (Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                    Affairs) to Ivan Selin (Under Secretary of State for Management)</head>
                <dateline>December 6, 1990</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Historical Documentary Publication</p>
                <p>Our efforts this year within the Department involving the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series (FRUS) have not and apparently cannot produce
                    a workable solution to the questions surrounding the reform of the project.</p>
                <p>Because of this inability to come to agreement internally, we have been
                    unsuccessful in quieting the public and Congressional criticism. Despite our
                    efforts, we are seen to be doing nothing.</p>
                <p>Should public criticism of the FRUS continue at the boisterous level it has
                    already attained, I have a very real concern that its target will shift to the
                    Secretary in such a manner as to question his commitment (and that of the
                    Administration's) to provide accurate and complete information to the public.
                    Blame could be placed in his lap for allowing (condoning?) a slow, bureaucratic
                    approach to the declassification process and hold him responsible for the
                    release of inaccurate and misleading historical documentation.</p>
                <p>I don't think it is an exaggeration -- the success of the criticism on the Hill
                    has resulted in proposed legislation. The Department incorrectly thought that
                    “if you ignore it, it will go away,” but Congressional oversight is a fact of
                    life. The Historical Advisory Committee is a fact of life. The Department must
                    accept these realities and make them work to our advantage.</p>
                <p>In an effort to reinvigorate our efforts to resolve these problems, the PA Bureau
                    has devised a four-part strategy that will enable us to modernize and improve
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, assure the continued
                    integrity of the publication and meet the concerns of the academic community,
                    and forestall intrusive legislation by Congress.</p>
                <p>This strategy has not been cleared around the building, but we think it is
                    responsive to the valid concerns of those in the Department and elsewhere who
                    are involved in some way with the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    project.</p>
                <p>The strategy takes into account the questions raised by the Historical Advisory
                    Committee at their recent meeting, the motivations and insights of the Senate
                    staffers most involved in drafting the proposed legislation about <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, and our own carefully thought out view
                    of how the Department can confront the troublesome issues and attempt to solve
                    them.</p>
                <p>The proposed four-part strategy includes:</p>
                <p>1. An <hi rend="underline">action plan</hi> for the modernization of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. This plan addresses both the
                    steps to be taken within the Department and those actions needed by other
                    agencies. It also provides Department or executive branch undertakings for all
                    of the operational provisions of the pending Congressional legislation on the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Key Advisory Committee
                    members have been briefed on the substance of the plan.</p>
                <p>2. The text of a <hi rend="underline">draft Presidential memorandum</hi>
                    directing the relevant agencies to cooperate with the Department in assembling,
                    declassifying, and publishing the modernized <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and giving the project the necessary priority to get
                    the job done. The memorandum would also request the Department to aim at opening
                    its historical files at 30 years. The draft memorandum should be an improvement
                    on a similar memorandum that was issued by President Reagan in 1985 but lost its
                    steam by 1988. Senate staffers who briefed the Advisory Committee indicated that
                        <hi rend="underline">a Presidential directive could be a key element in
                        deflecting the need for Congressional action</hi>.</p>
                <p>3. A draft <hi rend="underline">letter from Assistant Secretary Mullins</hi> to
                    the appropriate Senate and House Committee chairmen expressing support for the
                    general objectives of the pending legislations, willingness to have some general
                    legislative mandate for the research and publication of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series, but offering the Department's action plan
                    and the Presidential memorandum as the only appropriate and workable way of
                    dealing with the operational aspects of assuring an accurate and complete
                    published historical record.</p>
                <p>4. The outline of those internal Department measures that are necessary to have
                    the Historical Advisory Committee take on at an early date its heightened
                    responsibilities to verify the historical accuracy of the published record of
                    U.S. Foreign Relations.</p>
                <p>I have attached a <hi rend="underline">fifth paper</hi> that highlights those
                    issues arising from the four-part strategy that most conflict with current views
                    and attitudes within Department units concerned with various aspects of the
                    preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>PA needs your decisions to carry out our proposed four-part strategy:</p>
                <p>1. Your approval of the action plan and its implementation in the Department and
                    elsewhere.</p>
                <p>2. Your approval of the draft Presidential memorandum including its provisions
                    for you to chair occasional inter-agency meetings to promote priority for access
                    to and declassification of other agency documents for the published series.</p>
                <p>3. Your guidance on the steps to be taken to obtain early signing of such a
                    Presidential memorandum.</p>
                <p>4. Your review of the draft letter to Congress.</p>
                <p>5. Your instructions on the steps necessary to facilitate the work of the
                    Historical Advisory Committee.</p>
                <p>We feel we have tried to work within the Department for action. However,
                    bureaucratic foot-dragging has impeded any hope of getting Department-approved
                    proposed legislation to the Hill in the new year without your impetus.</p>
                <p>We appreciate very much your involvement in this issue and your efforts to reach
                    a solution.</p>
                <p>Attachments:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Draft Plan (to be submitted to Hill)</item>
                    <item>2. Internal Points of Concern with Draft Plan</item>
                    <item>3. Draft letter to Congressional Committee Chairmen</item>
                    <item>4. Presidential Executive Order</item>
                    <item>5. Draft guidelines on PA/HO and FPC/HDR Cooperation</item>
                    <item>6. Historical Committee - Internal Department Measures</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
