<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Summary of Unofficial Meeting Between HAC Members and
                    Department Officials, July 1990</title>
                <title type="short">Unofficial HAC Meeting, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-06-02">June 2, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-07-23">July 23, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1990-07-23-hac-meeting-summary.pdf">PDF</ref>, 123 KB, 6pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 6, Advisory Committee—1990—Correspondence
                    &amp; Memos.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn32">Footnote 32</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Summary Record of a Conversation Regarding the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Series</head>
                <dateline>July 23, 1990</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">Participants:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Prof. Betty Glad, University of South Carolina</item>
                    <item>Prof. Bradford Perkins, University of Michigan</item>
                    <item>Ms. Anne Van Camp, Archivist at the Hoover Institution, Stanford
                        University</item>
                    <item>Prof. Stephen Zamora, University of Houston Law Center</item>
                    <item>Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs V. Kim
                        Hoggard</item>
                    <item>Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Legislative Affairs Richard
                        Mueller</item>
                    <item>Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs George
                        Kennedy</item>
                    <item>The Historian of the Department, William Z. Slany</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Also Present:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>John P. Glennon, Office of the Historian</item>
                    <item>Elaine McDevitt, Office of the Historian</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ms. Hoggard began by expressing her pleasure at being able to discuss with the
                    four members of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation
                    the Department’s ongoing efforts to assure the comprehensiveness, accuracy, and
                    overall credibility of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The
                    Department takes very seriously the recent expressions of concern about the
                    completeness and usefulness of some recent volumes. These are also issues of
                    concern to the Department and the Bureau of Public Affairs. The Department and
                    its historians have themselves been wrestling with these issues for some years
                    and have been searching for solutions. Ms. Hoggard assured the four members of
                    the Advisory committee of her confidence in the professionalism of the Historian
                    and his staff and their commitment to the publication project. the Department’s
                    continued need for the recommendations of the Committee in the series.</p>
                <p>Ms. Hoggard summarized the process being followed by the Department for
                    modernizing and perfecting procedures for the preparation, declassification,
                    verification, and publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes. The process involves discussion among all the Department officials and
                    divisions who share the responsibility for the preparation and publication of
                    the volumes. These internal discussions were deliberate and sometimes more
                    time-consuming than the Bureau of Public Affairs would wish. Under Secretary for
                    Management Ivan Selin was taking a very strong personal role in giving overall
                    guidance to the process. The Department was centering its internal deliberations
                    on the basis of a plan developed by the Historian. Once this plan was fully
                    agreed upon within the Department, it would be fully coordinated with other
                    agencies in the foreign affairs community.</p>
                <p>The Historian offered a short outline of the four major elements of the plan for
                    the modernized <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series that the
                    Department now had under review. First and foremost was the urgent need for
                    Department historians to expand their documentary research to the records of the
                    other principal foreign affairs agencies of government. The agencies would be
                    expected to cooperate with the Department historians by providing access to the
                    historical records. In the case of intelligence agencies such cooperation might
                    consist of agency historians collecting documents for publication in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>The second aspect of the plan was the refinement of the declassification
                    procedures to provide a greater lean toward disclosure of complete historical
                    context. The key to such forward leaning declassification was the development of
                    an appeals procedure that involved policymakers at whatever leadership level was
                    necessary. These officials would apply a balancing test to difficult
                    declassification cases and reach final declassification decisions that assured
                    the most accurate and comprehensive historical record consistent with current
                    American policies and negotiations.</p>
                <p>The third part of the plan under study in the Department, and already partly
                    implemented, was the development of features in published volumes that would
                    maximize the readers’ understanding of research methodologies used in preparing
                    volumes, explain the relationship between what was published and what was
                    available in the historical archives, and indicate as precisely as possible what
                    subjects or particular information could not be included in a published
                    volume.</p>
                <p>Finally, the plan calls for expanded activity by the Advisory Committee in
                    assessing the scholarship and completeness of the published record and making
                    recommendations to the Department regarding the volumes. Access to the
                    classified documentation withheld from volumes was essential for the Committee
                    to make fully informed recommendations. It was also necessary for the committee
                    to expand its advice and insight into the planning of the volumes so that the
                    research efforts of Department historians in the archives of the various
                    agencies can be better focused.</p>
                <p>Prof. Perkins initiated a brief discussion of the use of disclaimers in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes in those instances when the
                    declassification procedure resulted in the withholding of documentation integral
                    to a coherent and comprehensive record. Perkins himself feared that use of
                    disclaimers might encourage a more inflexible declassification process. He posed
                    several examples of sensitive topics for which it would be difficult to write a
                    disclaimer on which historians and declassifiers could agree. Ms. Hoggard
                    indicated that the prefaces to the most recently published volumes showed the
                    Department’s intention to try to explain to readers as much as possible about
                    materials not included or withheld because of declassification decisions.</p>
                <p>Ms. Hoggard was glad of the opportunity to consult with the four Advisory
                    Committee members, and eager to convene a formal meeting of the full Committee
                    soon. She proposed that the next meeting be moved up from the original November
                    date to sometime in October. There was agreement that an earlier meeting would
                    be extremely useful. The Historian would arrange a date. There would not be
                    sufficient time to provide the Committee members with Top Secret security
                    clearances by the October meeting. The Committee might meet again in early
                    spring of 1991 when the members’ clearances were completed, and begin the
                    process of seeing the complete record of denied documents of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>The Committee members present for the consultation requested information about
                    forthcoming meetings. They wished to know whether the proposed October meeting
                    would include at least a continuation of the oral briefings regarding the impact
                    of the declassification process upon particular <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes. Ms. Hoggard indicated that the PA Bureau would try
                    to arrange such oral briefings for the next Committee meeting. She indicated
                    further that the Department had no wish to become involved in an overhaul of the
                    government’s entire declassification process. The Department’s immediate goals
                    were to improve the quality of the series, and to ensure that the Advisory
                    Committee was able, on the basis of access to withheld classified documents, to
                    verify the volumes or make recommendations regarding their editing and
                    publication.</p>
                <p>There was discussion about Top Secret security clearances. These clearances
                    involved certain responsibilities, and Committee members would have to decide
                    whether they wished to assume such responsibilities and potential constraints.
                    Those Committee members present requested information about the impact upon them
                    and their scholarly research and writing of Top Secret security clearances. The
                    Department will look into the issue and provide the Committee members with such
                    information.</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant Secretary Mueller provided an overview of the status of
                    legislation regarding the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    pending in the Congress. Such legislation had been included in S.2749 which was a
                    bill to provide supplemental authorization of appropriations for FY 1991 for the
                    Department of State and the USIA. The bill was approved by the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee without any discussion of the sections regarding the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. There appeared to be little
                    likelihood that the legislation would be acted upon by the time of the
                    Congressional summer recess in early August.</p>
                <p>The Department of state and other foreign affairs agencies have closely studied
                    the proposed legislation and found it seriously flawed. The Bureau of Public
                    Affairs understands that the legislation was well intended and had a worthy
                    goal--to strengthen the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The PA
                    Bureau feels that the goal could be better met by the Executive branch’s
                    adopting a plan for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series of the
                    sort being considered now within the Department, and subsequently to be
                    coordinated with other agencies.</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant Secretary Mueller and Dr. Slany explained some of principal
                    concerns with the legislation. The section of the proposed legislation creating
                    an Historical Advisory Committee is particularly flawed. It would require that
                    the chairman of a new Historical Advisory Committee be appointed by the
                    President and receive the consent of the Senate. Some members of the Advisory
                    Committee found this provision particularly objectionable. The new Committee
                    would not be a committee advising the Department and its historians on the
                    scholarship of the series but would instead become an operational body of the
                    government meeting frequently and for extended periods of time in order to
                    review and evaluate declassification decisions of the Department and other
                    agencies. The proposed legislation also fails to provide for the position of
                    Executive Secretary. Regulations assign the position of Executive Secretary of
                    the current Advisory Committee to the Historian who is particularly able to
                    connect the needs and experiences of the Department historians with the
                    recommendations and assistance of the Advisory Committee.</p>
                <p>Above all, the proposed legislation would establish standards of withholding that
                    were totally in conflict with the existing structure of laws, regulations, and
                    directives on classification, declassification, and access and use of special
                    types of security information. Several agencies have already begun their own
                    efforts to modify the draft legislation. Steps are also under way to remedy a
                    clause in the legislation that would require agencies to make available to the
                    Department, at considerable cost to themselves, vast numbers of copies of
                    documents for use in preparing the historical record.</p>
                <p>Anne Van Camp shared with others at the meeting information about the continuing
                    efforts within Congressional committees to revise and further develop the
                    language of the proposed <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation.
                    Some of the revisions under consideration, such as the explicit designation of
                    particular major professional societies to offer nominees to the new Committee,
                    might be improvements over the existing language. The scope and nature of the
                    responsibility of the proposed Advisory Committee to review all withheld
                    historical documents appeared to be totally unworkable.</p>
                <p>The PA Bureau regarded its draft plan for a modernized <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series as far preferable to any Congressional legislation. Of
                    the current proposed legislation, the provisions regarding a new and different
                    Advisory Committee were far more unworkable than the more general provisions
                    establishing the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series as a statutory responsibility of the Department and the Executive
                    branch.</p>
                <p>There was some discussion by the Advisory Committee members present as to how
                    they might make known their own views regarding the proposed legislation. Ms.
                    Hoggard urged against any collective Advisory Committee action on legislation at
                    this time, observing that individual Committee members like any other citizen
                    must decide for themselves. She did request that the Committee members wait
                    until the Department had prepared and sent to the Congress, a letter setting
                    forth in some detail, the Department and Executive branch position and policy on
                    the question of reforming the preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series, and on the particular legislation pending in
                    Congress. Advisory Committee members might agree or disagree with aspects of
                    Department policy, but it ought to be more clearly understood before strong
                    judgments were made about the pending legislation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
