<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Letter From William Slany to Kenneth McDonald, August
                    1990</title>
                <title type="short">Slany to McDonald, 1990</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2019-06-20">June 20, 2019</date>
                <date type="created" when="1990-08-17">August 17, 1990</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1990-08-17-slany-to-macdonald.pdf">PDF</ref>, 151 KB, 6pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the
                    Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1957-1990 (Lot File 96 D 292), Box 6, Advisory Committee-1990-Correspondence
                    &amp; Memos. Posted from a copy signed “Bill.”</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 10, <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn88">Footnotes 88</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-10#fn90">90</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Letter From William Slany (Director, Historian’s Office) to Kenneth McDonald
                    (Historian, CIA)</head>
                <dateline>August 17, 1990</dateline>
                <p>Dear Ken:</p>
                <p>You and I have talked on several occasions recently about the nature of the
                    future relationship between the Department of State’s historians and those of
                    your agency. We have also exchanged information on methods used by Department
                    historians to document the relationship between intelligence and foreign policy
                    for published volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952-1954, volume X Iran,
                    1951-1954, published last year and widely debated recently in the academic
                    arena, is an example of such a volume.</p>
                <p>Let me briefly outline the circumstances of preparing the Iran volume. This
                    volume is one of the most serious victims of the changing sensitivities in
                    American foreign policy. The documentation included in the volume was originally
                    compiled as (a) a separate 1951 compilation on Iran intended for inclusion in a
                    larger 1951 volume and (b) a 1952-1954 volume planned as part of the larger
                    triennium of 16 volumes. The original manuscripts were prepared between 14 and
                    16 years ago during the last major wave of accelerated compilation by the
                    Department historians. Like so many of the volumes compiled in the mid and late
                    1970s and early 1980s, they made little progress in the declassification process
                    during the early 1980s.</p>
                <p>The 1951 compilation on Iran was eventually combined with the 1952-1954 volume on
                    Iran to form a unique (for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series)
                    4-year volume covering the years 1951-1954. This volume became a victim of the
                    special nature of U.S. policy toward Iran during the hostage crisis. By 1985, it
                    was one of more than 40 volumes in the slow moving declassification pipeline. It
                    was in fact not in the pipeline, but on the shelf pending some significant
                    change in the difficult relationship between the United States and Iran.</p>
                <p>The documentation on Iran for the 1951-1954 period was compiled on the basis of
                    these guidelines for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> documentary
                    historians that were operative 10 years ago. The documenting of intelligence
                    activities and covert intelligence operations was considered a possibility and
                    was actively pursued, but no access to the records of the CIA was accorded to
                    Department historians. During the preparation of the compilations on Iran in the
                    mid-1970s, the then CIA Historian provided Department historians with 37 pages
                    of classified agency documents that effectively summarized events attending the
                    overthrow of Prime Minister Mosadeq. These, together with some scattered records
                    found in various State Department files, were included in the manuscript for the
                    1951-1954 volume.</p>
                <p>Department historians visited with CIA in the late 1970s to explore and develop
                    agreed terms of reference regarding the official disclosure policy for
                    intelligence documents. Agency officials were not able to offer any historians’
                    access to Agency historical records, and they explained the prohibitions to the
                    acknowledgement of intelligence activities in foreign countries, even when
                    previously disclosed unofficially by ex-officials or unintentionally included in
                    government documents and publications. This was at a time that the agency had no
                    historians.</p>
                <p>No high-level State Department appeal was made to challenge these CIA historical
                    access policies. The special overtones of U.S. relations with Iran during the
                    1980s not only brought about the extended suspension of declassification action
                    on the proposed 1951-1954 volume, but cast a pall over further research and
                    expansion or revision of the existing manuscript despite some significant
                    unofficial disclosures during the 1980s about the overthrow of the Mosadeq
                    regime in 1953.</p>
                <p>Once a decision was reached in the late 1980s to go forward with the publication
                    of the Iran volume, declassification proceeded briskly. Most documents on covert
                    operations in Iran that had been found in Department files or provided by the
                    CIA historian were denied declassification when referred to the CIA.</p>
                <p>The question of whether to go forward with the publication of the manuscript
                    despite the exclusion of most of the evidence of U.S. involvement in or
                    knowledge of the overthrow of the Mosadeq regime was discussed in the Department
                    in 1988. Six principal considerations were identified:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. The decision to allow the Iran volume to be published was perhaps a
                        short-term one and subject to reversal at any moment; it was necessary to
                        act swiftly to publish a volume that included an important body of documents
                        on Iran-U.S. relations.</item>
                    <item>2. Although CIA denied declassification of several critical documents, a
                        few significant allusions remained in the cleared manuscript, and all
                        scholars interested in the Iran area already shared the conventional wisdom
                        about the U.S. role in 1953.</item>
                    <item>3. Without access to the complete CIA historical record, it was impossible
                        for Department historians to decide whether the omission of the handful of
                        documents denied declassification by the CIA distorted actual U.S. policies
                        in 1953.</item>
                    <item>4. Agency declassification policies and attitudes toward acknowledging
                        covert activities had not changed at all during the decade. No additional or
                        new access or disclosure was possible.</item>
                    <item>5. One strongly held view among Department officials was that a challenge
                        to Agency declassification policies would negatively impact upon other
                        appeals of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes more likely to
                        be resolved in a positive manner.</item>
                    <item>6. CIA was not alone in refusing to agree to the disclosure of documents
                        in the Iran volume. A foreign government objected to the publication of its
                        documents in the volume, and declassification of other documents was
                        withheld by the Department itself.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Under the circumstances the Department historians concluded that the Iran volume
                    should be published as it was before anything happened to close the “window of
                    opportunity”.</p>
                <p>The volume was duly released in 1989. But not without misgivings among the
                    historians of the Department. With these misgivings in mind, I invited Prof.
                    Bruce Kuniholm to review the volume for the Department’s Advisory Committee on
                    Historical Diplomatic Documentation at its November 1989 meeting. Prof. Kuniholm
                    was invited because he was a scholar-expert on the area and also, perhaps just
                    as importantly, he had served in an important State Department position during
                    the Iran hostage crisis of 1979-1980 and was familiar with the historical
                    documentary record on Iran.</p>
                <p>You are already aware of Prof. Kuniholm’s negative evaluation of the Iran volume.
                    He took it upon himself to publish in the spring 1990 AHA <hi rend="italic"
                        >Perspectives</hi>, a version of the review that he gave the Advisory
                    Committee privately in November 1989. He did not ask me about it beforehand or
                    afterward. I never anticipated that he would “go public” with his private
                    analysis for the Committee and the Department. Prof. Cohen’s resignation from
                    the Advisory Committee in February and Prof. Kuniholm’s publication of his
                    analysis in March effectively took the issue out of the Advisory Committee
                    channel before we here in the Department could do anything about the Iran
                    volume. It is almost ironic that the Iran volume that was a prisoner of the
                    state of U.S.-Iran relations in the 1980s became a prisoner again in 1990, this
                    time of the dispute sparked by Warren Cohen’s resignation between the scholarly
                    community and the government. In any case the Advisory Committee won’t be able
                    to make its own evaluation of the issue before its annual meeting in November,
                    and may not even have time to take it up then.</p>
                <p>For my part I see a few possible courses of action to deal with the widely
                    perceived defects of the Iran volume:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. We in the Historian’s Office could publish an article describing the
                        circumstances and premises attending the preparation of the volume. The
                        article, which would include much of the information cited above, could be
                        published in several historical journals, including those of organizations
                        represented on the Advisory Committee.</item>
                    <item>2. The Department could be asked to revise its longstanding policies and
                        declassify some of its own documentation on the issues not accurately or
                        adequately documented in the 1951-1954 Iran volume.</item>
                    <item>3. The Department and your Agency could devise a joint statement on <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> access and declassification
                        guidelines for intelligence documentation. Such a statement could be
                        published separately and/or included in the prefaces of future volumes of
                        the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The proper response to academic user concern about the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volume on Iran is one aspect of the larger question of how,
                    in the future, to assure the comprehensiveness and accuracy of the historical
                    documentation published by the Department of State. Among the proposals that are
                    being considered within the Department is a request to agencies, including your
                    own, to work closely with Department historians in both the planning and the
                    access stages of the preparation of future <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes. In particular this would mean that other agency
                    historians could, during the planning of particular volumes or the designing of
                    the overall scope of the series, alert Department compilers/editors to the
                    existence of issues or bodies of documents that deserve special attention.</p>
                <p>As an alternative to the very difficult task of working out access for Department
                    historians at some of the more security-conscious agencies such as your own,
                    historians of these agencies could be charged with responsibility for collecting
                    from their agency files those documents that deserve consideration for inclusion
                    in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Such a selection would be
                    based, hopefully, on some constructive interplay between the agency historians
                    and the Department Historian. Finally, the agency historians would be expected
                    to help serve as advocates with agency declassifiers in securing a timely and
                    favorable declassification review of the documentation finally selected for <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>The preceding proposal is not yet Department policy, but may become so in
                    September. There is a long way to go until such an idea is coordinated among all
                    interested agencies. Some version of such a proposal may already have manifested
                    itself in revisions of the proposed Congressional legislation for the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. You and I may wish to work out
                    ourselves some agreed language that would meet the need for greater access for
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> historians and the realistic
                    possibilities for what you and your agency could do in terms of expanded
                    disclosure of historical information.</p>
                <p>I must not conclude this letter without reminding you of the great strides you
                    and I and our staffs have made in developing strong cooperation ties. Access for
                    Department historians to intelligence documentation has steadily expanded and
                    been facilitated, since you and your staff have taken up your tasks. I believe
                    we both are particularly pleased with the progress made by Tom Thorne, the
                    former Deputy Director of the Department’s Bureau of Intelligence Research, in
                    completing the projected <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume on
                    intelligence and foreign policy in the 1945-1951 period. The excellent support
                    Tom Thorne has received in compiling agency documentation augers well for the
                    future.</p>
                <p>I hope this has been helpful to you.</p>
                <p>Yours Truly,</p>
                <p>William Z. Slany</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
