<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, June
                    1991</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1991</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-06-02">June 2, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1991-06-18">June 18, 1991</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="1991-06-18-hac-meeting-minutes.pdf">PDF</ref>, 191 KB, 12pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of
                    the Historian, Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation Files,
                    1972-2007 (Lot File 09 D 473), Box 1, June 1991. Secret. Drafted by Elaine
                    McDevitt. Cleared by William Slany, Rita Baker, and David Herschler. Sent for
                    clearance to George Kennedy (PA), Frank Machak (IM/IS/FPC), and Richard
                    Morefield (IM/IS/FPC/HDR) on July 17. No record of their clearance has been
                    located. Another copy of these minutes, with comments from FPC, is present in
                    Department of State, CDC Lot File 95 D 113, Box 3, HAC—1991.</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn71">Footnotes 71</ref> and <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn74">74</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Minutes of the 1991 Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation</head>
                <dateline>June 18, 1991</dateline>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Members</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Warren Kimball, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Betty Glad</item>
                    <item>Margaret Hermann</item>
                    <item>Bradford Perkins</item>
                    <item>Emily Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Anne Van Camp</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</p>
                <list>
                    <item>George Kennedy, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <item>William Z. Slany, The Historian</item>
                            <item>Rita Baker</item>
                            <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                            <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                            <item>David Herschler</item>
                            <item>Edward Keefer</item>
                            <item>Gabrielle Mallon</item>
                            <item>Elaine McDevitt</item>
                            <item>James Miller</item>
                            <item>Nina Noring</item>
                            <item>Charles Sampson</item>
                            <item>William Sanford</item>
                            <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                            <item>Sherrill Wells</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Others</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Frank Machak, Director, Office of Freedom of Information, Privacy, and
                        Classification Review</item>
                    <item>Richard Morefield, Chief, Historical Documents Review, Office of
                        Information, Privacy, and Classification Review</item>
                    <item>Susan Tait, Bureau of Finance and Management Policy</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation met in Room 6800 of
                    the Department of State from 9:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball called the meeting to order at 9:00 a.m. He announced that all
                    members of the Committee with the exception of Ron Spector had received their
                    security clearances. Margaret Tutwiler and Grace Moe were traveling with the
                    Secretary in Berlin and were unable to meet with Committee members. Dr. Kimball
                    had received a letter from Ms. Moe and said he believed the atmosphere in the
                    Bureau of Public Affairs was good. He told the Committee that he had been in
                    touch with the Senate and House staffers about the legislation and had tried to
                    communicate the Committee’s views.</p>
                <p>The Committee decided to set aside the agenda and begin with a discussion of the
                    pending legislation. Dr. Kimball stated that the House version of the
                    legislation had been passed, and it was expected that the Senate would pass its
                    own bill. The two bills will then go to conference sometime after the Fourth of
                    July. There will be legislation; the only question is what the final legislation
                    will be.</p>
                <p>There was a discussion of the clause in the Senate bill which provides that the
                    Committee should report to Congress if agencies do not cooperate in the
                    declassification process. Dr. Kimball considered that since the Committee was a
                    Department of State committee, it should address its reports to the Secretary of
                    State. The Committee concluded that it would be preferable if the legislation
                    provided that the report be sent to the Secretary, with copies to Congress, and
                    that it should be sent periodically rather than every time there was a
                    disagreement. Dr. Kimball felt it was important to keep Congress involved from a
                    practical standpoint; without Congressional pressure, things would not have
                    evolved to the present stage. Dr. Rosenberg acknowledged that she would prefer
                    to see an annual report which would serve a variety of purposes; it could be
                    sent to the Secretary of State and to constituent organizations. Dr. Kimball
                    cautioned that the annual report was likely to be classified, and Dr. Perkins
                    suggested that a classified appendix might be attached to the general report.
                    Dr. Kimball proposed to talk with Frank Sieverts to give him a sense of the
                    Committee’s understanding of the issues.</p>
                <p>Deputy Assistant Secretary Kennedy welcomed the Committee. He stated that the
                    Department wanted to see the Committee continue to function effectively. He
                    believed it was important to reach an accommodation with the Congress and the
                    White House.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball advised the members that it seemed the appropriate time to engage the
                    constituent organizations in support of the legislation.</p>
                <p>Dr. Glad raised the question of the selection of the Advisory Committee members
                    under the new legislation. The House bill provides that the Committee be
                    appointed by the Secretary, with none of the members having to be from the
                    professional societies. The Senate bill, however, would stipulate that members
                    be selected from slates of candidates submitted by the professional
                    associations. Dr. Kimball was of the opinion that the resolution of the
                    reporting requirement issue would also resolve the appointment question. On
                    another matter, Dr. Kimball noted that the operations of the Committee, with
                    respect to declassification questions as well as specifically pertaining to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, would depend on the quality
                    of the information provided by the Historian and by the HO staff. Dr. Perkins
                    noted that an earlier version of the Senate bill had restricted the mandate of
                    the Advisory Committee to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series,
                    while the new bill includes oversight of records transferred to the National
                    Archives. Dr. Kimball suggested that the earlier restriction of the Committee’s
                    mandate was due in large part to the ignorance of the drafters regarding the
                    total body of information. Dr. Perkins raised the question of CIA documents. Dr.
                    Kimball recalled that CIA documents are protected under the pending legislation,
                    which would not require access, but would establish a mechanism for the Office
                    of the Historian to report a problem to the Secretary of State and to the
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hermann asked about systematic declassification. Dr. Kimball noted that the
                    principle of a 30-year line is in both pieces of legislation, though he believed
                    that the Senate version would be of more benefit to the Department. Mr. Machak
                    interjected that the Department did not believe that automatic declassification
                    at 30 years was possible. The Department, he said, favored the House version of
                    the legislation because it would give the Department some flexibility to come up
                    with a plan. The Senate version, it was felt, had a formula application. Mr.
                    Machak went on to emphasize that, in his opinion, this section of the proposed
                    legislation had not received satisfactory attention. The law requires
                    declassification, transfer to NARA, and opening of records to the public within
                    one year. Some categories of materials are excluded under the legislation. There
                    is no way to apply the exclusions without looking at every document. This
                    requirement raises a question of resources.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball thought that some documents should be declassified in bulk. He
                    believed that the Committee felt strongly that there should be something in the
                    legislation to pressure the government to open up its documents--requiring
                    systematic declassification at a 30-year line. Mr. Machak indicated that the
                    Department was not as concerned about systematic declassification as it was
                    about automatic declassification. He urged the Committee to educate their
                    constituencies about the practical problems of implementing a 30-year line. The
                    perception that legislation would change things overnight was erroneous. Dr.
                    Kimball asked for suggestions from the Committee and from Mr. Machak for wording
                    of this section of the legislation.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany pointed out that the Senate version would assign the Advisory Committee
                    a direct advisory role in systematic declassification, rendering the Committee
                    advisers to the records managers. He questioned whether this might necessitate
                    the Committee’s becoming heavily involved with records management issues,
                    perhaps detracting from its role with the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Dr. Kimball did not regard this responsibility as a
                    serious problem; the Committee would concern itself only with procedures. If it
                    became necessary to examine a random sampling of documents, this could be
                    accomplished with the assistance of the Historian.</p>
                <p>Ms. Van Camp recalled that at the Committee’s last meeting, the Department had
                    been opposed to any legislation. She asked for a statement of the Department’s
                    current position. Mr. Kennedy stated that the Department still thought its plan
                    was preferable to legislation but now recognized that legislation was
                    inevitable. Dr. Slany noted that the Administration preferred the language of
                    the House bill to that of the Senate bill but was willing to be flexible
                    depending on the resolution of the reporting issue.</p>
                <p>Mr. Machak added that the NSC was concerned with protecting the President’s
                    constitutional prerogatives. If the Committee could dictate to the Executive, it
                    was felt it should be appointed by the Executive.</p>
                <p>The Committee then recessed for a short break.</p>
                <p rend="underline">10:45 a.m. session</p>
                <p>Mr. Richard Morefield, Chief of the Historical Documents Review Division,
                    distributed to each member of the Committee copies of the Department of State
                    guidelines for transfer of official records to the National Archives. He
                    explained that each U.S. Government agency is required to have a records
                    management system and a records disposition schedule. The Department’s Records
                    Management Handbook contains a disposition schedule for every permanent file in
                    the Department. Mr. Morefield indicated that the Handbook was divided into three
                    sections, covering files of the Washington D.C. offices, overseas posts, and
                    field offices. He then outlined a series of definitions: permanent and temporary
                    files; central files; chron files; subject files; reference files; working files
                    and personal papers.</p>
                <p>Next he elaborated on the requirements for having the declassification
                    guidelines. When the Department of State transfers records to the National
                    Archives, it may first do a systematic review to downgrade or declassify as much
                    material as possible, or it may give guidelines for this review to NARA. The
                    guidelines are used in the preliminary review of files. The purpose of the
                    guidelines is to identify topics which a knowledgeable generalist could
                    declassify on his or her own. The Department pays a portion of the salary of the
                    reviewers at the National Archives charged with screening Department documents
                    for declassification. If problems arise concerning specific documents, we send a
                    Department declassifier to the Archives to render assistance. The National
                    Archives has no authority to declassify materials until they have been
                    accessioned.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball then raised the question of classification of information obtained
                    from foreign governments. He was concerned that a conversation between the
                    Secretary of State and the British Foreign Minister would remain classified
                    under this guideline. Mr. Morefield assured Dr. Kimball that this guideline was
                    intended to refer to situations when information from a foreign government was
                    given to the U.S. in confidence, for example, a position paper prepared by the
                    United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>The Committee then recessed to study the guidelines in more detail.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Luncheon Session</p>
                <p>During the lunch hour, the Advisory Committee discussed the updated <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Status and Projections Charts, in
                    addition to a written status report and summary of volumes ahead of and behind
                    schedule. There was a firm consensus that these reports were very useful. In
                    particular, the summary of volumes ahead of schedule and behind schedule made it
                    possible for the Committee to get a quick picture of the status of the series.
                    After a brief discussion it was agreed that copies of all three reports would be
                    updated and provided to the Advisory Committee on a quarterly basis. An
                    appropriate time would be prior to each Advisory Committee meeting (assuming
                    Committee meetings are to be held four times a year in accordance with the
                    pending legislation).</p>
                <p rend="underline">Afternoon Session</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball reconvened the meeting at 1:50 p.m. to discuss briefly the issue
                    raised by a letter from Gary Hess to Secretary Baker regarding closed lot files
                    at the National Archives for the period of World War II.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Mr. Machak</hi> said that there had been an ISOO-Archives
                    meeting on this issue on December 3, at which the State Department had not been
                    represented. Although he had not received a copy of the Hess letter, he
                    understood that it claimed that there was no guidance for the National Archives
                    on this issue. Jim Hastings at NARA had told him that NARA did have guidance and
                    had already acted on 700 of the 2600 feet of material involved. Mr. Machak
                    planned to recruit an employee from NARA to work on lot files at the Department
                    so that this problem would not recur. Dr. Kimball asked Dr. Rosenberg to inform
                    Mr. Hess about the outcome.</p>
                <p>The Committee then passed to the next item on the agenda: review of the still-
                    classified manuscript of selected <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield informed the Committee that they were seeing manuscript of
                    classified documents denied publication in the volume. The package did not
                    include Presidential documents which the National Security Council refused to
                    release to the Committee or documents on Japan which the Department of State’s
                    Japan desk refused to allow the Committee to see.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball reminded the group that the Secretary of State had authorized the
                    Committee to see denied Department documents. Mr. Morefield said the Secretary’s
                    authority was delegated to the Bureau, which had determined that the Committee’s
                    “need to know” was insufficient. The Bureau had had 72 hours to act, and there
                    was no time to appeal its decision. Dr. Perkins asked about the NSC
                    deletions--whether they were critical to the compilation. Mr. Morefield said
                    that they included NSC minutes, memcons of the President with foreign government
                    leaders, and national intelligence estimates.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball said that the Bureau had not followed the ruling of the Secretary of
                    State granting the Committee access to denied Department documents. He suggested
                    sending a letter to the Secretary outlining the problem of the Committee’s
                    access. Mr. Morefield thought that the issue for the Bureau was insufficient
                    time and was prepared to reopen the matter with the Bureau if the Committee so
                    wished. Dr. Rosenberg suggested that the Committee postpone sending a letter of
                    protest until its next meeting when there would be no problem of a 72-hour time
                    limit. Ms. Van Camp and Dr. Perkins concurred.</p>
                <p>Dr. Rosenberg asked to hear from the compilers about the relative importance of
                    the denied documents. Dr. Slany said that 20 percent of the documents on Italy
                    in the Western Europe volume for 1955-1957 were denied publication. Dr. Miller
                    said that although he was not the compiler of the section of the volume on
                    Italy, he had reviewed the volume, and he believed that the Italy compilation
                    was unsuitable for publication. The information in the denied documents
                    concerning U.S. views on the opening to the Italian left to participate in the
                    government had been published elsewhere. Policy on the opening to the left, on
                    U.S. attitudes toward Italian communism, on the relationship between Ambassador
                    Luce and President Gronchi, as well as other critical matters, had been excised
                    from the text.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield informed the Committee that any appeal for release of denied
                    documents must be directed to the responsible Bureau. Dr. Miller stated that he
                    had attempted to meet with the Department’s declassifier several times to
                    discuss the matter but had been unable to do so.</p>
                <p>Dr. Miller pointed to a denied document before the Committee, a memorandum from
                    Ambassador Luce to Elbridge Durbrow which discussed Roman Catholic Church views
                    on communism. He did not believe that this document was relevant to American
                    foreign policy and he did not understand why it had been denied.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany reminded the group that the purpose of the meeting was to look at what
                    had been eliminated from the volume. The Historical Documents Review Division
                    had not been asked to prepare a case to explain why certain documents had been
                    denied. Ideally, a volume should be looked at in its entirety.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield explained further that controversial matters were referred to the
                    appropriate Bureau for a decision. The “HO1” memo was a preliminary memo sent by
                    HDR to the Office of the Historian.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball asked if all denied documents were reviewed on a regular basis by the
                    regional Bureau. Mr. Morefield replied that this practice was not followed
                    unless the Office of the Historian appealed a decision of the Historical
                    Documents Review Division.</p>
                <p>Dr. Miller referred to denial of a “Dear Foster” letter from Ambassador Luce to
                    Secretary of State Dulles. Mr. Morefield said that it looked like a low-level
                    cut-and-paste job which might be published as an “unedited letter.” Dr. Miller
                    said that a historian should make this decision. Dr. Kimball said that the
                    purpose at hand was not to review the volume, but to discuss clearance
                    procedures.</p>
                <p>Dr. Herschler drew the Committee’s attention to portions of draft prefaces which
                    contained references to deleted material. Mr. Morefield suggested that the
                    proposed language for the preface to the Japan volume would be hard to
                    clear.</p>
                <p>Dr. Rosenberg said that when the preface deals with major lines of policy and
                    indicates that a large quantity of relevant information has been denied,
                    publication of the volume should be withheld.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball suggested that the Committee was dealing with two issues: whether to
                    have prefaces which would elucidate what material was deleted, and how to be
                    certain that declassification decisions are made wisely.</p>
                <p>Dr. Rosenberg remarked that in the case of a problem such as the Italian volume,
                    for which the preface would be long, the Committee should go back and request
                    changes in the compilation.</p>
                <p>Mr. Morefield reminded the members that they were seeing the difficult cases, the
                    volumes where there was something to point out to the reader.</p>
                <p>At the request of Dr. Kimball, Dr. Keefer discussed the 1958-1960 Indonesia
                    compilation. [<hi rend="italic">Remainder of paragraph not
                    declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Also denied were NATO discussions about the sale of arms to Indonesia. Mr.
                    Morefield pointed out that the problem was that these were NATO documents and
                    involved multiple clearances. The Office should try to get alternative documents
                    containing the same information. [<hi rend="italic">Remainder of paragraph not
                        declassified.</hi>]</p>
                <p>Dr. Glad asked what the law was on covert operations, and Mr. Morefield replied
                    that the CIA claimed that release would endanger [<hi rend="italic">text not
                        declassified.</hi>] He believed they were stretching things, but asserted
                    that it was their call. Dr. Glad questioned what the impact of the new
                    guidelines on the CIA would be, and Mr. Morefield responded that it was within
                    their competence to turn down our requests. He was asked whether CIA would clear
                    the preface, and he replied that something along this line could be worked
                    out.</p>
                <p>Dr. Hermann remarked that constituents didn’t seem to focus on the fact that this
                    was a Department of State publication, and suggested perhaps there could be a
                    stronger statement to that effect in the preface. Dr. Hermann said she had read
                    the newer prefaces, but that this point was still not clear to her. Dr. Keefer
                    agreed with Dr. Hermann’s point, that it was important to make clear that
                    Department historians did not have complete access.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Dr. Kimball as to whether he believed that the
                    omissions would damage the volume, Dr. Keefer replied that, although we had
                    evidence that the Eisenhower Administration disliked Sukarno and wanted him out
                    of the way, there was nothing in the compilation on U.S. actions. Dr. Hermann
                    believed that readers would put two and two together. Mr. Morefield then
                    commented that HO had identified 21 passages to be restored which did not
                    discuss [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] but that the effort to
                    include these also had failed. Dr. Kimball suggested that members needed to come
                    early to look at the volumes, talk with the compiler, and make recommendations.
                    What the Committee needed was a review procedure. Dr. Keefer noted that this
                    would not have to be done with every volume. Dr. Hermann suggested that the
                    Indonesia compilation was similar to the Iran volume, and the Committee must
                    decide whether there was a pattern that required a special preface.</p>
                <p>Ms. Van Camp noted that we were reaching a point where the Committee could play a
                    useful role, but also risked coming up against a problem if it decided a volume
                    should not be published. Dr. Kimball suggested the preface might state that the
                    Committee advised against publication because of extensive deletions. Dr. Glad
                    said the Committee needed to look at what had been included in the Indonesia
                    compilation to judge its value. Dr. Kimball then proposed that the Committee
                    recommend that the compilation on Italy not be published until after members had
                    had time to review it. In the future, the Committee would ask the Historian’s
                    Office to identify, for instance, six volumes that were troublesome; the
                    Committee would review these volumes. While the Committee did not want to appear
                    obstructive, its recommendation was that these compilations not be published as
                    they were, but only after they had been reviewed by Committee members. Several
                    members indicated a willingness to come to the Department as needed to help with
                    this task.</p>
                <p>Dr. Glad urged that the historians continue to try to negotiate to resolve the
                    differences with the declassifiers.</p>
                <p>Dr. Rosenberg wondered whether since the volume on Western Europe was already in
                    the page proofs, it was still possible to delay publication. Dr. Slany replied
                    that this was possible. Dr. Kimball suggested that the Committee not recommend
                    against publication but advise declassifiers that the Committee was not
                    satisfied.</p>
                <p>Dr. Kimball voiced concern about the omission of any reference to an “opening to
                    the left” in the volume on Western Europe which included a section on Italy and
                    what he termed a “gross distortion of foreign policy.” He asked Dr. Slany
                    whether he wanted a formal document stating that the volume is unacceptable. Dr.
                    Rosenberg expressed her concern that this approach to the volume could leave an
                    impression that the Advisory Committee would be withholding every volume.
                    Perhaps the Committee could link this protest of the Western Europe volume to a
                    more general statement regarding the success of other volumes, so as not to be
                    confrontational.</p>
                <p>While Dr. Kimball admitted this could be a problem, he strongly believed that for
                    the present, publication would be unwise. Dr. Perkins asked how this could hurt
                    foreign policy. Mr. Morefield replied that there would be a problem of physical
                    security for U.S. companies in Italy if their actions became known. Dr.
                    Rosenberg suggested omitting the names of the companies, and asked about the
                    status of the volume on Indonesia. Mr. Morefield replied that it was still being
                    reviewed at the other agencies. Dr. Glad then proposed having a Committee member
                    come in early to look at the Indonesia volume.</p>
                <p>Dr. Perkins asked what would be done about the Japan 1958-1960 volume. Could it
                    ever be published? Mr. Morefield indicated that the Japan desk was concerned
                    about mentioning the topics of nuclear weapons and status of forces. Dr. Perkins
                    replied that this type of information had been legitimately withheld and would
                    never be released. Dr. Slany said it was a balancing test, the right of the
                    people to know versus security concerns. The criteria for withholding documents
                    from the Japan volume was that they could damage current relations.
                    Periodically, there would be documents of importance that could legitimately be
                    withheld, but the omission of these would alter the record. Mr. Morefield stated
                    that the Department would not be able to print this volume for the foreseeable
                    future. Dr. Glad declared that the Committee did want to see the denied
                    materials next time.</p>
                <p>Dr. Slany stated that he hoped the Advisory Committee would not put itself in the
                    position of vetoing a volume every time a staff member complained. Dr. Glad
                    replied that she didn’t think it would come to that, but emphasized that she was
                    concerned about the national security standards. Dr. Slany then stated that the
                    issue was history versus secrecy. Would the withholding of information lead to a
                    faulty volume? Mr. Morefield emphasized that declassification standards should
                    remain constant over time. The same justification should be given today as was
                    given 20 years ago. Dr. Perkins then questioned the omission of the information
                    on U.S.-Italian relations, and Mr. Morefield’s reply was that, although we
                    intervened in the internal politics there, this was not something we should
                    comment on, even though it was in Clare Boothe Luce’s memoir.</p>
                <p>Dr. Sampson pointed out that with regard to the compilation on France 1955-1957,
                    he believed that the documents which were omitted from the volume did not affect
                    the overall presentation of the policy to the degree that the volume should be
                    withheld. How far one went back to show the roots of something that later turned
                    out to be important became a tactical maneuver. Dr. Glad stated that on the
                    basis of the preliminary data, she believed the European volume should be
                    withheld.</p>
                <p>Dr. Sampson indicated that certain European discussions of nuclear questions had
                    been denied to us since 1951. The Canada problem was similar to Japan but was
                    not as serious, and there was a disclaimer in the volume. Dr. Kimball felt that
                    it was not a distortion of the record to withhold details of where weapons were
                    stored. He asked whether <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes
                    currently contained surveys of memoir literature as had been done for the World
                    War II conferences in World War II volumes. Dr. Slany indicated that this was
                    not being done now. Dr. Sampson pointed out that it was difficult to get an
                    understanding of the nuclear question from Macmillan’s memoirs. Dr. Rosenberg
                    then asked about British financial problems, which the draft preface identified
                    as an area for deletions.</p>
                <p>Finally, Dr. Kimball raised the issue of procedures the Committee should follow
                    with regard to certain issues, such as whether HO should make an effort to
                    publish a supplement to the Iran volume. He mentioned that Dr. Slany had said
                    that there were signs that the CIA might be willing to release certain documents
                    which previously had been denied. The Committee agreed that it should include in
                    its report to the Department a recommendation to pursue with the other agencies
                    concerned the documents that were omitted from the Iran volume with a view to
                    publishing them.</p>
                <p>The Committee adjourned at 4:00 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
