<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Record of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, March
                    1991</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Record, 1991</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date type="posted" when="2014-06-02">June 2, 2014</date>
                <date type="created" when="1991-03-13">March 13, 1991</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus-history/documents/1991-03-13-hac-meeting-record.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 124 KB, 6pp.)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Administration, Office of
                    Freedom of Information, Privacy, and Classification, Historical Documents Review
                    Office Record Files, 1950-1993 (Lot File 95 D 113), Box 3, HAC—1991.
                    Confidential. Drafted by Susan Tait (FMP/MP/MAP).</hi></p>
            <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States Series</hi>, Chapter 11, <ref
                    target="../chapter-11#fn61">Footnote 61</ref></p>
            <div type="document">
                <head>Memorandum for the File</head>
                <dateline>March 13, 1991</dateline>
                <p>Subject: HAC Meeting on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Plan</p>
                <p>Attending:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>PA/HO - Messrs. Kennedy and Slany</item>
                    <item>IM/IS/FPC - Messrs. Machak and Hamilton</item>
                    <item>L/M - Catherine Skipper</item>
                    <item>FMP/MP/MAP - Susan Tait</item>
                    <item>Committee Members: W. Kimball (chair), E. Rosenberg, A. Van Camp, B.
                        Perkins, B. Glad, G. Herring</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="underline">Preliminary Remarks</p>
                <p>Mr. Kennedy opened the meeting by explaining that Assistant Secretary Tutwiler
                    had wanted to be present personally at this meeting, but she was traveling with
                    the Secretary in the Middle East. He said the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> plan
                    now on the table had been approved within the Department. It had four main
                    points: expand historical research, improve the declassification process,
                    explain the research methodology in the preface to each published <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume, and increase the committee members’
                    confidence in what the Department was doing to improve the quality and
                    timeliness of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Chairman Kimball said that part of the Department’s plan was window dressing and
                    other parts did not interest the committee. He asked Mr. Slany to provide
                    current background.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany noted that PA/HO has shut down other activities in order to devote all
                    18 to 20 office personnel to the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> program. A deputy
                    historian is being recruited. Relations with other agencies are being improved.
                    Because, in the future, 50 percent or more of the basic <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> materials will come from Presidential libraries, HO is devoting
                    much attention to them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany pointed out that the key to working with intelligence material was how
                    much access advisory committee members needed. The present <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> plan does not go into detail on committee access and need to
                    know. Will all the members need an SI clearance or should there be a working
                    group formed to handle compartmented information? The committee will have to
                    work out what the plan means in terms of practices and procedures and establish
                    a “model” for itself and its successors, and “we have to do this in a way that
                    will make the committee happy.” The committee, Mr. Slany stated, has to tell the
                    Department if it is heading in the right direction in planning and designing the
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes.</p>
                <p>There followed a brief discussion between Perkins and Slany on the need-to-know
                    process. Slany stated that a judgment is based upon the decision of a government
                    official in charge of a body of information. Perkins observed that the State
                    Department can grant access for documents it produces but does not have this
                    authority over other agency documents. This issue was raised several times as
                    the members struggled with the problem of how to obtain access to other agency
                    documents.</p>
                <p rend="underline">H Presentation on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Legislation</p>
                <p>The Deputy Assistant Secretary for Congressional affairs, Richard Mueller,
                    summarized the recent and current status of legislation concerning the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes and a statutory advisory committee. He
                    believes the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> issue will resurface on the Hill in
                    April. Mueller listed several objections to the current legislation: it uses the
                    advisory committee as a declassification group; it promotes Congressional
                    micromanagement which casts the most simple operational activities in concrete,
                    and it imposes a burden on committee members that many in the academic community
                    may not have time to assume.</p>
                <p>The committee members did not agree with this analysis. They believe that, if
                    other agencies cooperate, they will not have all that much to do. They feel
                    strongly that their responsibilities must be established in law, lest what they
                    see as the current favorable environment shift in the future. They did not agree
                    that micromanagement was a significant obstacle and argued for a “basic” law
                    that would establish <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in formal legislation, clothe
                    the advisory committee in a formal legal setting, formalize the 30-year plan,
                    institutionalize the appeal process, and establish meaningful time limitations.
                    They believe that such a basic bill can be worked out to meet everyone’s
                    needs.</p>
                <p>Mueller conceded from the outset that the Department’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> plan may not work and that we may have to fall back upon trying
                    to improve the present legislative language. He then announced that H had made
                    appointments for committee members to go up to the Hill this afternoon. He
                    emphasized that they were free to voice their own opinions and that the
                    Department was not stage-managing their appearance.</p>
                <p rend="underline">Committee Views on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Plan</p>
                <p>At the direction of the chairman, the committee undertook a paragraph by
                    paragraph consideration of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> plan.</p>
                <p>On the three paragraphs under “expanding the scope of research for the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series,” there was general agreement among the
                    committee members that a Presidential memorandum will not have any effect on CIA
                    or DOD. Some thought perhaps an Executive Order would be better. However, an EO
                    would need other agency concurrence and therefore is not a practical way to go.
                    Previous Presidential memos on this subject have been quickly discarded or
                    forgotten.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that to ask the President to ask other agencies to cooperate with
                    State is a “cliche”. Rosenberg asked what evidence there was that other agencies
                    have changed their views about cooperating with State. Slany said they have
                    asked about State’s plan and have opened some doors.</p>
                <p>Continuing on this subject, Kimball asked if there is any appeal from other
                    agency decisions on access. Slany responded that we have to find out what the
                    sticking points are, and noted that this plan mobilizes more support within
                    State than previous plans. The chairman characterized the plan’s reference to
                    enlisting House and Senate historians as “cute”, but there was no substantive
                    comment on this aspect of the plan.</p>
                <p>The committee’s main focus was on the plan’s declassification paragraphs. Kimball
                    said the committee wanted to see the procedures used to appeal withholding of
                    documents and to be assured that there is a timetable for moving such documents
                    along. The committee approved of the plan’s provisions for HO being able to
                    appeal to P and to M any issues not resolved at the bureau level.</p>
                <p>For clarification of the declassification problem and process, Machak offered
                    several observations on the committee’s discussion. Most importantly, provisions
                    of the proposed legislation would retard rather than help to accelerate
                    information retrieval and declassification review. The bill would establish
                    additional and complex procedures relating, notably, to committee review and to
                    appeals procedures. These processes would draw severely limited manpower
                    resources away from present efforts to speed the declassification aspects of the
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> process. The effect would be to slow down rather
                    than speed up publication schedules.</p>
                <p>Another provision in the draft legislation which would work counter to the
                    committee’s objectives is the proposed imposition of a 30-year line for
                    “automatic” declassification of State Department records. Machak noted that the
                    Department continues to press toward the 30-year line as an objective but that,
                    again, a legislative requirement would force diversion of resources from
                    processing documents for the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. The organization and
                    condition of State files preclude automatic declassification by file blocks
                    because of the frequent interlarding of other-agency material, or national
                    security information still protected by provisions of law and/or Executive
                    Order, and of non-security file material which by law must be segregated. The
                    latter categories include personnel and visa files. Enactment of the 30-year
                    provision would mandate review of some 16 million pages by 1993--a task that
                    would require additional manpower far beyond any reasonable expectation given
                    budgetary constraints and competing demands in other areas.</p>
                <p>Machak commented also that the limited listing of categories of information or
                    documents for possible withholding presents major problems for the
                    declassification process, for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and for release of
                    general files. There is no explicit provision for protection of foreign
                    government documents or of information provided by foreign governments in
                    confidence. Such protection of the diplomatic process is essential to avoid
                    damaging the conduct of contemporary foreign relations. The measures might
                    similarly force imposition of classification or comparable controls on visa and
                    personnel files to ensure proper protection.</p>
                <p>In the light of this discussion, the Chairman observed that he would not object
                    to incorporation of “the Kellogg principles” into the legislation.</p>
                <p>The committee then returned to a discussion of how to obtain access to other
                    agency documents. The members had no specific problems with the plan’s language,
                    but evidenced skepticism that anything in the plan would overcome this basic
                    problem. Slany’s assurance that “we are working on procedures” did not blunt
                    this line of thinking and there were repeated requests to “see these
                    procedures.” The members also wanted to be reassured that bureaucratic inertia
                    would be thwarted and urged some kind of a timetable to move documents through
                    the appeals process. They also voiced reservations about the feasibility of
                    preparing summaries of deleted information.</p>
                <p>Two members wanted stronger language on the access issue (e.g. other agency
                    historians should be “ordered” not just “requested” to cooperate with the State
                    Department). They also believe they need some kind of a commitment on the
                    question of other agency cooperation. The chairman wanted to know what would be
                    done in the case of non-compliance by other agencies, but this question was
                    finessed in his subsequent observation that he views the advisory committee as a
                    “goad.”</p>
                <p>In response to several questions on member clearances, Slany said the Department
                    is committed to the top secret level but that no other access clearances are
                    underway. Ms. Van Camp stated that the committee members need the same
                    clearances as the Department’s historians. Ms. Glad asked if they would have
                    access to covert operations material. Slany responded that “we will have to look
                    into this,” adding that the Department’s historians rarely see this type of
                    information.</p>
                <p>Several members said they would send out committee findings on declassification
                    issues to their professional societies. Kimball noted that the committee does
                    not want to get into attesting to the validity of each <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> volume, but it can attest to the integrity of the <hi
                        rend="underline">process</hi>. At this point there was a lively but
                    inconclusive debate on whether the advisory committee should either approve or
                    disapprove each volume or whether it should condense its views in its annual
                    report.</p>
                <p>There were several references to concern that nothing in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> plan itself insures the committee’s future position. There
                    appeared to be shared hope for some assurance of permanence and a shared fear
                    that the present amiable atmosphere could change quickly. Perkins recalled a
                    previous M memorandum that he said came close to abolishing the committee. No
                    one opposed the view that some kind of basic legislation, perhaps not as
                    detailed as that introduced in the Senate, was necessary to formally sanction
                    the role of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and the mandate of the advisory
                    committee and its members.</p>
                <p>Prof. Van Camp noted that the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> plan does encompass the
                    main concerns of the advisory committee. Prof. Kimball said that nothing
                    suggested in the course of this meeting impinges upon the Department’s plan, but
                    he urged that the committee <hi rend="underline">not</hi> take a position until
                    the plan’s procedures are worked out. The chairman stated he has consulted five
                    past chairmen of this committee and while they like the plan, they are skeptical
                    about chances for its implementation. Slany commented that “your skepticism may
                    not be as great as ours.” Kimball and Perkins both expressed the view that if
                    the plan does not work, there are other options. They observed, however, that
                    they do not see the committee’s future role as a watchdog for the Congress.</p>
                <p>At the end of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> plan review, the chairman announced
                    that the committee would go into executive session.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
