<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1992-11-05">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, November
                    1992</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1992</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1992-11-05">November 05, 1992</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[1]" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-november-5--6--1992_1">
                <head>ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON HISTORICAL DIPLOMATIC DOCUMENTATION NOVEMBER 5-6,
                    1992</head>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Committee Members</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Warren Kimball, Chairman</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Betty Glad</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>George Herring</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Anna Nelson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Bradford Perkins</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jane Picker</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Arnold Taylor</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Ann Van Camp</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Office of the Historian</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>William Z. Slany</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Glenn W. LaFantasie</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Rita M. Baker</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>M. Paul Claussen</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>W. Taylor Fain</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Vicki E. Futscher</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David H. Herschler</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Edward C. Keefer</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David W. Mabon</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Nina J. Noring</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David S. Patterson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Althea W. Robinson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Charles S. Sampson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Harriet D. Schwar</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Louis D. Smith</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeffrey A. Soukup</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Shirley T. Taylor</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Carolyn Yee</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Administration</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Historical Documents Review Division</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Joe H. Chaddic, Director</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>William C. Hamilton</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeanne Pryor</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Records Management Staff</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Kenneth Rossman, Chief</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>John T. Fawcett, Assistant Archivist, Presidential Libraries</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>George C. Chalou</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David A. Langbart</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeanne Schauble, Chief, Records Declassification Division</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Nancy Smith</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Others</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>J. Kenneth McDonald, Chief Historian, Central Intelligence Agency
                            (CIA)</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Ethel Theis, Associate Director, Information Security Oversight Office
                            (ISOO)</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Page Miller</p></item>
                </list>
                <pb n="2" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0002"/>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--november-5--9-30-10-45-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, November 5, 9:30-10:45 a.m.</hi></head>
                <p>Chairman Warren Kimball called the meeting to order at 9:40 a.m. Copies of the
                    “original” as well as “revised” minutes of the July meeting of the Committee
                    were distributed. In discussion of the minutes, David Patterson offered a
                    correction that he had not been at the Kennedy Library “the previous week” but
                    was in fact there during the meeting of the Committee. Anna Nelson asked the
                    Committee to accept the original minutes instead of the revised version with
                    bracketed additions. Kimball said the additions had allowed participants to
                    “recant,” hopefully for the sake of accuracy, but Jane Picker suggested that the
                    original minutes be approved, noting the additional bracketed materials for
                    informational purposes.</p>
                <p>Joe Chaddic did not agree that the original minutes were necessarily correct. The
                    Historical Documents Review Division (HDR) had corrected wrong information.
                    Bradford Perkins thought the additions were clarifying objections. Picker made
                    the point that there was a distinction between “accept” and “approve,” with the
                    former meaning the minutes had been received but not approved, but Nelson said
                    she made no such distinction and that the additions were changes, not
                    clarifications. Kimball wanted members to review the minutes that evening and
                    raise the problem tomorrow with emphasis on substantive issues. William Slany
                    remarked that in the future he would try to circulate the original draft to
                    participants and incorporate later revisions and proposed changes by the
                    Committee.</p>
                <p>Kimball raised the question of where to make the minutes of Committee meetings
                    available to the public. Slany indicated that the Historian’s Office (PA/HO) was
                    exploring several possibilities, but the matter remained unresolved.</p>
                <p>The Committee then approved the draft agenda.</p>
                <p>Kimball, noting that neither Richard Boucher nor Grace Moe was able to attend
                    this meeting, called on Slany for his report on the implementation of the
                    legislation. Referring to the agenda, Slany mentioned that Under Secretary
                    Rogers would be unable to meet with the Committee at lunch, which would now be
                    strictly a working session. Chaddic added that his superior, Admiral Fort, had
                    accepted the luncheon invitation for Friday. Jeanne Schauble from NARA would
                    attend the Friday morning sessions.</p>
                <p>Slany said he would focus on a few points. Although he had not sent the Committee
                    a written report, Slany stressed that PA/HO was making every effort to meet the
                    legislative requirements, including deadlines, even though they caused great
                    anxiety in both PA/HO and HDR. With regard to research, <pb n="3" xml:id="pg_3"
                        facs="0003"/> the access agreements are not quite complete but have served
                    PA/HO needs so far. DOD had not yet agreed to sign a memorandum of agreement.
                    DOD had exchanged letters with him but had not agreed to a process that is fully
                    consonant with the legislation, particularly with respect to Committee access.
                    The problem involves the military services, but the OSD and JCS (within OSD)
                    records are generally available.</p>
                <p>Slany continued that he had also written to and spoken with David Gaddy, the
                    Historian at NSA, whose position is that the agency cannot respond unless PA/HO
                    asks for something. Slany said he had sent them tables of contents from <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. NSA responded that its
                    records as a whole were not of interest to the series, and indicated that PA/HO
                    should ask for particular documents. George Herring suggested that PA/HO should
                    ask for the intelligence intercepts relating to the Gulf of Tonkin incident.
                    Kimball said we should ask for NSA’s finding aids. Slany pointed out that NSA
                    can say that they are “hard to assemble.” Kimball and Herring compared the
                    situation to the separate units of the CIA. Slany agreed but added that DOD is
                    cooperating and sharing its finding aids. They are still regulated by the 1978
                    interagency access agreement.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that the Legal Adviser’s Office could assist in driving home to
                    DOD what the recent law stipulated, or perhaps Jane Picker could write to DOD.
                    He inquired whether Committee help was required on the interagency agreements.
                    Slany indicated that for the moment it was not.</p>
                <p>Slany continued that John Fawcett’s presence reminded him of the recent agreement
                    between NARA and the State Department. He indicated that this is a good
                    agreement. It provides for a subvention to NARA to hire an archives technician
                    at the LBJ Library to facilitate PA/HO historians’ access to documentation
                    there. PA/HO provided NARA with a detailed, if optimistic, research plan. “It’s
                    as good as we can fashion,” he said. Patterson had already been to the LBJ
                    Library, and he (Slany), David Herschler, and others would soon follow.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked about the impact of PA/HO’s research at the Johnson Library on the
                    availability of materials to outside scholars and on the processing of mandatory
                    review requests. Fawcett remarked that the technician will be a help to NARA in
                    meeting State Department needs and minimizing the adverse impact on outside
                    researchers. Other forces were at play at the LBJ Library, however. The recent
                    JFK legislation mandates massive amounts of work in the review of and access to
                    these materials. A review board will determine how wide an area this covers.
                    NARA will ask for more funding which will not come until 1994. It has to respond
                    to two additional laws now, including the POW/MIA issue. Subpoenas for large
                    amounts of materials, moreover, have meant that NARA has lost control over its
                    own house. Herring commented that accelerated processing <pb n="4" xml:id="pg_4"
                        facs="0004"/> for the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    will help researchers in the long run, and Fawcett agreed.</p>
                <p>Kimball sought clarification from Chaddic on the declassification guidelines. He
                    speculated that HDR reviewers might accompany PA/HO researchers to the LBJ
                    Library with guidelines at the same time as research is conducted on <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Could the two activities go
                    on simultaneously, or did it have to be a two-step process? Chaddic replied that
                    his people did not go to the Presidential libraries; Fawcett added that the two
                    operated separately and he did not know how they could work better together.
                    Herschler interjected that HDR had declassification authority over State
                    Department information only, and the two processes had to be separate. Kimball
                    noted that HDR declassified only the documents selected by PA/HO (one percent or
                    so) and questioned the two stages, but Perkins said it was always a two-stage
                    process.</p>
                <p>Kimball persisted that a procedure needed to be worked out. Glenn LaFantasie said
                    he was not convinced that PA/HO research covered sufficient documentation at the
                    Library to conduct a systematic declassification review. Slany expressed anxiety
                    about giving historians declassification authority but noted that the selection
                    of documents for the series provides the basis for the Department’s guidelines.
                    Herschler pointed out that only a small percentage of documents at the
                    Presidential libraries are State Department documents and that other agencies
                    would need to provide guidelines of their own for such a procedure to work.
                    Fawcett commented that the reviewers would have to have interagency
                    declassification authority, which would be good if it could be done because the
                    present procedure was difficult.</p>
                <p>Regarding the compilation process, Slany said that PA/HO was generally on
                    schedule, and difficulties were being worked out with HDR. It was not possible
                    to complete every compilation on time because of problems of access and
                    receiving copies of agency documentation, e.g. CIA, so sometimes the manuscript
                    was submitted to HDR with comments that more documents would be forthcoming.
                    PA/HO was reorganized to focus almost entirely on the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. The Office delivered seven manuscripts in
                    1991 for declassification review, twice as many in 1992, and the pace would
                    continue in 1993.</p>
                <p>Perkins wondered whether this CIA problem would go away; he answered his own
                    query, saying that he thought so. Slany agreed, citing PA/HO’s good working
                    relationship with Ken McDonald and his staff, but the problem would not
                    disappear completely.</p>
                <pb n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0005"/>
                <p>Slany continued that PA/HO had recently made considerable progress with HDR, and
                    he cited Herschler’s work with Jeanne Pryor, which had made the work “leap
                    forward.” Yet some agencies are not meeting the 120-day cycle in every case, and
                    this fact may ultimately hold back the publication schedule more than anything
                    else. Kimball noted that in some cases reviewers argue that when additional
                    manuscript comes in, the 120-day clock restarts. Slany elaborated on the
                    agencies’ position. They feel they’re being “jerked around” when new documents
                    are submitted later. Whether it is 10 or 50 documents added, PA/HO has to work
                    out the procedures with the agencies. There has to be a regular dialogue
                    contributing to a closer relationship. PA/HO relies on HDR for coordination with
                    the other agencies.</p>
                <p>Kimball raised the issue of the report for Under Secretary Rogers recommending
                    that PA/HO take over coordination of declassification of <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, a proposal, he recalled, that Chaddic had
                    endorsed. Slany agreed that this had been suggested. He did not know the status
                    at the moment, and the transition to a new administration would likely cause
                    delay. Chaddic regretted that Slany did not have more information on this point.
                    Perkins thought that this proposal would require PA/HO to take on an additional
                    administrative burden of arguing with the agencies and White House, which would
                    be a big job. Slany replied that PA/HO would have to have additional resources
                    to take on this added burden.</p>
                <p>Pryor noted that the volumes on National Security Policy and Arms Control, both
                    for 1958-1960 and 1961-1963, were taking a long time to go through DOD and
                    especially the Department of Energy (DOE). Approximately 500-600 documents are
                    now at DOE for declassification review. These are the slowest subject areas.
                    When Kimball asked whether there was an access agreement with DOE, Slany
                    responded that there was not, but that the Office was working on it. Pryor
                    continued that she did not know what DOE’s problem is. Slany interjoined that
                    access is the other side of the clearance process and thus a different problem.
                    Kimball stated that the law did not exempt DOE from the 120-day requirement.</p>
                <p>Slany circulated a list of recently published volumes and those to be published.
                    He noted that several microfiche editions are out-of-print, so they actually
                    sell. Kimball remarked that the list contains information that the professional
                    associations should have. They can print parts of it in their publications.
                    LaFantasie said he was giving this information to Jim Herschberg at the Cold War
                    History Project, and Kimball said the reach of that organization, although
                    growing, was limited. Nelson said she prepared a summary list for the <hi
                        rend="underline">OAH Newsletter</hi>, which will publish it in the issue
                    after next.</p>
                <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0006"/>
                <p>Kimball inquired about the planning process for the Johnson volumes. LaFantasie
                    replied that he was moving ahead with the editorial format and design of the
                    volumes, and that a research and travel plan had been developed by working with
                    PA/HO staff and the Johnson Library. Herschler added that the most recent
                    Production Chart reflects the schedule for the Johnson volumes, and that the
                    first of the Johnson volumes was scheduled to be compiled by the spring.
                    LaFantasie pointed out that Arms Control is the first scheduled volume for the
                    Johnson presidency, and National Security Policy comes soon after it. Kimball
                    concluded that the Nelson/Taylor subcommittee should work with PA/HO on making
                    formal Committee assignments before the next Committee meeting to review
                    compilations in the Johnson volumes.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a coffee break at 10:50 a.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--november-5--11-noon_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, November 5, 11-Noon</hi></head>
                <p>The Committee reconvened at 11:10 a.m. Kimball raised the issue of the Department
                    of Energy’s declassification process. He said that DOE’s long delays in
                    declassifying <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, especially
                    the 1961-1963 volumes on National Security Policy and on Arms Control would
                    adversely affect PA/HO’s ability to meet its legally mandated publication
                    deadlines. He asked Chaddic to elaborate, if he could, on the reasons for DOE’s
                    delays and what measures the Committee could take to expedite the process.</p>
                <p>Pryor responded by saying that all attempts &#x02014; letters, phone calls, and
                    other engagements &#x02014; with DOE staff have failed to expedite their
                    declassification process. Pryor informed the Committee that the declassification
                    process for these volumes might be delayed longer than other volumes because
                    they will likely be given to 2 or 3 other agencies for their own internal
                    review. In addition, she suspected that DOE does not have the resources
                    necessary to successfully complete the review process within the 120-day
                    limit.</p>
                <p>Perkins suggested to Kimball that he request Chaddic or Slany to provide a list
                    of volumes that have been held up in the declassification process. Kimball could
                    then draft a letter to the House Foreign Affairs Committee and the Senate
                    Foreign Relations Committee in order to expedite DOE’s declassification process.
                    Kimball asked Chaddic to provide a letter, documenting clearance delays in other
                    agencies, to be forwarded to him through Slany, before the Committee would take
                    any action on the matter with Congress.</p>
                <p>After some discussion about the agenda, Picker reported on suggested boilerplate
                    language in <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> prefaces describing the
                    role of the Advisory Committee for a particular <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7"
                        facs="0007"/> volume. Picker began by saying that there are three proposed
                    boilerplate prefaces each concerning a different situation in regard to the
                    Committee’s treatment of each volume. She read four letters from Committee
                    members who had responded to her request for comments and/or revisions to the
                    boilerplate texts.</p>
                <p>Picker emphasized that the language of the boilerplates was taken directly from
                    the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> statute. The text of boilerplate
                    1, in the event the Committee fully approves of the volume, was discussed
                    specifically in regard to the word “comprehensive.” Emily Rosenberg (absent) in
                    a letter to Picker suggested that “representative” replace “comprehensive” since
                    the latter term is somewhat misleading. Picker said that Rosenberg’s suggestion
                    was the most “radical,” since it adds a new word to the existing statute
                    language. Perkins felt the word “representative” would not be a good choice.
                    Kimball added that the Committee should try to work within the confines of the
                    statute language. Nelson pointed out that the Committee should not get into the
                    business of putting its imprimatur on the volumes.</p>
                <p>Picker then asked for guidance on the particulars of the appeal boilerplate
                    language. A choice had to be made about the use of the word “misleading” in
                    version (b) and how it might replace, or be used in conjunction with, the words
                    “inaccurate” and “incomplete” in version (a) resulting in a wholly different
                    version. The crux of the issue was whether to retain the language of the statute
                    or to introduce new language.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested that it was important for the preface to include something to the
                    effect that the Committee does not review all volumes. Perkins added that
                    perhaps boilerplate 2 should include a sentence similar to: “the Committee
                    reviews only selected volumes.” Kimball expressed his discomfort with Perkins’
                    suggestion, while Glad wanted to get across the point that the Committee reviews
                    volumes on the basis, in part, of their potential problems with the
                    declassification process. Perkins also suggested that the Committee was not
                    “able” to review all the volumes given time constraints. Glad did not like the
                    word “able” since it implied that the Committee was, in some measure, not
                    carrying out its responsibilities.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that Picker and Glad work with LaFantasie to prepare new draft
                    boilerplate language for the prefaces that the other members of the Committee
                    could read and consider the following day, Friday, November 6, at 3:30 p.m. In
                    closing, Kimball thought that the preface had to include some “practical
                    instructions” to the reader regarding the Committee’s handling of each
                    volume.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for lunch at 12:10 p.m.</p>
                <pb n="8" xml:id="pg_8" facs="0008"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--november-5--1-30-3-15-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 5, 1:30-3:15 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>The Committee reconvened at 1:30 p.m. The Herring/Glad subcommittee that
                    evaluated the declassification review of <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, 1958-1960, vol. XVII, Indonesia, made its report to the full
                    Committee. Herring reported that there were many small excisions -- 1-2 words to
                    2-3 sentences.</p>
                <p>Herring reported that John Pereira, the CIA official who met with the
                    subcommittee, had told them that restoring some of these excisions would not be
                    a problem and suggested resubmitting the material and requesting expeditious
                    handling. The subcommittee recommended that the material be resubmitted on the
                    grounds that publishing the documents with the deletions would “grossly distort”
                    the picture of events in 1958-1959.</p>
                <p>The remaining denied material consisted of 11 fully withheld documents. The
                    denied documents mainly concerned foreign government information and these
                    documents should be resubmitted to HDR and CIA (although CIA had only concurred
                    in the original HDR decision to deny on the grounds of foreign government
                    information for many of these denied documents). Some documents were of higher
                    priority than others; Herring and Glad recommended publishing those portions of
                    the documents containing only U.S.-generated information and/or summarizing U.S.
                    policy contained in the documents if HDR would not clear without concurrence of
                    the foreign government involved. Herring and Glad also recommended that the
                    compiler in PA/HO should make the judgment of which fully denied documents to
                    resubmit.</p>
                <p>Glad expressed the view that differences between HDR and PA/HO with respect to
                    the appealed documents could be resolved if HDR were fully informed of new CIA
                    guidelines for declassification, copies of which were distributed by Pereira at
                    the subcommittee meeting.</p>
                <p>The subcommittee recommended that the Department declassifiers in the future
                    anticipate the less strict CIA guidelines and that State revise its guidelines
                    to be more specific about what is sensitive in relations with friendly
                    governments. Herring suggested that State and CIA declassifiers meet to discuss
                    the guidelines so that State’s guidelines would be more in line with CIA’s.</p>
                <p>Kimball next asked Perkins to report on the subcommittee that evaluated the
                    declassification review of <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    1961-1963, Vol. X, Cuba, Jan. 1961-Sept. 1962. Perkins felt that the withheld
                    documents were not important and furthermore would not be harmful if released.
                    He noted that the deletions and denials did not “fundamentally distort” the
                    record.</p>
                <pb n="9" xml:id="pg_9" facs="0009"/>
                <p>This subcommittee had the same experience with Pereira, the CIA official, who
                    indicated that things will loosen up in declassifying CIA material. It also
                    recommended that HDR be more familiar with the new CIA guidelines on
                    declassification.</p>
                <p>Kimball brought up the model guidelines on Mexico and the issue of foreign
                    government information. The guidelines provided NARA for declassification review
                    of State Department documents were too restrictive and too many documents had to
                    be referred back to State.</p>
                <p>Perkins made two additional points on the Cuba volume: 1) there were extensive
                    deletions of material that documented a certain aspect of U.S. attitude toward
                    Castro and 2) some documents previously reviewed under FOIA were not re-reviewed
                    for the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> manuscript.</p>
                <p>Taylor raised the question of CIA acknowledgement of information that was already
                    in the public domain. Nelson said that traditionally the CIA does not release
                    information just because it is publicly known. Kimball recalled that Pereira
                    indicated that his staff would reconsider this information under the new
                    guidelines.</p>
                <p>Based on their discussions with Pereira the previous day, both subcommittees
                    recommended resubmission of the denied material to the CIA for consideration by
                    the Historical Review Group under its new declassification guidelines.</p>
                <p>The Committee then discussed the issue of access to CIA records. Kimball noted
                    that to maintain the credibility of volumes, the compilers must account for
                    issues on which documentation is non-existent or not available to the compilers.
                    Slany believed that the preface should indicate the limits of access at the CIA,
                    but pointed out the difficulty of finding a middle course: PA/HO had access but
                    not complete access.</p>
                <p>The provenance cited for CIA material used or cited in <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> bears no correlation to the actual physical
                    whereabouts of the documents. The documents are given “job” numbers for handling
                    purposes. George Chalou of the National Archives pointed out, however, that
                    these job numbers stay with the records when they are transferred to NARA.</p>
                <p>Nelson pointed out that the CIA restricts its “openness” by restricting access to
                    its records. Kimball asked if the Committee felt that the preface should include
                    a statement about the nature of PA/HO’s access to CIA files, in neutral language
                    of course.</p>
                <p>In response to a question, Chalou explained that the range of CIA documentation
                    transferred to NARA under the Historical <pb n="10" xml:id="pg_10" facs="0010"/>
                    Review Program included CIA histories and high visibility files such as the
                    Cuban missile crisis and Guatemala. The Historical Review Program is only one
                    route for transfer to NARA of CIA documentation, as other CIA documentation is
                    transferred through the appraisal/accessioning process. In general, NARA takes
                    what CIA gives them.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that the Committee’s responsibility for the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series extended to all departments while its
                    responsibility for transfer of records to NARA extended to State only. He asked
                    if the PA/HO historians are asking the right questions when they go to an
                    agency, in a way that forces the agency to respond under the law, i.e., are you
                    meeting the requirements of access under the law? The Committee doesn’t want to
                    go to an agency and make unfounded accusations that it is not complying.</p>
                <p>Slany questioned how to define “full access.” Was it necessary to define in the
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes the nature of the
                    access? Kimball noted that the Committee has questions about whether the CIA is
                    meeting the access requirements of the law. Does the Committee need to develop a
                    way to monitor this process?</p>
                <p>Nelson said that the CIA is in a state of flux; PA/HO should resubmit the
                    documents for the two volumes (i.e., Indonesia, 1958-1960 and Cuba, 1961-1962)
                    and see if the agency will release them.</p>
                <p>Kimball pointed out that there were two issues: the declassification of CIA
                    material that PA/HO has seen and the material that PA/HO doesn’t see. He wanted
                    to raise this with Ken McDonald on Friday, appoint a subcommittee, and take it
                    up at the next meeting.</p>
                <p>Ann Van Camp said it was important to bring up this issue of access now to ensure
                    that changes were made in the proper way. Kimball agreed. Picker wanted to press
                    the issue now with officials at CIA before personnel changes resulting from the
                    change in administration occurred. Herring said that the issue should be raised
                    with someone higher than McDonald.</p>
                <p>Glad thought that since CIA records are compartmentalized, it would be difficult
                    to expect consistent records management policy. She also asked if there were
                    finding aids. Chalou said that there are finding aids but it appears that the
                    CIA History Staff is limited in the materials to which they have access. He said
                    that it would be helpful if the agency compiled a centralized finding aid
                    because often the records officers are not aware of the extent of documentation.
                    He was working on the appraisal of CIA records and thought it was doubtful that
                    any one person at the CIA knows the total universe of the records.</p>
                <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11" facs="0011"/>
                <p>Kimball gave Chaddic an opportunity to comment. Chaddic mentioned four
                    points:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>1) HDR should not anticipate agency declassification
                        decisions.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>2) He acknowledged the necessity of an initiative with CIA to examine new
                            guidelines.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>3) He welcomed the resubmission of Indonesia and Cuba
                        documents.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>4) It was HDR’s policy to re-review FOIA decisions; he would take up this
                            matter with his staff.</p></item>
                </list>
                <p>Kimball asked about NSC clearances. Herschler pointed out that often the NSC
                    releases more than other agencies by reducing or eliminating other agencies’
                    deletions. The problem with the NSC was time. Nelson asked what the schedule for
                    NSC clearances was. Pryor mentioned that the NSC currently has many special
                    projects: POW/MIA, Iran/Contra, Kennedy assassination.</p>
                <p>Following the presentations of the Glad-Herring and Kimball-Perkins
                    subcommittees, Slany showed the Committee a copy of an agreed Department policy
                    paper on the withholding of documents for national security reasons from the
                    1958-1960 compilation on Japan. The paper will serve as a model document
                    outlining the mechanism by which the State Department would justify (in
                    accordance with 22 USC 4351) the withholding of documents from the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> Series. This undertaking related
                    specifically to the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> compilation on
                    Japan, 1958-1960, which the Committee had considered the past spring and summer.
                    Slany said the document had taken 6 months to complete despite the fact that the
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation stipulated that it
                    should have been completed in 60 days. He said that it must be sent to Under
                    Secretary for Management Rogers for action.</p>
                <p>Kimball said it should be remembered that Rogers was a political appointee, so
                    any action on the paper would probably be delayed. He said that the provisions
                    of the document would make it a bureaucratic nightmare for the Department to
                    withhold documents from publication in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Slany said that the undertaking was basically the same document the Advisory
                    Committee had seen in July but that, on the insistence of the Office of the
                    Legal Adviser, the criteria for withholding documents from the compilation on
                    Japan had been made slightly more explicit. Kimball inquired whether Acting
                    Assistant Secretary Boucher’s minor corrections had been included in the version
                    that had gone for Rogers’ action. Slany indicated that they had. Kimball then
                    stated the Committee was satisfied and comfortable with the model.</p>
                <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12" facs="0012"/>
                <p>Discussion turned to Nelson’s draft “Consideration of a new Executive Order on
                    National Security Information.” Kimball said that Advisory Committee member
                    Emily Rosenberg (absent) had earlier suggested that the Committee consider such
                    an order in the event that a Clinton Administration should take office. The
                    Senate Foreign Relations Committee staff actively was exploring the need for
                    such an order. Kimball had then asked Nelson to formulate some thoughts on the
                    contents of the order.</p>
                <p>Nelson said that she had put together a brief (two page) memorandum on the topic
                    comprising five points to be contained in a proposed Executive Order:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>1) A new E.O. should specifically note that if a document has been
                            released it cannot be reclassified.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>2) All classified information should be declassified and made available
                            for research 30 years after it was prepared.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>3) If after 30 years, information should remain classified, the head of
                            the originating department must determine in writing that its continued
                            protection is necessary and must set a time for
                        declassification.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>4) Foreign government information in U.S. possession constitutes Federal
                            records over which the U.S. Government should have complete control.
                            Release determinations, therefore, are a matter of U.S.
                        policy.</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>5) Declassification of information under the provisions of mandatory
                            review should be subject to a balancing test. Information should be
                            released if the protection of this information is outweighed by public
                            interest in disclosure.</p></item>
                </list>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a break at 3:15.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--november-5--3-30-5-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 5, 3:30-5 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>Discussion returned to Nelson’s summary points on a new Executive Order. Kimball
                    suggested that a new order required both a short-term and long-term approach. In
                    the short-term, the Committee might establish a subcommittee to draft ideas and
                    act while the government was in transition. He stated that he was just trying to
                    get the Committee’s thoughts; the suggestions presented by Nelson could be
                    revised and modified. What was important was to create an atmosphere. He thought
                    that he would begin by talking to people on the Hill and that he might speak to
                    Frank Sieverts and Page Miller.</p>
                <p>Nelson said that the Committee needed to discover who was running the transition.
                    Glad noted that Warren Christopher was the Clinton foreign affairs adviser.</p>
                <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0013"/>
                <p>Nelson suggested that this is really a government information policy issue rather
                    than a strictly Department of State issue.</p>
                <p>Glad asked if it was appropriate for the Committee to be operating outside of
                    official channels. Should it send Nelson’s recommendations to the appropriate
                    people within the Bush administration with copies to members of the Clinton
                    transition team? Kimball responded that it was an unofficial paper.</p>
                <p>Picker stated that she understood that the deadline for the Department of State
                    transition was within the week. That did not leave much time. Slany indicated
                    that he had no knowledge of such a deadline within the Department. He suggested
                    that it was important to form the agenda for discussion.</p>
                <p>Kimball indicated that his intention to approach the transition team concerned
                    the short-term agenda; he also had in mind a long-term agenda. He reiterated the
                    importance of seeking to take advantage of whatever opportunity may be presented
                    by the transition, and perhaps act informally with members of Clinton’s
                    transition team. The Committee should also think long-term and, in deference to
                    Glad’s concerns, act more formally through government channels.</p>
                <p>Van Camp posed the question: “What are we trying to accomplish?” Kimball
                    responded that the question was whether and how to bring to the attention of the
                    transition team the Committee’s views on revision of E.O. 12356.</p>
                <p>Picker stated that during the transition period the Committee should concentrate
                    on getting President Bush’s signing statement rescinded. Van Camp noted that the
                    signing statement would no longer have effect at the end of the administration.
                    The Committee should concentrate on a new Executive Order.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that Nelson work with Herring in putting together a final copy
                    of the recommendations for a new Executive Order. The Advisory Committee would
                    receive copies, but would not be asked to clear the final version. Kimball would
                    use his contacts to raise the issue and other members could use theirs.</p>
                <p>Picker wondered if, for tactical reasons, the new Executive Order might suggest
                    25 years as the line of classification, giving the government the opportunity to
                    knock it back to 30. Nelson thought that would be a mistake because many
                    elements in the government really wanted 50 years as the line. NARA has found
                    that anything under 30 years proved too difficult to clear. She also worried
                    that 50 years for release of classified documents on nuclear, chemical, or
                    biological <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0014"/> weapons technology, as she
                    suggested in her paper, might be too soon, based on information provided by a
                    military person.</p>
                <p>Perkins noted that the British followed the 30 year line, which he suspected was
                    the norm. He wondered if the representatives from HDR and NARA wanted to make
                    suggestions to the paper.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked if Nelson was talking about all classified documents. Nelson
                    responded that she was only concerned with classified documents of historical
                    value. Chaddic asked about the protection of privacy. Shouldn’t that be included
                    in any new Executive Order? Perkins agreed that any Executive Order should
                    include the protection of privacy.</p>
                <p>Herring reminded the rest of the Committee that they were not writing an
                    Executive Order, just a statement of principles. Chalou asked whether the
                    Committee was trying to hit all the salient principles to be included in a new
                    Executive Order. Nelson replied that it was.</p>
                <p>Slany asked if the Committee intended to advocate another standard for
                    declassification other than the one that is in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> law. Nelson replied that the exemption for information which
                    “demonstrably imperils ongoing foreign relations” in the law is a tremendous
                    loophole. It certainly creates another standard. Kimball noted that the
                    government was already operating under two declassification standards &#x02014;
                    E.O. 12356 and the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> statute.</p>
                <p>Slany asked if the new Executive Order should address the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. Should it be used as a way for the President
                    to tell the Executive Branch to support <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>? Harriet Schwar recalled that we had Presidential directives
                    in the past. Wouldn’t one of these supersede Bush’s signing statement?</p>
                <p>Perkins wondered why the new Executive Order needed to limit itself to <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. There was an opportunity to
                    encourage application of new standards to all records at NARA.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested that the new Executive Order might also instruct agencies to
                    provide access for the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    research. Perkins thought that would be a mistake, that the Executive Order does
                    not need to become involved with access to finding aids.</p>
                <p>Slany suggested that the Executive Order should consider a system of access to
                    documentation before 30 years for scholars. Nelson asked Slany if he was
                    suggesting reestablishing privileged access. Kimball suggested that was a topic
                    for another Executive Order. Support for the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series was appropriate, but access to material less <pb
                        n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0015"/> than 30 years old for outside scholars
                    was outside the Committee’s purview.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie thought that the Committee should think big, and it just might get
                    what it asks for. Slany suggested that a Clinton administration might be
                    interested in liberalization of the existing Executive Order. Nelson expressed
                    her view that the government would never allow it. Perkins opined that
                    establishing procedures for “privileged access” was inviting chaos. Systematic
                    declassification would come to a grinding halt.</p>
                <p>Glad inquired what the current procedure was for individuals obtaining access to
                    documents outside the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA). Slany responded that it
                    depended on the agency in question. David Langbart of NARA recounted examples in
                    the past where State Department records were accessed outside the FOIA, and that
                    the procedures varied over the years.</p>
                <p>In response to Kimball’s request to restate his proposal, Slany explained that he
                    was looking for a practical way to allow access to classified material before 30
                    years. Kimball observed that Slany’s suggestion was too sweeping for a new
                    Executive Order and the Committee would not be prepared to support it. Van Camp
                    noted that perhaps the best course of action would be to encourage
                    declassification as soon as possible but not later than 30 years.</p>
                <p>Kimball then suggested that as the Committee was ahead of schedule on the agenda,
                    this would be a good time to hear from those compilers on the PA/HO staff who
                    were present, reserving time to hear from others on Friday.</p>
                <p>Schwar noted that the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation
                    asks for comprehensiveness and a 30-year publication date. In practice this
                    creates a contradiction. The current schedule is not realistic. She was being
                    asked to produce two volumes in 20 months. That did not allow time for sickness
                    or vacation. The deadlines were also unrealistic when one considers the
                    additional work given to compilers required to publish pre-1964 volumes already
                    in the pipeline.</p>
                <p>Kimball recalled that the Committee had discussed this issue in the past. For
                    that reason it wanted to look over the shoulders of the compilers as they
                    completed the first couple of volumes of the Johnson years. Kimball now wondered
                    if this projected approach will work. Taylor stated that the Committee had not
                    really discussed this issue beyond its intention to hear from the PA/HO
                    compilers.</p>
                <p>Nelson posed the question: Is it humanly possible for the staff to do its work
                    within the schedule mandated by legislative deadlines and still produce a
                    quality product?</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0016"/>
                <p>Kimball noted that the new editorial approach of Glenn LaFantasie might allow for
                    quicker compilation. Nelson inquired how long it took to produce a volume. Slany
                    responded that one year was about the average, although it varied according to
                    individual and subject.</p>
                <p>Ted Keefer suggested that one year was a very optimistic figure. No one can do a
                    volume in 6 months or even 8 months, therefore it would be difficult to average
                    a volume per year. Remember, of course, Keefer continued, Johnson volumes cover
                    40% more time than Kennedy volumes. Slany stated that one individual had done a
                    volume in 9 months. Herschler suggested that while the research and selection
                    will take more time under the legislation, annotation will not be as
                    time-consuming because of the reduced size of the volumes.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked if it takes more time to do a 600-page volume than a 1200 page
                    volume? He suspected that the more selective a volume is, the more difficult. He
                    did not hold out much hope for saving time because of smaller volumes. Keefer
                    agreed that shorter volumes are not necessarily faster to produce as they were
                    usually more difficult, although he conceded that they required less time for
                    editorial processing.</p>
                <p>Nelson noted that the spirit of the legislation was for a good <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series, faster, but also
                    comprehensive. Kimball wondered how the Committee could judge whether and to
                    what extent there was a problem.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie suggested that the Committee did not need to await a finished volume.
                    Compilers’ concerns should be raised with their division chiefs who would then
                    come to him. These kinds of concerns have not been brought to him in the past by
                    the division chiefs, who had worked closely with him in designing the compiling
                    schedule for the Johnson volumes. In Harriet’s case, her division has one of the
                    the heaviest loads -- 11 volumes for 4 people. The Office has been engaged in a
                    planning process and had agreed that for size and quality 800 pages seemed a
                    workable solution.</p>
                <p>Kimball observed that in the past the Committee had not become involved in the
                    resources question. PA/HO now has a plan; the Committee should allow time to see
                    how it works and then discuss it with the compilers. The Committee is certainly
                    concerned about the quality of the series, but he did not believe it should
                    micromanage PA/HO. Nelson thought that the issue should be on the agenda and, if
                    necessary, second-guess PA/HO’s management, because the Committee was doing so
                    with regard to all the other offices and agencies involved in the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Schwar felt that the problem was one of resources. Everyone was trying to work
                    efficiently and within the limits <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0017"/>
                    imposed. Glad asked if PA/HO had gained resources coincident to the legislation.
                    Slany indicated the resource problem was FTEs. He held out little prospects for
                    new hirings, as he had just fended off bureau-wide and Department-wide cuts in
                    the past year. He did have some contract resources in the budget, however.</p>
                <p>Picker stated that it was not a question of resources, but comprehensiveness. The
                    series by law had to be comprehensive. Perkins pointed out that
                    comprehensiveness is a subjective factor. Kimball suggested that serious
                    sacrifices in quality of the compilations should be brought to the Committee’s
                    attention.</p>
                <p>The Committee then returned to the matter of boilerplate language for the
                    prefaces as it related to the Committee. Picker suggested that the way to
                    explain why the Committee did not review all volumes was to use the following
                    language: “Time restraints prevent the Advisory Committee from reviewing all
                    volumes in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series.”</p>
                <p>Glad wondered if the language ought to reflect the fact that the Committee
                    reviewed problem volumes. Picker suggested that the fewer and simpler the
                    boilerplates, the easier it would be to apply to the volumes. The language
                    should be straightforward when admitting that the Committee could not review all
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>Glad persisted, questioning why the Committee did not admit that it looked at
                    problem volumes. Picker stated that it would open the Committee up to criticism.
                    She then proposed the following language for the appeal boilerplate: “The
                    Advisory Committee so advised the Secretary of State and submitted
                    recommendations to resolve the issue. They were accepted in part [rejected, or
                    rejected in part].”</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that the more detail the language provided, the more trouble
                    the Committee could get into. Glad disagreed, believing that it was better to
                    come clean. These boilerplates made it look like the Committee was doing
                    nothing. There was an obligation to the public to explain the Committee’s
                    actions. Picker argued that then the Committee would have to write separate
                    language for each volume.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that as there was a clear disagreement, there should be a vote.
                    After brief summary statements of their positions by Picker and Glad, the
                    Committee voted 6 to 1 with one abstention to accept the minimalist position
                    proposed by Picker. There was a second decision by consensus to dropping the
                    language referring to the recommendations and response to the Committee’s
                    recommendations. The appeal boilerplate language therefore ends with “so advised
                    the Secretary of State.”</p>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="pg_18" facs="0018"/>
                <p>The Committee adjourned for the day at 5:10 p.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--november-6--9-10-30-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed session, November 6, 9-10:30 a.m.</hi></head>
                <p>The Committee convened at 9:15 a.m. Kimball made three announcements: (1) the
                    Japan volume appeal had been signed off on by PA and sent to Under Secretary
                    Rogers for action. [NOTE: Under Secretary Rogers approved the document on the
                    Japan compilation on November 5.] The volume will include the preface the
                    Committee agreed on. After further discussion it was noted that the volume would
                    not appear before the Indonesia portion was decided upon and that might require
                    additional changes and clearance of the preface. Slany noted that the deleted
                    documents would be listed in the volume. After some discussion it was
                    acknowledged that this prefatory language might not be required in every case
                    the Committee looks at, such as Cuba.</p>
                <p>Kimball continued with: (2) it has now been decided that overall coordination of
                    the other agency declassification function would be transferred to PA/HO. The
                    policy has been set. The decision has been signed off on. [NOTE: Kimball spoke
                    on the basis of information from Executive Secretary Slany. This information was
                    subsequently determined to be premature. No formal action had been taken at the
                    time of the preparation of these notes.] (3) The Committee will go into
                    executive session at 11:45 a.m. that day.</p>
                <p>Ken Rossman, chief of the Department’s Records Management Staff, addressed the
                    meeting. He pointed out that he would have preferred waiting until several
                    programs that he had explained to the Committee last spring had been completed.
                    His remarks, therefore, should be considered an interim report.</p>
                <p>Rossman noted that the 1960-1963 central files were transferred to NARA in the
                    spring of 1992. The Department spent $60,000 in overtime to accomplish it and
                    the archives was pleased with the transfer. He stated that he planned to move
                    the 1964-1966 central files to NARA in 1993. Rossman said that one of the basic
                    problems of capturing the most important Department of State records was that
                    there was this tradition within the Department that the central file was <hi
                        rend="underline">the</hi> file for Department of State material and
                    everything else was considered working materials. So his operation had to raise
                    consciousness within the Department that they should be saving their important
                    documents. He had several projects underway to achieve this.</p>
                <p>Rossman indicated that the Office of the Legal Adviser (L) has been a special
                    concern. Their recordkeeping practices have not been good, but he has had high
                    level support in trying to change cultures within L and has hope for progress.
                    His staff <pb n="19" xml:id="pg_19" facs="0019"/> will next work to “schedule”
                    the records of the Bureau of Economic and Business Affairs (EB) and the Bureau
                    of Legislative Affairs (H). He preferred a scheduling system to the current
                    Department practice of screening lot files.</p>
                <p>Rossman reported on electronic recordkeeping. The central computer system (FAIS)
                    was huge. The Department will soon convert from this system to a fully automated
                    worldwide information network and that will be difficult. The question is what
                    will the Department retire for use by researchers when it gets to the National
                    Archives. It will be easier for researchers to use the computer than the
                    microfiche. He said the computer had the telegrams since mid-1973 on magnetic
                    tape. Rossman said he is hoping he can work with NARA in this area.</p>
                <p>Rossman said the computer system’s index was excellent. When Nelson objected, he
                    clarified that it was excellent for the Department but maybe not for researchers
                    20 years down the road. The Department was now developing a system that would
                    completely automate the indexing of Department telegrams and eliminate the team
                    of indexers who now read every document. He said that the biggest problem with
                    the system is that much of it is trash and would have been destroyed routinely
                    if it had been a paper file. He used as an example the instructions to April
                    Glaspie saying she could take leave in late July 1990. That kind of record would
                    normally be kept for 3 years and then be routinely destroyed. He also spoke of
                    eliminating documents with ADMIN tags.</p>
                <p>As for E-MAIL, Rossman said it was used within the department and in 60-70 posts.
                    There was a secure international E-MAIL network. People have been asked to make
                    a paper copy of substantively important documents and file them with their other
                    files. This was the only way right now that this material could be saved.</p>
                <p>Kimball said with his E-MAIL system everything was automatically saved and it was
                    difficult to destroy things. Rossman said there were many systems in the
                    Department. Pryor said that when she was in ARA their system was dumped every 30
                    days. Rossman pointed out that if we saved all the E-MAIL it would be difficult
                    to use the system. One option was to force people in the process of using their
                    E-MAIL to give a command indicating whether the document should be saved on a
                    long-term basis or not, but the Department was resisting this. Rossman said that
                    from the perspective of historians and archivists, E-MAIL was a good thing; it
                    was capturing information that formerly had gone over the telephone.</p>
                <p>In regard to use of the files for FOIA and Mandatory Review searches, Rossman
                    said there was a continuing problem, especially in tracking files and insuring
                    that material <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20" facs="0020"/> withdrawn from the files
                    was refiled promptly and properly. Education and proper tracking were part of
                    the solution. Automating of the 693s was another part of the solution. The
                    Department was looking for a better records storage facility than the
                    Hyattsville operation and planned to obtain one with better research facilities,
                    which should help PA/HO.</p>
                <p>On the question of personal papers of Department officials, Rossman had recently
                    signed off on a memorandum telling current political appointees that they could
                    not take official government records with them. He said what was needed in
                    addition was a memo to the new group that would be coming in next year telling
                    them that they should maintain their personal documents separately. He said his
                    office also conducts follow-up educational efforts. When Baker left he was in
                    Tutwiler’s office going through documentation they wanted to take with them.
                    Officials need Rossman’s permission (as exercised through subordinates) for
                    taking documents out of the Department’s custody. Rossman said he has found
                    documents indicating that very good policies in this area were promulgated in
                    1967 but he doesn’t know what happened in between. He said it is a real problem
                    that some officers, including FSOs, think of government documents as being their
                    personal files or simply extra copies.</p>
                <p>Picker said she really did not understand what is happening now in L and what
                    would happen in the future with record preservation. Dalton had spoken at the
                    last meeting and the situation seemed to be bad now. Rossman said he could not
                    speak to it. But if you don’t have good control over paper records you have even
                    less when electronic records come into play. Rossman said the Department is
                    trying to change the culture and impose controls - get L to close off case files
                    when a case is over. Taylor asked if his office maintained a listing of
                    documents destroyed. Rossman indicated they did.</p>
                <p>Glad, citing the Oliver North case, asked whether the “shredding” of E-MAIL might
                    not be a problem. Rossman stated it could be. Chaddic, however, noted that in
                    his experience overseas more sensitive documents tend to be preserved.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie pointed out that early moving of the 1964-1966 central files to NARA
                    would present major problems for PA/HO research. Rossman stated that as he read
                    the legislation, a 26-year line existed for PA/HO to use records in the
                    Department and that he was opposed to moving the records twice -- to the
                    Department Records Service Center, and then to NARA. Nonetheless, he would
                    consult with PA/HO prior to any move of these records.</p>
                <p>Ethel Theis, Associate Director of the Interagency Security Oversight Office
                    (ISOO) then briefed the Committee. She explained that her office reports to the
                    President and the NSC <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0021"/> and is responsible
                    for overseeing the implementation of Executive Orders on classification and
                    declassification by all agencies either creating or holding classified
                    information. ISOO was created by an Executive Order and sends a report to the
                    President once a year. The agency responds to appeals from individuals to
                    classification and declassification decisions by agencies under the Mandatory
                    Review process. Ms. Theis distributed to the Committee several pamphlets
                    summarizing ISOO functions.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked what role did ISOO play in decisions over declassification. Nelson
                    explained that most of ISOO’s work involved classification. She asked what
                    percent of ISOO’s time was spent on declassification. Theis said very little.
                    ISOO became involved when there was a dispute among agencies on how to interpret
                    the Executive Order concerning mandatory review. She elaborated that ISOO needs
                    to be asked to resolve differences; it did not routinely monitor or oversee
                    consistent execution of the Executive Order.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked what role ISOO would play in the writing of a new Executive Order.
                    Theis responded that her office had been working on refining the current
                    Executive Order. She said for policy purposes ISOO responded to the NSC but that
                    the Department of Justice had the legal power over the interpretation of the
                    Executive Order. ISOO had a policy role.</p>
                <p>Asked about conflicts between the law governing the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and the Executive Order, Theis stated that ISOO would
                    reconcile differences upon request by the involved parties.</p>
                <p>Nelson said one of ISOO’s best contributions was the data it collected on the
                    number of documents declassified in a given year. No one else was doing this.
                    Theis said that the agencies supplied ISOO with the statistics and that ISOO
                    compiled and disseminated them.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a break at 10:35 a.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--november-6--10-45-noon_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 6, 10:45-Noon</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball reconvened the meeting at 10:45 a.m. and introduced CIA historian Ken
                    McDonald. McDonald described the recent CIA symposium on the Cuban Missile
                    Crisis and referred to the publication <hi rend="underline">CIA Documents on the
                        Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962</hi> prepared for that symposium.</p>
                <p>McDonald reported on the status of CIA’s effort to provide documents on the
                    events in Iran in 1953 and Guatemala in 1954 for supplementary treatment in the
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series. The first step, that of
                    document collection, was underway. A <pb n="22" xml:id="pg_22" facs="0022"/>
                    larger number of documents on Guatemala had been identified. Another step in the
                    process, declassification review, would be carried out by the new Historical
                    Review Group in CIA. A third step was the preparation by the CIA History Staff
                    of historical studies on such major events as Iran 1953 and Guatemala 1954.
                    These studies would be undertaken on a classified basis with the hope that they
                    could eventually be declassified.</p>
                <p>Collecting documents on Iran in 1953 was a more difficult task. CIA provided 42
                    documents in 1975-1976 when the original compilation was underway. When State
                    presented the compilation for clearance in 1984, CIA withheld 13 of the 42
                    documents, three of which were State documents released by the Department
                    anyway, leaving the remaining 10 classified documents. There has been an
                    erroneous public perception that the CIA had mountains of documents on Iran that
                    the State Department had not seen. The CIA has continued to look for relevant
                    documents, and the Directorate of Operations is aware that many documents exist
                    that have not yet been found.</p>
                <p>John Pereira, a very senior officer, is in charge of the new CIA declassification
                    effort, and this reflects the seriousness with which the Director of Central
                    Intelligence takes the effort. Much of the current declassification effort has
                    focused on the Kennedy assassination papers, with the involvement of 10
                    employees and 10 re-employed annuitants. Until the Kennedy project is completed
                    by August 1993, it will be hard to take on Iran. In response to Slany’s reguest
                    for a timetable for delivery of documents, McDonald reported that Guatemala was
                    ready now; Iran was partially ready but would require more time.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if there were any classified CIA oral history interviews that could
                    be used to amplify documents on Iran and Guatemala. McDonald indicated that no
                    such interviews existed, and that oral history was not begun until the
                    1980s.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked about references to the “oral tradition” in the Church Committee
                    hearings on organized crime connections and Cuba. McDonald indicated that the
                    “oral tradition” referred to officers who joined the OSS or CIA in the 1940s,
                    who may have retired in the 1970s or 1980s, and who were sometimes asked for
                    information on an ad hoc basis about specific incidents.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that the supplementary volume on Iran should contain a footnote
                    indicating that the compilers were aware of the Church Committee hearings, but
                    could not find all the documents mentioned.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked McDonald if there was full cooperation within CIA in unearthing
                    records. McDonald described the compartmentalized system and felt that the CIA
                    History Staff <pb n="23" xml:id="pg_23" facs="0023"/> had received good
                    cooperation, but that when documents which they requested were not found, they
                    did not assume that heroic efforts had been made to find them.</p>
                <p>Taylor asked whether CIA had an independent timetable for the review of
                    documents. McDonald indicated that there is a plan for review of records over 30
                    years old but that operational records are exempted.</p>
                <p>The question of finding aids was raised. McDonald said they varied enormously
                    between parts of the agency and over time but in general they were not very
                    good. He compared the agency to a long-term wartime organization &#x02014;
                    nobody was much concerned with recordkeeping.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if PA/HO historians had access to CIA finding aids. He also asked
                    how PA/HO could explain in the preface to the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes about limitations on its access to CIA materials.
                    McDonald questioned why CIA should be singled out in this respect. It was
                    pointed out that PA/HO had access to the finding aids of other agencies. Kimball
                    explained that he was interested in shedding light on the procedure. Historians
                    who did not have access to finding aids or to the files needed a trigger of
                    interest for access. He was not accusing the CIA of withholding documents, but
                    some of the Committee’s constituents might. Van Camp pointed out the need to
                    identify the provenance of documents.</p>
                <p>McDonald indicated that the State Department had in the past relied mainly on
                    other agencies to root out the appropriate documents. The CIA History Staff also
                    works with the PA/HO historians. The only place where there is a problem is in
                    the Directorate of Operations, a culture of intense secrecy. He thought that
                    finished intelligence would be more relevant to <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> than raw intelligence. Nelson pointed out that covert actions
                    may be a matter of foreign policy. McDonald thought the problems were only
                    theoretical. Kimball stated that finding aids were not theoretical.</p>
                <p>McDonald said they could make finding aids available insofar as they could find
                    them. It was necessary to get cooperation from the Directorate of Operations,
                    which was not going to give historians carte blanche access to their records.
                    The History Staff is doing their best to supply the records to PA/HO
                    historians.</p>
                <p>Picker stated that the CIA is not like other agencies and the problems are more
                    difficult, but that the History Staff and the new Historical Review Group have
                    made some real changes. She suggested that the Committee have a session at CIA
                    and meet with some people beyond the History Staff. McDonald thought this was a
                    good suggestion.</p>
                <pb n="24" xml:id="pg_24" facs="0024"/>
                <p>Glad asked whether the CIA History Staff has access to intelligence oversight
                    committee records. McDonald said they did not have access to the records of
                    oversight committees in the legislative branch. Glad clarified that she was
                    asking about executive branch oversight groups such as the 5412 Committee.
                    McDonald said the records of such groups were NSC records. Nelson pointed out
                    that CIA briefing materials prepared for such groups would be very useful.</p>
                <p>Chaddic indicated that Pryor had been working closely with NEA on Iran. As a
                    result, NEA’s Assistant Secretary had indicated in a memorandum to the Under
                    Secretary for Political Affairs that NEA intended to take an open approach on
                    the subject, feeling that it was best to release as much as possible now on the
                    overthrow of the Shah, while relations with Iran were not good, rather than
                    later, when they might improve.</p>
                <p>Nina Noring referred to a specific incident on which she had requested documents
                    and asked whether if CIA did not produce the documents she could state in a
                    footnote that the CIA had no documents on this. McDonald didn’t want to answer a
                    hypothetical question. Kimball pointed out that such cases illustrated the need
                    to be very candid with the constituencies. McDonald indicated, in response to a
                    question from Glad, that PA/HO historians had access to classified histories,
                    including those prepared in the Operations Directorate. Noring had first asked
                    for CIA histories before passage of the law.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked McDonald whether he had tried to get information from KGB files.
                    He said that he had not, but pointed to news stories that a liaison with the KGB
                    now existed. Picker cited a short item in <hi rend="underline">The New York
                        Times</hi> concerning a trip by Gates to Moscow for liaison with the KGB.
                    Did the shortness of the story reflect the fact that the CIA released only
                    minimal information? McDonald indicated that liaison questions were among the
                    most sensitive. Picker asked whether there were any U.S.-Russian agreements on
                    the joint declassification of documents.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether the CIA had a policy on older records calling for “complete
                    declassification.” McDonald stated that most OSS records have been declassified
                    and transferred to NARA. About 3-4% was withheld. CIA is continuing to re-review
                    the withheld material. NARA has tried to get the British to release some joint
                    material, but they have denied most requests. In response to a question, he
                    stated that quite a bit was declassified on the Central Intelligence Group.</p>
                <p>At 11:45, Kimball announced that the Committee would recess into executive
                    session, and then proceed to lunch. The agenda item on the status of the
                    declassification and transfer to NARA of 30-year old Department records would
                    have to be put off <pb n="25" xml:id="pg_25" facs="0025"/> until after lunch.
                    Chaddic pointed out that this item had been scheduled for early that morning,
                    that Jeanne Schauble of NARA had set time aside to participate in the discussion
                    and had been at the meeting all morning, and that he had hoped to complete the
                    discussion before lunch so that he could get away. He asked for 5 or 10 minutes
                    for his and Schauble‘s report before the Committee went into executive session.
                    Kimball expressed his surprise that Chaddic had not raised these concerns
                    earlier, as he had been present throughout the entire morning session. He
                    pointed out that the discussion on this topic would be lengthy, since he and
                    other members of the subcommittee that met the previous day had very serious
                    comments. Chaddic stated that the discussion could be postponed until after
                    lunch but that his and Schauble‘s report could be completed in less time than
                    the discussion over its scheduling was taking. Kimball then called on Chaddic to
                    give a five-minute report.</p>
                <p>Chaddic indicated that HDR had made a major effort to revise the declassification
                    guidelines to make them all-inclusive of the historical record. The Mexico model
                    was distributed in both old and new form, and work is progressing on guidelines
                    under this new format. Chaddic reported that HDR had been impressed with the
                    initial review by NARA personnel of the 1960-1963 record bloc at Suitland and
                    anticipated that HDR would soon return to the system of spot-checking. With
                    respect to the report to Congress, HDR would let Congress know that State was
                    not able to complete the review in the one year given, and that the Department
                    would need more time. A draft was in preparation and would be shared with Slany
                    and Kimball.</p>
                <p>Schauble, chief of NARA’s Declassification Division, explained that NARA had been
                    able to assign only 12 people to the review of 1960-1963 files. Given the extent
                    of the files, and assuming certain “other factors” were in place, she estimated
                    it would take until the year 2010 to complete the review. “Other factors”
                    included the need for the State Department to make its reviewers available on a
                    timely basis; timely transfers of lot files to NARA; no substantial increase in
                    FOIA requests that would interrupt the review process; and using the computer to
                    reduce inefficiencies in the process. Schauble also indicated that her estimate
                    was based only on 30-year-old records currently in NARA’s custody and did not
                    include any additional lot files that may yet be in the Department’s
                    custody.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked if the declassification review could be completed in another year.
                    Chaddic said it would take many years.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed into executive session at 11:55 a.m.</p>
                <pb n="26" xml:id="pg_26" facs="0026"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="summary-of-luncheon-meeting-of-advisory-committee-with-assistant-secretary-for-administration-adm--arthur-fort--november-6--1992_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Summary of Luncheon Meeting of Advisory Committee With
                        Assistant Secretary for Administration Adm. Arthur Fort, November 6,
                        1992</hi></head>
                <p>Adm. Arthur Fort (Ret.), Assistant Secretary for Administration, joined the
                    Advisory Committee for luncheon. Secretary Fort inquired about the terms and
                    professional affiliations of the Committee. Kimball and other members of the
                    Committee explained the Committee’s organization under the legislation as
                    compared to the earlier Committee, and discussed the dual role of the Committee
                    under the legislation &#x02014; advising on the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series on the one hand and monitoring the declassification
                    and transfer to the National Archives of the Department’s 30-year-old records on
                    the other.</p>
                <p>Kimball expressed the Committee’s serious concern over the Department’s projected
                    completion date of the year 2010 &#x02014; reported to a subcommittee the
                    previous day and to the full committee just prior to lunch &#x02014; for the
                    declassification and transfer to NARA of the Department’s 30-year-old records.
                    Such a delay in the legislated deadline of not later than October 28, 1993
                    would, in the Committee’s view, cause a negative reaction from Congress and
                    might prompt Congress to „micromanage“ the Department’s declassification
                    process, something that would not be considered in the Department’s interest by
                    State Department officials.</p>
                <p>Kimball and other members of the Committee stated their view that delays in the
                    project could be substantially reduced by modifying the declassification process
                    to eliminate multiple document reviews by NARA and Department declassifiers, and
                    especially by adoption of a procedure for “bloc” declassification of all but
                    “designated” records that are older than a specified cut-off date. Kimball used
                    as an example records older than 50 years.</p>
                <p>The Committee also expressed the need for changes in the mind set of
                    declassification officials to reflect post-cold war attitudes and national
                    security matters. This changed mind set could be reflected in national
                    declassification policy in a new and less restrictive Executive Order. Members
                    of the Committee also referred specifically to the need for changes in the mind
                    set of Department declassifiers.</p>
                <p>Secretary Fort noted that from his perspective there was little the Department
                    could do to change declassification procedures in the MOU with NARA that he had
                    signed that morning. Department declassification requirements were set by
                    national policy as reflected in E.O. 12356. With regard to estabishing a policy
                    of “bloc” declassification of older records, Secretary Fort expressed doubt that
                    this would be <pb n="27" xml:id="pg_27" facs="0027"/> possible. He was not
                    willing to accept the Committee’s view that the sensitivity of most records
                    declines with their age. From his perspective, real questions of national
                    security interest must be addressed in records 30 years old and even older.
                    Unless and until a new Executive Order was promulgated, the existing procedures
                    followed by FPC/HDR would have to remain in place.</p>
                <p>Members of the Committee reasserted the notion that improvements in the
                    Department’s declassification procedures could be made within the broad scope of
                    the existing Executive Order. Secretary Fort indicated that Joe Chaddic would
                    certainly work closely with the Committee to do whatever could be done, but
                    expressed his doubt that much could be done, given current resources and
                    requirements, to reduce the delay in the projected completion date for
                    declassification and opening of the Departement’s 30-year-old records at
                    NARA.</p>
                <p>Kimball indicated that the Committee would be preparing a report to the Secretary
                    of State on the Department’s compliance with the legislated deadlines, copies of
                    which would be sent to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and the House
                    Committee on Foreign Affairs. Secretary Fort suggested that the Committee
                    include its concerns and suggestions in the report so that he could address them
                    as best as possible in the time remaining before his successor came on
                    board.</p>
                <p>After the luncheon meeting, the Committee met in executive session from 1:30 to
                    2:15 p.m. to consider comments by members of the PA/HO staff.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--november-6--2-15-3-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, November 6, 2:15-3 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>The Committee took up the question of the declassification guidelines. William
                    Hamilton of HDR described the comprehensive guidelines, which cover the period
                    1945-1963. They were produced because Schauble said at the last Advisory
                    Committee meeting that the NARA reviewers were handicapped by the necessity to
                    refer to multiple sets of guidelines in reviewing lot files with material
                    ranging over a period of time. Referring to the model guideline for Mexico,
                    Hamilton explained that Section A provides historical background; section B
                    lists subjects of special sensitivity for 1945-1959 and 1960-1963; Section C
                    lists subjects which are no longer sensitive. A new set of guidelines for other
                    subjects based on the improved Mexico model should be completed early in
                    1993.</p>
                <p>Schauble pointed out that NARA hasn’t had a chance to apply the new comprehensive
                    guidelines yet, but she thought they would save time. She explained that the
                    guidelines are still draft guidelines subject to change resulting from NARA
                    referrals to the Department. Not until they are final can they <pb n="28"
                        xml:id="pg_28" facs="0028"/> be sent to Presidential libraries or used for
                    FOIA requests. After they are finalized, they can be used by NARA reviewers
                    without referral to State. It would be helpful to have them as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>Kimball referred to the problem of foreign government information. He noted that
                    the sample guidelines permit the release of information given orally by foreign
                    officials, except British and Commonwealth officials. He asked why there was an
                    exception for British and Commonwealth officials. Hamilton stated that this was
                    because of requests by those governments, but that HDR thought the end of the
                    Cold War might bring about some change in this.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked about bloc declassification. He pointed to British declassification
                    in 1972 of all their wartime records through 1945 and asked if that had caused
                    any problems for the United States. Hamilton stated that the U.S. system of
                    declassification was different then.</p>
                <p>Taylor asked if there would be a savings if State hired more junior people to do
                    the reviewing. Hamilton said the Department’s view has been that it was better
                    if reviewers had some experience in the area under review.</p>
                <p>Kimball expressed the Committee’s gratitude to the PA/HO notetakers and stated
                    that the record they produced was very helpful to the Committee in doing its
                    work. He asked to put this in the minutes.</p>
                <p>The Committee adjourned into executive session at 3 p.m.</p>
                <pb n="29" xml:id="pg_29" facs="0029"/>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Compiled:</cell>
                        <cell>PA/HO - DHHerschler 663-1145</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>PC:ACMN1192</cell>
                        <cell>11/23/92</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>PA/HO Notetakers:</cell>
                        <cell>RMBaker</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>MPClaussen</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>WTFain</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>VEFutscher</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ECKeefer</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>DWMabon</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>JEMiller</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>NJNoring</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>DSPatterson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>AWRobinson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>CSSampson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>HDSchwar</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>JASoukup</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>CYee</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Clearances:</cell>
                        <cell>PA/HO - WZSlany</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>PA/HO - GWLaFantasie</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>PA/HO - RMBaker</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>FPC/HDR - JHChaddic</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>IMIS/OIS - KRossman</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>CIA - JKMcDonald</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>NARA - JSchauble</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
