<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1993-05-20">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, May
                    1993</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1993</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1993-05-20">May 20, 1993</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[1]" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-may-20-21--1993_1">
                <head>ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON HISTORICAL DIPLOMATIC DOCUMENTATION MAY 20-21,
                    1993</head>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Committee Members</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Warren Kimball, Chairman</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Betty Glad</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>George Herring</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Anna Nelson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Bradford Perkins</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jane Picker</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Emily Rosenberg</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Arnold Taylor</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Ann Van Camp</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Richard Boucher</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Susan Povenmire</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Office of the Historian</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>William Z. Slany, Historian</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Glenn W. LaFantasie</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Rita M. Baker</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>M. Paul Claussen</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Evan Duncan</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>W. Taylor Fain</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Vicki E. Futscher</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Evans M. Gerakas</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David H. Herschler</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Nina Howland</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Edward C. Keefer</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Gabrielle Mallon</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David S. Patterson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Charles S. Sampson</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Harriet D. Schwar</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeffrey A. Soukup</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Shirley T. Taylor</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Carolyn Yee</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Frank M. Machak, Director, IM/FPC</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Kenneth Rossman, Chief, Records Management, IM/IS/OIS/RA/RD</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Joe H. Chaddic, Director, IM/FPC/HDR</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>William C. Hamilton, HDR</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeanne Pryor, HDR</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Intelligence and Research</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jon Gibney, INR/IL</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>John T. Fawcett, Assistant Archivist (NL)</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Michael Kurtz, Acting Assistant Archivist (NN)</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Jeanne Schauble, Chief, Records Declassification</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>George C. Chalou</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>David A. Langbart</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Marvin Russell</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Nancy Smith</p></item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Central Intelligence Agency</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>J. Kenneth McDonald, Chief Historian</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>John Pereira, Chief, Historical Review Group</p></item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[2]" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0002"/>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="contents">
                <head>TABLE OF CONTENTS</head>
                <table cols="3">
                    <row>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>Open Session, May 20, 9-10:15 a.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of the Agenda</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_3">3</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Report by the Historian on the Status of the <hi rend="underline"
                                >Foreign Relations</hi> series</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_3">3</ref>- <ref target="#pg_6">6</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>Open Session, May 20, 10:45 a.m.-Noon</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>John Fawcett Report on Presidential Libraries</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_6">6</ref>- <ref target="#pg_9">9</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Kenneth McDonald Report on CIA Historical staff</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_9">9</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>General Editor’s Report (LaFantasie)</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">10</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>Luncheon Session, May 20, 12:15-1:30 p.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Meeting with Bennet Freeman</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_11">11</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>Closed Session, May 20, 1:30-3:30 p.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of Working Group Report on Opening of Department’s
                            Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref>- <ref target="#pg_18">18</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                        <cell>Closed Session, May 20, 3:45-4:30 p.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Tibet, 1958-63</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_19">19</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Cuba, 1961-62</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_20">20</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Indonesia, 1958-1960</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_20">20</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Middle East, 1961-1962</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_20">20</ref>- <ref target="#pg_21">21</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of Publication of CIA Documentation</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_21">21</ref>- <ref target="#pg_22">22</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6.</cell>
                        <cell>Closed Session, May 21, 9-10:30 a.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Review of Prefaces to Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_22">22</ref>- <ref target="#pg_25">25</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Report on INR Records (Gibney)</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_25">25</ref>- <ref target="#pg_27">27</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7.</cell>
                        <cell>Closed Session, May 21, 10:45 a.m.-Noon</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Report by John Pereira on CIA Declassification Activities</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_28">28</ref>- <ref target="#pg_30">30</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8.</cell>
                        <cell>Closed Session, May 21, 1:30-2:30 p.m.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of Gaps in Documentation for LBJ Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_31">31</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of PA/HO Staff Vacancies</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_32">32</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Discussion of Presidential Review Directive on Declassification</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_32">32</ref>- <ref target="#pg_34">34</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb n="3" xml:id="pg_3" facs="0003"/>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--may-20--1993--9-10-15-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, May 20, 1993, 9-10:15 a.m.</hi></head>
                <p>Advisory Committee chairman Warren Kimball called the meeting to order.
                    Department Historian and Executive Secretary of the Advisory Committee William
                    Slany informed the Committee that Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs
                    Bennett Freeman, who had been assigned oversight for PA/HO, would join the
                    Committee during lunch. Richard Boucher would speak to the Committee briefly
                    during the afternoon session.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that consideration of the minutes of the last meeting would be
                    postponed until the revised copies were ready. Nelson suggested that the minutes
                    should be modeled on the Gleason memos of NSC discussions, that is, that they
                    should include the gist of the discussion without attempting to be verbatim.
                    Kimball stated that he was satisfied with the existing format of the
                    minutes.</p>
                <p>In discussing the proposed agenda, Kimball noted that the time needed to discuss
                    the Working Group Report that afternoon could not be predicted. He thought, if
                    necessary, the subcommittee reports on <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> declassification matters could be succint, allowing more time
                    to discuss the Working Group report, if necessary.</p>
                <p>Slany pointed out that the agenda did not include a separate item for the
                    President’s Task Force on classification and declassification (PRD-29). He
                    indicated that Freeman would likely raise the matter of the Committee’s views on
                    this at lunch. Anna Nelson stated that the Committee needs to know specifically
                    how the task force was formed before it could offer useful comment. It was
                    agreed that the Committee would meet briefly in executive session just before
                    lunch to consider the materials in their briefing package on the PRD-29 Task
                    Force.</p>
                <p>Slany presented the Historian’s report. He stated that PA/HO is still publishing
                    backlog volumes for the late 1950’s. The Office will publish 12-14 volumes in
                    1993. The schedule calls for PA/HO to publish 18 or more volumes next year in
                    order to meet the legislative goal by 1996. The Office is on schedule.</p>
                <p>He stated that PA is committing all the resources necessary to meet the
                    requirements of the law. PA/HO is trying to keep costs down -- now ranging
                    anywhere from $25 to $35 thousand per volume -- through editorial measures and
                    less expensive arrangements with the GPO. He said that although the Office is
                    trying to whittle down the size of the volumes, PA/HO historians try to maximize
                    the amount of material within the smaller volumes.</p>
                <pb n="4" xml:id="pg_4" facs="0004"/>
                <p>Slany stated that 2 senior historians, Mabon and Noring, have recently retired or
                    are about to retire and that PA/HO will probably lose a junior historian in the
                    fall. David Humphrey will join the staff in July. Assistant Secretary for Public
                    Affairs Tom Donilan and Freeman have authorized us to fill the Mabon and Noring
                    vacancies. PA/HO will go as far afield as necessary in doing so, but Slany
                    pointed out that filling vacancies from outside the Department was a protracted
                    process at best. Humphrey’s security clearance had taken 8 months. Kimball
                    observed that this could mean vacancies for as long as a year. He thought this
                    was bound to have an impact on the work of the office. He noted that the
                    Committee had previously expressed concern about the length of time required for
                    clearance; he had written a letter to the Assistant Secretary for Diplomatic
                    Security (DS) about the Humphrey clearance. For the record, the Committee
                    expressed concern that vacancies in PA/HO be filled and security clearances be
                    obtained expeditiously.</p>
                <p>Slany stated that PA/HO is trying to deal with the problem of requirements for
                    special handling and storage of highly classified documents, especially those of
                    other agencies, which have to be kept in the PA/HO vault separate from other
                    material being compiled. The Office is trying to arrange with DS and the other
                    agencies for downgrading such documents or modification of the handling
                    restrictions. George Herring stated that if this will have a long-term impact on
                    the series, then the Committee should be concerned. Deputy Historian Glenn
                    LaFantasie stated that DS had agreed to separating the TS documents and keeping
                    the other material in barlocks within the PA/HO vault. Kimball asked if there
                    wasn’t a long-term plan for new quarters. Slany replied that it was very long
                    term. Kimball stated that PA/HO should let the Committee know immediately if it
                    concluded the problem would have a long-term impact on the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> schedule.</p>
                <p>With regard to declassification, Slany said the Department’s declassification
                    review, particularly for newly compiled volumes, is moving on schedule. The
                    problem is to clear and publish the backlog of volumes compiled in the 80s, some
                    of which were undergoing re-review by agencies. HDR and PA/HO have agreed that
                    PA/HO will assume responsibility for declassification coordination of material
                    outside the Department of State. Donilan has agreed to the establishment of a
                    4-person unit whose principal task will be to coordinate and monitor
                    declassification by other agencies. Slany thought it should be possible -- with
                    the implementation of new procedures such as simultaneous initial review by all
                    agencies except the NSC within the first 120 days -- to complete the
                    declassification of a volume within a year. Kimball asked whether these were new
                    positions. Slany replied that some came from HDR, some from PA. PA/Ho will try
                    to take over this <pb n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0005"/> responsibility next
                    month and fill the vacancies as soon as possible, probably using detailees from
                    within and outside the Department in the interim. Chaddic stated that for
                    administrative reasons, this was a good time for HDR to turn over this
                    responsibility.</p>
                <p>Arnold Taylor inquired about the status of the Congo volume. David Herschler
                    stated that 64 documents were sent to the NSC in April.</p>
                <p>Kimball pointed out that according to the status of volumes list, some documents
                    had been at other agencies for many months and in some cases, over a year. There
                    was some discussion of the problem of the Justice Department, which has had some
                    documents for over a year. Jeanne Pryor stated that declassification authority
                    at Justice was fragmented and there was no one with declassification authority
                    in the Attorney General’s office, although the Department had now appointed a
                    Deputy Attorney General who would have this authority. Slany stated that
                    agencies need to have centralized declassification authority. Kimball suggested
                    that PA/HO try to get an MOU on declassification with the Justice
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Noting some delays in the declassification schedule at the CIA, Kimball asked if
                    the Department was giving the agency a little leeway in the hope of obtaining
                    more favorable declassification action. Slany noted that CIA was facing the same
                    hurdles as the Department in responding to the transition in declassification
                    policy. He suggested that this matter be tabled until John Pereira joins the
                    Committee on Friday morning.</p>
                <p>Kimball then inquired if PA/HO had as yet worked out any MOU with the Defense
                    Department. Slany said no. He had invited Brian Kinney to come to the Committee
                    meeting, but Kinney thought he had nothing to say of interest to the Committee.
                    Kimball said the Committee would take the next step and send some members to DOD
                    to do some random sampling of documents, in accordance with the legislation. The
                    Committee agreed to proceed with a request for such access.</p>
                <p>Slany noted the Committee’s similar concerns expressed at previous meetings about
                    the NSA. He pointed out that PA/HO had established a new contact at that agency,
                    and asked the Committee to defer action regarding the NSA until the next
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Slany pointed out that the early transfer of Department records to NARA impinges
                    on PA/HO’s work in that records accessioned by NARA may be inaccessible for a
                    while. David Langbart said that Department records at Suitland are accessible to
                    PA/HO historians. Herschler said the Presidential Correspondence lot file which
                    was recently sent to <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0006"/> Main Archives was
                    inaccessible until PA/HO got them to do something. Kimball said PA/HO should
                    bring this to the Committee’s attention if it becomes an insoluble problem.
                    Slany said there may be a conflict between the goal of making records available
                    to the public and publishing the series as fast as possible. Nelson said the
                    series should take priority.</p>
                <p>Slany raised the question of making the Committee records available to the public
                    as required by law. There was general agreement that the records should be
                    retired to NARA but some uncertainty as to when this should be done. Ann Van
                    Camp proposed that the records should be transferred after two years. Herschler
                    stated that PA/HO had a draft disposition schedule which was under consideration
                    with the Department’s records managers. Kimball recommended that PA/HO work out
                    a disposition schedule in accordance with the spirit of Van Camp’s proposal.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a break.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--may-20--10-45-noon_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, May 20, 10:45-Noon</hi></head>
                <p>When the Committee reconvened, John Fawcett, Assistant Archivist for Presidential
                    Libraries, discussed the decision by LBJ Library Director Harry Middleton to
                    make available to the PA/HO staff and to the public the taped meetings and
                    telephone conversations recorded during the Johnson Administration. This was a
                    particularly noteworthy accomplishment, according to Fawcett, given that the
                    statutory 50-year opening date has not been reached. Fawcett stressed that
                    Middleton had asked the Department to assist in the declassification of
                    transcripts of the recordings used for <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> research by PA/HO historians, and that Middleton could
                    justify opening the materials in advance of the 50-year date on the basis of the
                    Library and Department’s cooperative effort.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked who reviews the tapes for privacy. Fawcett responded that the LBJ
                    Library does, and that David Humphrey and Tina Houston of the LBJ Library staff
                    were assigned the task of reviewing the tapes for privacy and national security
                    concerns. Middleton himself intended to begin reviewing transcripts of telephone
                    conversations in September.</p>
                <p>Fawcett noted Humphrey’s imminent departure from the LBJ Library to join the
                    PA/HO staff. Given the current staffing situation, he indicated there might be
                    difficulties in filling the foreign policy vacancy at the Library, which could
                    impact the process of opening the recordings and transcripts to the Department
                    and the public. He informed the Committee of NARA’s recent requests, under the
                    FY 94 budget, for additional staff to work at various Presidential libraries: 23
                    Bush, 6 JFK, and <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7" facs="0007"/> 13 positions to handle
                    access issues associated with the Nixon materials. Fawcett said that
                    unfortunately these requests were not approved, and were cut to 9, 0 and 0,
                    respectively. NARA staff levels, he added, were currently at the level expected
                    of it in three years under the Clinton Administration’s mandate to reduce
                    government personnel. He said that such a pared-down staff will adversely affect
                    the rate at which NARA will process and open documents.</p>
                <p>Bradford Perkins asked how many people were assigned to work on acess and
                    declassification of foreign policy materials at the Presidential libraries.
                    Fawcett indicated there were 3 at the JFK Library and 3 (plus 1 State-supported
                    detailee) at the LBJ Library. Perkins then asked about the possibility of moving
                    existing staff from one library to another, such as from the FDR library to work
                    on the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> project. Fawcett responded
                    that NARA does not move permament staff from one library to another since it
                    costs approximately $100,000 to move one staff person.</p>
                <p>Fawcett stressed that Presidential records beginning with the Reagan
                    administration are subject to the Freedom of Information Act five years after
                    being deposited at the Presidential library. This means that the Reagan
                    materials will be subject to the FOIA next January, and NARA anticipated a heavy
                    number of requests.</p>
                <p>Kimball expressed concern about NARA’s staffing problems and how they would
                    impact on <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. Fawcett responded that
                    the Nixon materials pose the biggest problem because of the very large volume of
                    material, the cuts in NARA’s staff, and the peculiar access agreement guiding
                    the Nixon papers. Fawcett informed the Committee that this access agreement
                    allows Nixon himself to grant or reject access to his papers.</p>
                <p>Betty Glad returned to the topic of the Johnson telephone tapes. She asked what
                    the law was concerning the rights of individuals who were taped without their
                    permission. Fawcett responded by saying that as long as one individual consents
                    to taping the conversation the other individual in effect reliquishes his or her
                    right to censor the tape.</p>
                <p>Fawcett reminded the Committee that these recordings include conversations with
                    individuals who are currently in Congress, and that other recorded individuals
                    are still alive. Thus, the issue of privacy was a crucial one, especially
                    because these recordings will be available before the 50-year release date.
                    Perkins asked if NARA was breaking the law by making these tapes available.
                    Fawcett said it was not so much the case of a barrier, but intrepretation of
                    Middleton’s authority to release of these recordings.</p>
                <pb n="8" xml:id="pg_8" facs="0008"/>
                <p>Kimball again asked what the Committee could do to help, especially with access
                    to the Nixon materials. Fawcett said that NARA’s relations with Nixon had become
                    adversarial, in that Nixon’s attorneys are suing the Archives over the agency’s
                    decision to allow FOIA requests for access to the finding aids to Nixon
                    materials. He anticipated that Nixon would be a tough negotiator who would
                    demand a quid pro quo. This might make access by PA/HO to the Nixon materials
                    more difficult.</p>
                <p>Returning to the question of the Johnson recordings, Nelson asked, considering
                    PA/HO’s time limitations, whether it was a good expenditure of PA/HO staff time
                    to listen to these tapes. LaFantasie said that these tapes could be particularly
                    useful as a source to turn to when gaps that could not otherwise be filled
                    appear in the record.</p>
                <p>Kimball reiterated his concern with NARA’s staff problems and asked again if
                    there was something the Committee could do. Fawcett replied that he thought it
                    would be helpful for the Committee to maintain a continuing interest in NARA
                    staff levels, but that even if it had received the 13 requested positions, such
                    staff would not help the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    immediately because these people would require clearances and training, and that
                    would take time.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked what the best plan should be for the Committee to respond to this
                    problem. He offered to write a letter, a memorandum, or wait to mention this in
                    the Committee’s annual report. Van Camp said a decision needed to be made now
                    about what the Committee should do. She supported the idea of writing a letter
                    to an appropriate official, and stated that the Committee represented a large
                    enough constituency to add credibility to such a letter. Kimball suggested
                    addressing the letter to Secretary of State Christopher and to the appropriate
                    official at NARA. Fawcett reminded Kimball that even when NARA had used the
                    language of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> statute to argue for
                    additional positions, these positions were not granted.</p>
                <p>Nancy Smith of the Office of Presidential Libraries referred to a meeting
                    attended by Harry Middleton, Slany and Herschler, at which Middleton expressed
                    the hope that State would declassify entire transcripts of taped Johnson
                    telephone conversations, and not only those extracts that State intended to use
                    in its <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Smith also reminded
                    the Committee that the Department should think hard about identifying specific
                    conversations in the Nixon tapes now, given its huge volume, in order to plan
                    effectively for the next round of research. She informed everyone that Nixon’s
                    diary is open, but that access to the log of recorded conversations is subject
                    to negotiation with Nixon’s attorney and to FOIA requests.</p>
                <pb n="9" xml:id="pg_9" facs="0009"/>
                <p>Kimball proposed to write a letter on behalf of the Committee to Secretary
                    Christopher, with a copy to an appropriate official at NARA, in which concern
                    over NARA’s staffing problems and potential access problems for PA/HO research
                    in the Nixon materials would be highlighted.</p>
                <p>Kenneth McDonald, Chief Historianr of the CIA, briefed the Committee on
                    collection of documentation on Iran and Guatemala. He said that work on
                    Guatemala documentation was going well, in fact all the material had been
                    identified. A member of his staff was preparing a history on Guatemala based on
                    the documentation, and the agency was undertaking systematic review of the
                    documents on Guatemala for 1954. His office was still working on identification
                    and collection of the documenation on Iran.</p>
                <p>McDonald then reported that the CIA’s Center for the Study of Intelligence has
                    planned conferences on: 1) Teaching Intelligence, October 1-2, 1993; 2) Harry
                    Truman and the Origins of the CIA, (cosponsored with the Truman Library), March
                    17-18, 1994; and 3) Soviet Strategic Estimates, October 1994. The History Staff
                    will publish documents on CIA’s origins for the Truman conference and a
                    collection of declassified estimates on Soviet capabilities for the third
                    symposium. He noted that the Historical Review Group plans to review for
                    declassification all estimates on the former Soviet Union 10 years old and
                    older, and that CIA had already relesased portions of the 1976 “A-Team, B-Team”
                    estimates.</p>
                <p>Kimball expressed concern with the possibility of a duplication of effort if both
                    State and the CIA publish histories on the foreign policy of the U.S. He
                    emphasized that there needs to be good communication, a liaison, between State
                    and the CIA. McDonald said that the CIA does not want to duplicate the efforts
                    of State, and is not trying to compete with <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. He added that his office had worked closely with Tom Thorne
                    on providing PA/HO with documents from the Truman era.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether Thorne’s effort provided an opportunity to publish in <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> documents that were previously
                    denied declassification during the years 1945-1950. Emily Rosenberg noted that
                    prefaces to the volumes mention the possibility of later publication of
                    documentation from the CIA. She asked if McDonald’s staff had a plan to publish
                    such documentation. McDonald responded that the CIA Historical Staff is not
                    currently working to publish documentation originally denied from <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, but that they could help
                    arrange for declassification review if State provided them with a list of
                    documents previously denied.</p>
                <pb n="10" xml:id="pg_10" facs="0010"/>
                <p>Bradford Perkins asked who at CIA is responsible for declassification policy. In
                    reply, McDonald emphasized that the CIA History Staff has no role at all in
                    declassification matters, which are the responsibility of John Pereira’s
                    Historial Review Group. The History Staff’s research program and publications,
                    he added, are reviewed by the CIA History Advisory Board, a body of about a
                    dozen senior Agency officers from all directorates.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie then gave his report. He said that the LBJ research plan has gone
                    forward with 8 research trips to the Library since last September. Some of the
                    research had been undertaken in a team approach which seemed to be particularly
                    effective. He informed the Committee of a new management tool that was recently
                    introduced to the PA/HO staff, outlining its provisions for periodic reviews
                    throughout the manuscript process to assess document selection, annotation and
                    other areas of preparation, and containing 10 milestones to monitor whether the
                    volume was meeting the schedule.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked how long it takes to complete a manuscript. LaFantasie said about a
                    year. Perkins asked LaFantasie to explain to him what a milestone was.
                    LaFantasie said, for example, halfway into the manuscript process, the division
                    chief, editor, and compiler would meet to discuss the status of the
                    manuscript.</p>
                <p>Perkins remarked that he thought meeting ten times a year corresponding to the 10
                    milestones seemed like it would be a lot of review in one year. LaFantasie said
                    that it was simply a management tool, and that its development was prompted in
                    part by a suggestion made by Emily Rosenberg at the last Advisory Committee
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg pointed out that she had not intended to suggest introducing a new
                    management tool, but to develop a means by which the Committee’s concerns over
                    the shortened manuscript page length could be addressed so that the targeted
                    page length for particular volumes could be shortened or lengthened depending on
                    the subject matter, and to ensure that a dynamic process exists while the PA/HO
                    staff prepares the manuscript. She said that she did not want her earlier
                    suggestion to be interpreted as a signal to increase PA/HO’s quantity of
                    paperwork.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie offered to let the Committee look at the first Johnson compilation,
                    Arms Control, Vol. XI, 1964-1968, before the next Advisory Committee meeting,
                    but warned that it is not complete. He added that the management tool would
                    facilitate his answering questions from the Committee about the status of
                    certain manuscripts.</p>
                <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11" facs="0011"/>
                <p>Kimball asserted that the Committee needed to define its role in assessing the
                    Johnson volumes. He stated that Anna Nelson and Arnold Taylor should look at the
                    Arms Control volume in advance of the next Advisory Committee meeting.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed at 11:45 into a brief executive session, followed by
                    lunch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="luncheon-meeting--may-20_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Luncheon Meeting, May 20</hi></head>
                <p>Bennett Freeman, Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Public Affairs Bureau, joined
                    the Advisory Committee toward the end of lunch. He welcomed the Committee and
                    said that the Department was grateful for all its fine efforts. Freeman
                    explained that Tom Donilon, the new PA Assistant Secretary, and Mike McCurry,
                    the Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary, were committed to supporting the work of
                    the Historian’s Office and making sure that the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> statute was fully implemented.</p>
                <p>Freeman said that personally he took an interest in the Historian’s Office
                    because of his own background as a student of history. Having only recently
                    arrived at the Department, however, he could not claim to have a command of all
                    the issues that are involved in the publication of the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series and the systematic declassification of the
                    State Department’s 30-year-old records. Most of his time, he said, has been
                    taken up with writing speeches and building a new speech-writing unit within the
                    PA Bureau. He said that in the coming weeks he expects to familiarize himself
                    with the key issues facing the Committee and that he will rely on Kimball’s and
                    Slany’s guidance in gaining a better understanding of the work that needs to be
                    done.</p>
                <p>In response to a question about the PA Bureau’s role in dealing with the
                    Presidential Directive on revising the Executive Order on Classification and
                    Declassification, Freeman said that he would have to study the directive more
                    closely, but he could tell the Committee that the PA Bureau leadership, and
                    Donilan in particular, felt that too much responsibility had been placed in the
                    hand’s of the Department’s security personnel. He said that the PA Bureau would
                    look into the possibility of correcting that situation.</p>
                <p>Freeman then excused himself, saying that he hoped to meet with the Committee
                    again before its meeting was over, and extended best wishes to the Committee for
                    a productive meeting.</p>
                <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12" facs="0012"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--may-20--1-30-3-30-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, May 20, 1:30-3:30 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball announced that the Advisory Committee had decided during lunch that a
                    subcommittee consisting of Nelson and Taylor would look at the Arms Control
                    volume for the Johnson Administration. He then called upon Frank Machak,
                    Director of the Department’s Office of Privacy, Freedom of Information, and
                    Declassification Review (FPC).</p>
                <p>Machak commented on the Working Group report on opening the Department’s 30-year
                    old and older records, which he called a step forward. He said that the report
                    makes clear that the Department takes the legislation seriously. Machak added
                    that from his perspective, as one who would have to be an implementer, the
                    report was a very good first product, although it was not perfect; the report
                    did have “soft spots,” and there continued to be disagreements on interpretation
                    of language. He repeated, however, that this was a good first step, and noted
                    that the report would also make others who had not been involved in the process
                    more comfortable with these issues.</p>
                <p>Michael Kurtz, Acting Assistant Archivist for the Office of the National
                    Archives, said that the data distributed to the Committee concerning the status
                    of declassification for the 1960-63 records showed that they had a long way to
                    go, adding that they were encountering resource and guideline problems which
                    explained this. Kurtz distributed a list of Department guidelines already in
                    NARA’s possession, and a list of guidelines for which NARA was waiting. He noted
                    that the National Archives had made a commitment to providing at least three
                    staff members for the project in addition to the six that would be funded by the
                    Department of State. Kurtz said that only three of those nine had been cleared
                    thus far, but pointed out that the Department of State does not pay for these
                    employees until they are cleared and on board.</p>
                <p>In response to a question by Kimball, Kurtz assured the Committee that archival
                    processing did not stand in the way of declassification. He said that the
                    Working Group had had a difficult series of discussions, but had attempted to
                    set milestones, which was essential from a management and public perception
                    point of view. They would have to do more work on how the process would work and
                    the operational details would have to be worked out, particularly concerning the
                    issue of other agency information, but the Working Group report provided a
                    framework for this. Kurtz added that the Presidential Task Force offered hope
                    for a broader level of declassification reform.</p>
                <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0013"/>
                <p>Kimball emphasized that he wanted the Advisory Committee to understand the
                    context of the report. He noted that monitoring and aiding the declassification
                    process would be a very challenging issue for the Advisory Committee and asked
                    if the Committee had any questions or comments about the report.</p>
                <p>Brad Perkins said that he thought there was supposed to be a “drop-dead date”
                    after which documentation would automatically be declassified. Kimball said that
                    the target date was January 1, 1997 for release of material through 1966.
                    Perkins said they needed to establish a “drop-dead date” so that the records
                    would be opened by that date even if the deadline for review was not met.</p>
                <p>At this point, the Committee interrupted its deliberations to welcome Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs and Deputy Spokesman Richard Boucher.
                    Boucher greeted the Committee and assured it that the Department had a
                    commitment to meeting the Congressional deadline. He noted that the Working
                    Group had come up with some practical ideas. Boucher said that the new team in
                    PA had been briefed on the Working Group report and had a commitment to the
                    process and everyone wanted to come up with practical, workable solutions. He
                    added, however, that there were still bureaucratic hoops to go through.</p>
                <p>When discussion of the Working Group report resumed, Perkins noted that the
                    report, while offering promise, was really nothing more than a “pious hope” that
                    the 30 year release line could be achieved. He argued that they had to have a
                    “drop-dead date” to make people do what they were supposed to do. Kimball
                    pointed out that the report was in its final form, but added that the Advisory
                    Committee could and should add its comments. Slany concurred in this.</p>
                <p>Emily Rosenberg said that she had understood that the Committee had previously
                    endorsed a “drop-dead date” and asked what had happened to this in the Working
                    Group discussions. Machak offered his personal opinion concerning a “drop dead
                    date” that he had been in the Department of State for a long time and he could
                    tell the Committee that “it ain’t going to happen in this building.” The
                    Committee might consider him a hardliner, but to many working in the
                    declassification field he was considered a liberal. No one in the Department was
                    going to say, “Open 9000 feet of records on January 1, 1997.” The notion of
                    automatic declassification was both impractical and illegal under the current
                    regulations. There was no way that documents were going to be released without
                    some analysis and recommendations to the Secretary of State.</p>
                <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0014"/>
                <p>Perkins pointed out that the Department would have four years to find out what
                    could not be released. Machak replied that the Working Group had tried to put
                    checkpoints in the report, calling for early analyses and mandatory reporting.
                    This provided a framework which would help them to keep their eyes on the ball.
                    Machak emphasized again that a “drop-dead date” scares people, but said that he
                    agreed that they had to have targets and checkpoints.</p>
                <p>Slany pointed out that the Advisory Committee had been given the power to monitor
                    this process and that it would know whether or not it was working. Kurtz said
                    that the National Archives had considered favorably a “drop-dead date” for
                    certain categories of records along with the notion of anlyzing the files more
                    important to researchers first, but pointed out that these are Department of
                    State records. The Working Group had established the principle of setting
                    priorities. Kurtz added that they also had to be concerned with other agencies’
                    equities.</p>
                <p>Kimball commented that he shared the doubts that the January 1, 1997 deadline
                    could be met and argued that this showed the importance of setting priorities,
                    since the deadline would likely not be met for all of the records. Rosenberg
                    suggested that the Advisory Committee should say that it would call for a
                    “drop-dead date” for the lowest risk categories if it appeared that the deadline
                    would not be met.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked Machak to discuss two aspects of the report -- setting priorities
                    and risk analysis. Perkins suggested that they could do risk analysis by
                    sampling documents. Machak replied that they would indeed have to sample
                    documents, as the volume of documentation precluded page-by-page review of all
                    categories of records, and there could no longer be a three-tiered review, as is
                    currently the case. He warned, however, that they might discover that sampling
                    would not provide the answers the Committee wanted. He hoped that their first
                    experience with sampling during the early stage of analysis called for in the
                    report would be helpful. Kimball noted that the new law defines exempted
                    categories in different terms than the Executive Order with regard to
                    information which “might reasonably damage” current foreign relations.</p>
                <p>Taylor asked Machak about personnel. Who would be the “qualified experts” who
                    would be part of the risk assessment analyses called for in item #4 and the
                    declassification center called for in item #7? Would these people play a
                    significant role in determining what was declassified or merely an advisory one?
                    Machak replied that they were meant to play a significant role, but until teams
                    were organized and sampling was under way, it was hard to speculate on the roles
                    of specific individuals. Taylor said that he was worried that the process would
                    be dominated by people with a bias for classification. Machak stated that he did
                    not buy the idea that there had been a bias against declassification in the
                    past, but he felt that the new teams would not have it in any case.</p>
                <pb n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0015"/>
                <p>Kimball suggested rephrasing Taylor’s question: will others who had appropriate
                    training besides retired Foreign Service Officers be used? Machak pointed out
                    that it would be teams who would make the decisions rather than any single
                    individual, although eventually one single person would have to sign off.
                    Kimball said that the Advisory Committee was interested in bringing different
                    people with a different approach into the declassification process, but wondered
                    whether they would have equal stature.</p>
                <p>Machak pointed out that such people would have to have Top Secret clearances,
                    which limited the universe they could choose from. He anticipated that some mix
                    of Foreign Service Officers, Civil NARA employees, and Foreign and Civil Service
                    annuitants would be in the pool. The Foreign Service annuitants were a viable
                    resource. Machak emphasized that the Department has to use experts for
                    declassification (i.e., former consular officers for consular files), who have
                    delegated authority from the bureaus. A bureau such as EUR would not be prepared
                    to authorize PhD historians to declassify its records.</p>
                <p>Nelson commented that the Advisory Committee’s role in this process would
                    probably be carried out by one person. Therefore, she wondered what would happen
                    and whether it would matter if the Advisory Committee member said, “I disagree,”
                    especially concerning national security issues. Would the results justify the
                    Advisory Committee’s optimism? Slany noted that the Office of the Historian’s
                    experience had been that while the Advisory Committee’s views perhaps were too
                    advanced to be fully accepted, the Department had already been moving in that
                    direction. Kimball suggested that the Working Group’s emphasis on results in its
                    recommendations was indicative of this. Nelson reiterated her skepticism.</p>
                <p>Van Camp commented on the positive elements in the Working Group report, which
                    were much more than she expected, but asked what was different about its
                    proposal concerning the Department of State’s responsibility under the new plan.
                    She was concerned that the new plan should offer real change and not be merely a
                    faster version of the old one; she also questioned NARA’s role in the new
                    system.</p>
                <p>Machak replied that he was not sure what would emerge. There had to be agreement
                    on what documents were involved. He said that the Department of State did not
                    intend to cut out the National Archives and saw it in a complementary role,
                    although he was still not sure how this would work. Machak suggested that
                    perhaps the Department would do the Decimal files and NARA the Post and Lot
                    files. He noted that Joe Chaddic thought there were “efficiencies” here.</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0016"/>
                <p>Kimball commented that the Working Group plan took some pressure off of Chaddic
                    because he did not have to have immediate guidelines. Still, guidelines for
                    already accessioned records -- some 3500 cubic feet -- would have do be done.
                    Smith pointed out that the guidelines were important to the Presidential
                    libraries.</p>
                <p>Chaddic noted that there would still be guidelines. He added that there were
                    various efficiencies in the Working Group report and that better cooperation
                    within the building and the synergy of a team effort rather than using one or
                    two senior reviewers at NARA would also help them to meet the deadlines. Other
                    agency officials could be invited to participate in the review. Chaddic warned,
                    however, that the projected completion date of January 1, 1997 was based on
                    starting the new process by April 1, 1993. There was already nearly a two-month
                    delay. Kurtz asked Chaddic when the guidelines would be ready, to which he
                    replied by the end of the current fiscal year.</p>
                <p>Perkins commented that they were evidently trying to speed up the
                    declassification process, but not to change the standards. He noted that he
                    remained sceptical about not having a “drop-dead date” and asked Chaddic how
                    much sampling and risk assessment did he contemplate? Chaddic replied that he
                    could not answer that now.</p>
                <p>Kimball raised the question of other agency equity. Should they get other
                    agencies involved in the process at an earlier stage? He thought that the idea
                    should be to place the burden for speedy review on the agency with the equity,
                    but feared this might be too confrontational. Chaddic replied that he was hoping
                    for help from the Advisory Committee on this. The Department of State would
                    consult other agencies or notify them that they had equity. If there was no
                    response, the Department could say that the documents were going to the National
                    Archives and would be open within six months. He added that he expected this to
                    raise legal issues that would have to be resolved at the time.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that Chaddic was talking about a “drop dead” date for other
                    agency equity. Slany noted that this was why the language in the Working Group
                    report had been carefully chosen to ensure that other agency material “would not
                    be permitted to delay the transfer and opening of Department of State
                    records.”</p>
                <p>Machak said that they had been having discussions with other agencies to alert
                    them to what was on the horizon in the Department of State. These discussions
                    had indicated that many agencies were down-sizing their declassification staffs.
                    The intention was to inform the leadership in these agencies that there was
                    going to be a demand and that they needed to be prepared. Because of clearance
                    problems, interagency representatives needed to have authority and not just take
                    back <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0017"/> copies of documents to be vetted
                    internally. He thought there might be a role for colonels and two-star generals
                    in this team approach. Machak reminded the Committee that cooperation was easier
                    and more effective than confrontation.</p>
                <p>Glad asked if other agencies, such as the CIA, would agree to sampling? Machak
                    responded that he hoped to involve them in the process. Kurtz commented that the
                    National Archives was very concerned with referring documents to other agencies.
                    This was the bane of its existence.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether the Working Group’s proposal regarding other agency equity
                    would apply to materials in the Presidential libraries. Herschler pointed out
                    that these materials for the most part are not Department of State records,
                    although many copies of Department records are contained in the files. Herring
                    expected that the Department’s new declassification effort would have a ripple
                    effect on the libraries. Kimball suggested that the declassification decisions
                    made by the Department on particular documents should be conveyed to other
                    agencies, particularly the Presidential libraries.</p>
                <p>Machak noted that while there was not much enthusiasm for interagency working
                    groups, they have in fact worked quite well in the past. He pointed out that the
                    Advisory Committee had the ability to influence others in this regard. He said
                    that the Department was working with the Presidential libraries on compatible
                    software so it could provide the libraries with data on documentation the
                    Department had declassified. This project was part of the Department of State’s
                    five-year plan. Nelson pointed out that since most of the earlier Presidential
                    libraries did not have computerized declassification systems, this project would
                    only be helpful for documents much more recent than 30 years old.</p>
                <p>Herschler stressed the importance of an interagency database for declassification
                    decisions. The Interagency Security Oversight Office had been working on this
                    question, but nothing had come of it thus far. Machak stated that when he had
                    suggested a government-wide database of declassified documents at one of these
                    meetings, he had met with considerable opposition. On the other hand, Machak
                    continued, FPC and PA/HO had developed an electronic link between the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> document list and the Department’s
                    declassification database. Herschler indicated that printout lists of
                    declassified Department documents could be provided to the Presidential
                    libraries in the same way lists of declassified <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> documents now could be provided to the libraries.</p>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="pg_18" facs="0018"/>
                <p>Herring expressed his concern with the mindset of the declassifiers. He asked if
                    there was any way that there could be re-education in order to bring the mindset
                    of the declassifiers up to date along with the declassification process. Machak
                    said that the Working Group had considered this and the idea was to motivate
                    people to get the job done. He emphasized the importance of having a covering
                    memo with the context and setting of the Secretary’s commitment to the process
                    to get the principals to sign on to the plan. He noted that the Department’s new
                    Assistant Secretary for Administration, Pat Kennedy, had already had two
                    conversations with him about the Working Group and its report. He added that
                    Kennedy expected to play a role in the Department’s response to the Presidential
                    Directive on classification and declassification.</p>
                <p>Betty Glad asked whether the Presidential Task Force on a new Executive Order
                    would make the declassification task easier. Kurtz replied that he was on the
                    Task Force and was chair of the Subcommittee on Declassification. He told the
                    Advisory Committee that there would be two days of public testimony on June 9
                    and June 10 in the Great Hall of the Department of Justice. The Subcommittee on
                    Declassification would welcome input from the Advisory Committee. Kurtz also
                    noted that the Task Force was supposed to have a draft Executive Order by
                    November 15, 1993.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked Machak what would motivate change in the new Executive Order? Machak
                    said that, from his personal perspective, the Working Group had been the most
                    positive thing he had seen in more than 20 years. The internal conditioning
                    process has begun in the Department. The Presidential Task Force was a forum for
                    issues raised in the Department’s Working Group.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked whether the Department intended to involve other agencies in risk
                    assessment during the first 60-day period. Chaddic reiterated that the Committee
                    should not start the clock on the 60-day period until the declassification
                    Center was funded, space allocated, and people assigned. Rosenberg asked again
                    if they would operate within an inter-agency framework, and Chaddic replied that
                    there would be informal cooperation.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a break.</p>
                <pb n="19" xml:id="pg_19" facs="0019"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--may-20--3-45-4-30-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, May 20, 3:45-4:30 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>George Herring indicated that he would summarize the subcommittee reports, which
                    covered declassification actions on four topics in five volumes. He noted that
                    Perkins and Van Camp would supplement his remarks.</p>
                <p>Herring said that some of the the documents on Tibet were discussed at the end of
                    the last Advisory Committee meeting. The subcommittee heard from the desk
                    officer, Gary Williams, and the HDR reviewer, Al Harding.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie pointed out that there were six documents for the 1958-1960 China
                    volume and two documents for the 1961-1963 China volume. After the Committee had
                    expressed concern at the last meeting, LaFantasie revisited the documentation,
                    instructed Harriet Schwar to collect additional documentation and secondary
                    literature, and worked with the Eisenhower Library to obtain the additional
                    materials. Out of the new sources collected, LaFantasie had selected five
                    additional documents for inclusion in the 1958-1960 China volume. Publication of
                    the volume was temporarily suspended and the volume would be remade with the
                    Tibet documents (mostly for 1959) in a separate compilation. He added that PA/HO
                    had met with the desk officer in advance of the subcommittee meeting.</p>
                <p>Herring reported that the desk officer explained that certain documents on Tibet
                    had been denied in whole or in part because it was felt that their official
                    publication could lead to further repression in Tibet. This reasoning, Herring
                    remarked, seemed “strained and tortured” to the subcommittee. Mr. Williams did
                    agree, however, to re-review the previously compiled documents and review the
                    newly compiled documents with an open mind. Herring noted that no decision of
                    the Advisory Commitee was needed now. The subcommittee supported the PA/HO
                    initiative on Tibet. He added that his conviction of the centrality of the Tibet
                    documents was reinforced.</p>
                <p>Perkins pointed out the difficulty in sorting out operational details from policy
                    considerations in some of the documents in question. He reiterated the
                    subcommittee’s view that the desk officer’s concern with political repercussions
                    in Tibet from publication of the documentation was “strained and
                    unimaginative.”</p>
                <p>Rosenberg complimented LaFantasie for his decision to stop publication of the
                    volume until the Tibet documentation issue could be resolved, and she
                    complimented LaFantasie and Schwar for their effort to uncover additional
                    documentation. She inquired whether the desk officer was better informed of the
                    review appeals procedures than the desk officer her <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20"
                        facs="0020"/> subcommittee had met with the past winter. LaFantasie replied
                    that it was clear to him that the desk officer had read the 1991 law. Herschler
                    said that PA/HO had covered these points in their April meeting with the desk
                    officer. Van Camp said the Tibet desk officer was cooperative, and Pereira later
                    said that he would meet with the CIA officer on the same issue. Herschler
                    confirmed that the Tibet documents will go to the CIA as well as the EAP
                    Bureau.</p>
                <p>Herring next reported on the Cuba, 1961-1963, volume. Here again the documents in
                    question did not require a Committee decision. John Pereira, director of the
                    CIA’s Historical Review Group, had reported that his office had recommended
                    --after re-review of the 14 documents submitted by PA/HO --release of five
                    documents in full and nine in part. Some deleted material was restored. The full
                    texts of the documents would be available in two or three weeks.</p>
                <p>Herring then discussed Indonesia, 1958-1960. The subcommittee had discussed this
                    issue in November 1992. The documents involved CIA issues also. The deletions
                    had removed evidence of covert operations in Indonesia, as well as other issues.
                    The CIA conducted a re-review and agreed to release some of the earlier
                    deletions. The record now shows that there were covert operations and one can
                    read between the lines to fill in much of the remaining missing information. The
                    PA/HO compiler, Edward Keefer, was satisfied that the volume was now much
                    improved, and the subcommittee was prepared to go along with that view. The
                    original documents did not contain much detail.</p>
                <p>Perkins added that these matters should be mentioned in the preface to the
                    volume. Herring noted that the subcommittee had reviewed a draft text of the
                    preface and had made a recommendation that seemed agreeable at the subcommittee
                    meeting, so the subcommittee recommended that PA/HO should move forward with
                    publication of the volume.</p>
                <p>Herring then turned to the question of the Israeli Dimona facility in the Near
                    East volume for 1961-1962 that had been discussed at the February Committee
                    meeting. Perkins reported that a long telegraphic report by the American
                    Ambassador was denied, but a previously released document in the fiche
                    collection covered much the same ground, and that has been moved to this print
                    volume. Much of the remaining documentation was released by the NEA Bureau,
                    including most portions of U.S. assessments of Israeli atomic capabilities.</p>
                <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0021"/>
                <p>Van Camp added that three issues were earlier studied and tagged as important by
                    the subcommittee, and Nina Noring was confident that these issues were now
                    adequately covered in the volume. Herschler had summarized the points in a
                    memorandum to Chaddic following the previous Advisory Committee meeting.</p>
                <p>Herring felt that the work of the subcommittees was very constructive in chipping
                    away at the institutional mindset against declassification. He also thought that
                    it chipped away at any PA/HO mindset not to bother appealing documents it may
                    view as lost causes. The subcommittee in effect encourages PA/HO to try again.
                    Van Camp concurred, adding that PA/HO has had success itself in getting specific
                    documents released with Advisory Committee support. Herschler noted that PA/HO
                    had received favorable results from several informal appeals, which had made it
                    unnecessary to bring the matter to the Committee’s attention. LaFantasie thanked
                    Jean Pryor and Joe Chaddic for their assistance in this process.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that the Committee should talk about the Executive Order
                    tomorrow morning. If members could come to the Department for their photographs
                    at 8:30 a.m., they could begin discussion on the Executive Order at 9 a.m.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked whether the Advisory Committee should take a position advocating
                    the publication of documentation previously denied for inclusion in the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes dealing with the late 1950s.
                    Could PA/HO catch up in these cases, as in Guatemala and Iran? Glad thought that
                    PA/HO should try to catch up, referring to the release of the CIA Center’s
                    narrative studies. Slany said he was reluctant to disrupt the current
                    publication schedule.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether the CIA should be encouraged to publish supplemental
                    documentation to these volumes. He noted, however, that Ken McDonald had told
                    the Committee earlier in the day that the CIA Historical Staff does not exist to
                    supplement the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg said her understanding of McDonald’s remarks was that his staff was not
                    involved in documentary editing but that he would listen to a PA/HO specific
                    request for such supplemental assistance in this area. Glad noted that there
                    were other areas that could be supplemented, e.g., the Hungarian revolution of
                    1956, which would be somewhat similar to Iran and Guatemala.</p>
                <p>Slany remarked that the Committee could recommend a supplementary volume covering
                    all these issues, as on the general relationship of the CIA to foreign policy
                    prepared by Tom Thorne covering the years 1946-1950. Picker said that it could
                    be pointed out in the prefaces that the omission of <pb n="22" xml:id="pg_22"
                        facs="0022"/> intelligence matters would be remedied in a future volume if
                    the Committee so agreed. Slany wondered how much of this record we have seen,
                    and Kimball said it is not the Committee’s responsibility to worry about
                    previously published volumes. He added that supplemental compilations on
                    intelligence would not be necessary if CIA documents were retired to the
                    National Archives.</p>
                <p>David Langbart remarked that NARA is not receiving CIA materials. They have
                    received two CIA histories, and George Chalou had noted that these materials
                    were “largely junk.” Much of this same material is in the State Department files
                    and has appeared in other volumes in the series. Nelson said that the CIA had
                    pulled records. Much that was sent to NARA was not open.</p>
                <p>Kimball suggested that Slany and LaFantasie study the issue and make
                    recommendations. Perkins asked whether the Committee wanted to put another
                    volume on PA/HO’s plate. Kimball replied that the Committee was just thinking
                    about it and wanted suggestions on feasibility. He did not want to impose a big
                    burden. Herring said they could talk tommorrow with Pereira and McDonald about
                    this.</p>
                <p>Kimball next turned to the issue of the prefaces to certain <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes to be considered by the Advisory Committee.
                    He noted that in language common to each preface it was stated that “selective
                    access” had been obtained by the Historical Office to the records of several
                    government agencies while researching these volumes. Later in each preface it is
                    stated that the volume was “prepared in a manner completely consonant with the
                    standards of the statute” governing the publication of the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. If the first statement is true, Kimball
                    said, the second must necessarily be false. The Advisory Committee agreed to
                    take up the matter the following day.</p>
                <p>The session adjourned at 4:25 p.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--may-21--9-10-30-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, May 21, 9-10:30 a.m.</hi></head>
                <p>The session convened at 9:20 a.m. to discuss the prefaces in some soon to be
                    published <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Kimball expressed
                    his concern over inflated claims in the prefaces that the volumes were prepared
                    “in a manner completely consonant with the standards and mandates of the
                    statute.” He felt this is misleading to readers especially when the preface also
                    states that the editors only had selective access. He had had comments from
                    historians about the preface in the 1964 Vietnam volume, which claims that the
                    editors were “confident” that they had complete access to all records. The
                    recent discovery of the McCone files illustrates how dangerous such a statement
                    can be. He thought that, in the long run, such a statement was misleading to
                    scholars.</p>
                <pb n="23" xml:id="pg_23" facs="0023"/>
                <p>Slany pointed out that the editors looked at everything that was available to
                    then at the time of compilation. Kimball still took issue with inflated claims
                    about access to all records and suggested using the phrase: “the editor had
                    access to all records located or known as of (date).” There was discussion about
                    which date to use -- the date of compilation or the date of publication.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked why the Committee’s boilerplate was not included in these
                    prefaces.</p>
                <p>Kimball reminded him that compilation of these volumes preceded the date of the
                    1991 statute, and the Committee had decided at one of its previous meetings not
                    to include the boilerplate language in those prefaces.</p>
                <p>Perkins then asked why the nature of the material deleted was not spelled out,
                    especially when the percentage was as large as 8 percent, as in the Western
                    Europe volumes. Charles Sampson, compiler of those volumes, explained that there
                    was no one topic that was extensively deleted; the excisions covered many
                    subjects in several compilations. Perkins reiterated that the reader should be
                    told what kind of subjects have been deleted and mentioned that the language in
                    the 1958-60 volume XII preface was a good model.</p>
                <p>Nelson commented that since this volume (West Europe) was compiled in 1981, the
                    preface did not even have to mention the 1991 law. Both Slany and LaFantasie
                    felt strongly that it was essential to account for the law. Nelson felt that the
                    prefaces for those volumes should ignore the fact that the law exists.
                    LaFantasie pointed out that the public expectation is that the Department would
                    respond to the law. Otherwise, readers would wonder what had happened to the
                    law.</p>
                <p>Glad agreed.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that the PA/HO staff did as much as possible, but that
                    declassification problems created limitations. The volumes were compiled in the
                    spirit of the law and he did not want to cast aspersions on the PA/HO staff.</p>
                <p>Kimball returned to the concept of inflated claims of access. Rosenberg and
                    Nelson pointed out that the phrase “range of sources” is also misleading.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked about the publication status of these volumes. Rita Baker,
                    technical editor, informed her that the two West Europe volumes were too far
                    along to stop, but the other prefaces could be changed.</p>
                <pb n="24" xml:id="pg_24" facs="0024"/>
                <p>Nelson thought it was essential to get the phrase “range of sources” out.
                    Rosenberg noted there were now two things significant to change: that phrase and
                    the term “consonant.” Kimball pointed out that these changes could not happen in
                    volume VII but the others could be changed.</p>
                <p>Glad resurrected the issue of including in the prefaces a statement about the
                    role of the Committee, such as “The compilation of this volume was completed
                    before the Advisory Committee existed.” Kimball reminded her that the Committee
                    had discussed that in previous meetings and had decided not include such a
                    statement. Glad thought it was important to explain about Committee involvement,
                    but Kimball said that no acceptable language had been found for these
                    pre-Committee volumes. The Committee will not be involved.</p>
                <p>Nelson separated the prefaces into three groups: those that cannot be changed
                    (i.e., volume VII); those that could still be changed; and those that included
                    the Committee boilerplate. Picker said she was confused by the language
                    “originally compiled.” Sampson noted that a large percentage (20 percent) of the
                    volume was originally denied; after the Berlin situation was clarified, the
                    volume was re-reviewed and documentation was restored.</p>
                <p>Kimball said he believed that PA/HO understood the Committee’s concerns and
                    summarized the changes they required in the prefaces:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <p>1) delete the phrase “range of sources;”</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>2) use less categorical statements about access;</p></item>
                    <item>
                        <p>3) characterize the excisions, especially when the amount of deletions
                            are significant, so that readers can be reassured there is no smoking
                            gun.</p></item>
                </list>
                <p>Slany then asked the Committee members if they had any comments on the preface to
                    the 1961-1963 volume on Berlin. The main difficulty had been how to describe the
                    historians’ access to CIA files.</p>
                <p>Herring commented that obviously it should be done very carefully. Kimball said
                    that the preface should make clear that access was selective and did not mean
                    full access to the files. LaFantasie pointed out that some researchers can ask
                    for specific documents in specific files based on their previous experience with
                    CIA records. Keefer noted that access to CIA records was better at the
                    Presidential libraries than at the CIA.</p>
                <pb n="25" xml:id="pg_25" facs="0025"/>
                <p>Rosenberg requested some specific changes to the language about CIA access to
                    emphasize that the historians had access to particular files, but not to all
                    records at the CIA.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked “if you ask for the Director’s files, what do you get?” Sampson said
                    that everything is the Director’s files. There was a brief discussion about the
                    provenance or lack of provenance of CIA documents.</p>
                <p>Kimball wanted to include a statement in the preface indicating that the
                    historians were allowed to see only what the CIA gives them. They agreed to the
                    language: “The Department of State historians have been provided access to
                    selective documentation of the CIA.” Kimball also wanted to include a statement
                    that the historians were not allowed to publish complete file citations for the
                    CIA documents.</p>
                <p>Taylor (later in the discussion) asked why it was necessary to note in the
                    preface what was excluded. If so, then there should be an explanation of why.
                    The Committee agreed. Sampson explained that there was an overwhelming amount of
                    very high-level documentation for this particular volume (1958-1960, VIII) and
                    the selection of documents came from that body. Taylor asked that that
                    explanation be included in the preface.</p>
                <p>Kimball introduced the next item on the agenda: INR records. PA/HO historians had
                    not previously been provided with access to INR files except those few that have
                    been retired to NARA. Langbart confirmed that there were very few INR files in
                    NARA except those in Lot 58 D 776 for the 1940s and 50s.</p>
                <p>Jon Gibney, Deputy Director of the Office of Intelligence Liaison (INR/IL),
                    introduced himself. He began by saying that there had never been a consistent or
                    systematic review and retirement of INR records, but because of an OIG
                    recommendation, INR was now working with the Department’s Records Management
                    staff to set up a disposition schedule. In a few months to a year, INR will have
                    completed this process of retiring files to preserve the historical record.</p>
                <p>INR has a large body of unique records, of which his office is custodian.
                    Although most of INR is an analytical bureau, his office is operational and is
                    responsible for liaison with other intelligence agencies. The INR files contain
                    documents dealing with various sensitive CIA, NSA, and DOD intelligence
                    programs, sensitive law enforcement issues, and the record copy of all Roger
                    Channel traffic; some of which date back to the 1950s. In some instances these
                    files constitute a unique record of intelligence activity and may never be
                    declassified. They mostly document other agency programs, and at least 1/3 are
                    NSC or CIA documents, but there are many INR documents that present the
                    Secretary with a framework for policy decisions.</p>
                <pb n="26" xml:id="pg_26" facs="0026"/>
                <p>He noted that it was difficult to understand the Reagan administration foreign
                    policy without understanding covert operations. Covert operations are set up to
                    be denied in perpetuity. Clandestine operations can be revealed by the U.S.
                    Government for its own reasons.</p>
                <p>Many of these records will now be retired, although they may not be declassified.
                    He then asked for questions.</p>
                <p>Without hesitation, Kimball asked about access by the historians to these files.
                    Gibney said there was none. Perkins pointed out and Gibney agreed that the
                    historians should have access to analytical files. Perkins said that access was
                    one issue, declassification was another; the PA/HO historians should have
                    access.</p>
                <p>Kimball then read portions of the 1991 statute that guaranteed full access to
                    historians to examine and select documents. Can that access to all INR
                    documentation be granted?</p>
                <p>Gibney said they were willing to look at the issue and agreed in theory, but most
                    of the documents concerned other agency programs and any access must have
                    permission of the agency involved.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if even the historical files (30 years or older) are so sensitive.
                    Gibney said yes. Nelson then asked if any analytical or policy files could be
                    declassified. Gibney said INR does not write policy memos, only analyses
                    condensed from all intelligence sources. The historians would be hard put to
                    find any connection between INR input and policy decisions.</p>
                <p>Keefer pointed out that INR memos for the Secretary are available in the
                    Secretary’s files. Gibney reminded the Committee that an intelligence product
                    does not necessarily guide or influence policy. In his view the most interesting
                    INR products are memoranda for the Secretary that devise a framework for the
                    Secretary’s decisions, or explain the impact of intelligence.</p>
                <p>Kimball said there are two problems: access for PA/HO historians and the transfer
                    of material to NARA. He wondered if INR has any finding aids or how usable the
                    records are. Could representatives from PA/HO and the Committee look at the
                    records in order to provide the Secretary with advice about this records
                    management problem? Gibney made a note.</p>
                <p>Glad asked if INR had any internal histories. Gibney said no, his office only has
                    files that officers can use.</p>
                <pb n="27" xml:id="pg_27" facs="0027"/>
                <p>Patterson noted that PA/HO has received a list of NIEs and SNIEs for the 1950s
                    and asked if there is one for intelligence estimates and INR numbered research
                    memoranda for the 1960s. Gibney made a note.</p>
                <p>Kimball again reminded Gibney that PA/HO should have full access rather than
                    having to ask for specific items. Gibney asked what dates of records PA/HO would
                    need to see. Kimball noted that PA/HO needs to see records at least 25 years
                    after the events. In response to a question from Rosenberg, Gibney said the
                    records go back to the end of World War II.</p>
                <p>Schwar asked if INR has files of restricted distribution telegrams from overseas
                    to State on intelligence information. Gibney noted that his office has such
                    records. He explained other ways that intelligence messages were transmitted to
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked what happens to records that are retired but cannot be
                    declassified. Gibney assured her that they are preserved and protected. Van Camp
                    asked if the Committee can help to designate these records as permanent.
                    Langbart interjected that INR was working with State’s Records Management staff
                    and that there was as yet no disposition schedule authorizing retirement. Gibney
                    noted that INR was reluctant to give up custody of the records at all.</p>
                <p>Kimball agreed with Van Camp that the Committee should emphasize the desirability
                    of maintaining the archival integrity of records retired by INR. Kimball pointed
                    out that if PA/HO has full access, the process of declassification of these
                    records is initiated.</p>
                <p>It was later decided to include in the Committee’s report the following language:
                    “the Committee appreciates Mr. Gibney’s informative comments, is pleased to
                    acknowledge that INR is making an effort to identify and preserve its valuable
                    records and hopes that INR will provide access to PA/HO historians to INR
                    records.”</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a break.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--may-21--10-45-noon_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, May 21, 10:45-Noon</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball reconvened the meeting at 10:55 a.m. He announced that Van Camp would be
                    the Committee’s representative for access to the records of the Bureau of
                    Intelligence and Research (INR), and that Picker would deal with the records of
                    the Office of the Legal Adviser (L). The Advisory Committee’s next report would
                    stress the question of archival integrity.</p>
                <pb n="28" xml:id="pg_28" facs="0028"/>
                <p>John Pereira, Chief of the Historical Review Group (HRG) at the CIA, reported on
                    declassification of CIA historical documentation. He began by observing that the
                    CIA had established an Historical Review Group last year to handle
                    declassification. New agency guidelines now presumed that documents would be
                    reviewed for release at the 30-year mark; Strategic Estimates for the Soviet
                    Union that were at least 10 years old would also be reviewed for release.</p>
                <p>Pereira said that the CIA was trying to cooperate with State on declassification
                    of documentation for <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. One person in
                    his office makes the declassification determination and refers documents to the
                    directorates for concurrence in the decision. “Bookkeeping” delays during the
                    transmission of documents had been reduced to 3-4 days from State to HRG, and to
                    about a week from CIA back to State. The FOIA workload is heavy and has
                    contributed to delays in transmitting completed work on <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> back to State.</p>
                <p>The new guidelines were gradually changing the Agency mindset; for the most part
                    only essentials like names of agents and operational details would remain
                    protected.</p>
                <p>The HRG would release the Job and Box Numbers of documents, although Pereira said
                    that people who processed FOI requests foresaw an increased workload how that
                    requestors would know what files to request. LaFantasie said that in the absence
                    of more specific identifying information on the provenance of CIA documents, <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> might need to include Job and Box
                    Numbers in the source notes. Perkins then wondered whether an increase in FOIA
                    requests was a legitimate Agency concern; Kimball added that they could easily
                    print more form letters reading “You’re in the queue.” Pereira replied that here
                    was one more incentive to transfer documents to NARA, especially since his
                    office must take custody of CIA records under its review, and therefore is
                    responsible for handling FOIA requests for such records.</p>
                <p>Nelson then asked when the JFK files would be open. Pereira replied that the
                    President had not yet appointed a review board, and that many documents would
                    not be transferred to NARA until the review board had had its say.</p>
                <p>Patterson asked about release of NIEs for the Soviet Union. Pereira replied that
                    all strategic estimates (not necessarily the raw data) and all political and
                    economic estimates that were over 10 years old would be released after review by
                    the intelligence community.</p>
                <p>Perkins asked whether all 20-odd agencies involved in the declassification review
                    process for the estimates would have to agree to release the NIEs. Pereira
                    replied that the presumption now favored release.</p>
                <pb n="29" xml:id="pg_29" facs="0029"/>
                <p>Nelson asked about the progress of declassification. Pereira replied that once
                    the JFK project was completed, Guatemala and Iran would be next. Later topics
                    would include the Bay of Pigs and the Cuban Missile Crisis. He reiterated that
                    progress could be slowed because although his staff takes possession of files,
                    they must coordinate with components that respond to FOIA requests.</p>
                <p>Kimball wondered whether “PR-related studies” affected support for PA/HO, and
                    said that he would like to see the new Director commit himself to giving
                    priority to support for <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. He feared
                    that Congress might divert CIA declassification efforts to more politically
                    popular topics. Pereira said that special studies did divert personnel and
                    resources from <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. Gates had tried to
                    emphasize declassification of areas of special interest rather than systematic
                    release of records. It was hoped that Woolsey would make a specific declaration,
                    or at least a general statement in favor of “openness.” He anticipated that once
                    his staff had completed work on the JFK documentation, in August, more resources
                    could be assigned to <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                <p>Betty Glad asked about finding aids at the CIA. Pereira replied that they had
                    only been developed so far for the JFK records. He would work with Kenneth
                    McDonald to devise some. In reply to a question from Herschler, Pereira said
                    that these finding aids might not necessarily meet PA/HO’s needs.</p>
                <p>Slany explained that the State Department is required by law to open all records
                    over 30 years old by October. A working group was devising a plan of action, but
                    he still wondered whether the process could be expedited for documents
                    originating in other agencies, in particular the CIA. Pereira said that release
                    might be done by topics. When the JFK files were being reviewed, the CIA sent
                    people to other agencies to expedite the process.</p>
                <p>Nelson inquired whether Pereira’s office was involved in the Presidential Task
                    Force on Declassification. Pereira replied that the CIA member on the Task Force
                    is the agency’s director of security. Pereira added that he hoped to insert his
                    staff’s perspective in the process in some way.</p>
                <p>Betty Glad asked about levels of classification of CIA documents. Pereira replied
                    that levels were subject to review, and that records disposition followed NARA
                    schedules. There was no classification in perpetuity.</p>
                <p>Kimball inquired when the internal debate over declassification at the CIA would
                    be resolved. Pereira suggested that the internal debate was tied to
                    determination of the CIA’s budget. The Historical Review Group, at least, <pb
                        n="30" xml:id="pg_30" facs="0030"/> had gotten more funding and personnel.
                    HRG had a staff of 20, 14 of whom worked full-time on the JFK request. Perkins
                    asked if the staff would lose positions once the JFK project had concluded.
                    Pereira said that he hoped it would not.</p>
                <p>Keefer asked about finding aids, including a central file of incoming and
                    outgoing cables. Pereira explained the files were set up for operational
                    support, not for research. The operational files, including reports of agents,
                    were organized not by subject, but by operational names.</p>
                <p>Van Camp asked whether reassembling documents by topic might, by creating new
                    files, cause problems for future researchers. Pereira said that there had been
                    proposals to hire an archivist and a records manager to organize a broad range
                    of CIA files.</p>
                <p>Nelson wondered whether an organizational directory or administrative history, if
                    available, would aid researchers. Pereira said that offices frequently changed
                    their names.</p>
                <p>Picker asked whether operational records would be put into electronic form.
                    Pereira replied that only 10-12 year-old records had been digitized, and State
                    was interested in 30-year-old records. Picker asked if it would be possible to
                    scan the older records. Herschler cited the cost, time, and accuracy factors in
                    scanning older documentation, and LaFantasie observed that the older documents
                    often included handwritten notes.</p>
                <p>Herring noted the agency’s resistance to retiring historical records to the
                    National Archives, and inquired whether this mindset was changing. Pereira
                    indicated that there had been selective change. Day-to-day operations remain
                    very compartmentalized. The BNL investigation has ensouraged the agency to
                    examine how its records are maintained.</p>
                <p>Kimball finally asked how the Committee could accelerate the declassification
                    process for <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>. Pereira replied that a
                    statement about the value of the material to the published historical record
                    would be helpful, especially in informing the CIA leadership.</p>
                <p>Pereira left the meeting at 11:45. The Committee then discussed how to phrase a
                    statement about the importance of CIA documents to the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series and foreign policy history, and on the
                    importance of archival considerations for CIA documenation. Kimball asked
                    Herring to draft the letter to the Director of Central Intelligence.</p>
                <p>The committee recessed at noon for lunch.</p>
                <pb n="31" xml:id="pg_31" facs="0031"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--may-21--1-30-2-30-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, May 21, 1:30-2:30 p.m.</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball asked for comments from the Historical Office staff on any subject
                    pertaining to the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series or the work
                    of the Committee.</p>
                <p>Sampson noted that it was difficult for the staff Historians to find documents
                    recording high-level Presidential meetings during the Johnson Administration
                    before the Tom Johnson notes beginning in late 1967. He had found this to be the
                    case in the Greece-Cyprus volume. LBJ disliked leaks on foreign policy matters
                    so notes and records apparently are scarce.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the newly available LBJ telephone and meetings transcripts would
                    help. Herschler pointed out that recordings of Cabinet Room meetings only exist
                    for 1968. Keefer noted that the CIA’s McCone Papers might be useful in filling
                    in the gaps in certain instances. Kimball said the problem was duly noted and
                    added that some reference to this problem might have to be added to the prefaces
                    of the Johnson period volumes.</p>
                <p>Sampson said the Department of State’s telegraphic records decline over the
                    Johnson Administration with the backup microfilm reels missing telegrams by the
                    dozens for 1967-1968. The use of nonspecific references to “Septels” within
                    telegrams (referring to a “separate telegram” rather than citing the telegram’s
                    full number) often caused insuperable annotation problems. Keefer said that
                    distribution limitations such as NODIS and EXDIS raised difficulties in getting
                    records into files. Recordkeepers have tried to refile these into the Central
                    File but have not always been successful. Kimball asked if this applied to
                    current records. Keefer said that it was less of a problem with telegrams kept
                    electronically since 1973.</p>
                <p>Patterson said that it would appear that the staff historians were not doing
                    their jobs completely when they could not locate so many SEPTEL references.
                    Nelson stated that the search for these reftels would prolong compilation time
                    and should be noted in the footnotes and prefaces of each volume.</p>
                <p>Nelson then suggested abbreviating citations. Sampson replied that the
                    Presidential libraries wanted full citations. Kimball left this matter for
                    LaFantasie to take up with his staff. In response to a question from Herring,
                    members of the staff indicated that they had been well treated by the Johnson
                    Library staff.</p>
                <pb n="32" xml:id="pg_32" facs="0032"/>
                <p>Keefer raised the problem of the loss of two senior historians and the impending
                    loss of one junior historian, pointing out that the time lag of 6 to 8 months in
                    hiring and the need for 3 months of on the job training meant that the departure
                    of each historian causes the loss in production of one volume. This meant that
                    PA/HO would lose ground in meeting its legally mandated production schedule.</p>
                <p>Kimball saw the need to speed up security clearances. Slany said that because of
                    the hiring freeze during the change in administration he was authorized to
                    replace Dave Mabon (who left at the end of February) only last Wednesday.
                    Kimball said that concern should be conveyed to the right people if vacancies
                    will cause a falling behind in meeting the 1996 deadline. Nelson asked whether
                    the Senate Foreign Relations Committee should be informed of this. Kimball said
                    that an appeal should go to the Hill only when there was no alternative. Perkins
                    said that the Office of the Historian has no case because all offices face the
                    same personnel problem. Keefer argued that this Office was unique in that it
                    must produce a tangible product, and noted that the production schedule was
                    predicated on full staffing of the Office.</p>
                <p>Nelson said she feared pressure to meet the publication schedule with fewer
                    historians would lead to “cutting corners” on the quality of the volumes.
                    Kimball asked Dr. Slany to investigate the impact of personnel losses on
                    production and report to him in 30 days.</p>
                <p>Patterson said that forthcoming subcommittee review of volumes would be helpful.
                    Kimball reasserted that Taylor and Nelson are to look at the first Johnson
                    Administration volume, the one on Arms Control.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested the use of temporary employees for expert advice. Kimball pointed
                    out that security clearance delays also applied to hiring temporary employees.
                    Slany gave an example of the use of a retired government employee, Tom Thorne,
                    for his expertise in preparing the Supplement on Intelligence. Rosenberg
                    proposed hiring an extra person to make up for time lost. Slany said that he
                    would try this proposal on Assistant Secretary Donilon. Keefer indicated that
                    this would be difficult because of the policy of reducing government employment.
                    Slany pointed out that this Office has the bulk of the Bureau of Public Affairs
                    budget. Kimball called for use of more historians, if the Office needs them to
                    meet the schedule. He said that if Slany reports slippage in meeting the
                    schedule because of personnel departures, the Advisory Committee would
                    react.</p>
                <pb n="33" xml:id="pg_33" facs="0033"/>
                <p>Rosenberg then asked about the effect of page limitations on compilers for the
                    Johnson volumes. Sampson replied that it was easier to compile bigger volumes,
                    but the page allotments for the Cyprus and Western Europe volumes were adequate.
                    Patterson said that the Arms Control volume was about on target in page count.
                    Keefer pointed out that President Johnson was so engrossed with Vietnam that he
                    neglected other topics, except brief crises. Therefore 800 to 1,000 page volumes
                    were feasible. Patterson said that annotation of longer volumes was time
                    consuming. The conclusion was reached that the staff was not terrified by page
                    constraints.</p>
                <p>Kimball turned discussion to the Presidential Review Directive on National
                    Security Information. He asked for information for a letter to be drafted by
                    Nelson to an as yet to be determined addressee or addressees (ISOO would get a
                    copy) on the Advisory Committee’s views on the Directive.</p>
                <p>Nelson, reading from her notes of Committee members’ discussion at lunch,
                    mentioned that there was no guidance on the public’s right to know and that the
                    membership of the Task Force largely of security officers under the Directive
                    was a disaster. There was no mention of its goals or objectives or of the
                    information user’s participation.</p>
                <p>Kimball stated that the Task Force’s work should be open to the public. Glad
                    called for naming the classifiers on documents for the sake of accountability.
                    Kimball pointed out that the authority to classify and declassify was not in the
                    author. Nelson said that periodic downgrading by date was not effective for
                    declassification. Perkins said that the new Executive Order must make the
                    previous Reagan-era order less vague.</p>
                <p>Van Camp stated the need to distinguish between historical and contemporary
                    information. The new Executive Order should separate the two. The Working Group
                    in the Department of State on retirement of its 30-year old records should
                    somehow relate to the work of the Presidential Task Force. Kimball agreed with
                    Van Camp that the draft letter should stick to the historical record.</p>
                <p>Glad and Rosenberg noted that the statement of objectives included in the
                    Presidential Directive was geared to protecting information, not opening it to
                    the public. In this way the document was skewed to the concerns of the security
                    people.</p>
                <p>Kimball said the letter would go to the professional groups with which the
                    Advisory Committee is most effective. He asked Nelson for the draft of the
                    letter within one week. Slany offered to FAX copies to the Committee. Van Camp
                    asked for <pb n="34" xml:id="pg_34" facs="0034"/> different or additional
                    representatives from the Department of State on the Task Force. Kimball said
                    that Assistant Secretary Donilon told Slany he was concerned about the Task
                    Force’s membership as is Assistant Secretary for Administration Pat Kennedy.</p>
                <p>Glad asked about Steven Garfinkel, Director of ISOO. Kimball considered Garfinkel
                    as a posssible addressee or recipient of a copy of the proposed letter.
                    Herschler pointed out the June 11 deadline for information to be submitted to
                    the Task Force. Slany asked whether Garfinkel should be invited to the next
                    meeting. Kimball said he would consider it. He asked Nelson to prepare her draft
                    letter within a week and keep it to one page.</p>
                <p>The Advisory Committee adjourned into executive session at 2:35 p.m..</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
