<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1994-08-05">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, August
                    1994</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1994</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1994-08-05">August 05, 1994</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="i" xml:id="pg_i" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-august-5--1994_1">
                <head>ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON HISTORICAL DIPLOMATIC DOCUMENTATION August 5,
                    1994</head>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Committee Members</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Warren F. Kimball, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Benton Vincent Davis</item>
                    <item>George C. Herring</item>
                    <item>Melvyn P. Leffler</item>
                    <item>Anna K. Nelson</item>
                    <item>Emily S. Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Arnold H. Taylor</item>
                    <item>Anne Van Camp</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Historian</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker</item>
                    <item>Michelle Bright</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Mike Davis</item>
                    <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                    <item>Vicki Futscher</item>
                    <item>David Geyer</item>
                    <item>Scott Heil</item>
                    <item>David Herschler</item>
                    <item>Kerry Hite</item>
                    <item>Nina Howland</item>
                    <item>David Humphrey</item>
                    <item>Donna Hung</item>
                    <item>Shelby Hunt</item>
                    <item>Edward Keefer</item>
                    <item>Glenn LaFantasie</item>
                    <item>Daniel Lawler</item>
                    <item>Gabrielle Mallon</item>
                    <item>Thomas Martin</item>
                    <item>James Miller</item>
                    <item>David Patterson</item>
                    <item>Harrier Schwar</item>
                    <item>Shirley Taylor</item>
                    <item>Carolyn Yee</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Brady Barr, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>Betty Bates, IS/OIS/RA/RD</item>
                    <item>Joe Chaddic, Director, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>William Hamilton, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>Jeanne Pryor, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>Kenneth Rossman, Chief, Records Management (IS/OIS/RA/RD)</item>
                    <item>George Tsukahira, FPC/HDR</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">National Archives and Records Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Michael Kurtz, Acting Assistant Archivist</item>
                    <item>David Langbart, Archivist, Records Appraisal and Disposition
                        Division</item>
                    <item>Marvin Russell, Chief, General Archives Review Branch</item>
                    <item>Jeanne Schauble, Director, Records Declassification Division</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">National Security Agency</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Thomas Johnson, Deputy Director, Center for Cryptologic History</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="ii" xml:id="pg_ii" facs="0002"/>
                <p><hi rend="bold">CONTENTS</hi></p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="underline">Open Session</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by the Historian, William Z. Slany</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by Archivist David A. Langbart</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_5">5</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on the Johnson Library Telephone Transcripts</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_9">9</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="underline">Closed Session</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Committee Consideration of Foreign Government Information</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_11">11</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on Appeal of Declassification Reviews of <hi rend="underline"
                                >Foreign Relations</hi> Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on Declassification Review and Opening at NARA of Department of
                            state Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_15">15</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Comments From THE Staff</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_19">19</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Annex: Remarks to the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                            Documentation by David A. Langbart, NARA</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb n="1" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0003"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session</hi></head>
                <p>Before the meeting began, a Department of state photographer took a picture of
                    all the Committee members.</p>
                <p>Chairman Kimball opened the meeting at 9:07 a.m. He announced that Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary Bennett Freeman would not be attending the meeting. He
                    expressed concern that the minutes for the meetings were so late in being
                    distributed. Slany promised that the minutes for this meeting would be available
                    in draft before the next meeting in November.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked Slany for his report on the status of the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <div type="section" xml:id="report-by-the-historian--william-z--slany_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Report by The Historian, William Z. Slany</hi></head>
                    <p>Slany noted that he wanted to discuss three issues that he had not included
                        in his written report:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1) relations with the CIA and access to and use of their
                                documents;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2) status of research in the Nixon papers;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3) staffing problems.</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Regarding the CIA, he thanked the Committee for its intervention at a time
                        when several volumes were blocked in the declassification process at the
                        Agency. However, some problems remain. He asked for Committee involvement in
                        gaining complete access to CIA records and access to documents 26 years old
                        and less, especially as historians are compiling volumes for the Johnson and
                        Nixon years.</p>
                    <p>Kimball mentioned that if the executive order moves to the 25-year mark, <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> will have a bigger problem.
                        Perhaps the Committee could ask Frank Sieverts (Senate Foreign Relations
                        Committee) to add a rider to a bill allowing HO historians access prior to
                        the 30-year timeline. The 26-year line had been a placebo to the CIA, and if
                        they won’t cooperate, then it should be amended in such a way as to afford
                        the access needed by the Department’s historians.</p>
                    <pb n="2" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0004"/>
                    <p>Leffler asked Kimball to write a letter to CIA in the name of the Committee
                        requesting access for HO historians prior to the 26-year line. Kimball
                        agreed to write the letter.</p>
                    <p>Herring asked what citation HO was using for CIA records. LaFantasie replied
                        that the compilers were only able to use “Director’s Files.” Keefer and
                        Schwar noted that they know what files the documents come from but the
                        information cannot be included in the volumes.</p>
                    <p>LaFantasie said that we know where the files are from but not where they
                        might go.</p>
                    <p>Kimball pointed out that they had discussed this issue before, and maybe the
                        Committee should go to the CIA to talk about this. Nelson said, and Kimball
                        agreed, that they needed to talk to the people who could make the decisions.
                        Herring noted that the CIA advisory committee had met and in its report
                        mentioned the lack of citations in CIA publications. The Committee should
                        put pressure on the CIA and try to force the issue.</p>
                    <p>Leffler suggested writing a letter enumerating the issues and inviting the
                        Committee to the CIA to discuss them. Kimball agreed, noting that the letter
                        would include access prior to 26 years and citations to CIA records. An
                        off-the-record discussion followed.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg wanted to add the point that the State declassification people need
                        CIA assistance in declassifying records at the Suitland Records Center, as
                        the CIA had promised. Kimball said he had talked to Chaddic about Chaddic’s
                        May 19 letter to Jack Wright, head of the CIA’s office that handles FOIA
                        requests, asking for CIA assistance. Then both he and Slany had called
                        Wright.</p>
                    <p>Kimball reported that Wright had said the CIA was looking at this issue but
                        was “deeply divided” on how to handle it: one group wanted each unit to
                        review its own documents; the other group wanted a team <pb n="3"
                            xml:id="pg_3" facs="0005"/> to review all documents. Parts of the Agency
                        did not want to delegate declassification authority outside their specific
                        areas. Wright said he was thinking of sending a team to Suitland within the
                        next 2 weeks.</p>
                    <p>Kimball decided that if, by August 17, neither Slany nor Chaddic had an
                        answer from Wright, Slany will call Wright to remind him of his promise.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg said that the letter should contain a statement that the Committee
                        encourages the use of assessment teams with members from all concerned
                        agencies to assist with declassification. The Committee decided that the
                        letter should go to CIA Executive Director Leo Hazlewood and that it was
                        important to meet with decision makers within the agency. Kimball offered to
                        send a draft to all the members.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp asked if access to 26-year old documents was an issue with other
                        agencies. Slany answered that all agencies are affected by this 26-year
                        minimum.</p>
                    <p>Herring asked if the HO historians have complete access to CIA records. Slany
                        said that no one knows for sure. Rosenberg asked if the compilers are
                        getting useful material from the CIA. Keefer said that they are getting more
                        each time they go, that the CIA History Staff is also getting more, even
                        though the directorates do not like giving up their records. The Agency
                        seems to keep everything, and the lists of job numbers are not very helpful
                        as a guide.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked if they were overloading the historians with “everything.” No
                        one knew for sure. She asked about the finding aids.</p>
                    <p>Keefer and Schwar said that HO historians have no access to the most useful
                        finding aids that the CIA has on microfilm.</p>
                    <p>LaFantasie noted that HO needs to explain access to CIA records in the
                        volumes’ prefaces. He had no desire to point a finger at the CIA History
                        Staff or at the Agency. Slany agreed.</p>
                    <pb n="4" xml:id="pg_4" facs="0006"/>
                    <p>A discussion followed about language for the preface to inform the users that
                        the provenance for CIA documents was incomplete and “inadequate for research
                        purposes.”</p>
                    <p>Slany continued his report, commenting on the status of the Nixon project. HO
                        intends to arrange during the fall and winter the terms under which HO
                        historians can do preliminary work in 1995. An off-the-record discussion
                        followed.</p>
                    <p>Slany had one last comment: the CIA clearance bottleneck has been overcome,
                        but HO now has a problem filling historian vacancies. State is operating
                        under a freeze that prevents outside hiring and PA already exceeds its
                        assigned FTE (full-time equivalency) level. This complicates the difficulty
                        in recruiting people with the necessary skills and knowledge. Assistant
                        Secretary Donilon has asked Under Secretary for Management Moose for a
                        waiver to lift the freeze and hire historians. The bottom line is that the
                        schedule is being compromised because of inadequate staffing.</p>
                    <p>Kimball pointed out that this sentiment is repeated in the Committee’s annual
                        report and asked if the Committee wanted to send a memorandum to Moose
                        reiterating its concern.</p>
                    <p>Leffler and Nelson said the Committee should wait until Moose makes a
                        decision on the Japan appeal before sending him a memorandum regarding
                        hiring. All agreed.</p>
                    <p>Taylor inquired about final declassification of the Africa 1961-1963 volume.
                        Herschler’s report indicates that four documents are pending CIA review.
                        Herschler explained that these are National Intelligence Estimates and the
                        CIA expects to clear the documents in the next 2 weeks.</p>
                    <p>Leffler wanted to hear reports at the next meeting on the 1964-1968 Cyprus
                        volume and the 1961-1963 Angola volume. Kimball said that he and Herring
                        would report on these volumes in the afternoon.</p>
                    <p>This completed Slany’s report.</p>
                    <pb n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0007"/>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="report-by-archivist-david-a--langbart_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Report by Archivist David A. Langbart</hi></head>
                    <p>Kimball called on David Langbart to present his report on records
                        disposition. (His written report is attached.)</p>
                    <p>Langbart said he would discuss three issues:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1) disposition of records regarding <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi> declassification;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2) disposition of Bureau of African Affairs post-war lot files;
                                and</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3) disposition of World War II naval records.</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>He informed the Committee that no agency can destroy records without
                        permission of the Archivist of the United States and the final decision to
                        keep or destroy records rests with NARA. Donating records must also be
                        approved by NARA.</p>
                    <p>Regarding the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> declassification
                        records, NARA determined to keep HO files instead of those held by HDR. (HO
                        files also included Committee records.) HDR files have been recommended for
                        destruction.</p>
                    <p>Regarding the AF lot files, he noted that this was the first time the lot
                        files of a whole bureau had been scheduled all together. All have been
                        approved for accession except the files of two regional offices. Those
                        records will be destroyed.</p>
                    <p>The World War II naval cryptologic files are important because they document
                        the impact of radio intelligence and crypto on naval operations. The
                        pre-1946 files -- 2,000 cubic feet plus 15,000 feet of microfilm -- will be
                        transferred as Naval records. The post-1946 records will be retained at the
                        Department of the Navy. There will be minimal archival processing. NSA,
                        which has authority over crypto files, has refused to bulk declassify.
                        Access will depend on FOIA requests.</p>
                    <p>Kimball had some comments. He questioned the NARA decision not to accession
                        HDR files. Herschler said that the HO files were not complete for volumes
                        from the creation of CDC/HDR in <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0008"/> 1981
                        until the transfer of the coordination function from HDR to HO in mid-1993.
                        Langbart pointed out that the essential documentation is duplicated.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if the Committee wanted to get involved. Langbart commented
                        that these were not high policy matters. Kimball therefore recommended that
                        HO and NARA resolve this between them.</p>
                    <p>Slany gave the Committee some background on the AF lot files: HO was worried
                        that these records would be destroyed and recommended they be transferred to
                        Howard University if it would accept them. NARA then reconsidered its
                        initial decision to destroy them. Langbart noted that NARA was now waiting
                        for State’s concurrence in the revised disposition schedule. Bates
                        (IS/OIS/RA/RD) said she was waiting for HO to indicate how long the
                        historians needed or wanted to keep the files before she returned the
                        schedule to NARA. The issue was when to destroy the records, not if they
                        will be destroyed. Slany again mentioned sending the records to Howard.</p>
                    <p>Lawler, who had served as a country desk officer, was opposed to destruction
                        of lot files. Bates explained that her office had developed screening
                        guidelines that would ensure that unique documents in the lot files would be
                        sent to OIS to be included in the central files.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked about the possibility that some other institution would be
                        willing to keep the records.</p>
                    <p>Rossman pointed out that donating classified records is very expensive: they
                        must first be declassified and then managed according to government
                        regulations.</p>
                    <p>Taylor asked if Howard could offer a subvention to NARA to finance. Langbart
                        replied that a subvention would have to cover <hi rend="underline">all</hi>
                        costs. And the issue of donation cannot be discussed until the records have
                        been scheduled for disposal.</p>
                    <p>Kimball was incredulous that the problem had to be solved before it happened;
                        he asked if the Committee could discuss the issue hypothetically. Langbart
                        said that even if the Department wants to address this issue, nothing can be
                        done until the schedules are signed.</p>
                    <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7" facs="0009"/>
                    <p>Rossman said that Department records managers believed that the records
                        should be retained, but expert appraisers from NARA had reappraised the
                        records and decided they should be destroyed. It’s hard to discuss the issue
                        without looking at the records, and he trusted the decision of these expert
                        appraisers. Bates said that she was willing to hold the records as long as
                        HO needed them.</p>
                    <p>Langbart clarified that the records dated only from 1990; everything previous
                        had been screened and destroyed.</p>
                    <p>Pryor commented that country officers’ files differ throughout the Department
                        of State. Some contain unique documentation including copies of documents
                        with handwritten notes. Each file must be appraised on its own merits.</p>
                    <p>Kimball recommended additional study, and he asked Van Camp to form a
                        subcommittee with Leffler and Taylor to study the issue and come back to the
                        Committee with recommendations.</p>
                    <p>Kimball reserved discussion of Langbart’s third issue until after the
                        break.</p>
                    <p>The Committee adjourned for a break at 10:39 a.m.</p>
                    <p>After the break, Kimball indicated that the issue up for discussion was the
                        declassification review of records of Navy cryptographers, dating from the
                        1920s to 1945, which had recently been transferred to NARA.</p>
                    <p>Kimball introduced Thomas Johnson from NSA. Johnson indicated that the
                        records contained no cryptographic sensitivity, but that there was some
                        concern in NSA that some post-1945 records might be mixed in with the
                        pre-1945 records transferred to NARA. Thus some screening might be
                        necessary, although no decision had yet been made on dealing with this
                        problem.</p>
                    <p>Johnson further stated that his office had proposed that the records undergo
                        bulk declassification, offering his personal opinion that bulk
                        declassification would be the only way to go. The issue was still in the
                        discussion stage. Current plans called for initial declassification of
                        German U-Boat records, followed by Japanese intercepts from the 1920s <pb
                            n="8" xml:id="pg_8" facs="0010"/> to 1945. Other increments would
                        follow, but the schedule had not been worked out beyond these two record
                        segments.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if archivists from NARA could thumb through the documents to
                        determine if some were post 1945. Kimball also wondered why the Japanese
                        records were not the first priority.</p>
                    <p>Leffler proposed that the Committee write NSA a friendly letter proposing
                        that the declassification process be completed by a specified date, a
                        50-year line. He hoped that NSA’s bulk declassification then could be used
                        as a precedent and would encourage others to release 50-year old
                        documents.</p>
                    <p>Langbart stated that NARA personnel had done the segregation of the material
                        transferred to NARA and that the paper records consisted exclusively of
                        material dated prior to the end of World War II. However, the microfilm
                        portion of the collection included material that post-dated 1945.It had made
                        sense to take all the microfilm irrespective of date. Post-1945 material
                        will have to be accessed through FOIA. Langbart indicated that there was a
                        good roll list for the microfilm but that it was codeword-level classified,
                        and he hoped it could be declassified.</p>
                    <p>Johnson said he could not respond since he had not looked at the list. The
                        NSA had not yet finally decided on bulk declassification, but Johnson
                        thought it was probably the only solution.</p>
                    <p>Kimball stated that liaison was needed between NSA and NARA to reassure NSA
                        about post-1945 material in the pre-1945 records. He asked Slany to keep the
                        Committee informed of developments concerning the material.</p>
                    <p>Langbart noted that NSA was seeking to schedule other pre-1945 material and
                        transfer the original records to NARA. Kimball mentioned the “Yardley
                        material” and indicated that he had heard that the State Department was
                        holding it up.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then introduced another issue involving NSA: a memorandum of
                        understanding between HO and NSA on access to NSA records by HO historians.
                        Johnson thought that existing <pb n="9" xml:id="pg_9" facs="0011"/>
                        arrangements might be adequate. He stated that he would explore the status
                        of that problem in NSA. Kimball indicated that he wanted to be informed of
                        progress on this issue.</p>
                    <p>Hamilton responded to a query by Chairman Kimball during the break. HDR had
                        received a request from NSA to consider release of a bloc of World War II
                        period files. HDR had responded by suggesting that NSC wait until issuance
                        of the expected new Executive Order governing material prior to 1950 as that
                        might make review unnecessary.</p>
                    <p>Regarding new Executive orders, Kimball stated he had no new information
                        beyond what Freeman had said at lunch the day before. He expected further
                        discussion of the matter at lunch today.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="report-on-the-johnson-library-telephone-transcripts_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Report on the Johnson Library Telephone
                            Transcripts</hi></head>
                    <p>Nelson reported that the tapes made for fascinating listening and there is no
                        substitute for hearing them. A transcript does not do a conversation
                        justice. The tapes had surprisingly good audio quality. The subcommittee
                        definitely agreed that they should be used in <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes. The subcommittee suggested that the Committee
                        write to Harry Middleton giving him a broad statement of support and stating
                        that it appreciated the difficulties faced by the Library. The letter should
                        state that the tapes will greatly amplify the documents printed in <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. The problem for HO
                        historians was that the deadlines for the volumes will occur before all the
                        relevant tapes are reviewed.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp expounded on the problems: duplication; and the time needed to
                        review the conversations under the donor’s deed of gift. The Johnson Library
                        would like to review the tapes chronologically; HO wants them reviewed
                        topically to fit its publishing schedule. The solution suggested by HO was
                        to identify priority tapes within discernible time frames and ask the
                        Library to review on that basis. Van Camp agreed that the tapes added an
                        important new dimension, especially in style and interaction of
                        personalities. Johnson was a verbal person, not one given to writing.</p>
                    <pb n="10" xml:id="pg_10" facs="0012"/>
                    <p>Nelson noted that although the tapes are a definite plus, they add another
                        problem to meeting deadlines.</p>
                    <p>Kimball stated that Harry Middleton should be encouraged to accept HO’s
                        priority list. Van Camp suggested that it be a supportive letter. Herring
                        noted that Middleton is taking a risk by opening these tapes before the
                        50-year restriction.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey agreed that a letter was a good idea. He noted there were some 275
                        transcripts of conversations with Rusk, McNamara, and McGeorge Bundy already
                        in HO’s possession. But there are many more conversations by these men for
                        which there are no transcripts, and there are other important people Johnson
                        talked to.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if HO had sole access. Humphrey answered that it did. Davis
                        stated that he supported the subcommittee views as presented by Nelson and
                        Van Camp and agreed there was no substitute for listening to the tapes.</p>
                    <p>Slany asked that the Committee remind NARA not to use the Department of State
                        funded position, the subvention, to fortify position strength in the face of
                        the pressures to reduce personnel.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey stated that the position as funded by the Department of State was a
                        2-year temporary position without job security and it might be difficult to
                        convince a NARA employee to accept it.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked why a 2-year temporary job. Why not a transfer? Humphrey
                        responded that NARA’s problem would be saving the job-slot for 2 years if it
                        was not temporary.</p>
                    <p>Kimball was dubious about telling NARA and Trudy Peterson how to to do their
                        job. Nelson wondered if NARA could not be convinced to add another position
                        to the task.</p>
                    <p>Slany suggested that the Committee stress its commitment to the project.
                        Kimball suggested that it would be best to do this informally. Nelson agreed
                        to pass it to Trudy Peterson on that basis.</p>
                    <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11" facs="0013"/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="compilation" xml:id="closed-session_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session</hi></head>
                <div type="section"
                    xml:id="committee-consideration-of-foreign-government-information_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Committee Consideration of Foreign Government
                            Information</hi></head>
                    <p>Herschler then commented on the issue of foreign government information,
                        indicating that there had been some success in dealing with FGI problems in
                        the months since his written report had been prepared. Nelson noted that
                        Herschler’s report contained nothing new on the issue of FGI. Kimball asked
                        whether there had been any progress in getting the British to agree to
                        release documents at the 30-year line following a review prior to the
                        30-year mark. It was indicated that no such progress had been made.</p>
                    <p>Pryor discussed a meeting with British representative Richard Bone, who
                        stated that he saw no possibility of releasing British documents short of
                        the 30-year mark even if the new U.S. Executive order established a 25-year
                        time line.</p>
                    <p>Schwar questioned HO’s agreement with the British on identifying British
                        documents denied because they are less than 30 years old in <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. The agreement specified
                        that such documents should be identified only by year and place of origin
                        and by the term “Intergovernmental Communication.”</p>
                    <p>Several members of the Committee expressed opposition to this arrangement. It
                        was noted that U.S. law called for fuller identification of denied documents
                        and that the Committee had been urging the CIA to follow proper procedure.
                        Kimball stated that this was not a negotiable issue and that HO should not
                        abide by the agreement with the British.</p>
                    <p>Slany agreed that if the Committee thought the arrangement for citing
                        documents less than 30 years old that was reached with the British was
                        inadequate, then HO will reopen the issue. He noted that the Committee’s
                        reach was now crossing the Atlantic. Slany stressed that HO will have to
                        present the British with the argument that the Advisory Committee insists
                        upon renegotiation.</p>
                    <p>The Committee adjourned for lunch at noon.</p>
                    <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12" facs="0014"/>
                    <p>The Committee reconvened at 1:15 p.m. The members approved the Annual Report,
                        and Kimball asked Slany to circulate it to the professional associations,
                        members of Congress, etc.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section"
                    xml:id="report-on-appeal-of-declassification-reviews-of-foreign-relations-volumes_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Report on Appeal of Declassification Reviews of
                            Foreign Relations Volumes</hi></head>
                    <p>The Committee then turned to the report by the subcommittee, consisting of
                        Rosenberg, Leffler, Taylor, and Kimball, which reviewed the documents on
                        Japan for <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1961-1963 (including
                        some 1958-1960 documents). It was pointed out that the 60-day clock had not
                        yet started for the appeal on the British Guyana compilation but was over
                        for the Japan compilation. Taylor asked if the Committee should submit an
                        addendum to the appeal package as suggested by Bennett Freeman.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg pointed out that the Committee had essentially three choices: let
                        the documents go without action; write a letter to Moose with a fuller
                        rationale and ask Slany to attach it to the appeal package; or follow
                        Quainton’s suggestion of attaching a statement on this subject to the new
                        Executive order to the effect that some embarrassing things might be
                        released as a result. Attaching the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> series to the Executive order might be an ingenious
                        solution. She thought that a possible course of action might be a follow-up
                        letter to Moose that would summarize the Committee’s arguments without
                        reference to the Executive order.</p>
                    <p>Nelson agreed with Rosenberg that a letter should be sent, but it should not
                        be tied to the Executive order. Kimball wondered whether a letter to Moose
                        was necessary. Moose showed the Committee at lunch that he understands all
                        the issues, and he listened carefully. Herring pointed out that Moose’s last
                        words were, “I understand the seriousness of your position.”</p>
                    <p>Kimball suggested that Slany find out if anything else was required.
                        Rosenberg asked Slany for his opinion, and Slany responded that he thought a
                        decision would be made by next week. He also thought there was little else
                        that the Committee could do at this time.</p>
                    <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0015"/>
                    <p>Nelson reiterated that the Committee had had a good lunch with Moose, and
                        Kimball concluded that the Committee should do nothing. Bennett Freeman
                        could find out what, if anything, needed to be done. Rosenberg recalled that
                        Moose had said that release of the documents might cause a flap in Japan and
                        she wondered if he realized that non-release might cause a big flap
                        here.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp asked whether the Committee had to take any action before next week.
                        Kimball said that he would be on vacation next week so if the Committee
                        wanted to write a letter to Moose, someone else should draft it. Leffler
                        agreed to write the letter, if necessary. Davis said that if there was not
                        much to lose by writing a letter, then the Committee should do it. Kimball
                        thought there was something to lose because he believed Moose was the type
                        of person who could be annoyed by excessive amounts of paper. Leffler added
                        that he thought the Committee was going to lose on this issue, and it would
                        be much better to press on the issue of Guyana, a country of less importance
                        to current U.S. foreign policy.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then mentioned the documents for the Japan volume sanitized by HO.
                        The concept was left in, but the real issue is that this activity was part
                        of U.S. policy. He asked what if Moose allowed this issue to sit. The 60
                        days are up.</p>
                    <p>When Leffler asked whether Guyana will be up for decision, Kimball answered
                        affirmatively. Leffler then said that if the Committee waited until the next
                        meeting on both the Japan and Guyana issues, it might find two bad decisions
                        without an opportunity to have any input beforehand. He agreed to monitor
                        the situation with Slany.</p>
                    <p>Nelson reminded the Committee members that they had already told Moose that
                        the Japan compilation probably would not be printed. Kimball added that in
                        May the Committee recommended that the Northeast Asia volume be published
                        without the Japan compilation, but “Japan” would appear on the spine of the
                        volume and in the Table of Contents. The withholding of the Guyana
                        compilation, however, would prevent the publication of the entire volume on
                        the American Republics. Nelson said it <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0016"
                        /> was too bad the Committee did not tell Moose about its May decisions on
                        the Japan compilation, but Leffler and Herring believed that the Committee
                        members had gotten across the essential points to Moose.</p>
                    <p>The Committee then turned to the compilations on Cyprus and Greece
                        (1964-1968) and on Angola (1961-1963). Herring called the reviews in both
                        cases “outrageous” and “ridiculous.” In the case of Angola, only a few
                        documents were involved. No rationale had been given for the denials.
                        Kimball said that the decision had been made by the Angola and Portugal
                        desks, although HDR had recommended clearance of all the documents with
                        perhaps one exception.</p>
                    <p>Howland interjected that the desk officer argued that the release of the
                        documents on this issue, which was inherited from the Eisenhower
                        administration, would harm current U.S. relations with Portugal. Kimball
                        pointed out that Kissinger had acknowledged U.S. assistance to Angolan
                        liberation groups in congressional hearings in the mid-1970s. LaFantasie and
                        Herschler both commented that HO could not get a substantive answer on the
                        reasons for the denials.</p>
                    <p>On Greece and Cyprus, Kimball said that the compiler had noted that the
                        office director had been uncooperative, even “rude” to the compiler when he
                        requested the reasons for the denials. The office director, claiming the
                        issue had already been decided, refused to meet with HO. There was an
                        “attitude problem” here. The volume was being typeset now, but documents
                        could be added later. Kimball thought no action was required now, but the
                        attitude problem should be addressed.</p>
                    <p>Kimball told the Committee members that they could read the compiler’s
                        memorandum on the subject. Kimball added that Slany has promised to get
                        Freeman to convene a working group that might promote more cooperation.</p>
                    <p>Miller noted that the appeal on his volume (Greece, Turkey, Cyprus) would be
                        directed to the Director of the Office of Southern European Affairs (Adair),
                        rather than a desk officer.</p>
                    <pb n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0017"/>
                    <p>On Tibet, Kimball remarked that HO had gone back to the CIA declassification
                        staff with documents for decision, but the directorates have been obdurate
                        and have not made a decision. The 60-day clock has been “broken,” and the
                        Committee needs an appropriate answer by its next meeting.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section"
                    xml:id="report-on-declassification-review-and-opening-at-nara-of-department-of-state-records_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Report on Declassification Review and Opening at NARA
                            of Department of State Records</hi></head>
                    <p>The Committee took up the proposed Executive order on the declassification of
                        World War II documents. Russell (NARA) noted that there was disagreement
                        about the scope of the new Executive order. Chaddic said that HDR was in the
                        process of re-reviewing approximately 250,000 pages of pre-1950 documents;
                        some were pre-1945. Most of the previously withheld documents were now
                        releasable. Once the new Executive order was issued, review of withheld
                        records would be expedited according to the E.O.’s new criteria.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then urged the automatic release of all pre-1945 State documents.
                        Chaddic said that if he could have his way, all these documents would be
                        available immediately. Kimball said that all he wanted was to make HDR’s job
                        easier by not having it review documents unnecessarily, especially because
                        many of the documents were dated before 1945.</p>
                    <p>Nelson asked what reasons existed beyond “national security” that would
                        prevent the opening of the pre-1945 documents, and Chaddic responded that
                        the documents contain FBI and intelligence materials. Rosenberg said she had
                        seen some of the boxes and documents had been withheld by both CIA and by
                        State. Chaddic replied that under the new Executive order a smaller
                        percentage would be held back, but until the new order State would continue
                        to withhold documents.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked how national security could possibly be affected by pre-1945
                        documents. He said that he was concerned with the standards HDR was using to
                        guide its declassification decisions; he wondered whether HDR might be too
                        quick not to declassify documents. Chaddic replied that foreign government
                            <pb n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0018"/> information was usually the
                        reason, although he admitted that some items had been inappropriately
                        withheld.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg observed that a further problem at NARA was the requirement that
                        HDR personnel complete cover sheets for code-word documents. Chaddic said
                        that there were more code-word documents than expected, and he was working
                        to revise that procedure.</p>
                    <p>The Committee turned to Chaddic’s letter to Wright (CIA) and the follow-up
                        telephone calls. Kimball repeated that the CIA was divided on
                        declassification. Wright had suggested that he might send a team drawn from
                        the various CIA directorates to NARA in 2 weeks to assist in the
                        declassification of CIA documents. Slany was asked to monitor Wright’s
                        replies.</p>
                    <p>Leffler then said that during his visit to Suitland he reviewed the
                        “guidelines” for reviewers. He pointed to the example of India (through
                        1963). He was “appalled” at the restrictive language, which called for the
                        withholding of any information relating to counteracting Soviet actions in
                        India as well as any derogatory language about the motives or objectives of
                        Indian Government policy. He suggested that at each upcoming meeting a
                        subcommittee look at the guidelines for two or three countries and see if
                        they were appropriate for the post-Cold War world.</p>
                    <p>Chaddic emphasized that the guidelines were written for NARA reviewers, not
                        for HDR, and specified areas where documents should be referred to the State
                        Department for decision. Now there is one-step declassification review by
                        HDR. There are about 115 guidelines, mostly geographic, and a few on Latin
                        America and Africa cover three or four countries. There were also guidelines
                        on about six general subjects, such as petroleum, Law of the Sea, and
                        international organizations. He had a complete set of the guidelines in his
                        office.</p>
                    <p>When Leffler asked if the guidelines could be changed, Chaddic said he would
                        consider suggestions. Nelson said it was difficult to evaluate guidelines
                        and how they were interpreted in practice. Leffler said they were in the
                        reviewers’ heads now when they made decisions denying material.</p>
                    <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0019"/>
                    <p>Nelson then offered a summary of her subcommittee’s visit to HDR. She
                        described the process in which the withdrawn documents were separated from
                        the cleared ones. The “open” boxes contained withdrawal sheets for those
                        items withdrawn. Then HDR would write guidelines for other agency “equity,”
                        which NARA would apply. NARA would take over these documents this September,
                        but there was a potential problem because it was not clear whether NARA
                        would simply store them or formally take custody of them.</p>
                    <p>Nelson reported that NARA seemed pleased with the declassification review by
                        the State Department. The subcommittee looked at withdrawn documents, but
                        there was not enough time to look at many. Most documents were withdrawn
                        because of foreign government information. In at least one case she agreed
                        that the document should be withdrawn, but other cases were not so
                        clear-cut.</p>
                    <p>Overall this system was much quicker and more competent, she thought, and HDR
                        would likely complete the review by September. This was later clarified; HDR
                        hopes to begin reviewing the political files in September. The State
                        Department offices housing the documents were, however, very crowded; no
                        center or work area had been established. There will still be guidelines,
                        but Nelson endorsed Leffler’s suggestion that a subcommittee review the
                        guidelines at future Committee meetings.</p>
                    <p>Kimball wondered whether it might be time to issue an ultimatum to other
                        agencies: unless we hear otherwise, we will release your documents. He
                        doubted that many would respond.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp disagreed with Nelson’s comment that the subcommittee did not have
                        enough time to review documents. She noted NARA’s concerns and felt that
                        NARA and State should not blame each other. When there was talk of the
                        1964-66 documents being open, did that mean only after the documents were
                        transferred to Archives II?</p>
                    <p>Michael Kurtz affirmed that all the RG 59 records, including the 1960-63
                        Central File documents reviewed by HDR, would be sent to Archives II in
                        September. This had been <pb n="18" xml:id="pg_18" facs="0020"/> worked out
                        with Chaddic, Machak, and Rossman. “Open” meant for public access. Their
                        problem was the hiring freeze at NARA (45-50 vacancies). State reviewers had
                        reviewed the Central, post, and lot files, so that deadlines could be met.
                        So, Kimball asked, are we going to meet the schedule? (Heads nodded.)</p>
                    <p>Nelson mentioned that Chaddic agreed that there would still be guidelines.
                        Barr noted that the talk about the guidelines was not entirely accurate, as
                        HDR reviewers often used them as a “framework” for their review. The HDR
                        reviewers were not experts on every part of the world, but the guidelines
                        allowed them to make decisions on everything. Kimball said there would be a
                        NARA subcommittee during the next meeting of the Committee, and he might
                        want to be on it. He agreed when Rosenberg pointed out that the Committee
                        needed to select the countries for which it wanted to review the
                        guidelines.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then asked about the “Yardley” material. Chaddic noted that these
                        were the “Magic” records. HDR had received a request from NSA for bulk
                        declassification of the 1942-1945 records. INR was opposed to bulk
                        declassification, and HDR asked NSA to put these documents on hold until the
                        new Executive order on World War II records was issued. The NSA position was
                        that these Magic records contained nothing on sources and methods, but
                        Hamilton pointed out that INR argued that they include diplomatic
                        intercepts. He did not agree with the NSA representative (Johnson) in the
                        morning session that these records were limited to the 1930s.</p>
                    <p>Kurtz pointed out that the proposed new Executive order applied only to those
                        documents already accessioned by NARA. Chaddic did not realize this.</p>
                    <p>Kimball stated that he was at loss about how to handle this issue. He was
                        appalled at the notion that any agency thinks that records that old are
                        still sensitive. INR should explain its position, which seems “irrational.”
                        The Committee might send a letter to the agencies asking for their
                        explanations.</p>
                    <p>Chaddic said the State Department was not ready to go to bulk
                        declassification, but he was willing to go back to INR and <pb n="19"
                            xml:id="pg_19" facs="0021"/> NSA and try to work it out. He personally
                        did not see anything that needed to be withheld. Rosenberg thought the
                        Committee should ask HDR for a verbal report next time on this issue.
                        Kimball agreed. Nelson and Kimball added that NARA should be included.</p>
                    <p>This session ended at 3:10 p.m.</p>
                    <p>Joe Chaddic left the room to a round of applause; it was his final official
                        appearance before the Committee.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" xml:id="comments-from-the-staff_1">
                    <head><hi rend="underline">Comments From the Staff</hi></head>
                    <p>Kimball asked if the staff would like to make any comments.</p>
                    <p>Keefer commented that it is the “same old story,” citing the recurring
                        problems with the LBJ tapes and files transferred to Archives II. These
                        problems, and the consequent delays in compiling, are making it difficult to
                        meet the schedule.</p>
                    <p>Kimball replied that, although the compilers must by law adhere to the
                        schedule, the Advisory Committee had resolved that the quality of the <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series must not be compromised
                        in the process. If specific problems arise, the Committee will deal with
                        them on a case-by-case basis.</p>
                    <p>Nelson said that the Committee would need to step in if any problems should
                        arise with Archives II, e.g., transfer of records, copying, etc. Kimball
                        agreed.</p>
                    <p>Kimball thanked Keefer for raising the issue {schedule vs. quality) again. He
                        suggested that Slany or LaFantasie should let the Committee know if the
                        compilers required any further assistance.</p>
                    <p>Miller explained that the Historian’s Office was relying on the 1991 <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> statute to secure access to
                        other agency records. A contact of his at CIA, however, had informed him
                        that the Agency had other statutes to consider -- statutes that were in
                        conflict with the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> law. Miller
                        said it was difficult for the CIA to appreciate the HO point of view,
                        especially since the unauthorized disclosure of information could lead to
                        disciplinary action by the Agency against its employees, i.e.,
                        termination.</p>
                    <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20" facs="0022"/>
                    <p>Kimball explained that Frank Sieverts (Senate Foreign Relations Committee)
                        had tried to resolve any discrepancies between the relevant statutes, but
                        had been forced to finesse the issue in order to ensure passage of the <hi
                            rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation.</p>
                    <p>Nelson cited the possibility of conflict of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> statute with the National Security Act of 1947. Kimball
                        agreed with Nelson’s assessment that any further legislation might have to
                        exclude the CIA from participation.</p>
                    <p>Kimball adjourned the meeting at 3:20 p.m. and the Committee went into
                        executive session.</p>
                    <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0023"/>
                </div>
                <div type="section"
                    xml:id="remarks-to-the-advisory-comittee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-august-5--1994_1">
                    <head><hi rend="bold">REMARKS TO THE ADVISORY COMITTEE ON HISTORICAL DIPLOMATIC
                            DOCUMENTATION</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"/>
                        <hi rend="bold">AUGUST 5, 1994</hi></head>
                    <p rend="center">(<hi rend="bold">DAVID A. LANGBART, NARA</hi>)</p>
                    <p>I have been asked to speak to you about three things, two concerning recent
                        ongoing developments regarding records of the Department of State and one
                        relating to records of interest to this committee: one, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> clearance files maintained by the Historical
                        Documents Review Division; two, selected records of the Bureau of African
                        Affairs; and, three, world war II era Navy crypto records.</p>
                    <p>Before discussing these three topics, I think it might be l useful to say a
                        few words about the process of scheduling records. By law, agencies are
                        required to schedule their records and no Federal records may be destroyed
                        without the approval of the Archivist of the United States. For the most
                        part, the process begins when an agency submits a schedule to the National
                        Archives and Records Administration. On a schedule, an agency identifies
                        series of records and proposes a disposition (for example destruction after
                        a period of time or future transfer to the National Archives). It is the
                        responsibility of the NARA staff to review the records and, in the context
                        of all relevant records, make a final decision on whether they are only of
                        temporary value or warrant permanent retention in the National Archives. We
                        may sustain an agency’s recommendation or we may decide that the records
                        warrant a different disposition, but the final decision rests with NARA.
                        Notices are published in the <pb n="22" xml:id="pg_22" facs="0024"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Federal</hi> Register of all schedules calling for the
                        destruction of records or a reduction in retention period. Persons
                        interested in a particular schedule may request a copy and then provide us
                        with comments.</p>
                    <p>One possible means of disposing of records that NARA determines to be
                        temporary is donation to an appropriate person, organization, institution,
                        corporation or government that has requested them. No records may be donated
                        without prior written approval from NARA. Among the limiting factors
                        involved, donations must be done at no cost to the government and the
                        records may contain no information the disclosure of which is prohibited by
                        law or is contrary to the public interest.</p>
                    <p>One pending schedule covers the Foreign Relatione of the United States Record
                        File created and maintained by HDR. In addition to the schedule from HDR, we
                        also received a schedule covering the records of the Historical Office. That
                        schedule, also still pending, includes an item for HO’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> Clearance File. After reviewing records covered
                        by these two schedules, we chose to focus our attention on the HO files
                        because that office has ultimate responsibility for the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> series. Furthermore, its clearance files contain
                        essentially the same information as the HDR review files and they cover all
                        volumes since the World War II compilations. Despite the fact that these are
                        essentially routine publication clearance files, in recognition of the
                        importance of the series, <pb n="23" xml:id="pg_23" facs="0025"/>
                        controversies surrounding compilation and declassification, and in the hope
                        that somebody might some day write a history of the publication, NASA
                        determined that the HO publication clearance files warrant eventual transfer
                        to the National Archives and that is how the schedule sent for signing
                        reads. Since the material in the HDR files is essentially duplicated in HO
                        files we determined that it is not necessary to preserve both series and the
                        HDR records are scheduled for eventual destruction, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >you</hi> may be interested to know that the HO schedule also provides
                        coverage for the records of this advisory committee.</p>
                    <p>The set of six schedules covering records of the Bureau of African Affairs,
                        submitted by the Department on December 18, 1992, represent the first time
                        all records of a geographic bureau have been scheduled. In the past, we have
                        received schedules covering only isolated series maintained by any
                        geographic bureau. Appraising all of the records of a bureau at one time
                        provided valuable context for us in making our decisions. The six schedules
                        cover:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1. the Assistant Secretary and other Front Office records</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2. the Office of Regional Affairs</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3. the Public Affairs Staff</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>4. the Economic Policy staff</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>5. the Office of the Executive Director</p>
                            <p>and</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>6. the geographic offices.</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <pb n="24" xml:id="pg_24" facs="0026"/>
                    <p>All but the two schedules covering the Office of Regional Affairs and the
                        geographic offices have been approved by the Acting Archivist.</p>
                    <p>During review of the records, we determined that the annual Program Files of
                        the Office of Regional Affairs and the geographic offices do not merit
                        transfer to the National Archives. It is important to note that the proposed
                        schedules do not make all records of those offices disposable. Both
                        schedules call for transfer to the National Archives of Special Collections
                        of files. Those records generally cover on-going issues and special problems
                        for which an annual cut off of files would not be appropriate. The schedule
                        for the geographic offices also designates as permanent records of
                        bureau-level task forces and working groups, briefing books, and certain
                        Fair Labor Standards files unique to the Office of South African Affairs.
                        Significant documentation on African affairs will be found in the Automated
                        Data System (ADS), the files of the Department’s principal officers (the
                        Secretary of State, the Deputy Secretary, and the Under Secretaries), and
                        the files of Foreign Service Posts. Other permanent records will also
                        include documentation on African matters. The files we have appraised as
                        disposable consist overwhelmingly of copies of telegrams, memorandums, and
                        other documents that will be found among the permanent records of the
                        Department of State. The schedules will genrally cover the period from 1990
                        to the present.</p>
                    <pb n="25" xml:id="pg_25" facs="0027"/>
                    <p>In reaching a final decision, we took some extraordinary steps because of the
                        precedent setting nature of the work in this geographic bureau. After the
                        initial appraisal and review, the Records Appraisal and Disposition Division
                        held extensive internal discussions on this matter. In addition, we met with
                        our colleagues in the Textual Projects Division and the Textual Reference
                        Division to review and discuss the appraisal. That discussion upheld the
                        conclusions of the initial appraisal. In order to ensure the best possible
                        appraisal, however, we decided that a visit to the Department was warranted
                        in order to conduct a further review of the records and to discuss the
                        appraisal. The results of that review once again upheld the initial
                        appraisal. The files reviewed by NARA staff consisted overwhelmingly of
                        copies of telegrams. The files also include lesser amounts of other types of
                        documents such as memorandums and correspondence. They contained only a
                        handful of unique documents, certainly no more than one or two percent of
                        the total volume, and those few items supplement in very modest fashion the
                        permanent Department files that document decision making and policy
                        formulation. We then prepared a report on our findings for the Acting
                        Archivist who indicated approval. We are now waiting for the Department to
                        revise the schedules as requested before they are sent for final approval.
                        The situation in the Bureau of African Affairs is not unique. We have just
                        concluded a review of the analogous files of the Bureau of Inter-American
                        Affairs and reached the same conclusion about the annual program files of
                        the geographic offices in that bureau.</p>
                    <pb n="26" xml:id="pg_26" facs="0028"/>
                    <p>The Navy intelligence records in question relate to World War II-era
                        communications security and communications intelligence as well as Navy
                        operational records supported by those programs. The records consist of a
                        number of series, the most important of which are:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1. Inactive Stations Library</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2. Active Stations Library</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3. Radio Intelligence Publications Library</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>4. Translations of Intercepted Enemy Radio Traffic and Miscellaneous
                                World War II Documentation</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>and 5. Microfilm Collection</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In March 1993, at the request of the Naval Security Group Command, a
                        successor to OP-20-G, two appraisal archivists visited the remote Navy
                        storage facility and carried out an appraisal and review of the records. The
                        pre-1946 records deal mostly with Navy radio intelligence and cryptography
                        activities from the late 1930s through the end of World War II. They
                        document the impact of radio intelligence and cryptographic work on Navy
                        operations in all theaters of operations. Our conclusion was that these
                        records are vital to analysis and understanding of Navy operations during
                        World War II that they should retain their identity as Navy records and be
                        transferred to the National Archives. Our recommendation received support
                        from many elements within the Navy and legal transfer of the records took
                        place in September 1993. Actual physical delivery of the records came in May
                        of this year.</p>
                    <p>The records recently transferred to the National Archives <pb n="27"
                            xml:id="pg_27" facs="0029"/> include approximately two thousand cubic
                        feet of material including fifteen thousand three hundred and forty two
                        rolls of microfilm. For the most part, the records transferred to the
                        National Archives date to about 1946. Perhaps the most comprehensive records
                        will be found on the microfilm. These include Japanese raw intercepts,
                        station files, subject files from various OP-20 offices, German U-boat
                        files, intercepted German clandestine traffic, analyses of intercepted
                        German traffic, intercepted diplomatic traffic, ULTRA summaries, work
                        sheets, captured documents, Navy message traffic, and other
                        intelligence-related material. The Navy retains in its possession records
                        from about 1946 to the present, included in the records retained by the Navy
                        are files relating to both the U.S.S. Liberty and the U.S.S. pueblo.</p>
                    <p>The records we received in May of this year are in SCI storage at Archives 2.
                        At this point, there has been minimal archival processing. We basically know
                        where things are Declassification is dependent upon the National Security
                        Agency which asserts authority over final declassification of all crypto
                        records throughout the government. My understanding is that NSA is still
                        trying to figure how to deal with these records. They are reluctant to
                        commit to undertaking a systematic review of the files, particularly the
                        microfilm. There is some discussion about a bulk declassification of the
                        Japanese Orange Translations, but no final decision has been made.
                        Therefore, access will be dependent upon FOIA requests unless something <pb
                            n="28" xml:id="pg_28" facs="0030"/> happens to cause NSA to change its
                        mind or policies. One thing I am happy to report is that NSA has scheduled
                        for transfer the so-called Red Machine intercepts of Japanese diplomatic
                        messages. The approximately 3300 translations cover the period from mid-1934
                        to the end of 1938.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
