<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1994-05-05">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, May
                    1994</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1994</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1994-05-05">May 05, 1994</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[1]" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section" xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation_1">
                <head>ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON HISTORICAL DIPLOMATIC DOCUMENTATION May 5 and 6,
                    1994</head>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Committee Members</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Warren F. Kimball, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Betty Glad</item>
                    <item>George C. Herring</item>
                    <item>Melvyn P. Leffler</item>
                    <item>Anna K. Nelson</item>
                    <item>Jane M. Picker</item>
                    <item>Emily S. Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Arnold H. Taylor</item>
                    <item>Anne H. Van Camp</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Public Affairs</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Bennett Freeman</item>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Office of The Historian</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Historian</item>
                    <item>Glenn W. LaFantasie</item>
                    <item>Rita M. Baker</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Evans Gerakas</item>
                    <item>David C. Geyer</item>
                    <item>David H. Herschler</item>
                    <item>Kerry E. Hite</item>
                    <item>Donna C. Hung</item>
                    <item>David C. Humphrey</item>
                    <item>Edward C. Keefer</item>
                    <item>Daniel Lawler</item>
                    <item>James E. Miller</item>
                    <item>Harriett Schwar</item>
                    <item>Jeffrey Soukup</item>
                    <item>Shirley T. Taylor</item>
                    <item>Carolyn B. Yee</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Bureau of Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Frank M. Machak, Director, A/IM/IS/FPC</item>
                    <item>Kenneth Rossman, Chief, Records Management IS/OIS/RA/RD</item>
                    <item>Joe H. Chaddic, Director, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>William C. Hamilton, IS/FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>Nina Noring</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[2]" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0002"/>
                <p><hi rend="underline">National Archives and Records Administration (NARA)</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>George C. Chalou, Archivist, Records Appraisal Division</item>
                    <item>David A. Langbart, Archivist, Records Appraisal and Disposition
                        Division</item>
                    <item>Jerome Nashorn, Chief, Military Appraisal Branch</item>
                    <item>Marvin Russell, Chief, General Archives Review Branch</item>
                    <item>Nancy Smith, Archivist, Presidential Libraries</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Central Intelligence Agency</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mary McAuliffe, Deputy Historian</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Public</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Page Putnam Miller, Director, National Coordinating Committee for
                        Promotion of History</item>
                    <item>Karen Gatz, Department of Justice, Office of Special Investigations</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[3]" xml:id="pg_3" facs="0003"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="table-of-contents_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">TABLE OF CONTENTS</hi></head>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>1. Open Session, Thursday, May 5, 9:00 - 10:30 A.M.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Opening of the Meeting</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_3">3</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Remarks by Bennett Freeman</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_3">3</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by the Historian on the Status of the Foreign Relations
                            Series</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_4">4</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on the Status and Prospects of Declassification of
                            Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2. Open Session, May 5, 10:55 - 12 noon</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on Access to INR Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_11">11</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on the status of Tapes at the Johnson Library</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3. Luncheon Session, May 5, 12:00 - 1:30 P.M.</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_18">18</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4. Closed Session May 5, 1:30 - 3:00 P.M.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by Nancy Smith on the Nixon Presidential Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_20">20</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Opening Department 30 year old and Older
                            Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_21">21</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Subcommittee Report on Foreign Relations Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_23">23</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5. Closed Session, May 3:15 - 4:25 P.M.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by Deputy Historian Declassification and Appeal Issues</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_25">25</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Committee Discussion of PRD-29</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_28">28</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6. Closed Session, Friday, May 6, 9:08 - 10:30 A.M.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Deputy Historian Report on Research for Foreign Relations
                            Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_31">31</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Comments by CIA on Foreign Relation Reviews</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_40">40</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7. Closed Session, Friday, May 6, 10:45 - 11:30 A.M.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Discussion on PRD-29</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_42">42</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Staff Comments and Conclusion of Meeting</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_43">43</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb n="[4]" xml:id="pg_4" facs="0004"/>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--may-5--1994--9-12---10-30-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, May 5, 1994, 9:12 - 10:30 A.M.</hi></head>
                <p>The Advisory Committee convened at 9:12 a.m.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked the Committee members if anyone had any objections to the agenda.
                    No one objected. He asked the Committee members for written comments for the
                    Annual Report.</p>
                <p>Bennett Freeman entered at 9:18 a.m. He said he had spoken to all but one of the
                    Committee members prior to today’s meeting, and that he had shared the
                    Department’s response regarding PRD-29 with all the members by mail. He said
                    that he was satisfied that members of the Department who wrote the Department’s
                    response to PRD-29 had fully heard the Committee’s views. He acknowledged that a
                    25 year declassification line was desirable but not attainable; because of a
                    lack of resources, only a 30 year line was feasible. He added that the Advisory
                    Committee oversight mechanism should value its role and the future role of the
                    academic community. The Bureau of Public Affairs (PA) is satisfied that the
                    Committee’s views were heard and aired fully in the Department. He said the
                    Department’s response and the Interagency response were sent to the National
                    Security Council (NSC). He said that the Committee could discuss PRD-29 but that
                    the Department could not make any further response. Finally, he said the
                    drafters of the Department’s response had heard the Advisory Committee’s views
                    though they had not adopted them completely.</p>
                <p>Herring asked, when will the process end?</p>
                <p>Freeman said the NSC’s redraft is underway taking into account the Interagency
                    response, but he himself did not know when the final PRD-29 draft would be
                    ready.</p>
                <pb n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0005"/>
                <p>Kimball asked whether the Department’s response would include the roles of the
                    academic and scholarly communities.</p>
                <p>Freeman said, yes, and he was willing to send a letter to the NSC to seek
                    clarification on this point.</p>
                <p>Freeman was thanked for coming to the meeting and sharing his views on how the
                    Committee’s views on PRD-29 were being handled. He exited at 9:28 a.m.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the revised agenda was adopted. The committee members
                    assented.</p>
                <p>The report on the status of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi> series was given by William Z. Slany, the Historian.
                    Slany said the series was proceeding approximately on schedule. He said the
                    1980’s volumes being published now do not reflect changes in the standards of
                    publication brought on by the <hi rend="underline">FRUS</hi> legislation. Slany
                    said there was one retirement (Charles Sampson), and he introduced two new
                    historians, Dr. Karen Gatz and Mr. Daniel Lawler. He added that it was difficult
                    to hire new employees because of complicated personnel rules.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if there was a funding problem?</p>
                <p>Slany replied that he was concerned with government downsizing, but that the
                    Historical Office (HO) is authorized to recruit and maintain staff at the level
                    of a few years ago. He went on to say that HO is unable to continue the <hi
                        rend="underline">Current Documents</hi> series; 75 percent of the
                    information in <hi rend="underline">Current Documents</hi> is already printed in
                        <hi rend="underline">Dispatch</hi> and that the remaining 25 percent would
                    be added to a CD-ROM. He said the CD-ROM will have more information than the <hi
                        rend="underline">Current Documents</hi> series.</p>
                <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0006"/>
                <p>Kimball asked if the CD-ROM would be distributed automatically to all government
                    depository libraries.</p>
                <p>Slany said yes.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether letters were sent to Journals to inform the public about
                    these changes.</p>
                <p>Slany said he wanted to discuss this first with the Committee and that McCurry
                    was concerned.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked if there would be a timelag caused by the discontinuation of the
                        <hi rend="underline">Current Documents</hi> series as it exists now and the
                    proposed transference of it onto CD-ROM.</p>
                <p>Slany said no.</p>
                <p>Picker asked if <hi rend="underline">Dispatch</hi> was on CD-ROM.</p>
                <p>Slany said yes, and that there is search software.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the Committee was satisfied? No one objected so Kimball said the
                    Committee concurred with this change.</p>
                <p>Slany then discussed the Committee’s Charter (TAB C [package distributed to the
                    Committee members prior to the meeting]). He said that the Federal Advisory
                    Committee Act requires charter renewal every two years; and that the only change
                    in the Charter is an increase in the amount of money needed to sustain the
                    Committee. He then discussed the question of dissemination of Advisory Committee
                    documents. He asked if the charter was adequate to deal with the dissemination
                    of information that HAC receives.</p>
                <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7" facs="0007"/>
                <p>Kimball said that the Advisory Committee is responsible to the public through the
                    organizations it represents. He said that the Committee has access to privileged
                    information of ongoing discussions within the Department which State does not
                    want released to the public. He said the amount of information the Committee
                    receives would be affected by whether it accepts restrictions on release of
                    privileged information. He said the Committee needs full access to advise the
                    Secretary of State and that by reason of law it cannot be excluded. He asked how
                    to deal with privileged information and how to deal with “outside”
                    information.</p>
                <p>Nelson said the Department decides and the Committee abides by the decision. She
                    said it was up to the Department to decide what is privileged information.</p>
                <p>Glad asked how is privileged information handled now?</p>
                <p>Machak said that the majority of officials don’t mark privileged information, and
                    that it is dealt with on a case by case basis. He said there is a chilling
                    effect when comments of officials get into the hands of an audience outside the
                    decision making body when there is considerable disagreement among officials
                    about the Executive Order.</p>
                <p>Picker added that she thought it was the Department’s responsibility to define
                    what is privileged information.</p>
                <p>Machak said that the principle of “need to know” is applied by senior officials
                    in regard to dissemination of information. He said that they have the
                    prerogative to decide when to bring in other people into the decision making
                    process.</p>
                <pb n="8" xml:id="pg_8" facs="0008"/>
                <p>Kimball said the Committee has outside responsibilities. He wanted to assure the
                    Department that they are not nine loose canons, but at the same time they cannot
                    stop discussing not-yet-decided issues with their constituents. He said that
                    there were rumblings that the Committee had revealed privileged information on
                    PRD-29 discussions in the state Department.</p>
                <p>Slany said nothing given to the Committee is withheld except classified
                    documents. He said all the rest of the information is open.</p>
                <p>Kimball said there is no Committee statement or rule to solve this problem but
                    that the Committee will handle privileged information in a responsible way. At
                    the same time, he said that there will be times when the Committee “will do
                    “otherwise.” But in such cases, he said, the Committee will discuss it with the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Machak said he was unaware of any criticism of the Committee but that there was
                    uncertainty within the building about when to ask the Committee for advice.</p>
                <p>Kimball said that if the Advisory Committee is not engaged until late in the
                    process, then it cannot be effective. He went on to ask when the Department’s
                    fiscal year ends.</p>
                <p>Slany said it ends on September 30.</p>
                <p>Kimball said the Committee turns over on August 31, one month short of the fiscal
                    year but that this would not affect the Committee’s access to the Secretary.</p>
                <p>Glad asked what happens to the Committee’s papers?</p>
                <pb n="9" xml:id="pg_9" facs="0009"/>
                <p>Langbart said the Committee’s records are retired to the Archives after two
                    years.</p>
                <p>Herschler delivered his report (Tab E). He said that delays by the CIA in
                    declassifying FRUS manuscripts have resulted in a backlog of 15 volumes, a 1-1/2
                    year delay. However, under a crash program 12 volumes were cleared for the NSC,
                    but only 2 volumes have been cleared for typesetting. The remaining volume is at
                    the CIA. He also said the NSC is on schedule with the declassification
                    deadline.</p>
                <p>Kimball said that he had spoken to John Pereira and that he was aware of the
                    problem and that Pereira would like to cut down on the amount of internal
                    bureaucracy at the CIA to the point where one person would manage the clearance
                    process.</p>
                <p>Herschler said the CIA is behind schedule on one volume; HDR has provided
                    additional staff at the NSC, and HO will help the NSC with data-input. He said
                    that two volumes have not reached the NSC, one is still at the CIA, and the
                    other is at the Department of Defense, the 1958-1960 National Security and
                    Disarmament volume.</p>
                <p>Herschler then went on to discuss Guidelines for Declassification (Tab G).</p>
                <p>Kimball referred to the phrase “informal appeal…” which appears on the last page
                    of the Guidelines. He said that he thought HDR’s role in this process had
                    already been defined.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if the work HDR does at State and at the NSC is a duplicate effort.
                    Do they use different guidelines, she asked.</p>
                <pb n="10" xml:id="pg_10" facs="0010"/>
                <p>Chaddic said there were two HDR reviewers now three at the NSC who prepare
                    documents and research on what is in the public domain but they do not make any
                    declassification decisions.</p>
                <p>Noring said that at the time of HO #1 memorandum HDR sends memos to the Desks to
                    expedite clearance of volumes without appeal.</p>
                <p>Herschler said that there are two volumes in preparation for referral, one on
                    foreign economic policy and another on Congo and West Africa.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if the communication problem between HDR and HO had been resolved
                    with appropriate liaison?</p>
                <p>It is not a problem of liaison but rather HO keeping to its schedule, Noring
                    said.</p>
                <p>Slany said that 1995 could either be a good year or a down year, but in either
                    case the outcome will affect the 1996 production schedule. He also said that
                    delays at the NSC will be referred to Assistant Secretary Donilon for his
                    assistance, and that the backlog problem is not a matter for the Committee.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg, asked if the HO problem of meeting the FRUS production schedule was a
                    staffing problem?</p>
                <p>Slany replied that until HO had a full staff next year it cannot meet the
                    schedule.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if it was a matter of setting more reasonable deadlines?</p>
                <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11" facs="0011"/>
                <p>LaFantasie replied that the targets are reasonable but findings of new documents
                    at the end of the process caused delays. He cited the example of the INR vault
                    as a new source of documents.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg commented that that was excusable and suggested the possibility of the
                    need for a more flexible schedule.</p>
                <p>Herschler said that when new documents were added HO must send them to HDR and to
                    other agencies.</p>
                <p>Noring said that HDR accepts late documents and it does not take its full 120
                    days to review FRUS manuscripts.</p>
                <p>Slany said that he would like members of the Committee to review the Cyprus
                    volume to determine if it is what we and the Committee’s constituents
                    expect.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked when should this be done?</p>
                <p>Now, replied Slany.</p>
                <p>Schwar said because of the requirements of the law, combined with the shortage of
                    staff, HO sets compiling schedules based on the most favorable assumptions:
                    everyone will be healthy, there will be no research snags, there will be no
                    major declassification problems or additional assignments to take historians
                    away from the volumes they are compiling.</p>
                <p>The meeting recessed for a coffee break.</p>
                <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12" facs="0012"/>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="open-session--thursday--may-4--1994--10-55-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Open Session, Thursday, May 4, 1994, 10:55
                    A.M.</hi></head>
                <p>Chairman Kimball reconvened the meeting at 10:55 a.m. He asked the members if
                    anyone felt a need for an executive session before lunch. All felt that it could
                    be skipped.</p>
                <p>He announced that Ann Van Camp would be in Washington next week to meet with
                    David Langbart at Suitland to check on progress of preservation of State
                    Department records. He also announced that she would be attending a meeting of
                    an interagency group on electronic records.</p>
                <p>Kimball raised a question about the Memorandum of Understanding with the
                    Department of Defense. He read part of paragraph 7 and commented that the
                    Secretary of Defense could deny the Advisory Committee access to records. He
                    pointed out that that was illegal. Nelson said it depended on the level of
                    security clearance of the Advisory Committee member.</p>
                <p>Slany clarified that the Secretary of Defense could, under paragraph 5a, deny
                    access, but he must justify the denial in writing.</p>
                <p>Kimball then brought up paragraph 9, which referred to the President’s statement
                    upon signing the bill into law. Picker suggested that the statement should be
                    taken out. Kimball agreed that the phrase has no validity. Slany pointed out
                    that the new E.O. will make this point moot.</p>
                <p>Kimball called on Keefer to give his report on access to INR records. Keefer
                    reported that HO historians were getting full access to records and had a
                    standing invitation to explore code word material. Some documents have been
                    added to <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> manuscripts and will go
                    through the declassification process.</p>
                <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0013"/>
                <p>Kimball asked if the documents would be declassified by HDR. Keefer said they
                    would be reviewed by HDR and agencies with equity.</p>
                <p>Slany also brought up the question of the future permanent status of the records.
                    David Langbart informed the Committee that there is a retirement schedule. He is
                    working with INR and the Records Management staff to work out the details.</p>
                <p>Kimball said that the Committee appreciates the efforts of all concerned -- NARA,
                    Records Management, and INR -- to ensure appropriate access to and use of INR
                    records.</p>
                <p>Kimball then asked David Humphrey for the report on the status of the tapes at
                    the Johnson Library.</p>
                <p>Humphrey began his update by informing the Committee that there were 7,000
                    dictabelt recordings of Johnson’s telephone conversations, 2,000 of which had
                    been transcribed or summarized. The Department of State’s initial request was to
                    process transcripts of 400 conversations with Rusk, McGeorge Bundy, and
                    McNamara, and this has now been moved to the front burner.</p>
                <p>Herring asked if the 400 tapes covered the whole 1963-68 period. Humphrey said
                    yes.</p>
                <p>Nancy Smith said that the Library could not vouch for the accuracy of the
                    transcripts, which had been done by the White House staff, not the Archives.
                    Humphrey said that the recordings were useful as a starting point, but at least
                    4-5,000 tapes have not been transcribed. He said that the historians needed
                    access to the dictabelts themselves.</p>
                <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0014"/>
                <p>Page Miller asked how many hours of conversations are we talking about. Humphrey
                    explained that this was unknown because the project was still at a very early
                    stage and some of the tapes have never been heard.</p>
                <p>Humphrey reported that he was going to Austin at the end of May to discuss
                    procedures, problems, a schedule for access, and possibly to look at transcripts
                    if any were ready. Most have not yet been reviewed for privacy issues. The
                    Library sees this as a staffing problem, and Humphrey commented that the
                    Committee may want to recommend State funding of one position for 2 years to
                    accelerate access.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if this was necessary. Humphrey said yes, from what the staff at
                    the Library says, the material is valuable for <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>. He could only rely on people who are familiar with the
                    material.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie said that we anticipate this to be a rich resource and he hopes that
                    the tapes will allow us to fill in gaps in the record or better record the
                    outcome of a meeting. Maybe we won’t print the whole transcript, but use it for
                    annotation.</p>
                <p>Herring commented that the tapes were valuable because they give insight into
                    Johnson’s character and attitude toward foreign policy. Nancy Smith pointed out
                    that Johnson did not always commit to paper.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked if annotation will be the primary way to use the transcripts;
                    actual quotes will be more appropriate. LaFantasie said that he would not rule
                    out publishing the transcripts. An oral source that constitutes a record will
                    certainly be published.</p>
                <pb n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0015"/>
                <p>Luke Smith said that we have set a precedent in using transcripts in the Cuban
                    missile crisis. He put the information in editorial notes.</p>
                <p>Glad asked about the general problem of declassification and how to excise
                    material on the tapes. Humphrey responded that the majority may not be
                    considered classified and that technology exists to cut out portions of the
                    tapes.</p>
                <p>Humphrey said that the HO researchers will decide which conversations to listen
                    to by using the subject log and the transcripts. He said that, given the fact
                    that Johnson wrote so little, these tapes are a very valuable resource.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked what the Committee could do. Slany said the Committee must keep
                    three things in mind: 1) this will take more resources; 2) this will have an
                    impact on the schedule and will raise the question whether <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes should be published without the tapes; and
                    3) the priority given to <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> compilers
                    will hinder other users. We need some guidance on the hierarchy of importance.
                    Is it worth slowing the schedule to ensure inclusion of this material?</p>
                <p>Kimball said that unless the delay is “unconscionable,” the Committee would
                    rather delay publication. Herring pointed out that this will have an impact on
                    every Johnson volume. Leffler said it was important to know what was in the
                    collection. Kimball asked how many person hours were needed at the LBJ Library
                    to keep to the 30-year schedule and ensure access. How much delay and how big a
                    job?</p>
                <p>Rosenberg disagreed. She wanted to make a general endorsement of the importance
                    but to make no specific recommendations. Kimball said the Committee needs to
                    know what scale of resources will be necessary.</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0016"/>
                <p>Smith said that, although there initially was a 50-year restriction on this
                    material, Harry Middleton had decided to break the restriction to allow scholars
                    access to the collection. But the tapes must still be reviewed under the donor’s
                    deed of gift. Kimball asked if we could speed that process. Humphrey said it was
                    hard to get a specific number of man hours but the Library needs immediate help
                    to review the tapes.</p>
                <p>Humphrey said that HO is compiling volumes now without this information, and we
                    need to get access as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>Van Camp said that the experience with the JFK tapes should afford the Library an
                    idea of how much time and money would be required. Smith said she has budgetary
                    figures for the JFK project that she will share.</p>
                <p>Kimball pointed out that there are two parts to this issue: 1) this is a resource
                    problem and the Committee recommends that State Department fund a position for 1
                    year to evaluate and help to get the material into <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> manuscripts; and 2) what impact will the priority given to HO
                    historians have on other scholars.</p>
                <p>Smith pointed out that the Johnson Library wants State’s help to get all the
                    transcripts declassified and available to all scholars. Glad agreed that it was
                    important to use the priority given to HO historians to open the door for other
                    scholars.</p>
                <p>Chalou asked about the preservation of the dictabelts. Smith and Humphrey assured
                    him that the Library was already preserving the dictabelts.</p>
                <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0017"/>
                <p>Kimball said that Slany and Humphrey would work out a specific recommendation for
                    the Committee to make to PA. This will be discussed tomorrow.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked about the other volumes compiled without the tapes. She said she
                    was uncomfortable with volumes being published without this material. Why wasn’t
                    the Committee alerted about this earlier? Humphrey pointed out that the issue
                    was a recent one. The collection was originally closed for 50 years, and only in
                    1993 was the restriction lifted.</p>
                <p>Kimball said there are three categories of volumes: 1) those currently being
                    compiled, 2) those ready for the declassification pipeline, and 3) those in the
                    pipeline.</p>
                <p>Picker asked about a separate volume of these transcripts. Kimball pointed out
                    that this would mean publishing out of context. Picker explained that the legal
                    profession handles these kinds of updates with a pocket in the front of the book
                    to contain a subsequently published pamphlet.</p>
                <p>Van Camp remarked that this is only the “tip of the iceberg.” This issue of oral
                    records will only get worse.</p>
                <p>Smith wanted to make three points:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1) the conversations were not easy to understand</item>
                    <item>2) they were a running dialogue and switch from subject to subject</item>
                    <item>3) sometimes the tapes lead to different conclusions from the written
                        record; if the transcript is published later, it might be misleading.</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="pg_18" facs="0018"/>
                <p>Leffler suggested holding back the 1965 Vietnam volumes because a lot of the
                    discussion during this period concerned Vietnam. Kimball said that the Preface
                    could refer to the tapes at the LBJ Library and note that they were not
                    available at the time the volume was published.</p>
                <p>Smith said that there are approximately 400 key transcripts. Leffler asked if
                    they would be available in the next 12 months. Slany said it would be more
                    likely if State funds a position. Glad said that the 30-year line should be
                    pushed back to include this material.</p>
                <p>Taylor asked how the transcripts would be declassified. Herschler said the
                    declassification process was the same as for all <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> manuscripts, but the tapes must also be listened to. Luke
                    Smith asked about the reliability of the transcripts. Humphrey said they are
                    relatively accurate but that HO historians should compare a transcript to the
                    corresponding dictabelt before publishing it.</p>
                <p>Picker agreed with Glad that the completeness of the record was more important
                    than meeting the publication deadline. We should try to establish a procedure or
                    precedent to deal with this issue in the future.</p>
                <p>Leffler reiterated that access will be available within 12 months and the Vietnam
                    volumes should not be published without this material. Picker repeated that it
                    was necessary to establish a consistent approach. Nelson said that the Committee
                    needs to repair the volume (64 VN) that is out and hold the others for the
                    tapes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold"><pb n="19" xml:id="pg_19" facs="0019"/></hi></p>
                <p>Kimball asked how many volumes are involved. Slany said only two would be held
                    up. Kimball asked for how long. Humphrey said this would be a long project.
                    Kimball asked how long it would take to identify key conversations and pull them
                    out. Humphrey explained that the file HO had asked for was in alphabetical
                    order, but the dictabelts were organized chronologically. It was his
                    understanding that the Library will proceed chronologically in processing the
                    dictabelts.</p>
                <p>Kimball calculated a minimum of 18 months delay: 12 months to review the 400 key
                    transcripts, and 6 months to declassify.</p>
                <p>The Committee adjourned for lunch at 11:58 a.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="luncheon-meeting--may-5--1994_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Luncheon Meeting, May 5, 1994</hi></head>
                <p>Mr. Bennett Freeman, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, joined the
                    Advisory Committee for a working lunch. Mr. Freeman opened his remarks by asking
                    the Committee for its response to the latest draft executive order on
                    classification and declassification that had been prepared by the NSC.</p>
                <p>Warren Kimball spoke for the Committee and said that it believed the exemptions
                    were far too extensive and foreign government information was too stringent. In
                    several instances the Committee recommended substitute language for various
                    passages in the draft executive order, including those sections dealing with
                    exemptions and the potential harm that release of U.S. and foreign government
                    information might have on present U.S. foreign policy. Prof. Kimball also
                    pointed out that the terms of the draft executive order essentially would create
                    a 35 year implementation period rather than the intended 30 year period because
                    an extra 5 years is allowed for phasing in. The <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20"
                        facs="0020"/> Committee, said Prof. Kimball, also saw a problem in the fact
                    that the draft actually upheld page by page review, and that this could have a
                    political impact by making it appear that the administration was <hi
                        rend="underline">not</hi> in favor of openness after all. The Committee also
                    believed that the Appeals Committee should not be watered down in its authority
                    and that its membership should include academics.</p>
                <p>Mr. Freeman thanked the Committee for its thoughtful response, but he said that
                    the situation presented a rather awkward one. The problem, he said, was that the
                    Department had already delivered its own commentary upon the draft to the NSC,
                    and Mr. Freeman could not thus encourage the Advisory Committee to send forward
                    its own dissent. He recommended that the Committee devise a memorandum that
                    elaborated its points, give the memorandum to the PA Bureau, and PA would send
                    it forward to NSC. He said that in doing so, PA would have to point out that the
                    opinions expressed by the Advisory Committee did not represent the Department or
                    the Bureau.</p>
                <p>The Committee agreed with this approach. Mr. Freeman said he would clear this
                    approach with Mr. Donilon and would inform the Committee later whether the
                    memorandum should be handled this way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--thursday--may-5--1994--1-30---3-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, Thursday, May 5, 1994, 1:30 - 3
                    P.M.</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball asked Nancy Smith of the Presidential Libraries of the National Archives
                    to address the Nixon Presidential records issue.</p>
                <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0021"/>
                <p>Nancy Smith expressed her concern that the Advisory Committee be aware of the
                    looming problem with the Nixon materials. So far, Nixon’s death had not changed
                    the access situation regarding the Nixon Presidential materials. The National
                    Archives (NARA) was currently being sued by Nixon, who contended that, before
                    opening any additional tapes, NARA should complete its review of the tapes for
                    personal and private material and return that material to Nixon. On the other
                    hand, Public Citizen had sued because the tapes were not being opened quickly
                    enough.</p>
                <p>Smith emphasized that HO needed to begin negotiating with the Nixon lawyers and
                    that it was better for State to negotiate directly with them rather than to go
                    through the Office of Presidential Libraries, especially since the office was
                    involved in a suit with Nixon.</p>
                <p>Smith assumed that in his will Nixon had made provision for agents to carry on
                    his litigation under the Presidential Materials and Recordings Act.</p>
                <p>While many issues of privacy died with Nixon, Smith stated that there were 4,000
                    hours of voice-activated tapes. The tapes were being processed, but it was
                    extremely hard to understand the voices on the tapes. As for the textual
                    records, she hoped it would be possible to work out a partial processing
                    arrangement, similar to that worked out with the Kennedy and Johnson libraries.
                    There was a serious staffing problem at the Nixon project, since so much of the
                    staff was tied up in the litigation issue, working on the tapes.</p>
                <pb n="22" xml:id="pg_22" facs="0022"/>
                <p>Jane Picker asked for clarification on the matter of agents having been appointed
                    in Nixon’s will. Smith said that the issue of access was reserved for agents
                    under the 1974 Act covering Nixon’s papers.</p>
                <p>Smith noted that President Nixon was the last President to make tapes. David
                    Humphrey added that the Archives has not yet begun to process Nixon’s National
                    Security file. After some further discussion of the issue by the Committee on
                    the probability that the Nixon family would want to release his foreign policy
                    record, Kimball concluded that Slany should take up the issues raised by Smith
                    and prepare a status report for the next Advisory Committee meeting, indicating
                    what had been done and what was planned.</p>
                <p>Ann Van Camp indicated that she was not able to come to Washington for a
                    subcommittee meeting on Wednesday, thus she had no report to make.</p>
                <p>In her report on the preservation and publication of the Department’s
                    International Law Documentation, Jane Picker indicated that there was some
                    possibility for compromise on the issue and she was waiting to see how the
                    situation developed. Anna Nelson reported for the Subcommittee on the Opening of
                    the Department’s 30-year old Records. Based on her and Arnold Taylor’s Wednesday
                    visit to Suitland, where they examined documents concerning China, they
                    recommended the following:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1) that CIA send somebody out to Suitland or provide the State Department
                        with the declassification authority for dealing with documents marked with
                        the three letter acronym; the problem was widespread in the documents and
                        was proving very time consuming to deal with.</item>
                    <pb n="23" xml:id="pg_23" facs="0023"/>
                    <item>2) that State be provided with DOD guidelines like those that NARA had
                        from DOD. Currently State has to tab DOD documents for NARA, since it has no
                        declassification authority itself.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Nelson also noted that State could not declassify ACDA documents, so they had to
                    go to ACDA for review. Commenting on the random sampling procedure for examining
                    files at Suitland, Nelson stated that the technique was adequate. Arnold Taylor
                    stated that they needed to look at documents for more than one country before he
                    felt totally confident.</p>
                <p>Kimball stated that he had proposed to John Pereira of CIA that CIA provide
                    guidelines for declassifying the three letter acronym. Kimball also reported
                    that Pereira had stated that CIA was trying to arrange for a single person to
                    make the necessary CIA declassification decisions for the project at
                    Suitland.</p>
                <p>Emily Rosenberg stated that State should get the three letter acronym issue made
                    known to whomever in the Department could get it resolved, emphasizing the
                    resources issues. Kimball asked if Assistant Secretary Kennedy was the
                    appropriate person. He said he would get in touch with Kennedy, emphasizing the
                    waste of resources in the current setup and the importance of notifying CIA of
                    the problem. He asked Joe Chaddic and Slany to get back to him on the
                    appropriate way to proceed.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked Chaddic about the new declassification center. Chaddic responded
                    that the center itself was not ready, but that the declassification work was
                    already underway <pb n="24" xml:id="pg_24" facs="0024"/> with declassified files
                    being placed in Ken Rossman’s area. Kimball stated that the committee would
                    include in its annual report a statement that delays in establishing the
                    declassification center were proving costly.</p>
                <p>Melvyn Leffler reported on yesterday’s committee meeting with Gloria Boyd and
                    John Pereira of CIA. Nina Noring was also present along with Edward Keefer,
                    David Herschler, and Glenn LaFantasie.</p>
                <p>There was positive news regarding China and Tibet. An agreement had been reached
                    that one more review would be done by CIA, and Leffler thought there was a
                    possibility of an acceptable compromise. So, given the prospect of an agreement,
                    his recommendation was to wait one more time.</p>
                <p>The news on the contested Japan and British Guiana documents was not nearly so
                    good. The issues for the Committee’s decision were:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>-- Should the documents in both cases be moved from the fiche to the print
                        volumes?</item>
                    <item>-- Should the print volumes be published without the Japan and British
                        Guiana sections or should the entire volumes be withheld?</item>
                </list>
                <p>Leffler proposed linking Japan and British Guiana to make clear that we cannot
                    have a complete picture of our relations with those countries without
                    acknowledging the certain activities. Kimball stated that this issue is going to
                    come up again and again. He would like to get the issue as a policy matter out
                    in the open. Alternatives included:</p>
                <pb n="25" xml:id="pg_25" facs="0025"/>
                <list>
                    <item>-- Prefaces explaining that the record was not complete;</item>
                    <item>-- A Department decision to publish the volumes against the advice of the
                        committee;</item>
                    <item>-- Leaving the documents in the fiche and withholding the fiche
                        publications, not the print volumes.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Kimball recommended that the British Guiana documents be included in the print
                    volume because they provided such important insight into the Kennedy foreign
                    policy. Betty Glad recommended withholding the print volumes and seeing what
                    happens. Slany asked if linking the two countries was wise.</p>
                <p>Kimball and Leffler stated their non-negotiable demand for the inclusion of
                    intelligence information in the volume. Rosenberg asked if that kind of
                    information was an issue that came up frequently, could we identify other
                    instances and broaden the appeal? Had volumes been published without such
                    information?</p>
                <p>Leffler mentioned that during the previous day’s meeting Edward Keefer had
                    outlined other instances of certain kinds of U.S. involvement in foreign
                    elections during the Johnson presidency. Rosenberg asked if we were not making
                    it appear that such involvements began with the 1960s, since they had not been
                    included in previous volumes? LaFantasie said that the problem would be covered
                    by a separate intelligence volume.</p>
                <p>Ann Van Camp asked if the appeal process had been exhausted. If not, shouldn’t
                    the appeal process be pursued to the end. Slany stated that the process had not
                    been exhausted, an appeal had yet to be made to CIA, and a general discussion of
                    appeal procedures ensued.</p>
                <pb n="26" xml:id="pg_26" facs="0026"/>
                <p>The Committee decided to recommend moving both the Japan documents and the
                    British Guiana documents to the print volumes, publish the Northeast Asia volume
                    without the Japan compilation, if the CIA’s involvement was not acknowledged,
                    and withhold the entire American Republics volume if the CIA’s role in British
                    Guiana was not acknowledged.</p>
                <p>At this point the Committee adjourned for a coffee break. The discussion was
                    continued after the break.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--thursdaymay-5--1994---3-15-5-00-p-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, Thursday, May 5, 1994 - 3:15-5:00
                        P.M.</hi></head>
                <p>The committee reconvened at 3:15 p.m. and continued its discussion of
                    declassification problems.</p>
                <p>Kimball thought the Committee should give the Department and the CIA time to
                    respond to HO’s appeals, and that if the problems were not resolved
                    satisfactorily, then the Committee should recommend holding up publication. He
                    stated that the subcommittee had set forth minimal requirements for the volumes.
                    If (1) the Committee agreed and (2) the documents were withheld, then the
                    Committee should advise the Secretary whether or not the volumes met the
                    requirements and what should be done.</p>
                <p>The question was raised whether CIA’s clearance decisions in these compilations
                    could be appealed before State’s objections had been resolved. Kimball noted
                    that different issues were involved. CIA had to address the issue of its
                    equities in the documents, while State addressed the foreign policy implications
                    involved. If the Department was unwilling to appeal, the Committee would have to
                    do so.</p>
                <pb n="27" xml:id="pg_27" facs="0027"/>
                <p>Picker stated that the Committee needed to know where the barriers were. Slany
                    noted that responsible officials needed to be informed and to have an
                    opportunity to make decisions.</p>
                <p>Kimball raised the question of whether the Committee should take a position on
                    the issues involved at present. Glad noted that similar issues would arise again
                    and again. She thought this was a propitious time to put pressure on CIA on this
                    matter. Picker strongly supported Glad as to the opportunity presented by the
                    political pressures the CIA was currently facing from Congress. Kimball
                    concluded that even if State ultimately sought to deny publication of the
                    documents at issue in the two compilations, it would go a long way toward a
                    solution to confront and solve the CIA side of the problem.</p>
                <p>Kimball reverted to the question of whether to move the contested material from
                    the fiche to the print publications. He asked whether the committee agreed that
                    the Japanese documents at issue belonged in the volume rather than in the fiche.
                    There was general agreement. He asked whether they also agreed that the British
                    Guiana compilation belonged in the volume rather than in the fiche. Again there
                    was general agreement. Kimball noted that these changes would permit the
                    microfiche compilations to go forward to publication. The committee endorsed the
                    idea. Ted Keefer observed that he was being offered two fiche but no loaves.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked whether the committee wanted to recommend publication of a
                    Northeast Asia volume including the China and Korea compilations but omitting
                    Japan, should the Japan clearance problems remain unresolved. Such a volume, he
                    suggested, should include a preface indicating that the Japan compilation could
                    not be published as a full and accurate <pb n="28" xml:id="pg_28" facs="0028"/>
                    record of U.S-Japanese relations without the documents denied in the clearance
                    process. The other option, he noted, would be to withhold the entire volume from
                    publication. In that case, the documents declassified in the China and Korea
                    compilations might be made available to researchers in a State Department
                    reading room.</p>
                <p>Taylor thought it was unnecessary to hold up publication of the China and Korea
                    compilations in order to fight for the release of the contested material in the
                    Japan compilation. Glad supported Taylor’s position. She thought withholding
                    publication of an entire compilation, and emphasizing the omission in the
                    preface, might have more public impact than withholding the entire volume. She
                    felt, however, that the Latin America volume containing the compilation on
                    British Guiana should not be published without the documents the Committee had
                    agreed were essential to an accurate account. She also felt that the China
                    volume discussed earlier should not be published without resolution of the
                    clearance problems relating to Tibet along the lines of the minimum requirements
                    outlined by the committee.</p>
                <p>Kimball proposed that Glad’s analysis be adopted as the Committee position. The
                    Committee agreed. Kimball added that it would lend impact to withholding
                    publication of the Japan compilation if Japan was printed, along with China and
                    Korea, on the spine of the volume. He also suggested the omission could be
                    highlighted by including a separate statement in the front matter explaining the
                    necessity to publish without the Japan compilation.</p>
                <p>Van Camp pointed out that the law made provision for publication of descriptions
                    of withheld documents. Kimball stated that the subcommittee had raised this with
                    Gloria Boyd <pb n="29" xml:id="pg_29" facs="0029"/> and that the CIA is
                    unwilling to declassify even the title of some of the documents at issue.
                    LaFantasie stated that the question is whether the denied documents are crucial
                    to the integrity of the record. Kimball suggested that HO ask CIA whether there
                    are ways that summaries of the documents could be printed in lieu of the
                    documents themselves.</p>
                <p>Rosenberg asked whether the committee could expect to see replies from the
                    Secretary of State and DCI concerning these problems at the next advisory
                    committee meeting. Slany stated that HO would make every effort to obtain
                    responses.</p>
                <p>Picker asked, looking ahead, about problems that might arise in clearing language
                    for prefaces to explain omissions growing out of declassification problems.
                    Slany indicated that HO would address the question in the interim before the
                    next meeting.</p>
                <p>Moving on to the subject of the Department of State’s response to PRD-29, Kimball
                    summarized the letter the Committee intended to draft in response to the
                    position taken by the Department. The Committee had discussed the issue over
                    lunch with Deputy Assistant Secretary Freeman and, at the end of the discussion,
                    had decided that a response was necessary.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>(1) Kimball noted three specific issues concerning categories of documents
                        to be exempted from declassification: <list>
                            <item>(A) The Committee considers that FGI should be submitted only to
                                the same test as other foreign relations information. It thinks the
                                Department’s language represents a retreat from the language of the
                                draft executive order. The Department’s language provides for no
                                drop-dead date on FGI. The Committee considers that the presumption
                                should be that documents will be opened unless they meet an
                                exclusion test.</item>
                            <pb n="30" xml:id="pg_30" facs="0030"/>
                            <item>(B) The Committee thinks the language should read: “reveal
                                information that would cause exceptionally grave damage to U.S.
                                foreign relations or endanger a living source.” It agrees with the
                                removal of the words “between the United states and a foreign
                                government” but objects to the phrase “foreign activities.” Picker
                                urged insertion of the word “demonstrably” so that the language
                                would read “demonstrably cause exceptionally grave danger. …”</item>
                            <item>(C) The Committee disagrees with the recommendation to change the
                                authority of the appeals committee. It thinks that the appeals
                                committee should be able to make decisions.</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item>(2) The committee will point out that a 30-year rule with a 5-year
                        phase-in period is in fact a 35-year rule. The committee is concerned that a
                        30-year rule would encourage page by page declassification review rather
                        than a bulk approach. The letter will note that a 25-year rule is
                        effectively a 30-year rule, which the State Department has previously
                        supported. The committee will argue that to move to a 30-year rule, which
                        would effectively be a 35-year rule, would be to move away from a policy of
                        increased openness.</item>
                    <item>(3) The Committee disagrees with the recommendation to change the
                        authority of the appeals committee. It thinks the appeals committee should
                        be able to make decisions.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Kimball noted also that the committee intended to express a concern about undue
                    layering in the appeals process.</p>
                <p>Glad noted that the Committee would compliment the Department on its progress in
                    reviewing the Department of state records under the legislation. Kimball stated
                    that the <pb n="31" xml:id="pg_31" facs="0031"/> Committee appreciates the fact
                    that many in the Department are working hard to open the Department’s records.
                    Nelson noted that many of the concerns raised by the Committee would be raised
                    by outsiders as well.</p>
                <p>Machak was present during Kimball’s summary of the committee’s intended response
                    to the State Department’s position on PRD-29. He expressed appreciation for the
                    advance notice. He noted that the scheduled meeting of the electronic
                    information group had been postponed to May 18. He stated that Van Camp’s
                    perspective lent balance to the group’s deliberations, and he expressed the hope
                    that Van Camp could reschedule her travel plans to enable her to attend the
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Leffler asked Machak if outside researchers could be given access to the data
                    base listing documents declassified by the State Department. Machak responded
                    that there are some one million documents listed on the data base, which will
                    soon be available to researchers in the State Department reading room. Leffler
                    asked if the data base could be made accessible on the Internet system. Machak
                    stated that the Department was looking into the possibility of making it
                    available through the Internet system or putting it on a disk, which would be
                    updated on a regular basis. Leffler requested that Machak summarize in a brief
                    document what was available to researchers in the State Department and what was
                    planned for the future with respect to making declassified documentation
                    available to the public. Machak offered to provide a demonstration of his system
                    at the next (August) meeting, rather than a document.</p>
                <p>Nancy Smith noted that the draft executive order, like the present one, makes
                    mandatory review open only to U.S. citizens. Presidential Libraries takes the
                    position that mandatory review should be open to everyone, like the FOIA.</p>
                <pb n="32" xml:id="pg_32" facs="0032"/>
                <p>As the final business conducted by the Committee for the afternoon, Slany agreed
                    to poll the committee concerning dates for future meetings. The committee
                    adjourned for the day at 4:25 p.m.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-friday--may-6--1994_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Friday, May 6, 1994</hi></head>
                <p>The meeting was called to order at 9:08 A.M., Friday, May 6, 1994.</p>
                <p>Kimball distributed copies of a recommendation written by Dr. Slany and David
                    Humphrey concerning State funding of a person at the Johnson library to
                    accelerate HO access to dictabelt recordings and transcripts. He also gave S.
                    Taylor a diskette containing a memo drafted by Kimball and Herring and addressed
                    to Assistant Secretary Donilon about the new executive order on
                    declassification. S. Taylor was attempting to find a computer to convert the
                    document to the Department’s word processing system and print out with copies
                    for members of the Committee.</p>
                <p>Slany advised the Committee that he anticipated that Assistant Secretary Donilon
                    would visit the Committee meeting sometime between 9:00 and 12:00 noon.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie presented his report indicating that research at the LBJ library was
                    on schedule, and more trips to the Kennedy library were needed to complete the
                    last Kennedy volume (Paul Claussen’s volume dealing with the United Nations,
                    Scientific and Humanitarian Affairs).</p>
                <pb n="33" xml:id="pg_33" facs="0033"/>
                <p>LaFantasie said that HO is “casting its research net wider” to encompass still
                    more documentation from other agencies, particularly the CIA, ACDA, AID, and
                    Commerce. He mentioned the advances HO has made in access to INR files and the
                    LBJ tapes, and that the plan is to incorporate all of these sources whenever
                    possible in order to meet the requirements of the law.</p>
                <p>He said that State Department documentation is no longer adequate to provide the
                    complete historical record in a changing world of historical documentation. This
                    changing world affects the way the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series is prepared and published. <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> is
                    no longer the first place that people can get documents because of public access
                    through FOIA and mandatory review. We have seen examples where researchers
                    receive copies of documents through FOIA and then compare them to <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> for consistency.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> should remain the “master” of these
                    documents, therefore, we need to make sure that we know more. We must have more
                    background on the issues, not just the documents so that we can answer questions
                    that historians ask, not just print documents. LaFantasie stressed the
                    importance of addressing bibliographic issues, telling the reader what we have
                    and have not consulted and why or why not.</p>
                <p>Slany commented that the effort to find out what is already in the public domain
                    makes it necessary for us to consult with the National Security Archive. Nelson
                    added that the NSA zeros in on topics, not just documents.</p>
                <pb n="34" xml:id="pg_34" facs="0034"/>
                <p>Dr. Slany agreed and said that the antagonistic relationship between NSA and
                    State must be bridged by us, so that we know what they know. The NSA is holding
                    a conference in Georgia (United States) on SALT II. The Russians have come to
                    State with their documents that they would like to release and HO has been
                    assisting in getting the Department to agree to their release. Kimball commented
                    that it was his understanding that USSR documents were not considered FGI by the
                    State Department and wondered why State was reviewing them as we do not refer
                    documents to them. Slany said that the Russians were being courteous, and that
                    he understood that the documents were cleared by State yesterday (Thursday, May
                    5). Kimball pointed out that it was not a public relations coup by the State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>Nelson remarked that when researchers go to the National Archives, they still use
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> as a first step finding aid for
                    research. Other records tend to be incomplete, and <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> is used because it is a complete story.</p>
                <p>Kimball reported on the issue of CIA job and box numbers. He had raised this
                    issue with John Pereira and Gloria Boyd (CIA) in the declassification
                    subcommittee meeting on Wednesday. Kimball was concerned that CIA review
                    responses “thanked HO for not publishing the job and box numbers.” Boyd said
                    that job numbers are not always reliable and do not represent a good archival
                    citation. She and Kimball discussed the possibility of including a note in the
                    prefaces of volumes stating that these numbers are not always reliable.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie said that he and Ken McDonald had discussed the issue and were looking
                    to establish a far better method of citing CIA documents. McAuliffe concurred.
                    Kimball said that <pb n="35" xml:id="pg_35" facs="0035"/> this issue should be
                    settled quickly, and if not, HO should consider the idea of a statement in the
                    preface.</p>
                <p>Kimball inquired whether HO had made progress with the National Security Agency
                    in arranging for an access agreement. He brought up the subject of the Tonkin
                    Gulf intercepts, which should be part of the Johnson administration historical
                    record. These are located at the National Security Agency. Herring pointed out
                    that the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volume for Vietnam, 1964
                    had already been published.</p>
                <p>LaFantasie continued with his report. He said that HO has initiated a program of
                    outside review of volumes before publication. In the past, HO has reviewed the
                    quality of volumes in increments, first the compiler, then the division chief,
                    the General editor, and when necessary, the Committee. He has initiated a
                    program of expert review in which active Foreign Service personnel, who are
                    between assignments, review these manuscripts. With this program, these FSOs
                    have so far reviewed or are reviewing 1961-1963, Soviet Union, and both
                    1961-1963 Cuba volumes. A Department notice went out reporting HO as a “short
                    tour” assignment for Foreign Service Officers.</p>
                <p>These reviews are not as effective as an academic peer review, LaFantasie said,
                    but they can provide important insights, particularly on the completeness of the
                    volume, based on their experience and knowledge obtained in the field. He said
                    that it is difficult to use outside reviewers because they must have clearances.
                    From his perspective, thus far the reviews have been mixed. Substantively they
                    have been on the whole favorable. The reviewers prepare a report which is shared
                    with the compilers. The report is discussed and changes to the volume are made
                    if deemed necessary.</p>
                <pb n="36" xml:id="pg_36" facs="0036"/>
                <p>Slany pointed out that State, for budgetary reasons, is trying to limit its
                    hiring of contractors. HO is required to use active duty Foreign Service
                    Officers as a first step in order to demonstrate their effectiveness and justify
                    the cost of outside academic peer reviewers. LaFantasie mentioned the problem of
                    conflict of interest concerning cleared outside reviewers. Once they read
                    classified material, they can never write on the subject.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked why the documents were classified. Several people pointed out that
                    these reviews take place as early in the process as possible, and are therefore
                    done before the volumes have been completely cleared. Kimball asked if these
                    people are reviewing the full manuscript. Herschler said that was correct and it
                    included material recommended for excision or denial.</p>
                <p>Leffler commented that he thought this program would help generate support for
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> in the Department but was not
                    likely to lead to an objective review. He questioned the FSO’s ability to
                    accurately identify the key historical issues. He said that HO should not react
                    to outside critics (such as William Burr) because the compilers have a better
                    overall knowledge and familiarity with the sources. He suggested having
                    compilers review each other’s manuscripts. He said HO should ask itself, “are we
                    looking at the best documents?”</p>
                <p>Herring agreed with Leffler that reviews by FSOs are not likely to be objective,
                    but that it was cost effective for the Department. He also raised a concern
                    about the potential for losing time with these reviews. Slany said that these
                    reviews do not slow down publication of the manuscript.</p>
                <pb n="37" xml:id="pg_37" facs="0037"/>
                <p>Nelson said that she also agreed with Leffler. She suggested that an FSO would
                    see documents and want to take them out of the manuscript for reasons of
                    sensitivity or embarrassment. Slany said it was more likely to work the other
                    way around, the reviewers would question withholding information that younger
                    FSOs recommend for excision or denial. LaFantasie said that there would be
                    hairbrained suggestions by the reviewers, but that the role of a responsible
                    General Editor is to weed these out.</p>
                <p>Glad said that she thought it would be useful to get the “participant” reaction
                    to the volumes as long as their criticisms are not taken too seriously. Kimball
                    closed the discussion by stating that it was the consensus of the Committee that
                    the in-house review is okay, but not as helpful as an academic, peer review.</p>
                <p>Van Camp wanted to know more about the relationship between <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> and the National Security Archive. Slany explained
                    that the National Security Archive is the largest user of the FOIA, and that
                    when their cases are done by State, records are not returned to their original
                    files, nor does State always have accurate records of the results of
                    declassification actions. He said that as a result, the National Security
                    Archive can be used in two ways, first as a means of finding documents that can
                    no longer be found in State files, and secondly it can serve as a check on the
                    declassification status of documents until the new interagency declassification
                    database, proposed by the draft new Executive Order, becomes a reality.</p>
                <p>Van Camp stated that we must be careful about using National Security Archive
                    records because they do not always identify the correct provenance of
                    documents.</p>
                <pb n="38" xml:id="pg_38" facs="0038"/>
                <p>Nelson commented that it should be used as a source only as a last resort.
                    Kimball pointed out that it was just a safety check, and that he did not think
                    it was a major issue.</p>
                <p>Kimball then called on Harriett Schwar for her report on Iran document.</p>
                <p>Schwar referred everyone to her written report in the briefing package. She
                    reported that the History staff at the CIA (especially Scott Koch) has been very
                    helpful in getting documents from DO (Directorate of Operations). However, she
                    added that for awhile she was not allowed to look at the documents he
                    discovered. She now has enough information to tell a story, as she has Kermit
                    Roosevelt’s documents, which are very rich and explain the lack of
                    documentation. This collection of documents does not contain telegrams. In the
                    past, Jack Pfeiffer found some carbon copies of telegrams from poor quality
                    microfilm. There were problems identifying the provenance of these documents.
                    Pfeiffer retyped the telegrams. They were denied release, but the Department
                    still has copies. She added that she provided copies of these telegrams to Koch
                    so that he could attempt to find the originals.</p>
                <p>McAuliffe said that the historians at CIA did not even know about these documents
                    until Schwar told them.</p>
                <p>Schwar commented that there may be more material. There are carbon copies of some
                    operations plans. There must be a ribbon copy that went to the White House from
                    Allen Dulles to Eisenhower that shows approval of these plans, but she has not
                    found it. She found it hard to believe that CIA did not keep these records. She
                    commented that Dulles’ files have not been very helpful. Records show that some
                    lot files were <pb n="39" xml:id="pg_39" facs="0039"/> destroyed. She said that
                    INR has unretired files, so maybe CIA does too, and this should be explored. She
                    noted possible clearance problems for this documentation.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked about the meager size of the Dulles files. Schwar responded that
                    they were very thin. McAuliffe said that Dulles was not a note keeper, there are
                    “dibbles and dabbles” but not what you would expect.</p>
                <p>Glad asked if Schwar was using oral histories for dates. Schwar responded that
                    she is doing this on the side so there was not sufficient time to consult oral
                    histories.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if she was focusing on what the CIA has on Iran. Schwar responded
                    that she was exploring what CIA has in order to get a feeling about the amount
                    of documentation there is, and that any new compiler will have to do the
                    digging.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if there seemed to be enough documentation to keep searching. Schwar
                    said there was, but she did not think there was enough for an entire volume.</p>
                <p>Glad suggested a volume on Eisenhower covert operations. Kimball agreed, saying
                    that an intelligence volume would be helpful.</p>
                <p>An exchange was made about the telegrams that Schwar provided to CIA, and that
                    they were not originally sent to CIA because they were denied at State.
                    McAuliffe commented that the paper trail at the CIA has long since vanished. The
                    DO is there to provide support to field operations, not to support historical
                    research. Therefore, the history staff <pb n="40" xml:id="pg_40" facs="0040"/>
                    has engaged in much “sleuth” work in looking for the microfilm containing the
                    telegrams. They were not giving up, and she thought that they would find the
                    microfilm.</p>
                <p>Glad inquired about whether Schwar had used British sources to augment her
                    research. Schwar said that the UK does not release intelligence records.</p>
                <p>Keefer said that HO recently met with Heather Jasmine, the head of the British
                    equivalent of <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>, who said that they
                    were planning on producing a volume on the Middle East covering the 1950s, which
                    would include Iran.</p>
                <p>Schwar said that an intelligence volume would be interesting. Kimball suggested
                    that they broaden the discussion to a retrospective volume on intelligence.</p>
                <p>Slany said that Dave Patterson is now working on cleaning up an earlier
                    retrospective volume on intelligence from 1946-1950. Editing will be done in the
                    Spring. The office will then proceed to the retrospective volume suggested by
                    the Committee.</p>
                <p>Nelson said that from what she had heard, it must be a retrospective on several
                    actions. Rosenberg agreed, adding that the volume would probably cover the 11
                    covert actions mentioned by Woolsey.</p>
                <p>Slany commented that those are the known, but the unknown ones should also be
                    found and documented.</p>
                <pb n="41" xml:id="pg_41" facs="0041"/>
                <p>Glad said that she thought it would be important to include something on the
                    Hungarian revolt of 1956, Rosenberg suggested that HO prepare a written outline
                    of what should be included in this volume as a handout for the next meeting.
                    Kimball said that HO should work on getting State and CIA to acknowledge these
                    operations, so that it is not a wasted effort.</p>
                <p>Kimball then asked about the CIA’s current plans for publication.</p>
                <p>McAuliffe said that she is worked on an unclassified history of the CIA, which
                    she jokingly called “CIA, The Book”. She said that it would not contain any
                    surprises, but CIA would be officially acknowledging some things for the first
                    time. She is also checking the record for accuracy.</p>
                <p>McAuliffe said that the History staff hoped to declassify Nick Cullather’s
                    classified history on Guatemala, and that there was nothing startling here, but
                    it would correct some inaccuracies. They are also working on classified
                    histories on McCone, Helms, and Colby, which they hope to have declassified.</p>
                <p>Kimball asked if there would be a conference that would include release of a book
                    of documents on Guatemala. She responded that they are trying, but nothing had
                    yet been scheduled. She said that they are planning a conference for which
                    invitations had gone out, but the subject of the conference is classified.</p>
                <p>Nelson asked if the Soviet strategic estimates are already out. McAuliffe said
                    that one volume has been released containing economic and political estimates
                    for the period 1950-1959. A volume on Soviet strategic estimates will not be <pb
                        n="42" xml:id="pg_42" facs="0042"/> released until around November. Glad
                    asked what years it will cover. McAuliffe said it will cover the period up to
                    about 10 years ago.</p>
                <p>Leffler asked about a CIA volume on covert operations. McAuliffe responded that
                    Pereira’s staff was bogged down with reviews for <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, JFK, and the block declassification of the 11 covert
                    operations.</p>
                <p>Kimball stated that the Committee was concerned about access and resources. He
                    asked for reassurance that the CIA projects are not unearthing new documents
                    that were not available to HO. He stressed that <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> has to come first as far as the Advisory Committee is
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>McAuliffe responded that her staff was more involved with finding documents than
                    last year, because the staff has been increased. This includes finding computer
                    records because these new people have more computer expertise. If any of these
                    documents had not been available to <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>,
                    it is because they are just finding them now. She added that their publication
                    plan is not well-defined and that she and McDonald were meeting monthly with
                    Slany and LaFantasie.</p>
                <p>Kimball concluded with a few odds and ends: that Van Camp would be able to go to
                    the records management conference on May 18th after all; that he would pass out
                    the memo to Donilon (which S. Taylor had printed out); and that he would pass
                    out the minutes of the April 11th meeting on the Executive Order. He volunteered
                    that he did not see anything wrong with it except for a typo, and that he would
                    assume it is okay with everyone unless they say something to him. He noted that
                    Freeman told him that the NSC will complete its review of the agency comments on
                    the draft Executive Order <pb n="43" xml:id="pg_43" facs="0043"/> today (Friday)
                    and a revised text will be sent to OMB by May 13th, so it was important that the
                    Committee get its comments to the NSC by the end of the day.</p>
                <p>The Committee recessed for a coffee break at 10:30.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="closed-session--friday--may-6--1994--10-45-a-m-_1">
                <head><hi rend="underline">Closed Session, Friday, May 6, 1994, 10:45
                    A.M.</hi></head>
                <p>Kimball called the meeting to order. He outlined the remaining items on the
                    Committee’s agenda, including the wording of a draft memorandum to the National
                    Security Council concerning the draft Executive Order on information security
                    management, the wording of a letter preceding a visit to the LBJ Library, and
                    approval of the minutes of the April 11 meeting. Assistant Secretary Donilon
                    might appear in the course of the morning for a brief introduction, and Deputy
                    Assistant Secretaries McCurry and Freeman would be ready to deal with specific
                    concerns.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted that the committee’s memo for the NSC on PRD-29 had not as yet been
                    sent to the PA front office, but he had secured PA’s agreement that after the
                    Committee finalized the language it would be hand carried to the NSC. Friday was
                    the last day for such submissions, and’ the NSC would be forwarding its
                    recommendations to OMB for finalization the following Friday. It was not clear
                    whether OMB would request public comment, so the Committee should get its views
                    on record at this point.</p>
                <p>Discussion of the draft reply focused on limiting the definition of “sources” for
                    the purpose of declassification. The Committee sought to keep this term as
                    specific as possible without becoming involved in listing all possible types of
                    intelligence sources. In phrasing criteria for exempting <pb n="44"
                        xml:id="pg_44" facs="0044"/> documents from automatic release after 30
                    years, Leffler recommended the phrase “endangering a living source involving
                    drugs and terrorism.” Rosenberg proposed adding “nuclear proliferation.” Nelson
                    pointed out the need for a phrase broader than “intelligence sources.”</p>
                <p>The phrase “endangering a living human confidential source” should be retained in
                    section 3B of page 6, but Rosenberg suggested changing “revealing” a foreign
                    confidential source” to “endangering” the same. Otherwise a memorandum that read
                    “The Prime Minister told me confidentially” could be held back. The committee
                    also agreed on an exception covering “grave damage to foreign relations.”</p>
                <p>Rosenberg left the meeting at 11:23, after which the Committee agreed the memo
                    was ready to be put into final form. A five minute recess followed for
                    consultation with Slany and Herschler.</p>
                <p>The committee agreed to support sending a staff member to the LBJ Library to
                    study the Johnson tapes. Leffler asked whether HO had an alternative plan in
                    case it could not find funding to accomplish its mandated objectives. Slany
                    replied that while there was an alternative plan, more funding would be
                    preferable to attempting to carry out more work with the same number of
                    positions. LaFantasie suggested that the subject not be discussed in the
                    presence of NARA personnel. Leffler stated he was satisfied with Slany’s
                    reply.</p>
                <p>At 11:29, the Executive Session began, and Kimball invited staff comments. Keefer
                    observed that HO was falling behind schedule because it was losing people more
                    rapidly than it could fill positions. Two out of four vacancies had been filled,
                    and now two more people were about to retire under the <pb n="45" xml:id="pg_45"
                        facs="0045"/> buyout option. Kimball asked Slany to elaborate on the hiring
                    process. Slany pointed out that HO could not take applications, but was
                    dependent on candidates furnished by OPM, who might have government, but not
                    necessarily historical, experience. OPM’s regulations made it difficult to hire
                    specialists from outside the Civil Service. Limited appointments seemed to be
                    the only alternative, and State was reluctant to authorize them. Picker
                    suggested rewriting the job descriptions to include the sort of professional
                    background required, but LaFantasie pointed out that terms like “familiarity
                    with research” could be circumvented. Kimball proposed that Picker could assist
                    in the preparation of job descriptions. The Committee unanimously went on record
                    to support the hiring of qualified persons on term appointments because of the
                    backlog of FRUS work and the problem of filling existing vacancies
                    expeditiously.</p>
                <p>Schwar pointed out that the law provided on the one hand for speed of compiling
                    and on the other hand for comprehensiveness and thoroughness of research. The
                    two were increasingly in conflict, and the burden was increased by the need to
                    stop compiling in order to deal with declassification issues. Glad indicated
                    that the Committee was well aware of the situation, and Leffler asked where the
                    balance should be. Schwar replied that the Office needed more staff.</p>
                <p>Glad asked if there was any advantage in working in the new genre of smaller
                    volumes. Keefer indicated that this did not in itself represent a breakthrough.
                    A broader universe of sources and the compression required by smaller volumes
                    actually made the process more difficult. Schwar indicated that with each time
                    period the documentation was growing while the space available was shrinking,
                    with the 1960’s, because of technical feasibility, telegrams became longer.
                    Compilers were forced to limit annotation while indicating other sources.</p>
                <pb n="46" xml:id="pg_46" facs="0046"/>
                <p>Keefer said that HO’s only hope was to acquire a full compiling staff. Young Ph.
                    D. candidates would be preferred. Kimball asked about the status of the intern
                    program. Slany said that State managed it centrally. HO tried to get an intern
                    or two per semester, although the regional bureaus tended to get the pick of
                    them. HO expected to get four interns this summer. Smith observed that interns
                    were of limited usefulness for FRUS: by the time they learned the procedures, it
                    was time to leave.</p>
                <p>At 11:52 am, the Committee turned to preparation of its Annual Report, and the
                    note-takers were dismissed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
