<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1995-12-11_minutes">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, December
                    1995</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1995</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1995-12-11">December 11, 1995</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[i]" xml:id="pg_i" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-december-11-12--1995_1">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation
                        December 11-12, 1995</hi></head>
                <list>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Committee Members</hi></head>
                            <item>Warren F. Kimball, Chairman</item>
                            <item>B. Vincent Davis</item>
                            <item>George C. Herring, Jr.</item>
                            <item>Michael J. Hogan</item>
                            <item>Melvyn P. Leffler</item>
                            <item>Jane C. Picker</item>
                            <item>Emily Rosenberg</item>
                            <item>Michael R. Schaller</item>
                            <item>Anne H. Van Camp</item>
                            <item>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the
                                    Historian</hi></head>
                            <item>William Z. Slany, Director</item>
                            <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                            <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                            <item>Bruce Duncombe</item>
                            <item>Vicki Futscher</item>
                            <item>Karen Gatz</item>
                            <item>David Geyer</item>
                            <item>Deb Godfrey</item>
                            <item>David Goldman</item>
                            <item>David Herschler</item>
                            <item>Kerry Hite</item>
                            <item>Susan Holly</item>
                            <item>Nina Howland</item>
                            <item>David Humphrey</item>
                            <item>Donna Hung</item>
                            <item>Michael Joyce</item>
                            <item>Edward Keefer</item>
                            <item>Dan Lawler</item>
                            <item>Gabrielle Mallon</item>
                            <item>William Marsh</item>
                            <item>Jim Miller</item>
                            <item>Gerald Monroe</item>
                            <item>Robert Pace</item>
                            <item>David Patterson</item>
                            <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                            <item>Kent Sieg</item>
                            <item>Luki Smith</item>
                            <item>Shirley Taylor</item>
                            <item>Gloria Walker</item>
                            <item>Carolyn Yee</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Bureau of Administration</hi></head>
                            <item>Frank Machak</item>
                            <item>Anthony Dalsimer, Director, FPC/HDR</item>
                            <item>Nina Noring, FPC/HDR</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <pb n="[ii]" xml:id="pg_ii" facs="0002"/>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Office of the Legal Adviser</hi></head>
                            <item>Peter Pfund, Assistant Legal Aviser for Private International Law
                                John Kropf, L/LM</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Library of Congress</hi></head>
                            <item>David Wigdor, Director, Modern Manuscript Division</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Central Intelligence Agency</hi></head>
                            <item>Brian Latell, Chief, Center for the Study of Intelligence</item>
                            <item>Kay Oliver, Chief, History Staff</item>
                            <item>Paul Cocks, CIA History Advisory Board</item>
                            <item>Donald Steury, History Staff</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Information Security Oversight Office</hi></head>
                            <item>Ethel Theis, Assistant Director</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">National Archives and Records
                                Administration</hi></head>
                            <item>Michael Kurtz, Assistant Archivist, Office of the National
                                Archives Nancy K. Smith, Office of Presidential Libraries</item>
                        </list></item>
                    <item><list>
                            <head><hi rend="bold">Private</hi></head>
                            <item>Jane Loeffler</item>
                            <item>Martha Mautner</item>
                            <item>Page Putnam Miller</item>
                        </list></item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[iii]" xml:id="pg_iii" facs="0003"/>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="contents">
                <head>Table of Contents</head>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Closed Session, December 11</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Seminar on the Inclusion of Intelligence Documents in the <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Series</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Open Session, December 12</hi></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_7">7</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report of the Executive Secretary</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Series Goals and Staff Vacancies</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Declassification</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Introduction of New Staff</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>New Access to Intelligence Documents</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>The Continuing Case of Guatemala</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Management of the Historical Advisory Committee</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_9">9</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament</hi></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_9">9</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Follow-up From July 1995 Meeting</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">10</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Preparation for the Nixon and Ford Volumes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">10</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Access to the Nixon Project</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">10</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Access to the Kissinger Papers</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Status of Foreign Building Operations Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_13">13</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Information Management Issues</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_13">13</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Implementation of Executive Order 12958 on National Security
                            Information</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_14">14</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Closed Session, December 12</hi></cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_17">17</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>More on Implementation of Executive Order 12958</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_17">17</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Status of the Legal Adviser’s Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_21">21</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Classified Material in Non-Governmental Respositories</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_23">23</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Declassification of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                            Series</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_24">24</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="[1]" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0004"/>
            <div xml:id="closed-session-december-11">
                <head>Closed Session, December 11</head>
                <div xml:id="seminar-on-the-inclusion-of-intelligence">
                    <head>Seminar on the Inclusion of Intelligence Documents in the Foreign
                        Relations Series</head>
                    <p>Chairman Warren Kimball opened the session at 1:45 p.m. by stating that the
                        purpose was to get a handle on the selection of intelligence documents that
                        should be included in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.
                        He noted that the discussion would proceed on the assumption that HO would
                        continue to have access to intelligence documentation and that the access
                        would expand. Kimball also pointed out that according to all indicators the
                        body of material for HO is sizable, and he wanted to discuss where HO’s
                        emphasis should be so that the amount of material can be used most
                        effectively. Kimball then introduced each of the presenters.</p>
                    <p>William Slany began the discussion by expressing his desire to emphasize
                        Kimball’s comments. He noted that HO’s access to CIA records has increased
                        and the office looks forward to even greater access to intelligence records.
                        He pointed out that HO now has access not only to CIA, but also to NSA
                        documentation. This year HO acquired approximately 1,000 documents of which
                        up to of 300 were selected for inclusion in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                    <p>Slany explained that HO now has more documentation containing different types
                        of information and is in the process of trying to develop guidelines for its
                        use as well as for its declassification. He noted a central issue facing the
                        Committee was whether or not to recommend that the Department publish
                        volumes with or without CIA documents. Slany said that he had been
                        discussing documents relating to the Soviet Union with Kay Oliver and that a
                        good place to start the discussion was by looking at the case of policy
                        toward the Soviet Union in the Kennedy administration. He then turned the
                        floor over to David Humphrey and Michael Joyce.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey began by noting that his comments would not be confined to the
                        Soviet Union, but would focus on the more general problem of what kind of
                        intelligence information should be included in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes with specific reference to the issues of covert
                        political action and covert paramilitary operations. He noted that the Draft
                        Principles of State-CIA Cooperation refer to “major covert actions
                        undertaken as a matter of U.S. foreign policy,” and asked what that
                        definition actually means.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey outlined six criteria that could be used to evaluate whether
                        documentation on covert actions could or should be included in <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1) did the covert action bear significantly on U.S.
                            policy;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2) was it considered and approved by the 303 Committee;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3) did top policymakers, such as the President and the Secretary of
                                State, take a direct interest in it;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>4) did it involve a substantial sum of money in relation to the
                                country involved;</p></item>
                        <pb n="2" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0005"/>
                        <item>
                            <p>5) if on a small scale, was it tied to a significant policy
                                initiative (such as support for a group in the process of taking
                                power) or did it eventually blossom into a major covert action and
                                have major consequences; and</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>6) does publishing the documentation clarify or correct an important
                                issue in the historical record, such as in the case of U.S.
                                non-intervention in Greece in the 1960s?</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Humphrey continued by raising a closely related issue of how much information
                        needs to be included about a covert action or paramilitary operation and by
                        asking whether the action or operation could be documented without revealing
                        sources and methods. He asked whether paramilitary operations could be
                        properly documented without also conveying their scope and consequences,
                        using as an illustration the Bay of Pigs operation.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey then turned to issues relating to the collection and consumption of
                        intelligence. He noted that there were instances that warranted
                        documentation of clandestine intelligence collection, namely if it affected
                        U.S. relations with another country. He pointed out several examples, such
                        as electronic eavesdropping in the cases of the <hi rend="italic">Maddox,
                            Liberty</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Pueblo,</hi> and the effects of
                        intelligence collection on U.S.Pakistani relations in the 1960s. He also
                        raised some related questions, notably, how much of the intelligence
                        operation needed to be revealed in documenting the episode and whether an
                        intelligence relationship with another country merits documentation because
                        it is an integral part of that relationship or only when an operation
                        reaches high-level diplomatic negotiations.</p>
                    <p>Focusing on intelligence itself, Humphrey asked what makes intelligence worth
                        printing. While pointing out that most intelligence documents printed in <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes are finished intelligence,
                        raw intelligence could also appear in a volume, for in some instances raw
                        intelligence was provided to the President, such as President Johnson
                        receiving Gulf of Tonkin intercepts. Such raw intelligence is in the files
                        at Presidential libraries and merits inclusion in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                    <p>In assessing the role of intelligence in U.S. relations with another country,
                        Humphrey raised two questions: how dependent were policymakers on
                        intelligence as opposed to other sources of information, such as Embassy
                        reports, and to what extent did specific policymakers use intelligence.
                        Humphrey then suggested that several factors be considered when judging the
                        significance of specific intelligence information:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1) what did policymakers know about the contents of the
                                intelligence;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2) what did they do with it;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3) did it influence their decisions; and</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>4) did it analyze circumstances that policymakers were seriously
                                concerned about?</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Humphrey concluded by suggesting that general questions such as those he
                        presented should be considered in evaluating intelligence and covert actions
                        and when considering publishing documents on those issues.</p>
                    <pb n="3" xml:id="pg_3" facs="0006"/>
                    <p>Mike Joyce prefaced his presentation by stating that he would provide a
                        different view of the issue by focusing specifically on the role of
                        intelligence and the USSR. He stated that intelligence was the foundation
                        upon which U.S. policy toward the USSR was built. He described his own
                        intelligence-gathering work going back to 1959 involving collecting and
                        transmitting to Washington bits of intelligence information for analysis. He
                        performed that work in Moscow, Havana, and elsewhere.</p>
                    <p>Joyce reminded the audience that it was important to keep in mind how little
                        the United States knew about the intentions and capabilities of governments
                        in closed societies, like the USSR and Cuba. He stated that only on the
                        basis of covert as well as overt information could the United States build a
                        picture of the reality in such countries. He emphasized that intelligence
                        was an essential part of the decisionmaking process and that the development
                        of U.S. policy toward the USSR could not accurately be reconstructed by
                        looking solely at diplomatic documents. Instead, he argued, one must examine
                        the bits of intelligence gathered on a daily basis by the CIA, NSA, covert
                        photography (after 1961), and the like.</p>
                    <p>Joyce went on to explain that each morning higher-level officials wanted to
                        see the bits of intelligence gathered, for the information gave policymakers
                        a daily update on where things stood. He noted that the information came
                        from a mixture of overt information and information acquired by covert
                        means. Most of the intelligence that had an impact on decisionmaking was an
                        analysis of both overt and covert information.</p>
                    <p>Joyce explained that 1961 was a watershed year in intelligence gathering
                        because of the advent of overhead photography. As a result, the NIEs
                        suddenly became more important because of the inclusion of satellite
                        information. He also noted that the impact of other kinds of intelligence
                        gathering was also significant in formulating policy.</p>
                    <p>Joyce concluded by stating that accounts of U.S. policy in the 1960s need to
                        include more intelligence and related types of information. In his view,
                        intelligence gathering was at times the most important aspect of U.S.
                        relations with another country, such as Germany, and is part of policymaking
                        decisions.</p>
                    <p>Martha Mautner began her presentation by explaining her background in the
                        analytical side of intelligence in INR. She estimated that the product of
                        that analysis was an amalgam of information, about 80 percent of which came
                        from open sources and about 2–5 percent from clandestine information. She
                        noted that the finished analysis could be written in unclassified form for
                        public consumption and that individual pieces of covert intelligence were
                        not that important in and of themselves but as a check to confirm
                        information gathered by other means.</p>
                    <p>In particular cases, such as the Berlin crisis and Ostpolitik, Mautner
                        explained, the United States would not have been able to reach an
                        understanding of the situation without acquiring highly classified
                        information. She noted that Ostpolitik cannot be understood without taking
                        that information into account. She cautioned that there is always some
                        question about covert information, and one must ask why it was provided and
                        if the provider had a particular agenda that must be considered. She noted
                        that important covert information on the USSR and East Germany provided the
                        key to a U.S. understanding of <pb n="4" xml:id="pg_4" facs="0007"/> the
                        Ostpolitik operation and that the information was invaluable to formulating
                        the U.S. position toward and response to Ostpolitik. She emphasized that in
                        that and other instances intelligence is part of the record and the record
                        would not be complete without it. She also cautioned that the value of
                        intelligence to decisionmakers depends on the personalities
                        involved&#x02014;sometimes a provider had an agenda&#x02014;and it also
                        depends on the analyst involved.</p>
                    <p>Mautner noted that in the case of the Berlin crisis the United States had
                        little information from the East German side because it was a closed society
                        and had no contacts with top East German officials or other providers of
                        information in that society. She indicated the importance of intelligence,
                        which came from irregular channels, to the United States in that
                        instance.</p>
                    <p>Mautner agreed with Joyce, stressing that the information given to U.S.
                        policymakers is an amalgam of overt and covert information and that the
                        totality of information is used in the decisionmaking process. She believed
                        the release of military intelligence was very important, but noted that
                        political information needs to be evaluated as to when, why, and by whom it
                        was given. She concluded by noting that the material must be examined if a
                        history of the period is to be written, and indicated that significant
                        amounts of intelligence information may be available.</p>
                    <p>Joyce added that one needs to look at intelligence capabilities at a specific
                        point in time, for technological advances produced different types of
                        intelligence.</p>
                    <p>Brian Latell then took the floor and argued for a threshold to determine what
                        kind of intelligence is important for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> series. He welcomed Humphrey’s six criteria, noting that
                        it was not easy to reach a bottom line or a threshold on the issue, but
                        recommended adding a seventh point to Humphrey’s list: was there a third or
                        fourth country involved in the intelligence operation or covert action and,
                        if so, how much information should be included about that country in the
                        volumes?</p>
                    <p>Latell then asked what constitutes intelligence sources and analysis. He
                        suggested that to talk only about individual sources may be taking the
                        discussion and the threshold too far, noting that the Agency was very
                        concerned about protecting the individual source. He also asked about
                        requests for raw source information and indicated that it may be useful to
                        discuss that area.</p>
                    <p>As clarification and background, Latell reported that the Center for the
                        Study of Intelligence has been engaged in an aggressive effort to declassify
                        significant amounts of intelligence information. He noted that over 400 NIEs
                        on the Soviet Union had been declassified and hoped that more of the recent
                        estimates would soon be declassified as well as substantial amounts of other
                        types of intelligence information.</p>
                    <p>Latell applauded the purpose of this session. He believed one of the purposes
                        was to allow all parties to reach a consensus about the threshold and to
                        give the Center more information about the use of CIA materials in the
                        series. He explained that the position of the Center was to be as open as
                        possible, but he reminded all present that the Center had to work with the
                        Operations Directorate, which is committed to protecting sources and <pb
                            n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0008"/> documents to the greatest extent
                        possible. He ended by noting that the more the issue of threshold is
                        discussed and clarified, the better the situation will become.</p>
                    <p>Kay Oliver believed that different opinions expressed about the impact of
                        intelligence on policymaking reflected confusion concerning the definitional
                        issue of what constitutes “intelligence.” She noted that CIA officers
                        generally used the term “intelligence” to refer to all-source analysis
                        (i.e., analysis informed by both overt and covert sources). The relative
                        importance of different types of source materials varied from issue to
                        issue. During the period under consideration for this volume (1961–1963),
                        for example, some of the best analysis of Soviet politics done at
                        CIA&#x02014;the work of FBIS media analysts such as Carl Linden&#x02014;was
                        based on open source materials. At the same time, for some types of
                        analysis&#x02014;particularly in the military area&#x02014;information
                        clandestinely acquired through technical means was of paramount
                        significance.</p>
                    <p>Oliver noted that in assessing the impact of intelligence on policy, the
                        importance of different categories of intelligence publications varied from
                        one period to the next. During the period in question for this volume, for
                        example, DDI Ray Cline was emphasizing the use of typescripts tailored for
                        particular high-level consumers rather than serial publications such as the
                        Current Intelligence Weekly Review (CIWR). Nevertheless, inclusion of CIWR
                        articles would provide <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> readers with
                        a flavor of the type of analysis being sent to policymakers.</p>
                    <p>Joyce reiterated the need to include daily intelligence in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. He said that policymakers
                        paid more attention to daily intelligence items than to the handful of NIEs
                        that were included in the Soviet Union volume for 1961-1963.</p>
                    <p>Humphrey suggested that daily intelligence was not appropriate for the
                        volume. What was significant was how the policymakers used intelligence, not
                        simply the fact that the intelligence was produced. Joyce countered that
                        daily intelligence was vital to the creation of a mindset of
                        policymakers.</p>
                    <p>Latell cautioned against giving too much importance to some daily
                        intelligence or weekly intelligence products, noting from his experience as
                        an analyst that some such serial publications were of low level and
                        represented only the view of a few analysts. Not all daily publications were
                        the products of wide coordination within the intelligence community.</p>
                    <p>Joyce reiterated his view that daily intelligence was the key.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then asked about the location of daily intelligence
                        documentation&#x02014;a question earlier asked by Mel Leffler. Where were
                        the daily intelligence summaries for the President or other principal
                        figures? Edward Keefer suggested that each foreign policy agency created its
                        own daily intelligence file; hundreds of thousands of documents were
                        involved. Luke Smith noted that space limitations in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes often meant that only summary portions
                        of NIEs could be printed. He wondered if the CIA should not consider
                        publishing its own series on finished intelligence, which could be used to
                        supplement the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Latell
                        thought that was an interesting idea.</p>
                    <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0009"/>
                    <p>Paul Cocks thought that the mix of finished intelligence in the Soviet Union
                        volume for 1961-1963 which he saw, weekly summaries and NIEs, was good,
                        especially when added to the memoranda from McCone.</p>
                    <p>Emily Rosenberg stated that it seemed as if the discussion had reached an
                        interesting point&#x02014;CIA arguing for more intelligence coverage and HO
                        holding back. Humphrey stated that HO was not holding back on covering
                        covert operations, far from it, but the historians felt that finished
                        intelligence was massive&#x02014;even that which made it into the White
                        House files&#x02014;and should not overwhelm the series.</p>
                    <p>Joyce stated that he thought that the 1961-1963 Soviet Union volume needed
                        more intelligence assessments on the Soviet economy.</p>
                    <p>Keefer suggested that the access to both finished and covert operations
                        documentation was increasing, and although each new Presidential
                        administration created more important records, the size of the series was
                        either static or shrinking. Kimball suggested that the growth in
                        documentation necessitates a need for greater and more careful assessment of
                        intelligence materials to be included.</p>
                    <p>Latell offered the idea that perhaps the solution to Joyce’s concern was to
                        add a sample of different kinds of intelligence. Rosenberg asked if one of
                        the problems with using documents on covert operations was the issue of
                        foreign liaison with allies. Keefer suggested that this was the major
                        problem.</p>
                    <p>The meeting adjourned for a break and resumed at 3:20 p.m.</p>
                    <p>Continuing the discussion of intelligence, Kimball proposed that the group
                        focus on such questions as what to look for and what’s there. Van Camp asked
                        for information on the CIA’s archives. Oliver responded that CIA records
                        were organized on the basis of functional components. The types of
                        documentation created corresponded to the type of work the component did,
                        analytical work being far different from operational activities.</p>
                    <p>After Joyce commented on the need to remember that there were a variety of
                        members in the “intelligence community,” he and Humphrey exchanged views on
                        what criteria should be employed in the selection of intelligence records
                        for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. Joyce viewed
                        intelligence as the humus out of which policymaking decisions were made.
                        Thus, the volumes should be rich in use of these materials. Humphrey tended
                        to view intelligence records as important in relation to the level at which
                        they were employed. White House and high-level State Department files were a
                        guide to what was important. Keefer added that the records were too
                        voluminous for any but the most limited inclusion. Schwar suggested a
                        statement in the preface to indicate the limits on using these records.</p>
                    <p>The CIA representatives then discussed the value of the various intelligence
                        products they were involved with. The question of the importance of NIEs and
                        NIDs within the policymaking process was discussed. HO historians tended to
                        argue that each volume needed to be treated on a case-by-case basis but that
                        intelligence definitely had a role in the volumes.</p>
                    <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7" facs="0010"/>
                    <p>Rosenberg indicated that she found the discussion disturbing, since it
                        suggested that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes did not
                        allow adequate space to document properly the decisionmaking process and the
                        role of intelligence in it. Michael Hogan asked whether the compilers felt
                        that they were able to incorporate intelligence adequately. Humphrey
                        responded that he felt comfortable with the amount of intelligence
                        incorporated in the Vietnam volumes for 1965 and 1966, but George Herring
                        noted that Vietnam was unusual in the number of volumes devoted to it.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked whether we can get our arms around the volume of intelligence
                        material. How can the Committee help HO historians deal with the amount of
                        material? Commenting on the problem of limited space that Smith had
                        emphasized, Oliver stated that NIEs were worthwhile and that maybe Joyce’s
                        idea of sampling intelligence material should be explored. Don Steury noted
                        problems with recordkeeping in the Directorate of Intelligence&#x02014;it
                        was not easy to find what you wanted.</p>
                    <p>Bruce Duncombe and Jane Picker raised the issue of the Aldrich Ames case and
                        its implications for using intelligence. What would historians like to see?
                        Kimball noted that we are writing the history of foreign policy and not
                        intelligence.</p>
                    <p>Turning to the question of covert action, Rosenberg asked about the
                        significance of the seventh criterion&#x02014;concerning liaison with third
                        countries&#x02014;that Latell had added to Humphrey’s criteria. Would it be
                        an occasional stumbling point or a regular one? Oliver thought it would have
                        a rather broad impact. Keefer saw it as the principal problem. Humphrey
                        noted that his six criteria were criteria for including covert actions in
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, whereas Latell’s was a
                        criterion for excluding them. Jerry Monroe commented that relations with a
                        country that was an object of covert action was also commonly a complicating
                        factor.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked how can we be confident that we have at least been shown all
                        the relevant material on covert actions. Oliver commented that there was
                        reason for more confidence than in the past. Smith noted that we now have
                        access to records of the 303 Committee.</p>
                    <p>The Committee adjourned at 4:30 p.m.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="open-session-december-12">
                <head>Open Session, December 12</head>
                <p>Prior to the beginning of the meeting, members of the Advisory Committee were
                    photographed by the State Department photographer for inclusion in a future
                    issue of <hi rend="italic">State</hi> magazine.</p>
                <p>Chairman Kimball convened the open session at 9:17 a.m. and issued the customary
                    warning about discussion of classified material. He then asked for approval of
                    the minutes of the July 1995 meeting. One correction was called for by Kimball
                    and approved. The minutes as amended will stand.</p>
                <p>Kimball then turned to the approval of agenda. Slany said that there were no
                    changes other than that a different attorney would be attending on behalf of the
                    Legal Adviser’s Office. Kimball then asked Slany as Executive Secretary to give
                    a report.</p>
                <pb n="8" xml:id="pg_8" facs="0011"/>
                <div xml:id="report-of-the-executive-secretary">
                    <head>Report of the Executive Secretary</head>
                    <p>Slany advised the Committee members that since they already had a general
                        written report on the status of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        series in their packets, he would bring them up to date on other
                        matters.</p>
                    <div xml:id="series-goals-and-staff-vacancies">
                        <head>Series Goals and Staff Vacancies</head>
                        <p>Slany said that the staff has achieved much in implementing the 1991
                            statute but continues to have great difficulty in fitting more
                            documentation into smaller volumes and had not been successful in
                            meeting the ambitious goals for completion. He said that the project was
                            slipping behind in some areas and not all Kennedy volumes will have been
                            published by 1996. The problem was exacerbated by two professional staff
                            vacancies: the Deputy Historian/General Editor and a historian in the
                            European Division. He explained that even with a full staff, it was hard
                            to make the series broader and more inclusive and still keep up the
                            pace. Slany welcomed the advice of the Committee on what to do about the
                            problem.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="declassification">
                        <head>Declassification</head>
                        <p>Slany noted that the matter would be discussed in the closed session.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="introduction-of-new-staff">
                        <head>Introduction of New Staff</head>
                        <p>Slany introduced Kent Sieg who has joined the Asia and Americas Division.
                            He noted that Sieg is compiling materials for the Vietnam volumes, an
                            area in which he is very experienced.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="new-access-to-intelligence-documents">
                        <head>New Access to Intelligence Documents</head>
                        <p>The staff takes great pride in the wider inclusion of intelligence
                            materials, including those of the NSC, CIA, and other special group
                            files. Slany said that the staff would soon gain access to documents
                            from the President’s Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board. David
                            Patterson explained that the materials were an additional record and
                            would supplement the documentation in the Presidential libraries.</p>
                        <p>As an example of the benefits derived from these newly available
                            archives, Slany cited the Kennedy/Khrushchev correspondence collection
                            in which the staff turned to the records of the Russian Foreign Ministry
                            to fill in the gaps. While the Russians could not provide everything,
                            the volumes had moved forward toward publication.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="the-continuing-case-of-guatemala">
                        <head>The Continuing Case of Guatemala</head>
                        <p>Slany said that the staff had been working with the CIA historians on the
                            Guatemala problem. The CIA had intended to hold a conference and release
                            a facsimile publication dealing with the 1954 events but now will not be
                            able to do so within the next year. It seems desirable, Slany said, for
                            HO to pursue this publication as part of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi> series since senior Foreign Service advisers Bill
                            Marsh and Jerry Monroe have already collected approximately 900
                            documents. Selections from this collection would be compiled in a larger
                            Eisenhower volume that also will include materials on Iran, Indonesia,
                            and any other covert actions that may be relevant. “While we would like
                            to cooperate with the CIA,” Slany said, “if they can’t do it, it seems
                            unreasonable to delay.”</p>
                        <p>Slany went on to explain that with the staff already fully committed, HO
                            would propose to use senior Foreign Service advisers to assist in the
                            compilation of compile the volume. Kimball said that perhaps the
                            Committee should seek reaction to the proposal to <pb n="9"
                                xml:id="pg_9" facs="0012"/> move this volume from the back burner to
                            a priority. Hogan asked why the CIA could not hold a conference. Slany
                            replied that the CIA historians had not yet gained the full endorsement
                            of their own agency but that the leadership of the Department of State
                            was behind it.</p>
                        <p>Hogan then asked if there was a better prospect of moving ahead without
                            the CIA historians. Slany agreed. Kimball added that the CIA History
                            Staff was not opposed to State’s initiative on this matter, and Slany
                            said that State will still try to get CIA’s cooperation.</p>
                        <p>Kimball said that the Committee should go on record in support of the
                            entire project, which will include Iran, Indonesia, Guatemala, and “any
                            other significant bits of information.” The volume will be about 800 to
                            1,000 pages. Rosenberg asked if extra money hadn’t been found to do the
                            compiling a year ago, and referred to a presentation by Steve Kane
                            (PA/PC), who was the compiler of the 1952-1954 Guatemala volume. Slany
                            explained that Kane’s assignment involved no funding, but was a limited
                            detail.</p>
                        <p>Kimball then asked if it was appropriate for the Committee to ask for an
                            expansion of resources. Rosenberg felt that it was most appropriate for
                            Slany himself to decide who will do the compiling, and Picker commented
                            that the Committee would not want its actions to preclude Slany from
                            going forward. Kimball then called for a vote, which was unanimous in
                            favor of proceeding with the volume.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="management-of-the-historical-advisory-committee">
                        <head>Management of the Historical Advisory Committee</head>
                        <p>Because the work of the Committee has expanded, the amount of time and
                            money to support the work of the Committee has also expanded. Slany said
                            that HO has added a staff member, Gloria Walker, to provide needed staff
                            support. In addition, in order to track reimbursement for travel and
                            expenses, Rita Baker will supplement the existing effort to bring the
                            claims up-to-date.</p>
                        <p>Slany also said that the Internet may be a useful vehicle for
                            dissemination of information. Next year, HO will try to put out biweekly
                            reports on the Internet, which will be available to everyone. He
                            believes that there is enough going on in the “dark periods” between
                            meetings to distribute information more broadly and more regularly.</p>
                        <p>The Advisory Committee’s charter is open for revision every 2 years,
                            Slany said, and it will be circulated to those who do not currently have
                            a copy with a request for revision suggestions. Kimball said that
                            everyone should have a red-covered copy and advised those who did not to
                            get one from HO. Picker and Vince Davis needed copies.</p>
                        <p>Kimball also asked that revision suggestions be sent to him before the
                            next scheduled meeting in February. He stressed that the charter was an
                            important document within the State Department because it gave the
                            Committee authority.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="documents-on-disarmament">
                        <head>Documents on Disarmament</head>
                        <p>The last volume published in this series covered 1986, and ACDA is
                            responding to the recommendation of the Inspector General’s report to
                            abolish the position of ACDA historian, which has been occupied only on
                            a sporadic basis since the late 1980s. The IG report also recommended
                            that the documents collected since the last published volume be turned
                            over to HO. Slany said that steps will be taken in <pb n="10"
                                xml:id="pg_10" facs="0013"/> coordination with ACDA to ensure the
                            distribution of the important arms control agreements and documents of
                            the late 1980s and early 1990s, but no decision has been made on how
                            exactly to proceed given the lack of staff. He said that at a minimum
                            the documents would be made available in an electronic format and that a
                            decision would be made in the next 6 weeks or so.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="follow-up-from-july-1995-meeting">
                    <head>Follow-up From July 1995 Meeting</head>
                    <p>Kimball noted that at the last session Slany had expressed concern about
                        personnel issues and asked for an update. Slany said that a short-list of
                        candidates for the Deputy Historian/General Editor now existed and, once the
                        leadership of the PA Bureau had examined the list, a decision would be
                        forthcoming perhaps as early as December.</p>
                    <p>Slany explained that a candidate had been selected for the 4-year position in
                        Humphrey’s division and had just finished the DS clearance process. However,
                        he added, severe budgetary constraints meant that the Bureau must seek to
                        reconfirm this exemption from the hiring freeze. Slany explained that while
                        this would not be easy, he was “fairly sanguine” about the possibility of
                        success.</p>
                    <p>No additional questions or concerns were raised by the Committee.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="preparation-for-the-nixon-and-ford-volumes">
                    <head>Preparation for the Nixon and Ford Volumes</head>
                    <div xml:id="access-to-the-nixon-project">
                        <head>Access to the Nixon Project</head>
                        <p>Slany introduced Nancy Smith of the Office of Presidential Libraries of
                            the National Archives and David Wigdor, Chief of the Modern Manuscript
                            Division of the Library of Congress. As an introduction to their
                            comments, Slany said that HO had a research plan that was being advanced
                            and that five or six historians would begin work next year in the Nixon
                            collections.</p>
                        <p>Smith then reported that good progress had been made on gaining access to
                            the Nixon project materials. She had arranged two meetings between the
                            Department of State and the Nixon lawyers to share information on both
                            the needs of the historians as well as the type of access agreements the
                            lawyers will require. Smith assured the Committee that based on her
                            conversations with Stan Mortenson, the main Nixon lawyer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> historians would have access to
                            textual Presidential historical materials.</p>
                        <p>Smith said that HO researchers may begin work in the National Security
                            Files at any time and that action is currently with the Department of
                            State to draft an access agreement on taking copies back to State that
                            will maintain of the copies status as Nixon historical materials. She
                            explained that discussion on access for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi> historians to the approximately 3,700 hours of
                            audiotapes had been reserved for the future.</p>
                        <p>Kimball asked if “sheer access” was the issue over the tapes, to which
                            Smith responded in the affirmative. She believed that Mortenson wanted
                            to see how research in the paper collections proceeded before making
                            decisions about tapes&#x02014;there is no access at the moment. Smith
                            said her impression was that the Nixon lawyers believe that the <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series is important.</p>
                        <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11" facs="0014"/>
                        <p>Kimball then asked the HO staff if use of the tapes usually came after
                            searches of the paper collections were complete. Patterson said yes and
                            Humphrey agreed, explaining that it had been done that way because
                            “we’ve had to.” He added that this was not a particularly desirable way
                            of proceeding.</p>
                        <p>Smith explained that there were no transcripts of the tapes. She urged
                            the historians to get into the paper collections since the volume was so
                            much greater than those of Presidents Kennedy or Johnson.</p>
                        <p>Hogan asked if deterioration of the tapes should be a concern in the
                            access debate. Smith said that although the National Archives had made a
                            new archival preservation copy of the Nixon tapes beginning in 1992, the
                            original tapes eventually would deteriorate because magnetic tape was
                            not a permanent medium.</p>
                        <p>Michael Schaller asked if access was limited to the National Security
                            Files. Smith said that discussions had been geared to this file as being
                            the most obviously useful to the historians, but that access had been
                            granted to all the textual files. She explained that NARA must review
                            all materials proposed for inclusion in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi> according to the seven factors in the Presidential
                            Recordings and Materials Preservation Act (PRMPA). Access itself was not
                            a problem but the issues of providing copies to <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Relations</hi> historians and making copies available to
                            the public might be a problem; someone&#x02014;Henry Kissinger for
                            example&#x02014;may object to opening the items. Again, she emphasized
                            that Mortenson wants a memorandum of understanding. David Herschler
                            added that the right to take copies back to the office must be part of
                            the agreed arrangement.</p>
                        <p>Herring asked if the declassification procedure will be complicated. The
                            process will not be like dealing with the other Presidential
                            collections, Smith explained, because the Nixon materials are covered by
                            a unique statutory authority (the PRMPA) and additionally complicated by
                            the ongoing mediation process and court injunctions. She said that
                            everything must be declassified and reviewed in accordance with the
                            authorities governing the Nixon material and that NARA will then publish
                            a <hi rend="italic">Federal Register</hi> notice that will give people
                            30 days to object. Kimball quizzed her on what the grounds for objection
                            could be and whether or not such grounds were detailed in the law.</p>
                        <p>Smith said that the grounds could be invasion of individual privacy or
                            that the item is personal and returnable. If an objection were lodged,
                            the dispute would go to the Presidential Materials Review Board, chaired
                            by the Archivist, which would look at the issue and reach a decision. If
                            the decision was to open the document, the individual would have 30 days
                            to file an objection in court. Herring asked if this meant literally
                            anyone who was mentioned.</p>
                        <p>Smith explained that the Archives had a list of about 70 individuals who
                            were always alerted when any materials were opened, in addition to the
                                <hi rend="italic">Federal Register</hi> notice, and explained that
                            this was the source of her concern about declassification. Again, she
                            urged the historians to get into the documents as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>Given your experience, Kimball asked Smith, will the kinds of documents
                            we pull cause problems? Yes, Smith replied, although she declined to
                            mention specific names. NARA already has a collection of 200 hours of
                            Watergate-related tape that it will propose <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12"
                                facs="0015"/> for release when the litigation is resolved. She again
                            explained that it was her impression that Mortenson and the other Nixon
                            people support the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and
                            were willing to be cooperative. Anne Van Camp asked if Smith thought
                            that the documents “would be released in your lifetime?”</p>
                        <p>Smith responded that she would love to have all the tapes open since they
                            have been closed for 22 years. She added that it was hard to be
                            optimistic or pessimistic because whenever a breakthrough seemed
                            imminent, something always came up.</p>
                        <p>Schwar asked if the Nixon family had the right, in addition to the 70
                            named individuals, to review the documents. Absolutely, Smith responded.
                            Would the declassification review take place before the NARA review,
                            Humphrey asked, and would NARA oversee the review by other government
                            agencies with an interest in declassification? Smith explained that the
                            declassification review would take place first, and then when it was
                            clear what HO wanted, NARA would then see if the Nixon estate objected.
                            Humphrey restated his question for clarification: after HO has gotten a
                            volume reviewed and declassified then NARA will do its review? Smith
                            said that was correct, but mechanisms will be established to speed the
                            process along.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="access-to-the-kissinger-papers">
                        <head>Access to the Kissinger Papers</head>
                        <p>Kimball then turned to the Kissinger collection at the Library of
                            Congress. Wigdor said that the Committee’s request for a report came at
                            an opportune time since the Library had been organizing the Kissinger
                            papers for the past 2 years so that the collection will be an easy one
                            to use. The Library has written to Kissinger about the HO access
                            question but there had not yet been time for a response. Wigdor said
                            that over the years Kissinger’s papers have been used by various State
                            Department offices so that he was “guardedly optimistic” about access.
                            He believes that there will be no administrative problems except
                            regarding copying classified documents. The biggest problem will be
                            finding the staff to work with HO in handling such large requests.
                            Security is the biggest problem, and the documents will have to be
                            carried by a State Department courier.</p>
                        <p>Kimball asked if there were donor restrictions, and Wigdor said not of
                            the magnitude of the Nixon papers. Van Camp asked if Kissinger could
                            refuse access; Wigdor said yes. Kimball interjected that the question of
                            whether the papers were public or private was challenged in court and
                            that the public lost&#x02014;the papers are considered to be
                            private.</p>
                        <p>Humphrey asked if a description of the collection existed. HO has an old
                            description, but a new one is being drafted, Wigdor said. He explained
                            that the collection covered the same papers Kissinger used in drafting
                            his memoirs. The Library is hopeful that he will add more papers in the
                            future, but the collection at the moment covers only 1969-1976. Wigdor
                            explained that access was restricted to the documents for either 25
                            years from the date of the document or until after Kissinger’s death,
                            whichever was later. He assumed, at this point, that lifetime closure
                            was most likely.</p>
                        <p>Rosenberg then asked if the documents could now be selected and
                            declassified. Not in their present status, Wigdor said. Herring asked if
                            Kissinger could add other conditions in granting access. Wigdor said
                            yes.</p>
                        <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0016"/>
                        <p>Davis asked if other materials, such as the Kissinger-Rockefeller
                            correspondence, are in the collection. No, Wigdor explained; if he is
                            the donor, Kissinger still owns the correspondence, which means that he
                            has the rights over it, although not, perhaps, copyright.</p>
                        <p>Kimball asked what the law says regarding public access to private
                            collections of government officials that include classified materials.
                            Can these materials be declassified? Picker cited the example of an
                            author who was not allowed to have a copy of her own book pending
                            declassification. In the case of the Kissinger papers, Wigdor said that
                            declassification still requires the permission of all agencies with
                            equity. Dan Lawler said that for the last several years classified
                            information has been considered, by definition, the property of the
                            government.</p>
                        <p>Wigdor said that it worked the other way as well: If a document was
                            stamped classified in one collection but not in another, then it was
                            released, e.g. the Oppenheimer papers at Princeton. The journals of AEC
                            Chairman Glenn Seaborg were another example of an agency (Energy)
                            preventing the release of documents, Patterson interjected. The
                            Department of Energy held up publication of his private journals while
                            they excised classified material. Smith said that NARA held the Mondale
                            papers for the University of Minnesota because the University could not
                            house classified documents. But the Humphrey papers are at the Minnesota
                            Historical Society, Van Camp said. How is declassification handled in
                            such cases, Patterson asked. Kimball asked if the guidelines in the new
                            Executive Order were interpreted to mean that these non-governmental
                            holders of classified materials must do their own systematic review.
                            Smith said that FOIA cannot be done since they cannot be considered
                            federal records if held in a university library.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="status-of-foreign-building-operations-records">
                    <head>Status of Foreign Building Operations Records</head>
                    <p>Slany then introduced Jane Loeffler, who has recently completed her doctoral
                        dissertation on the history of buildings at overseas Embassies. She voiced
                        concern about the “housekeeping” practices of the Department’s Office of
                        Foreign Building Operations. Because the office no longer has an archivist,
                        she believes that an important collection of documents and photographs is
                        not being preserved or adequately controlled. Loeffler said that many
                        records could no longer be found and that staff members could sign out
                        materials with no adequate controls. Kimball said that she should consult
                        with the NARA representatives during the break. Smith said that Loeffler
                        should speak with her colleague, Michael Kurtz, who was in attendance, and
                        Kimball concurred.</p>
                    <p>The session adjourned at about 10:30 am.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="information-management-issues">
                    <head>Information Management Issues</head>
                    <p>Kimball called the meeting to order at 10:45. He said that they needed to
                        continue the previous discussion and that Nancy Smith and Michael Kurtz
                        would speak to these issues. He noted, however, that some questions
                        concerning information management had been raised during their Monday
                        meeting with Ken Rossman. Since Kurtz could not come back after lunch, he
                        suggested that they deal with these first.</p>
                    <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0017"/>
                    <p>Van Camp said that she wanted to bring up a very practical idea that had
                        arisen during their discussion with Rossman. In its declassification review,
                        the Department of State separated the files that may be opened from those
                        that will remain classified. Rossman had suggested that the Department might
                        put these in archival boxes and label them before shipping them to NARA.
                        Committee members thought this sounded like a good idea, and Kurtz agreed
                        that it was one that NARA would support.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp noted that a larger issue that had arisen during their discussion
                        was how to transfer the Department’s electronic records to NARA. Rossman had
                        said that by 1998, State would be transferring its files (beginning with
                        1973) in electronic form. The Department planned to send the data tapes to
                        NARA without the software used here. The Advisory Committee’s concern was
                        that the software was also part of the record and that NARA should have this
                        as well. She wanted NARA’s reaction to this concern. A third issue was what
                        was going to happen to such records in the future. Should the Department
                        keep control of these records with NARA providing access?</p>
                    <p>Kurtz responded that these were very complicated issues. NARA had been
                        exploring ways to handle electronic records. One possibility was the
                        non-custodial method used in Australia and Canada, under which government
                        agencies kept control of the records and the archives set standards and
                        arranged access. He noted that there were problems with the OASIS system,
                        which they had had a meeting to explore. They were planning to set up a
                        joint State-NARA group to work out methods of transferring electronic
                        records. This was going to require lots of interagency dialogue and would be
                        a long process. There was not going to be an abrupt change.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if the Advisory Committee could have a report on this at their
                        next meeting. Kurtz suggested that it be at the following meeting.</p>
                </div>
                <div
                    xml:id="implementation-of-executive-order-12958-on-national-security-information">
                    <head>Implementation of Executive Order 12958 on National Security
                        Information</head>
                    <p>Kimball proposed that the discussion return to the issue of implementation of
                        the Executive Order, which Smith and Kurtz could address. Ethel Theis,
                        Associate Director of ISOO, would either answer questions or make a
                        statement. Theis said she would do whatever the Committee wanted.</p>
                    <p>John Kropf from L said that he was there to answer one question, whether
                        “should” was mandatory or discretionary, and that the short answer was that
                        it was discretionary.</p>
                    <p>Kurtz reported that NARA had been working on implementation of the Executive
                        Order since it was signed in April. In June, there had been an interagency
                        meeting to assess classified files, of which there are an estimated 460
                        million pages. He noted that there were three categories of classified
                        files:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>1) files that were so replete with sensitive material that they were
                                exempt;</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>2) files that had to be looked at; and</p></item>
                        <item>
                            <p>3) files that were not so sensitive, requiring little or no
                                review.</p></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>NARA was now doing for the agencies a more detailed review of classified
                        files, finding aids, equities, etc. NARA had also briefed various agencies
                        on implementation of <pb n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0018"/> the Executive
                        Order, including DOD, but most were leaning toward page-by-page review. Some
                        agencies had already submitted their plans for implementation. Kurtz noted
                        that NARA was very concerned about the need for on-site review.</p>
                    <p>Smith said that the Office of Presidential Libraries had sent a plan to the
                        National Security Adviser for declassification of the 7 million pages of
                        classified material at the Presidential libraries, including many high-level
                        policy papers. She gave some examples of the number of pages of classified
                        documents: The Hoover Library has 22,750 pages, and the Roosevelt Library
                        has 2,000-3,000 pages. The big collections were at the Kennedy, Johnson,
                        Nixon, and Ford Libraries.</p>
                    <p>Smith stated that NARA would like to give high priority to material on
                        Vietnam and Southeast Asia (at the Kennedy, Johnson, and Ford
                        Libraries)&#x02014;around 250,000 pages&#x02014;because of high interest by
                        researchers in this material. Much of this sort of material has been
                        declassified in other places, and most of it could be declassified. NARA is
                        proposing reviewing files by subject but is willing to consider any approach
                        that would deal with the Presidential papers in a systematic way. NARA wants
                        to propose systematic declassification at the Truman and Eisenhower
                        Libraries but is waiting until next year.</p>
                    <p>Smith noted that NARA is concerned that some agencies want to address
                        low-level material first and delay dealing with the high-level material.
                        NARA wants Presidential papers included in the first year of
                        declassification because of researcher interest. Some proportion of
                        high-level material should be released in the first year.</p>
                    <p>Smith stated that some agencies are proposing the use of optical disc
                        scanning and expressed concern that much delay might be involved in working
                        out the technical aspects and coordinating different approaches by the
                        different agencies. NARA planned to discuss this with the agencies. She
                        noted that the Executive Order requires declassification of a proportion of
                        the classified material each year.</p>
                    <p>Kurtz emphasized the need to discuss the problems with the technological
                        approach. NARA needed to get the agencies together. NARA was open to
                        suggestions. He noted that under the Executive Order, everything not
                        reviewed was to be declassified at the end of 5 years, which leaves NARA
                        with real problems. He asked Leffler if he agreed that the DOD meeting on
                        implementation of the Executive Order had seemed to be very conservative.
                        Leffler replied that he would not disagree with that assessment.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked Theis if ISOO had any comments. Theis noted that they were
                        dealing with a culture in which many agencies think that everything they
                        create has to be classified. The Executive Order would help to change this
                        culture. Agencies were beginning to come around, but they had to keep
                        working at changing their outlook.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked Theis about oversight. She replied that the Executive Order
                        created an appeals panel, the Information Security Policy Advisory Council,
                        with representatives from the major classifying agencies, which would have
                        to review material declared exempt from declassification and report to the
                        President. Maybe this would help Smith address some of her problems and help
                        in reaching a compromise. She noted that the Council had not yet been set
                        up, and that its members had to be appointed by the President. Kimball <pb
                            n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0019"/> said that a copy of anything the
                        Advisory Committee decided would be sent to Steve Garfinkel.</p>
                    <p>Kimball declared the session open for discussion. Van Camp asked whether an
                        interagency group could get together. Kurtz stated that he and Smith had
                        been meeting with an interagency declassification subcommittee under ISOO,
                        chaired by Steve Garfinkel. Smith noted that she was not saying that the
                        agencies were not cooperating, but rather that each agency was dealing with
                        its own problems. Kimball asked if it would be useful for the Advisory
                        Committee to encourage this sort of interagency dialogue. Smith replied that
                        it would, and that if the Advisory Committee wanted high-level
                        declassification in the first year, it should say so.</p>
                    <p>Tony Dalsimer stated that HDR was working on Top Secret files through 1976;
                        it had started with the most difficult files, rather than the less difficult
                        files. Kurtz asked whether the Department had NSC and DOD declassification
                        authority. Dalsimer replied that it had DOD authority, but no NSC
                        authority.</p>
                    <p>Kimball said that the Advisory Committee would express its interest in
                        declassification of high-level material and point out that the Department of
                        State was already doing this. Leffler suggested that the letter be sent also
                        to DOD, where there seemed to be no interest in reviewing high-level files.
                        Theis suggested that the Committee might also want to send a letter to
                        National Security Adviser Anthony Lake asking that the Advisory Council be
                        established as soon as possible because it was supposed to specify
                        categories for systematic review. Kimball said that this was a good idea.
                        Page Miller agreed that the person to write to was Anthony Lake. The
                        Committee agreed, and Kimball said that this would be coordinated with Page
                        Miller.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg suggested that after the establishment of the ISOO Advisory
                        Council, the Committee should send them a letter outlining some of its
                        experiences that might be relevant to their structure and procedures.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if there were any other issues NARA wanted to raise, to which
                        Kurtz replied no. Rosenberg asked Kurtz if he was concerned with how many
                        files would be exempt from declassification. Kimball asked how many such
                        files there were. Kurtz said that NARA did not have that information.
                        Agencies were working on it and DOD had an extension. Theis said that some
                        agencies had submitted declassification plans as required under the
                        Executive Order. Steve Garfinkel thought that some of the exemptions
                        agencies had requested were too broad, and ISOO was negotiating with those
                        agencies.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked what the Department of State was doing. Frank Machak said that
                        the Department would request exemption of three categories of
                        files&#x02014;central files, lot (office) files, and post files&#x02014;in
                        order to do a page-by-page review. Leffler asked whether the Department
                        planned to exempt everything and then review it. Machak pointed out that the
                        Department’s declassification record was 97 percent. Kimball said the
                        Committee was asking about process, not criticizing the Department’s
                        record.</p>
                    <p>Leffler asked again whether everything would be exempt. Machak replied no.
                        Kimball asked if this meant automatic declassification for some files.
                        Machak said no; he was talking about risk assessment. Kimball commented that
                        if the Department of State, <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0020"/> which
                        had the best declassification record, did not have any files that would be
                        automatically declassified, it did not look good for implementation of the
                        Executive Order. Machak stated that when reviewers were reviewing the files,
                        some files required intensive review and some required very little, but it
                        was not possible to identify those files in advance.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked what would happen after 5 years. Theis said that 180 days
                        before the end of the 5-year period, an agency would have to make a request
                        for an extension and state why certain files should still be exempt. Kimball
                        asked how often the Advisory Council would meet. Theis said twice a year.
                        Kimball asked if that constituted “heavy involvement” and she responded that
                        it was supposed to meet at least twice a year. Kimball asked if the Advisory
                        Council members would have clearances; Theis said yes. He asked which
                        organizations had been asked to submit nominations for the Council. Theis
                        read the names of some of the organizations, including the American
                        Historical Association, the Society of American Archivists, and the Society
                        for International Law. Kimball commented that the Council needed to get
                        underway fast.</p>
                    <p>Kimball noted that the Advisory Committee had not yet finished its discussion
                        of the Executive Order and its implementation; it needed to allow time after
                        lunch to discuss this further. The meeting adjourned at noon for lunch.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="closed-session-december-12">
                <head>Closed Session, December 12</head>
                <p>When the meeting reconvened at 1:30 p.m., Kimball asked Langbart about Naval
                    records stored at the Naval facility at Crane, Indiana, and mentioned
                    specifically the <hi rend="italic">Maddox, Pueblo</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi> incidents. Langbart said that these were the records of the
                    Naval Security Group Command and included inactive and active station files. He
                    added that it did include a special set of files for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liberty</hi> and investigation of the <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi>
                    incident particularly, and that the files were rather voluminous. Herring asked
                    where Crane is located, and Herschler responded that it was half an hour
                    southwest from Bloomington, Indiana.</p>
                <div xml:id="more-on-implementation-of-executive-order-12958">
                    <head>More on Implementation of Executive Order 12958</head>
                    <p>Kimball asked Kropf if he had any comments concerning the implementation of
                        E.O.12958.</p>
                    <p>Kropf raised one question previously addressed to him in writing: is it
                        mandatory or discretionary to refer documents containing foreign government
                        information (FGI) to a foreign government? Kropf said the ISOO guidelines
                        indicate that State “should” refer such documents to the foreign government,
                        but that, in his opinion, “should” implies an element of discretion. If so,
                        this would not represent a change in the status quo. He thought Theis would
                        agree with this interpretation; Theis nodded in agreement.</p>
                    <p>Picker asked for a specific reference to the Executive Order that would
                        support this interpretation, i.e., that “should” implies discretion. Kropf
                        cited references to FGI in the definition (ID) and automatic
                        declassification (3.4) sections of the E.O. After some discussion, Kimball
                        explained that the Committee wanted to know specifically where “should”
                        appeared in relation to the handling of FGI; Kropf replied that the language
                        came <pb n="18" xml:id="pg_18" facs="0021"/> from the ISOO Implementing
                        Directive. Kimball expressed concern that “should” could also be interpreted
                        to require mandatory referral of FGI.</p>
                    <p>Dalsimer said that there was no need to change present practice: the State
                        Department would continue to implement its policy minimizing the referral of
                        documents to foreign governments. He said the Department had recently
                        discussed the issue with the British, Australian, and Canadian Governments.
                        The Department is also drafting guidelines to delegate limited
                        declassification authority, similar to those adopted by DOD.</p>
                    <p>Kimball raised the issue of FGI for foreign governments that no longer exist.
                        Machak had already conceded that the Soviet Union no longer exists, Kimball
                        argued, so the Soviet Union should not be considered under the E.O.
                        provision to protect FGI. Kimball turned to Machak for clarification. Machak
                        said the new E.O. allowed nine exemptions to declassification; he did not
                        recall an exemption for FGI. In other words, under the new E.O., FGI is not
                        sufficient grounds to exempt a document from declassification, whether or
                        not the originating government exists.</p>
                    <p>Kimball feared a “disconnect” in the current lines of communication. The
                        Committee understood that documents had been routinely withheld on the basis
                        of FGI. Would a document originated in 1965 by the Soviet Government be
                        considered classified today? Machak said only limited circumstances would
                        force the Department to refer documents to a foreign government. The
                        Department did not interpret the new E.O. to require the referral of all
                        FGI.</p>
                    <p>Kimball said he was not talking about the Executive Order, he was talking
                        about practice. He reiterated the question: how does the Department handle
                        FGI when the foreign government doesn’t exist? Kimball cited South Vietnam
                        as an example, i.e, the Department does not refer documents originated by
                        the former Republic of Vietnam to the current Communist government in Hanoi.
                        Kimball thought the same practice would now apply to the Soviet Union. In
                        response to Kimball’s question, Machak said he did not see the Department
                        adopting the position that documents originated by the former Soviet and
                        South Vietnamese Governments be handled in the same way.</p>
                    <p>Picker remarked that the Department could not send documents if no one is
                        there to receive them. Kimball agreed. Picker also reminded the Committee
                        that the new E.O. does not include FGI as a declassification exemption
                        category. Kimball said he knew that.</p>
                    <p>Kimball mentioned a case at the Johnson Library in which a memorandum of a
                        conversation with Andrei Gromyko had been withheld on the basis of FGI.
                        Dalsimer suggested that Kimball address the question to Nancy Smith, since
                        the Department is handling FGI in accordance with the Committee’s
                        wishes.</p>
                    <p>Smith said that NARA had not received any guidance under the new E.O. that
                        would change the current practice for handling FGI: documents containing FGI
                        are sent to State. In other words, it’s still State’s call.</p>
                    <p>Kimball retorted that the Committee does not want it to be State’s call.</p>
                    <p>Theis said the question is: if a foreign government no longer exists, who has
                        authority? She said that the question of how to handle the FGI of the former
                        Soviet <pb n="19" xml:id="pg_19" facs="0022"/> government had come up in a
                        recent meeting of the declassification working group. The working group
                        determined that the new Federation should assume responsibility. Kimball
                        asked what Federation she meant. Theis repeated the point: the successor
                        government would take over authority. Picker explained that the Russian
                        Federation acknowledged itself as the “successor government” to some extent;
                        Picker asked, however, if this authority extended to FGI. Kimball replied
                        that the responsibility for determining FGI rests with the U.S. Government.
                        Kimball said that he wanted to avoid using FGI as a reason to withdraw
                        documents and that State had agreed to justify withdrawal on other
                        grounds.</p>
                    <p>Dalsimer admitted that Kimball was right: a State Department document would
                        not remain classified solely on the basis of FGI. Dalsimer also said that
                        NARA had State Department guidelines that cover FGI. Nancy Smith replied
                        that NARA has very little declassification authority, and is otherwise not
                        in a position to determine FGI.</p>
                    <p>Machak said the Department would make certain that the guidelines are clear,
                        but that each agency would be responsible for applying the guidelines in a
                        sensible way.</p>
                    <p>Kimball expressed some concern about a misunderstanding between NARA and the
                        Department regarding State’s willingness to delegate its declassification
                        authority to the Presidential libraries.</p>
                    <p>Patterson said his experience had been that HDR would not refer documents to
                        the Soviet Union, reasoning that it was unnecessary to send documents to our
                        enemies. Kimball said that this point was understood.</p>
                    <p>Machak insisted that South Vietnam is not a good example. The Department
                        would judge on a case-by-case basis rather than rely upon sweeping
                        generalizations. Turning to Machak, Kimball shot back: “we understand that
                        the words ‘page-by-page’ are printed on the backs of your eyes.”</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if Theis had any comments on the implementation of the E.O. and
                        ISOO’s role in the process.</p>
                    <p>Theis noted that she is always ready to talk about these issues, and
                        commented that it would be best for the Committee to ask her questions. She
                        reminded the Committee of Kimball’s inquiry regarding oversight; she
                        wondered if anyone required clarification.</p>
                    <p>Kimball said he had written a letter to Steve Garfinkel; Theis said she had
                        seen it. Kimball asked if she would comment on it, especially the questions
                        he posed in the letter. Specifically, who will ensure agency compliance with
                        the requirement for agency guidelines to NARA. Theis said that ISOO is
                        responsible for making sure that the guidelines are timely and up-to-date.
                        ISOO is now a part of NARA, and NARA participates in the declassification
                        working group. This group will ensure compliance with the guidelines and
                        conduct on-sight inspections at least once a year at each agency. Kimball
                        asked if that means that ISOO will monitor the agencies, and Theis replied
                        that ISOO will contact the agency head if there is a problem.</p>
                    <p>Kimball said that the Committee is concerned because there is nothing in the
                        Executive Order addressing other agency equities. Theis replied that the
                        originating <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20" facs="0023"/> agency has control and
                        responsibility for the declassification of a document. She said that she
                        would be happy to give the Committee a written response on this question.
                        Kimball remarked that they had sent the letter in July. Theis repeated that
                        she will write a response. Kimball said that he has come across the problem
                        with other agency equities in State records; one agency in particular is not
                        cooperating. He wanted to know if the Executive Order provides means to
                        require agencies to cooperate.</p>
                    <p>Theis said that the purpose of the declassification working group is to raise
                        problems, not policy. If agencies cannot solve problems the issue will go to
                        ISOO to mediate. Kimball said that it is fair to say that CIA equities in
                        State files is a problem the Committee has been fighting for 4 years without
                        progress. He further requested that Theis put the issue on the agenda of the
                        declassification working group.</p>
                    <p>Theis said that Garfinkel will be more than willing to meet with State and
                        CIA representatives to facilitate an agreement.</p>
                    <p>Hogan suggested that the Committee put the request in writing to ISOO.</p>
                    <p>Machak said that the equities issue is a complex problem for other agencies.
                        The only agency that he is comfortable with is NARA. Some people in the
                        Department believe that NARA has tools to help but is not using them, while
                        NARA says the Department’s guidelines are not specific enough. Some agencies
                        have not yet gotten over the shock of the new Executive Order. For agencies
                        that have no relationship with NARA, this has been a difficult period. Some
                        think that the Executive Order does not apply to them, so it has been
                        difficult. State and NARA are pretty much in agreement. He said that he is
                        not a proponent of applying technology to 30 year old documents. He warned
                        that the Committee should not write the Secretary of State. Your targets
                        have to be carefully selected,” he said “You may stop good things at State.”
                        He added that there is a lot of uncertainty about what the provisions of the
                        Executive Order mean.</p>
                    <p>Kimball remarked that the Department has the law, and for 5 years the
                        Committee has been told that the biggest problem is other-agency equities.
                        He said that he wants to get this on the ISOO agenda. The issue is about
                        process, getting other agencies to participate. He asked if there were any
                        more questions on implementation of the Executive Order. When there were
                        none, he asked Machak if it was safe to say that State was not yet ready to
                        present its implementation plan.</p>
                    <p>Machak confirmed this. He continued that there is nothing unique about it. He
                        said that they are still at the working level and that they hope to meet the
                        numbers requirement fairly easily (i.e., 15 percent each year for 5 years).
                        He added that FPC is still working to establish its Declassification Center
                        and that the Director General has recognized that FPC needs an
                        infrastructure, that they need to get away from temporary employees. He said
                        that there is a need for site visits. In his opinion there is merit in
                        approaching implementation of the Executive Order much like the Kennedy
                        assassination project, which brought agency resources together. He said that
                        there is no groundswell in other agencies for taking these approaches. Other
                        agencies are looking for precision that will never occur (interpretation of
                        the Executive Order) to manage their limited work force.</p>
                    <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0024"/>
                    <p>Kimball asked if Machak or someone can report to the Committee at the next
                        meeting on the status of implementation or if the Department needs
                        additional Committee support. He said that Machak’s report sounded like
                        “testimony for the liberal approach.”</p>
                    <p>Machak replied that the Department does not have a liberal approach; his job
                        is to protect national security and individuals. He continued that State
                        does not want to lead the pack. He said that if he had $150,000 he would put
                        it on systematic review rather than on FOIA and get “more bang for the
                        buck.”</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg commented on the ISOO structure. She said that ISOO anticipates
                        meeting twice a year and having one site visit a year, and that in this
                        Committee’s experience there is a need for more meetings. That is not enough
                        time to catch an agency that is slipping. The Committee has found that
                        regular monitoring is crucial.</p>
                    <p>Theis replied that the Executive Order requires agency self-inspection
                        programs. ISOO has the option to look at what the agency has done with these
                        self-inspection programs to make sure that they are doing what they are
                        supposed to and that these mechanisms are formal. All of the mechanisms work
                        in tandem to find solutions to the problems.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if there were any other questions on the Executive Order and
                        said that he has notes on the Garfinkel letter and the Committee will talk
                        about them later. He said that Machak and Theis were free to go. He said
                        that the Committee will talk to L, then to Bill concerning problems.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="status-of-the-legal-adviser-records">
                    <head>Status of the Legal Adviser’s Records</head>
                    <p>Peter Pfund, Assistant Legal Adviser for Private International Law, attended
                        in place of Bob Dalton. He said that the second volume in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Digest of U.S. Practice in International Law</hi> that
                        covers through 1980 has been published and that the third volume will be
                        published soon. However, there is a question whether the Legal Adviser’s
                        Office can continue to produce the series. He said that the International
                        Law Institute, associated with Georgetown University Law, is considering
                        producing a digest of international law in lieu of the Department, but he
                        believes that it would be difficult for an outsider to compile. It would
                        also be difficult to get attorneys in L to devote time to the series. He
                        remarked that the purpose of the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> needs to be
                        clearly defined, including who is the target audience. Some parts of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Digest</hi> would, for example, not be of interest to
                        foreign governments if the first priority purpose of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Digest</hi> should be its normative effect on the actions and
                        justifications of the foreign policy of other countries.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked Pfund how much of a project it would be to identify who would
                        be the target audience and what should be included in the volumes. Pfund
                        replied that he does not know; L would have to ask the users. The answer
                        will likely be that the users want the <hi rend="italic">Digest.</hi> In any
                        event, L does not have the resources to continue the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Digest.</hi></p>
                    <p>Kimball asked Pfund to describe the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> for the
                        Committee.</p>
                    <p>Pfund replied that the contents of the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> have
                        been reduced to what is not readily available in other public sources. He
                        noted that 8 years (when Ronald Reagan was President) have been covered in
                        three volumes, and consequently the coverage is less <pb n="22"
                            xml:id="pg_22" facs="0025"/> complete than before. He added that there
                        is now less quotation from U.S. case law and other published materials.</p>
                    <p>Kimball leafed through the latest volume of the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi>
                        and noted a section on the Deep Seabed and said that in his opinion that was
                        not an insignificant issue. He asked if that material was readily available
                        elsewhere or if the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> performs a unique function
                        to pull it all together.</p>
                    <p>Pfund answered that the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> pulls things together
                        in an “official” source in a coherent manner.</p>
                    <p>Picker returned to the question of the target audience, and added that the
                        most recent volumes, including a cumulative index, are all out of print.
                        Copies are grabbed up when they are printed. The demand is higher than the
                        supply.</p>
                    <p>Pfund brought up the possibility of converting the series to CD-ROM or an
                        on-line service. Picker pointed out the issue of cost. Kimball noted Pfund’s
                        comment that the real problem was getting someone with authority to allocate
                        resources.</p>
                    <p>Pfund said that the form of the publication should be related to the target
                        audience. Some of the volumes are sold abroad. Picker commented that some
                        are sent to Embassies, and Kimball added that the majority go to government
                        depository libraries and law school libraries. He asked Picker if the
                        Committee should be concerned.</p>
                    <p>Picker replied that her original concern was whether documents that would
                        have been included in the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> should be in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, and she felt that the
                        Committee needed to consider this. The American Society of International Law
                        has also expressed great concern about discontinuance of the series. Kimball
                        asked if there were any letters on this. Picker replied no, but that L is
                        well aware of ASIL’s concerns. She added that on May 11 she met with Robert
                        Dalton of L and Paul Claussen about getting another organization either to
                        take over the publication or to finance it. The initial response from L was
                        that more than cost was involved. The time devoted by L lawyers to the
                        collection of materials is the real issue. The Committee needs feedback on
                        cost.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if the project is an orphan in the State Department and Pfund
                        replied that it is becoming one. Picker commented that it does have a highly
                        motivated mother (Marian Nash).</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if there were any comments on the possible impact of the
                        elimination of the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> on the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                    <p>Slany responded that the series does not need to document case law, only the
                        legal framework and explanations for U.S. foreign policy and related
                        decisions. Picker pointed out that the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> is
                        broader than case law and Pfund agreed that it relates to the many different
                        aspects of U.S. foreign policy.</p>
                    <p>Hogan recommended that HO look through the volumes, and Pfund suggested that
                        Marian Nash, editor of the <hi rend="italic">Digest,</hi> be given a chance
                        to comment.</p>
                    <p>Kimball said that the Committee needs to find out if this is an issue for
                        concern.</p>
                    <pb n="23" xml:id="pg_23" facs="0026"/>
                    <p>Picker asked Slany to comment on what extent HO should become involved with L
                        and seek access to L files for use in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes.</p>
                    <p>Slany replied that it is unplowed terrain. HO has not searched L files; they
                        are as obscure to us as the INR files were before we got into them. The
                        files are not routinely retired so that the historians can have access. He
                        said that he did not know if Langbart has had any success with their
                        records.</p>
                    <p>Langbart replied that he has had some. There is a schedule but it needs
                        work.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked that HO study the question: should we be concerned and how?</p>
                    <p>Claussen said that in some of his research he has used L files extensively,
                        and he added that he knows that members of the international law community
                        use the <hi rend="italic">Digest.</hi></p>
                    <p>Pfund commented that discontinuing the publication sends a message that
                        resources are not available, once the United States has become the world’s
                        only superpower, to continue to texplain the legal context and justification
                        for U.S. foreign policy, which is not necessarily a good message to send to
                        other countries. Picker pointed out that L is considering discontinuing a
                        series that has been in existence since the beginning of the century.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="classified-material-in-non-governmental-repositories">
                    <head>Classified Material in Non-Governmental Repositories</head>
                    <p>Kimball asked Dalsimer about collections of classified materials in
                        nongovernmental repositories, mentioning as an example the Dulles material
                        at the Seeley Mudd Library at Princeton University. Are the records now
                        automatically part of a systematic review process or are they regularly
                        opened?</p>
                    <p>Dalsimer replied that he can only discuss the collection he knows of at
                        Princeton. Princeton is an approved repository, so State will either do the
                        review or provide guidelines. He does not know of another collection like
                        this, and worries about non-official repositories and unauthorized release
                        of documents. The Executive Order does not mention these.</p>
                    <p>Hogan asked what is the issue? Is the material at Seeley Mudd a duplicate
                        set? Kimball said Kissinger claims that his materials at the Library of
                        Congress are only duplicates, but this has not proven to be the case. He
                        added that if the Committee finds other examples, these should be identified
                        so that the State Department can conduct a systematic review.</p>
                    <p>Langbart explained that Secretary Dulles hired a research assistant and
                        microfilmed material that would illustrate his (Dulles’) impact on foreign
                        policy. Dulles paid for it and owned the film but said that he would abide
                        by the rules for declassification. Kimball repeated that he just wanted to
                        make sure that the material would be reviewed for declassification.</p>
                    <p>Langbart said that Dulles thought that his papers would eventually all be
                        open. Hogan questioned the quality of the microfilm after such a long
                        period.</p>
                    <p>Van Camp suggested that the way to identify bodies of records like this is
                        through the Defense Investigative Service, which conducts routine
                        inspections of records <pb n="24" xml:id="pg_24" facs="0027"/> depositories.
                        Dalsimer said that they had checked with DOD about this but were told that
                        they know of no such holdings.</p>
                    <p>Langbart said that Dulles left a copy of the microfilm at the State
                        Department. Slany said that the Department knows where it is. Dalsimer said
                        that he doesn’t know where it is. Slany said that HDR has it.</p>
                    <p>Langbart noted another example, the G. Mennen Williams collection at the
                        Michigan Historical Society.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked if the same procedure was followed for the Humphrey papers at
                        Minnesota. Langbart replied that the Vice President can take whatever he
                        wants.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="declassification-of-the-foreign-relations-series">
                    <head>Declassification of the Foreign Relations Series</head>
                    <p>Kimball asked Slany for an update on declassification of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Slany said that there are
                        the same problems with CIA as reported before. Assistant Secretary/Chief of
                        Staff Donilon and CIA Executive Director Slatkin have worked out and agreed
                        on some principles of declassification. Three volumes have gone to CIA under
                        these guidelines. We will see by February if this system works.</p>
                    <p>In response to a question from Herring, Herschler said that the China, Laos,
                        and Cyprus volumes were sent to CIA. CIA responses on three other volumes
                        are due: Italy, Africa, and Thailand, and in the case of the Southeast Asia
                        and Africa volumes, the CIA responses are not complete. There are some
                        declassification issues with State as well. Miller interjected that the
                        problem with the Cyprus volume is not Cyprus, but Greece.</p>
                    <p>Kimball suggested that HO set up a tickler file to revisit the appealed
                        volumes. Hogan asked how often a case could be appealed. Kimball believed
                        that the new E.O. required a 2-year waiting period after the first
                        appeal.</p>
                    <p>Slany reported that the National Security Agency had filed a FOIA request
                        regarding the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> documents and other
                        Department records identified in a <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>
                        article on Japan. Kimball said that he had heard that.</p>
                    <p>Hogan went back to the question of re-appeals and asked about the Iran
                        volume. Slany said that the issue will be covered in the intended
                        retrospective volume on covert operations.</p>
                    <p>Davis remarked that 2 years is too long, it should be 1 year. Hogan suggested
                        that the Committee check the law to see if it really is 2 years. Kimball
                        said that he thought it was tied to costs, etc. and that he is almost
                        positive it is 2 years. Information on this will be included in the briefing
                        material for the next meeting for the Committee to revisit if desired. Slany
                        agreed.</p>
                    <p>The meeting adjourned at 4:10 p.m.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
