<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="hac_1995-02-14_minutes">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of Historical Advisory Committee Meeting, February
                    1995</title>
                <title type="short">HAC Meeting Minutes, 1995</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <date type="created" when="1995-02-14">February 14, 1995</date></publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="[i]" xml:id="pg_i" facs="0001"/>
            <div type="section"
                xml:id="advisory-committee-on-historical-diplomatic-documentation-february-1415--1995_1">
                <head><hi rend="bold">Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation
                        February 14–15, 1995</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Committee Members</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Warren F. Kimball, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Benton Vincent Davis, Jr.</item>
                    <item>George C. Herring, Jr.</item>
                    <item>Michael J. Hogan</item>
                    <item>Melvyn P. Leffler</item>
                    <item>Jane M. Picker</item>
                    <item>Emily S. Rosenberg</item>
                    <item>Michael R. Schaller</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Executive Secretary</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bureau of Public Affairs</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Susan Povenmire</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bureau of Public Affairs, Office of the Historian</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, Director</item>
                    <item>Rita Baker</item>
                    <item>Paul Claussen</item>
                    <item>Evan Duncan</item>
                    <item>Karen Gatz</item>
                    <item>David Geyer</item>
                    <item>David Herschler</item>
                    <item>Kerry Hite</item>
                    <item>Nina Howland</item>
                    <item>David Humphrey</item>
                    <item>Donna Hung</item>
                    <item>Ted Keefer</item>
                    <item>Harmon Kirby</item>
                    <item>Glenn LaFantasie</item>
                    <item>Dan Lawler</item>
                    <item>Gabrielle Mallon</item>
                    <item>Jim Miller</item>
                    <item>David Patterson</item>
                    <item>Harriet Schwar</item>
                    <item>Luke Smith</item>
                    <item>Shirley Taylor</item>
                    <item>Carolyn Yee</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bureau of Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Frank Machak, Director, A/IM/IS/FPC</item>
                    <item>Anthony Dalsimer, Director, FPC/HDR</item>
                    <item>Nina Noring, FPC/HDR</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[ii]" xml:id="pg_ii" facs="0002"/>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Office of the Legal Adviser</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>James Thessin, Deputy Legal Adviser</item>
                    <item>Mary Comfort, L/LM</item>
                    <item>Mary Beth West, L/LM</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">National Archives and Records Administration</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Regina Greenwell, Archivist, Johnson Presidential Library</item>
                    <item>David Langbart, Archivist, Records Appraisal and Disposition
                        Division</item>
                    <item>Jerome Nashorn, Branch Chief, Records Appraisal and Disposition
                        Division</item>
                    <item>Marvin Russell, Chief General Archives Review Branch</item>
                    <item>Nancy Smith, Office of Presidential Libraries</item>
                </list>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Private</hi></p>
                <list>
                    <item>Kazuyoshi Imohara, TV Asahi</item>
                    <item>Christopher Poston, TV Asahi</item>
                    <item>Tim Weiner, <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi></item>
                </list>
                <pb n="[iii]" xml:id="pg_iii" facs="0003"/>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="contents">
                <head>Table of Contents</head>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Open Session, February 14</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Comment From the Public Affairs Leadership</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Changes to the Agenda</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Approval of the October 1994 Minutes</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Public Access to Records of the Committee</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_1">1</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report by the Historian</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Schedule for Meeting the 30-Year Line</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_3">3</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Access to CIA Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_5">5</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Status of Japan and British Guyana Appeals.</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_7">7</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Johnson Telephone Conversations</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_8">8</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Nixon Presidential Historical Materials</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">10</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Outside Academic Reviewers</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_10">11</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Closed Session, February 14</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>State Department Documents in the Presidential Libraries</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report of the Subcommittee on Opening the Department of State’s..
                            30-Year Old Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_12">12</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Draft Executive Order on Declassification</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_13">13</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report of the Subcommittee on Declassification</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_17">17</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Report on the Visit to the National Security Council</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_19">19</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="bold">Closed Session, February 15</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Comments by the CIA Historian on Access to CIA Records</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <ref target="#pg_21">21</ref></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="[1]" xml:id="pg_1" facs="0004"/>
            <div xml:id="open-session-february-14">
                <head>OPEN SESSION, February 14</head>
                <p>Chairman Warren F. Kimball called the meeting to order at 9:09 a.m. He first
                    noted that Ann Van Camp would be absent from this Advisory Committee
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>Kimball then gave an explanation of how to take minutes for the meeting. He
                    reminded the staff that the speaker is responsible for clarifying when a comment
                    is meant to be off-the-record. The speaker must also indicate when a statement
                    should be considered classified or as part of the deliberative process. It is
                    not the responsibility of the notetakers to identify this information.</p>
                <p>Kimball noted the presence of several visitors, including Regina Greenwell of the
                    Johnson Library, two reporters representing Japanese television (TV Asahi), and
                    Tim Weiner from <hi rend="italic">The New York Times.</hi></p>
                <div xml:id="comment-from-the-public-affairs-leadership">
                    <head>Comment From the Public Affairs Leadership</head>
                    <p>William Z. Slany explained that the absence of PA Bureau leadership was due
                        to the pending testimony of Secretary Christopher on the Hill. He added that
                        Deputy Assistant Secretary Bennett Freeman might join the Committee for
                        lunch; the attendance of Assistant Secretary and Chief of Staff Tom Donilon
                        would depend on the demands required for Christopher’s testimony. Kimball
                        interjected that the Committee would certainly like to have the opportunity
                        to talk with Donilon if at all possible. Slany mentioned Mike McCurry’s
                        continuing interest in the Committee and suggested that he might wish to
                        meet with the Committee in spite of his new responsibilities as the
                        President’s Press Secretary.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="changes-to-the-agenda">
                    <head>Changes to the Agenda</head>
                    <p>Slany suggested that the discussion of the draft executive order be moved to
                        the afternoon by rearranging the schedule, i.e., trading places with the
                        session on the LBJ tapes. Kimball and Nancy Smith (NARA) discussed this and
                        Smith agreed to the substitution. With the general agreement of the
                        Committee, Kimball announced that the meeting would proceed along Slany’s
                        suggested changes.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="approval-of-the-october-1994-minutes">
                    <head>Approval of the October 1994 Minutes</head>
                    <p>Kimball said that he wanted to make one minor correction to the minutes of
                        the October 1994 meeting: substitute “advisory” for “executive” body on page
                        6. He asked if the Committee had any other changes to suggest. In the
                        absence of any suggestions, Kimball announced that the minutes were approved
                        as corrected.</p>
                    <p>Kimball suggested that Slany begin his report, since the Committee was
                        uncharacteristically ahead of schedule, and Mary Beth West (L/LM) was not
                        yet due to arrive. Slany began by referring to his written report as a
                        general overview of all aspects of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> program.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="public-access-to-records-of-the-committee">
                    <head>Public Access to Records of the Committee</head>
                    <p>Before Slany could continue, Mary Beth West arrived. Kimball then initiated
                        the session on public access to the records of the Committee.</p>
                    <pb n="2" xml:id="pg_2" facs="0005"/>
                    <p>Emily Rosenberg began the discussion by relating what the subcommittee
                        learned at its meeting on Monday. The Office of the Legal Adviser has
                        determined that the records of the Advisory Committee, including the minutes
                        of its meetings, must be treated like all other records of the Department of
                        State: Department documents, other than those expressly intended for public
                        discussion must either be released through the FOIA process or be opened at
                        the National Archives pursuant to a formal records disposition schedule.
                        Each document must be screened for classified and deliberative process
                        material. The chairman of the Committee should clarify the rules of
                        discussion as Kimball already had at the beginning of the meeting. The
                        notetakers for each meeting must be given clear cues by the participants
                        regarding the need to protect the information they present&#x02014;because
                        of security or deliberative sensitivity. After each Committee meeting, the
                        Executive Secretary should segregate the clearly unclassified information
                        intended for public disclosure from deliberative material requiring
                        clearance from the FOIA office. The minutes of the open meeting, and part of
                        the closed session, should be available to the public in the FPC reading
                        room within 3 months. The briefing materials and other documents would be
                        similarly disposed.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg raised one problem with this procedure: the Committee must
                        officially approve the minutes before they can be made available. This would
                        generally postpone public release of the minutes until the next meeting
                        (i.e., 3 months later). The FOIA office has indicated that it could probably
                        clear the minutes within 24 hours of receipt. The Executive Secretary will
                        prepare the record of both the open and closed portions of the Committee,
                        segregate the classified portions, and identify the portions at which
                        deliberative discussions were held. Rosenberg Suggested that the Committee
                        accept this process on a provisional basis, and return to the issue in 3
                        months. She also repeated the Committee’s concern that the minutes, and
                        other records of the Committee, be available for the public’s use.</p>
                    <p>Mary Beth West stated her appreciation for the concerns of the Committee on
                        this matter. The Office of the Legal Adviser is working with FPC to create
                        an expedited process that could deposit any of the Committee’s records in
                        the reading room once they had been cleared for classification and privacy
                        information.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg stated the Committee’s apprehension concerning the use of the term
                        “deliberative process.” She said that the Committee was not ready to commit
                        itself thoroughly to the proposed procedures, and may need to revisit the
                        issue at a later date.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked the Executive Secretary (Slany) to monitor the process; perhaps
                        there would not be much public interest. Slany said he would be surprised if
                        that were the case.</p>
                    <p>Jane Picker asked if the Office of the Legal Adviser made any distinction
                        between the deliberative materials of the Committee and those of the State
                        Department&#x02014;between the status of an advisory committee and that of a
                        formal agency of the executive branch.</p>
                    <p>West admitted that there was a distinction to be made; a problem arose,
                        however, because of the interplay between the Committee and executive branch
                        agencies. The deliberations of the Committee would not be subject to any
                        restrictions unless they <pb n="3" xml:id="pg_3" facs="0006"/> included
                        information concerning the deliberations of the State Department or other
                        agencies of the government.</p>
                    <p>At this point Frank Machak (FPC) arrived, and West provided a review of the
                        previous discussion for his benefit. Kimball then asked if the Committee had
                        any further questions for either Machak or West. There were none.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="report-by-the-historian">
                    <head>Report by the Historian</head>
                    <div xml:id="schedule-for-meeting-the-30-year-line">
                        <head>Schedule for Meeting the 30-Year Line</head>
                        <p>Slany then continued his report by stressing the statutory responsibility
                            of HO to reach the 30-year line by 1996&#x02014;and to do so without
                            sacrificing the quality and integrity of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi> series. He expressed optimism that the staff might
                            meet the deadline, or at least had a reasonable chance of doing so.
                            Slany did introduce, however, one important qualification: the
                            organization of the series on the basis of Presidential term. Although
                            HO would publish all of the volumes for the Eisenhower and Kennedy
                            administrations by the end of 1996, some of the Johnson volumes might
                            not appear in print until 1998. These volumes would necessarily include
                            documents older than 30 years, but, taken as a whole, the Johnson
                            subseries would be finished within the terms of the statute. Slany added
                            that 1995 would be a big year with the publication of as many as 15
                            volumes.</p>
                        <p>Slany asked the Committee for its help and recommendations concerning the
                            15 volumes scheduled to be published this year, drawing special
                            attention to the “adequacy of documentation” issue. These volumes, which
                            have not been read by the Committee, might possibly require an outside
                            review. Slany asked if the Committee would recommend that the Department
                            hire contractors to review the manuscripts. He explained that, in
                            proceeding with the Johnson subseries, HO is concerned that the
                            Committee has not adequately addressed the issues that confront each
                            volume, including scope and size of volumes and coverage of intelligence
                            matters. Slany asked what the Committee would recommend: is it
                            reasonable to assume that the Committee members would review the volumes
                            or should outside contractors be found to do this?</p>
                        <p>Slany raised the issue of delays caused by the process of
                            declassification. He was quick to note that the problem of
                            declassification delays does not apply to the Department of State
                            itself: the number of HDR reviewers apparently exceeds the number of
                            manuscripts that HO can supply. In fact, due largely to the chronic
                            staff shortage, HO is admittedly behind its original schedule of
                            referrals to HDR. The problem of declassification delays is due
                            primarily to the delinquency of responses from other agencies,
                            particularly DOD, DOE, Treasury, and the CIA. These agencies regularly
                            exceed their statutory responsibility of responding within 120 days.
                            Slany added that these issues would be further addressed in the
                            afternoon.</p>
                        <p>Slany reiterated that, although the occasional desk officer has not been
                            helpful, the Department leadership has been supportive of HO’s mission.
                            He noted in particular that Secretary Christopher remains committed to
                            the principle of promoting public access to the Department’s historical
                            records. The problem, of course, is in getting other agencies to share
                            in, and cooperate with, that commitment.</p>
                        <pb n="4" xml:id="pg_4" facs="0007"/>
                        <p>Kimball interrupted to add that the Committee certainly appreciated the
                            support it has received from the Department, and he wanted this
                            appreciation to be appropriately noted in the record.</p>
                        <p>Slany responded that any internal success can be partially attributed to
                            HO’s proximity to the people necessary to the success of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> program within the Department.
                            Our relations with other agencies, on the other hand, remain relatively
                            distant. The government-wide declassification bureaucracy is so large
                            that its very size constitutes a threat to the series. Other agencies
                            have their own considerations and seem to have trouble accepting State’s
                            priorities, even when the latter are required by the law. He noted that
                            the failure of some agencies to respond was forcing delays in the
                            publication of two volumes from the end of the Eisenhower administration
                            as well as others covering the Kennedy Presidency. Slany asked the
                            Committee for its recommendation on how to deal with this problem,
                            particularly when certain agencies regularly miss deadlines mandated by
                            the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> statute. He remarked that
                            Kimball occasionally scolded him for being “too courteous”; perhaps HO
                            should develop a tougher “complaint system.” In bureaucratic terms, it
                            might be easier for the Committee to complain to other agencies and be
                            heard.</p>
                        <p>Slany mentioned that, although the State Department has been generally
                            supportive, HO was currently having difficulty gaining consistent and
                            effective access to the Department’s older records, which have recently
                            been moved to a warehouse in Newington, Virginia. He asked David
                            Patterson to comment on this issue.</p>
                        <p>Patterson said that Ken Rossman of the Department’s Records Management
                            Staff had reported to him last week that the records are already stored
                            at Newington, but that he (Patterson) had received conflicting reports
                            about their availability. Rossman thought that HO could possibly resume
                            its research at Newington by the middle of this week. Patterson also
                            mentioned that he had raised the issue of transportation with Rossman.
                            Rossman did not know if the shuttle bus would stop at the research
                            facility (SA-13) in addition to its other three stops. Otherwise the
                            closest stop is a mile away.</p>
                        <p>Herring asked if the move to Newington was in addition to or in lieu of
                            the proposed move to Berryville. Slany replied: “In lieu of.”</p>
                        <p>On behalf of the Committee, Kimball expressed the hope that the shuttle
                            “goes the extra mile.” He then asked if anyone had checked the facility
                            to see if it meets the minimum standards required of a research
                            facility.</p>
                        <p>Patterson said that he had been told that the facility would meet the
                            standards that one would expect of such a facility.</p>
                        <p>Kimball said that he wanted the record 10 show that the Committee fully
                            supports the shuttle stopping at the facility in Newington. He asked if
                            a memorandum to the appropriate authority would be required to formalize
                            the Committee’s position on the issue; he received a negative
                            response.</p>
                        <p>Anthony Dalsimer (FPC/HDR) interjected that HDR is still waiting for
                            office space to be developed. Kimball suggested that a Committee member
                            visit the facility <pb n="5" xml:id="pg_5" facs="0008"/> before the next
                            meeting to judge whether the space is adequate; he volunteered Mel
                            Leffler to look into this on his next trip to the D.C. area.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="access-to-cia-records">
                        <head>Access to CIA Records</head>
                        <p>Slany raised another issue that threatens the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi> schedule: access to the intelligence records of the
                            CIA. He noted that a decision to include more intelligence documentation
                            in the series would increase the time required to compile the volumes,
                            particularly since these documents are usually more difficult to locate.
                            He said that the issue of access to CIA records would be discussed in
                            the afternoon. Slany also remarked that Kimball often calls to complain
                            that HO historians have not received access to the records of the
                            National Security Agency. Slany said that HO needs to know what the
                            Committee expects from the series, especially for volumes near
                            completion. HO cannot continue to revise and augment completed volumes
                            and, at the same time, stick to the publication schedule. He asked if
                            the Committee had any recommendations on how to do both.</p>
                        <p>Kimball asked for comments. He said that all historians must face the
                            difficult question of when to stop looking for documentation. The HO
                            historians, however, have the additional burden of the schedule as
                            mandated by law.</p>
                        <p>Rosenberg commented that the Committee has seen an increase in access
                            over the last year. In view of this consideration, the original schedule
                            may have to be changed. This might require making changes or additions
                            to volumes that are otherwise ready for publication, i.e., in page
                            proofs. Rosenberg stated her conviction that the schedule cannot be the
                            highest priority, that the historical community expects the volumes to
                            reflect the policy of greater openness. Rosenberg admitted that she was
                            not certain how to do this and meet the demands of the schedule at the
                            same time. She further noted that according to Slany’s report to the
                            Committee on the scope of inclusion of CIA documents in recent <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes, recently published
                            volumes on Europe during the Kennedy administration contained no
                            documentation from the CIA. In her opinion, this was a disturbing
                            development. CIA documents were retrieved&#x02014;not from the CIA
                            itself&#x02014;but from the Kennedy Library. Nancy Smith remarked that
                            the Presidential libraries are a prime repository for significant
                            intelligence documentation. The CIA is often forced to send historians
                            to the Presidential libraries in order to find their own documents.</p>
                        <p>Slany explained that the volumes in question had been done at a time when
                            HO had yet to work out arrangements for access to CIA records. He did
                            not think that HO could afford to hold up these volumes in order to
                            search for additional documentation from the CIA.</p>
                        <p>Leffler seconded Rosenberg’s reaction to the lack of CIA documentation in
                            certain volumes; he was “shocked.” Leffler said that the Committee
                            should reassess the discrepancy in coverage devoted to intelligence
                            issues in the Kennedy volumes, determine what can be found, and decide
                            whether a new search is worth the effort.</p>
                        <p>Kimball agreed, delegating the task of further recommendation and
                            estimates to HO. A decision would have to be made for each volume.
                            Kimball reminded the <pb n="6" xml:id="pg_6" facs="0009"/> Committee,
                            however, that Slany cannot recommend a schedule that is in violation of
                            the law.</p>
                        <p>Tim Weiner asked for clarification on the subject of access to CIA
                            records. Were the HO historians hampered by the necessity of asking the
                            right question in order to get an appropriate answer?</p>
                        <p>Kimball explained that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                            series had been in transition at the time the volumes on the Kennedy
                            administration were being compiled. In 1991, the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Foreign Relations</hi> statute signaled a new era of openness:
                            agencies were required to agree to written procedures giving HO (and the
                            Committee) full access to the records necessary for the completeness and
                            integrity of the series. The CIA files, however, are not organized in a
                            way that could be considered conducive to the kind of research normally
                            conducted for the series. HO researchers are learning how to exploit CIA
                            files and have made some progress in recent months.</p>
                        <p>Kimball was careful to point out that progress in access does not imply
                            similar progress in declassification. The former is “promising”; the
                            latter is not. Kimball said that the researchers do find more once they
                            learn how to ask the right questions. Now the issue is how to go back to
                            the CIA for additional documentation without forcing the series to be in
                            violation of the law.</p>
                        <p>Rosenberg used the common metaphor of perspective: the glass is either
                            half empty or half full. The current level of access must be considered
                            a major breakthrough in comparison to the access of the past. Maybe the
                            Committee is inclined too often to see the glass as half empty. The
                            historical community, however, will likely see the results of increased
                            access in some volumes and question the relative lack of coverage in
                            others.</p>
                        <p>Herring noted that, according to the Perkins Chart, the European volumes
                            had been compiled in 1992 and were due for publication this year. There
                            is little that can be done about them now.</p>
                        <p>Slany mentioned the Soviet Union volumes for 1961–1963, that are being
                            revised to include intelligence and other documents, to show how the
                            search for supplementary documentation often forces a lengthy
                            postponement in publication.</p>
                        <p>Picker worried that the failure to conduct additional research might lead
                            to a distortion of the record. If the record is distorted, the Committee
                            may need to add new language to the preface as a warning. The preface
                            could state that HO is continuing its research and might include
                            additional documentation in a future volume.</p>
                        <p>Kimball said that Slany’s request is legitimate, and the Committee does
                            need to think about the general schedule. Slany, however, will have to
                            insert “intellectual impact statements” for each volume to account for
                            the issue of access.</p>
                        <p>Herring added that the Committee needs to assess whether new
                            documentation would materially affect the historical record and
                            determine whether such a search would be worth the resulting delay.</p>
                        <pb n="7" xml:id="pg_7" facs="0010"/>
                        <p>Slany said that HO is currently using senior Foreign Service officers to
                            evaluate volumes. Some of these FSOs were involved in the events
                            documented and can therefore recognize any gaps in the record. He
                            conceded that this method had not always worked, but that it has
                            recently produced good results on the Soviet Union volumes.</p>
                        <p>Kimball said that he had reviewed the Perkins Chart, marking any problems
                            that seemed readily apparent. He suggested that the Committee review the
                            chart as a group in order to identify the delays confronting each
                            volume:</p>
                        <table cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>1946-50, Intelligence Supplement</cell>
                                <cell>Baker said the volume is in page proofs and should not be
                                    considered a problem.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1958-60, National Security Policy</cell>
                                <cell>Herschler said that several documents are still outstanding at
                                    DOD. These documents were sent for re-review in 1992.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1958-60 China/Tibet</cell>
                                <cell>Several documents remain outstanding with other
                                    agencies.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1961-63, National Security Policy</cell>
                                <cell>Herschler explained that the volume had been held up due to a
                                    problem in clearing NIEs; the “intelligence community review,”
                                    as coordinated by CIA, is behind schedule.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Kimball asked what the CIA had done about declassifying the NIEs.
                            Patterson replied that the CIA had released a number of strategic
                            estimates, most of which concern the Soviet missile program. Hundreds of
                            NIEs, however, remain classified, including estimates for nearly every
                            country in the world.</p>
                        <p>Weiner asked about the China/Tibet volume. He wondered whether the
                            documentation denied in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                            volume might confirm a story already in the public domain.</p>
                        <p>Kimball replied: “God, I wish I could answer that!”</p>
                        <p>Kimball belatedly introduced two new Committee members, Michael Hogan
                            (Ohio State University) and Michael Schaller (University of
                            Arizona).</p>
                        <p>The Committee adjourned for the scheduled coffee break at 10:30 a.m.</p>
                        <p>The meeting reconvened at 10:55 a.m. Kimball reviewed the ground rules
                            concerning minutes: notes would be taken on everything said in the
                            meeting, classified and unclassified, unless the speaker requested that
                            his or her remarks be off-the-record. The classified portion would be
                            segregated. The draft minutes would continue to be circulated to all
                            agencies.</p>
                        <p>Kimball noted that among the eight Committee members were seven proposals
                            for improving access to documents.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="status-of-japan-and-british-guyana-appeals">
                    <head>Status of Japan and British Guyana Appeals</head>
                    <p>Kimball then opened the floor to questions generated from the earlier
                        discussion. Tim Weiner of <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> asked
                        Kimball if he could state for the record the <pb n="8" xml:id="pg_8"
                            facs="0011"/> status of the Japan and Guyana issues. Slany indicated
                        that the volumes containing these compilations were still in the interagency
                        review process. One or more might also fall into the category, discussed
                        earlier in the morning, of adding more documents to make the record more
                        complete. At one time the volumes were considered finished, but the
                        opportunity now exists to add material.</p>
                    <p>Weiner asked whether the Department of State had approved the Japan
                        compilation; Slany reported that it had. Weiner asked whether the CIA had
                        said yes or no; Slany indicated that the matter was still under discussion
                        in the Agency, and because the process was not complete, the Office did not
                        accept CIA’s answer as a final yes or no. In response to Weiner’s question
                        concerning Guyana, Slany indicated that it was also in the interagency
                        review process. Weiner asked to whom in the Agency the matter was addressed.
                        Slany indicated that it was addressed to the person who has authority over
                        declassification matters. Weiner asked whether this was done last month.
                        Slany replied that it had occurred last year. Weiner asked whether there was
                        a time clock. Slany indicated that the Agency had come back with an initial
                        response, and that the answer was not “yes.”</p>
                    <p>Kimball noted that the CIA’s initial finding that the documents were not
                        releasable initiated an appeal process. Weiner asked what would happen if a
                        negative answer were received in the appeal process. Slany indicated that
                        the Advisory Committee would then become involved, and it would consider
                        such options as publishing the volume without the documents in question, or
                        not publishing the volume. Weiner asked when or at what point the Department
                        would consider that it had received a final yes or no from the Agency. Slany
                        indicated that it would be about another month.</p>
                    <p>Christopher Poston of the Asahi National Broadcasting Company asked whether
                        the Department was strictly interpreting the 60-day appeal period. Slany
                        replied that the Department would try to avoid a quick response if the
                        answer was likely to be a flat “no.” In some cases where it could be
                        beneficial to the historical record, the Department might allow the 60-day
                        limit to be exceeded.</p>
                    <p>Weiner asked whether there could be a mixed answer, with some documents
                        cleared and others denied. Slany and Kimball pointed out that this was not
                        only possible but occurred routinely. Weiner asked Kimball if he could say
                        what the CIA’s objections were based on in the appeal. Kimball said he could
                        not.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="johnson-telephone-conversations">
                    <head>Johnson Telephone Conversations</head>
                    <p>Kimball then turned to the subcommittee that was dealing with the recorded
                        telephone conversations of President Lyndon B. Johnson in the LBJ Library
                        and an HO plan to gain access to and include portions of these records in
                        the series. Herring indicated that the LBJ Library had decided some time ago
                        to make the telephone conversations available. This represented a windfall
                        of useful material for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series,
                        especially because so little of President Johnson is reflected in the
                        Johnson papers. This raised problems that could cause significant delays in
                        compiling the 1964–1968 volumes: many hours were required to process the
                        material, researchers and transcribers would have to listen carefully to
                        catch nuances and details, and donor <pb n="9" xml:id="pg_9" facs="0012"/>
                        restrictions would have to be dealt with. Regina Greenwell of the LBJ
                        Library pointed out that, in keeping with NARA policy, the Library did not
                        make transcripts.</p>
                    <p>Herring noted that David Humphrey was working on an action plan that would
                        allow the Office to focus on the periods and subjects of greatest
                        importance: the crises in 1964 in Cuba and Brazil, for example, and the
                        Dominican crisis of 1965. The greatest volume of material was from 1964; of
                        the over 7,000 recordings of telephone conversations, 4,000 were from 1964.
                        The Office was most interested in the conversations during the first half of
                        1964; most for August through early November 1964 were election-related. As
                        the administration went on, the volume of recorded conversations decreased,
                        and during the years 1966-1968 they dealt primarily with Vietnam. (The HO
                        plan is to work with the LBJ Library and give priority review to about 1,000
                        conversations most relevant to major foreign policy issues.)</p>
                    <p>Herring noted the importance of picking up items that might have been missed
                        during the first review but identified later by the LBJ Library, and the
                        importance of providing access to scholars. He indicated that there was no
                        doubt of the utility and significance of the material for the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                    <p>Slany agreed, adding that the volumes must make clear what the compilers did
                        and did not see, and inform readers that only about 10 percent of the
                        conversations could be reviewed. Herring noted that there was much useful
                        material on Vietnam for 1964, but the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volume had already been published. Kimball said that it
                        was important to establish criteria for retrofitting the LBJ volumes and
                        adding supplementary material where appropriate.</p>
                    <p>Schaller pointed out that intonation and expression added other dimensions to
                        the interpretation of the tapes; the transcripts alone did not capture the
                        nuances of the conversations. Hogan agreed and asked about publishing the
                        recordings on CD-ROM. Greenwell emphasized that the LBJ Library considered
                        the tapes to be the original records, not any transcripts that might be
                        made! Nancy Smith indicated that there was no substitute for the recordings,
                        since a transcript could contain erroneous attributions.</p>
                    <p>Greenwell noted that 33 hours of telephone conversations have been made
                        available thus far in the LBJ Library reading room in the form of digital
                        audiotapes. Eventually the entire collection will be available. Classified
                        and donor-restricted portions are excised from the digital tapes; a tone
                        warns the listener and textual notes indicate the duration in seconds and
                        grounds for excision. Smith indicated that the JFK Library had used the same
                        system for the Cuban Missile Crisis tapes. With respect to the Nixon tapes
                        at Pickett Street, there were other complicating factors, including a
                        prohibition on the sale of reproductions.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked about a timetable for release of the LBJ recordings.
                        Greenwell said the Library expected to complete the process of duplication
                        from the original dictabelts onto tapes by March 1995. The tapes should be
                        open to the public in 5 years.</p>
                    <p>Kimball summarized the sentiment of the Committee as agreeing that a
                        carefully-constructed paragraph concerning the tapes should be added to the
                        preface to each 1964-1968 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume.
                        The paragraph should indicate that the tapes exist, <pb n="10"
                            xml:id="pg_10" facs="0013"/> describe the nature of their use in the
                        particular volume or indicate that a review of the database revealed few or
                        no relevant conversations, and emphasize the importance of listening to the
                        tapes.</p>
                    <p>Herring noted that great progress had been made during the past year in
                        resolving the issue of the LBJ recorded telephone conversations. Kimball
                        asked that the minutes reflect that the Committee was pleased by the
                        progress made during the last year. Originally there was a donor restriction
                        of 50 years following President Johnson’s death; now there were arrangements
                        in place to ensure access to both HO researchers and the public. Slany
                        commended Humphrey for his work on the LBJ telephone conversations, and
                        announced that he had been promoted to Chief of the Office’s European and
                        General Division.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="nixon-presidential-materials">
                    <head>Nixon Presidential Materials</head>
                    <p>Nancy Smith urged the Committee not to lose sight of the urgent need to
                        address the Nixon Presidential materials. NARA was concerned because it was
                        involved in litigation. The Department should begin negotiations with the
                        Nixon lawyers as soon as possible to avoid delays in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> schedule. Kimball asked Slany if there had been
                        any contact with the Nixon Library. Slany indicated that the first step
                        would be to have a plan for the contents of the Nixon subseries. Such a plan
                        would build on the experience in documenting the Kennedy and Johnson
                        administrations. Kimball said he felt there should be something more
                        concrete on the Nixon years by the next Committee meeting; a bad plan that
                        moves things along is better than a good plan that is too late.</p>
                    <p>Nancy Smith pointed out that one of the Nixon lawsuits deal with the question
                        of whether NARA had returned all the personal and returnable material on the
                        Nixon tapes to the President’s agents. The Department of State would have to
                        talk to the Nixon agents about this. There was an existing procedure for the
                        Department to approach the Nixon agents on ongoing foreign policy issues,
                        but not on the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. It should be
                        possible to work out an arrangement similar to those with the JFK and LBJ
                        Libraries whereby Department historians would select documents and copies
                        would be sent for review to the appropriate agencies.</p>
                    <p>Kimball stated that while the Department had usually relied on NARA as a good
                        faith agent for access to Presidential materials, in the case of the Nixon
                        materials, the Department might want to act independently to move the
                        process along. Smith agreed that this was a good idea, pointing out that
                        NARA was going into non-binding legal mediation in an attempt to try to
                        resolve some complex issues of access and returnability. The mediation
                        covers all Nixon Presidential materials, not just the tapes. Nixon is a
                        unique and unprecedented case&#x02014;unprecedented in the amount of
                        material involved and with respect to the tape collection. The Nixon
                        Presidency was the last to have tapes and even has its own law, the Nixon
                        Historical Presidential Materials Statute.</p>
                    <p>Luke Smith pointed out that the Nixon administration was also unique in that
                        Secretary of State Kissinger sent his materials to the Library of Congress,
                        where they are considered private papers. Nancy Smith, responding to
                        Kimball’s question about how the situation has changed, indicated that the
                        1978 Presidential Recordings Act changed the <pb n="11" xml:id="pg_11"
                            facs="0014"/> ownership of all future Presidential materials from
                        private to public. But the Federal Records Act did not change as a result of
                        Kissinger’s action. The Justice Department issued an opinion that the
                        Kissinger records were not official records but only copies of records in
                        Department of State files, and they therefore have private, non-record
                        status.</p>
                    <p>Schwar wondered whether the Kissinger materials covered his years as National
                        Security Adviser. Smith said these files were part of the Nixon project,
                        although it was likely that some Kissinger National Security files were at
                        the Library of Congress.</p>
                    <p>Slany reminded the Committee that the Department had provided subventions to
                        the Johnson Library. He was faced with the problem of presenting and
                        defending requests for a rising sum to ensure priority support. What sort of
                        expenses would the Nixon volumes entail? Nancy Smith said that state was
                        paying two archivists at the LBJ Library (one to expedite access to the
                        paper records and the other to assist in the preparation of selected records
                        of Johnson’s telephone conversations) and hoped the precedent would continue
                        for Nixon.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="outside-academic-reviewers">
                    <head>Outside Academic Reviewers</head>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked about the use of outside reviewers from the academic
                        community for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. The
                        Committee had discussed the idea in the past. Kimball pointed out that there
                        was a money issue; reviewers would presumably be paid $1,000 or more to
                        review a volume. There must be a fair fee that will attract good people.
                        Kimball wondered about the value of published academic reviews. LaFantasie
                        said they had been helpful.</p>
                    <p>Slany pointed out that another alternative was to make use of active duty
                        senior officers who have security clearances. The Committee’s briefing
                        materials had included Slany’s report on the reviews completed by various
                        senior experts on 13 different volumes. There was a problem in using outside
                        experts. They must sign a security disclaimer that would prevent them from
                        using the material in their own research. Leffler pointed out that HO had
                        survived for generations without external review, but Slany pointed out that
                        the Office had never before compiled 70 volumes in 5 years. Kimball said
                        that the Committee was not responsible for the content of volumes; compilers
                        were being paid for producing quality work. Kimball suggested that it might
                        be better to hire another HO historian than to seek outside reviewers. The
                        idea of outside reviewers sounded good, but it was hard to put into
                        effect.</p>
                    <p>The Committee adjourned at noon.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="closed-session-february-14">
                <head>CLOSED SESSION, February 14</head>
                <p>The Committee reconvened after lunch, with Herring presiding in Kimball’s
                    absence.</p>
                <div xml:id="state-department-documents-in-the-presidential-libraries">
                    <head>State Department Documents in the Presidential Libraries</head>
                    <p>Nancy Smith provided a status report on what Presidential Libraries have been
                        doing regarding State Department documents in Presidential Library
                        files.</p>
                    <pb n="12" xml:id="pg_12" facs="0015"/>
                    <p>The Presidential Libraries are seeking revocation of a 1983 State Department
                        memorandum that postponed indefinitely the automatic declassification of
                        documents marked Group 4 (automatic declassification after 12 years). Prior
                        to 1983 such documents, including many State Department cables, could be
                        automatically declassified as soon as they were 12 years old. Dalsimer has
                        drafted a memorandum for Assistant Secretary of State for Administration
                        Kennedy that requests DS to revoke the policy in the 1983 memorandum. The
                        memorandum is going forward. There are many officers in the State Department
                        who do not follow the guideline of the 1983 memorandum.</p>
                    <p>Smith has a call out to the Libraries to draft declassification guidelines
                        for certain categories of information in State Department documents that are
                        less than 30 years old. It is anticipated that these guidelines would be
                        similar to those adopted more than a decade ago by the National Security
                        Council for information in White House and NSC documents at the Presidential
                        Libraries. The guidelines would permit the Libraries to declassify limited
                        amounts of State Department information in documents less than 30 years old
                        without referring the documents to the State Department.</p>
                    <p>Smith also noted that a recent NSC letter states that the Truman, Eisenhower,
                        Kennedy, and Johnson Libraries no longer need to refer classified White
                        House and NSC documents to the NSC for declassification, although such
                        documents would still require referral to other agencies with equities.
                        Smith also raised the issue of heads of state correspondence in light of the
                        recent NSC change in policy. Are there categories of subject matter that can
                        be opened without going through the Department of State?</p>
                    <p>Leffler stated that he would like to have a report back in 6 months as to the
                        effect of NSC’s revocation of its equity in White House and NSC documents at
                        the older Libraries. He also asked whether NSC can delegate to the State
                        Department the same authority that it is giving to the Libraries to
                        declassify NSC and White House documents.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg suggested that the Committee might express its support for State’s
                        giving the Libraries clearance for releasing certain categories of
                        information in heads of state correspondence.</p>
                </div>
                <div
                    xml:id="report-of-the-subcommittee-on-opening-the-department-of-state-30-year-old-records">
                    <head>Report of the Subcommittee on Opening the Department of State’s 30-Year
                        Old Records</head>
                    <p>Rosenberg then presented the report of the subcommittee on 30-year old
                        records. She was particularly concerned that the Committee be assured that
                        the records would not only be reviewed by 1996 but also be transferred and
                        opened by that date, as required in the legislation. Marvin Russell (NARA)
                        stated that the legislation would be met. Rosenberg noted that by 1996
                        everything dated up to 1966 should be open. Russell stated that it will
                        happen.</p>
                    <p>David Langbart (NARA) also noted that the lot files for 1964-1966 need to be
                        appraised and scheduled. Rosenberg asked if this threw into question her
                        statement about opening everything by 1996. Langbart repeated that the issue
                        of lot files needed to be explored and resolved. Rosenberg asked him to
                        speak to Ken Rossman about it. Herring <pb n="13" xml:id="pg_13" facs="0016"
                        /> asked if there was anything the Committee needed to do about it as a
                        committee. Langbart said no.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg commented on the issue of getting other agencies involved in the
                        review of 30-year old records. Efforts were being made to get DOD and NSC
                        guidance. The big problem was CIA. She stated that the Committee needed to
                        go on record again expressing the wish that CIA would be more cooperative.
                        Dalsimer said that he had discussed the matter with Jack Wright and John
                        Pereira of CIA but that neither is at the policymaking level. Frank Machak
                        was going to talk to people at the policymaking level.</p>
                    <p>Herring asked Dalsimer if he had a plan for anticipating the new executive
                        order on declassification. Dalsimer said no.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg discussed the issue of guidelines, noting that they have been
                        reviewed, updated, and disseminated to the Presidential Libraries and that
                        further updates will go out to the Libraries. She also noted the need for a
                        regular training program for those using the guidelines and mentioned other
                        “culture-changing” mechanisms for declassifies. In HDR openness is
                        specifically encouraged and attention called to the standard of
                        “demonstrable damage” for withholding material. HDR monitors the quality of
                        the review through a 5 percent sample of documents reviewed at College
                        Park.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="draft-executive-order-on-declassification">
                    <head>Draft Executive Order on Declassification</head>
                    <p>Kimball returned at 2:35 p.m. and introduced James Thessin, Deputy Legal
                        Adviser, and Mary Comfort of the Office of the Legal Adviser, who would
                        provide greater background on the new draft executive order. Frank Machak
                        subsequently joined them.</p>
                    <p rend="center">[Begin Deliberative Discussion]</p>
                    <p>Comfort noted that a draft dated January 1, 1995, had been circulated to
                        agencies for comment. The Department of State had made a couple of major
                        comments. OMB was now compiling agency comments. She noted that State had a
                        continuing concern over what could be exempted both at the time of original
                        classification and at 24 years. In particular she stated that the exemption
                        clause referring to demonstrable damage to relations with another country
                        required amplification. The Justice Department had ruled that it did not
                        apply to instances where release of a document damaged U.S. interests but
                        not those of another country, such as could be the case if a negotiating
                        position were released. The document’s release could damage U.S. interests
                        in a current negotiation but be welcomed by the country with which the
                        United States was negotiating. In its other comments on the draft executive
                        order, State asked, among other things, for a precise definition of “foreign
                        governments” and for a revision in the procedure for notifying ISOO.</p>
                    <p>Thessin discussed maximizing benefits in terms of the number of documents
                        that could be squeezed from the Executive order. The best means to
                        accomplish that goal was, in his view, to concentrate on the end of the
                        25–30 year cycle. In that regard, the mechanism for declassifying the
                        historical series under the 1991 law could serve as a model for examining
                        and reviewing documents after 25–30 years.</p>
                    <pb n="14" xml:id="pg_14" facs="0017"/>
                    <p>According to Thessin, analyses show that 97 percent of classified documents
                        can be released after 25–30 years and, he felt, the Executive order should
                        pay more attention to that end of the time scale. Earlier release resulted
                        in something closer to only a 50 percent release rate. He explained that
                        continuous declassification procedures are counterproductive and waste
                        resources, whereas concentrating on the later end of the time scale was most
                        economical.</p>
                    <p>Kimball commented first that State had not allowed for full consultation with
                        the Advisory Committee on this matter. He pointed out, however, that HO had
                        sent him a copy of the Executive order and he, in turn, had consulted with
                        his colleagues on the Committee about it by E-mail. He proffered his view
                        that the Committee should not be thought of as part of the problem, but part
                        of the solution. Better efforts are needed to ensure that the Committee is
                        part of the process and not left out. He went on to express his appreciation
                        that the Advisory Committee at least had had some limited input and that
                        some of its advice had been accepted.</p>
                    <p>Kimball, speaking for the rest of the Committee, then questioned the approach
                        taken to the Executive order, that is, the joining of resources and
                        procedures. That approach struck the Committee as being the wrong way to
                        develop procedures.</p>
                    <p>Thessin responded by saying that the fact that the Advisory Committee did not
                        get a copy of the order earlier was not a deliberate act. An attempt was
                        made to reflect all comments made about the order, and he noted that Mary
                        Comfort and Bill Slany had met for that purpose.</p>
                    <p>Turning to the question of joining resources and procedures, Thessin reminded
                        the Committee that this is a time in which government resources are under
                        threat&#x02014;there are fewer resources, tough choices to be made, staff
                        reductions through early outs, and no increase in funds since 1993, although
                        the workload has expanded in some areas. As a result, resource allocation
                        must be a major consideration. In terms of document reviews, that means that
                        the areas in which payoffs are the greatest must be examined, and that is
                        where the approach to the Executive order comes in.</p>
                    <p>Kimball raised the question of bulk declassification and asked about its
                        impact.</p>
                    <p>Thessin indicated that the risks of accidental disclosure through bulk
                        declassification could be avoided by “portion marking,” that is, marking
                        each paragraph in a document with a classification code, so a reviewer can
                        go through the document quickly and release part or all of the document</p>
                    <p>Thessin recommended moving the declassification target date back to 25 years.
                        The cut-off point is now 30 years, but in reality it is closer to 33 years.
                        In addition, reviewers now have more documents per year to review.</p>
                    <p>Frank Machak stated that the Department recognized the issue of life-cycle
                        management of records. The executive order might be the proper vehicle to
                        accomplish the goal of selecting those documents worth preserving. He
                        indicated that there are now officers in the State Department who are
                        sensitive to these issues and noted that the Assistant Secretaries are
                        willing to help by watching out for unnecessary classification.</p>
                    <pb n="15" xml:id="pg_15" facs="0018"/>
                    <p>Kimball expressed concern that such procedures may be of benefit in 25 years,
                        but again questioned their immediate effectiveness.</p>
                    <p>Machak responded by again pointing to the issue of resources and the fact
                        that work can be done only with the means at hand. He explained that the
                        current distribution of resources&#x02014;one-third devoted to systematic
                        reviews, one-third to FOIAs, and one-third to the Secretary’s litigation,
                        congressional investigations. Systematic review should be the priority
                        program. He pointed out that Dalsimer has expanded access to the reviewer
                        pool in order to cover target areas.</p>
                    <p>Machak also stated that the Committee’s help was needed to amend the Freedom
                        of Information Act. As it stands, too much time and money are spent on
                        “snapshots,” and those resources could be better used on issues of greater
                        general interest. He indicated that the Executive order engages the
                        Archivist of the United States to make some suggestions on its provisions.
                        He also pointed that the program at State is the only one to hold its own.
                        The Assistant Secretary and the Under Secretary for Management support it
                        and will cooperate with the National Archives.</p>
                    <p>Thessin responded to Kimball’s earlier question by stating that a new
                        procedure would not take 25 years to implement, but would require
                        approximately 5 years to catch up.</p>
                    <p>Leffler raised a question about whether the executive order would be amended
                        to cover documents 25 years old.</p>
                    <p>Thessin replied that documents could remain classified after 25 years for few
                        reasons; for example, documents deemed to contain information that could put
                        the United States at a disadvantage, even if release of the information did
                        not harm U.S. relations with a foreign power. He clarified his point by
                        using the example of documents pertaining to the comprehensive test ban
                        treaty. Although the documents record 25-year old policies, the information
                        they contain could still be relevant to current negotiations, and therefore
                        their release could put the United States at a disadvantage in ongoing
                        talks. He indicated that the Legal Adviser’s Office believed the language on
                        these matters needs to be broadened.</p>
                    <p>Leffler questioned the need to protect documents covering 25-year-old
                        negotiating positions.</p>
                    <p>Comfort noted that if the negotiations are not new and different, but rather
                        a continuation of the negotiation process stretching back over a long period
                        of time, such as the test ban treaty negotiations, the documents need to be
                        protected. Thessin agreed there should be a means to protect such
                        documents.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked what wording State had suggested to cover such
                        situations.</p>
                    <p>Comfort and Thessin explained that the words “ongoing diplomatic activity of
                        the United States” were added.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if a clear and unqualified definition of the word “ongoing”
                        existed or had been established, to which Thessin replied no.</p>
                    <pb n="16" xml:id="pg_16" facs="0019"/>
                    <p>Kimball expressed his view that declassification is an art rather than a
                        science&#x02014;it is subjective and this causes problems. He indicated that
                        by using words such as “ongoing” and “activities,” which are very vague,
                        many documents may remain classified without justification.</p>
                    <p>Nancy Smith also noted that the new executive order would send Presidential
                        material back to the agencies for review.</p>
                    <p>Thessin responded to those comments by pointing out that clear wording will
                        not solve declassification problems, for the review process will always
                        involve judgments.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked if any thought had been given to the procedure or structure for
                        the balancing test requirement.</p>
                    <p>Thessin was not aware of any. Machak indicated that views differed on that
                        topic and that some agencies had expressed concern about it. In any event,
                        the situation depends on the wording in the Executive order in that the
                        reviewer’s decision must be justifiable. In any situation, a reviewer must
                        be able to make a case to support and justify all decisions, and the
                        argument in support of any decision must be able to stand up to the scrutiny
                        of the appeals process.</p>
                    <p>Kimball spoke for all members of the Committee when he stated that the
                        Department will find it useful to consult with members in order to seek
                        their opinions and to help develop procedures regarding the Executive order
                        and its implementation.</p>
                    <p>Thessin welcomed the input from Committee members and others in the scholarly
                        community in order to demonstrate why documents needed to be declassified.
                        He warned against appealing each and every document to the highest levels,
                        however, as being overburdensome and in the end self-defeating. He suggested
                        some selectivity be employed to identify documents needing high-level
                        scrutiny and review.</p>
                    <p rend="center">[End Deliberative Discussion]</p>
                    <p>After reiterating the advantages of early consultation with the Advisory
                        Committee, Kimball inquired into the possibility of acquiring stationery on
                        Department letterhead for use by himself and other members for official
                        correspondence.</p>
                    <p>Thessin pointed to some obvious problems inherent in that request, but
                        indicated he would look into the matter.</p>
                    <p>At approximately 3:15 p.m. the meeting recessed for the afternoon break.</p>
                    <p>Kimball reopened the session at 3:40 p.m. with comments on two matters.
                        First, after discussing the matter of ambiguous equities with Nancy Smith
                        during the immediately preceding break, he suggested that guidelines might
                        be drafted for these equities. These guidelines would be circulated to the
                        other interested agencies. If they all approved, then the matter could be
                        handled in that way. Second, he again raised the clause in the draft
                        executive order that would allow agencies to exempt entire files. If
                        agencies exempted some files in this way, they might never be released. He
                        compared the problem with the British refusal to release intelligence
                        documents. This clause was open to tremendous abuse, he concluded, and he
                        wanted Smith to keep the Committee <pb n="17" xml:id="pg_17" facs="0020"/>
                        continuously informed on how the agencies were using the files exemption.
                        Leffler said he would like a copy of the latest draft executive order.</p>
                    <p>In response to a question by Herring, Kimball said he thought the file
                        exemptions clause would remain in the final executive order. Smith remarked
                        that NARA commented on this files exemption. How damaging it is to release
                        of documents depends on how broadly the agencies utilize it.</p>
                    <p>Leffler then asked what would happen if an agency were not in compliance with
                        the executive order. Marvin Russell commented that nothing would happen, and
                        cited the example of the Carter executive order. Picker said that any
                        penalties would be bureaucratic. The President might deny the agency certain
                        rights subject to litigation.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="report-of-the-subcommittee-on-declassification">
                    <head>Report of the Subcommittee on Declassification</head>
                    <p>Herring reported that his subcommittee discussed Tibet, Japan, Cyprus,
                        Guyana, and Angola. Only Tibet was a problem, he said, but Rosenberg
                        requested a briefing on the others as well. LaFantasie remarked that Cyprus
                        has now been cleared in the Department of State. Herring added that the
                        problem was solved by sending a senior Foreign Service officer, a former
                        Ambassador, to the desk. He persuaded the desk officers to release the
                        documents. He was able to change the officers mindset, perhaps because they
                        spoke the same language. He got good results, and Herring thought this
                        experience was “interesting, significant,” and promised to be helpful for
                        the future.</p>
                    <p>LaFantasie explained that it was Harmon Kirby who went to the European Bureau
                        (EUR), and perhaps because he was a former Ambassador, his involvement “did
                        seem to do the trick.” The desk had earlier refused even to give reasons for
                        its denial of five documents. This informal appeal process is not in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> legislation. He added that Kirby
                        was now working on Angola and he has succeeded in getting the documents
                        cleared by the Portuguese desk in EUR and was now trying to get a favorable
                        decision from the Bureau of African Affairs.</p>
                    <p>Herring continued that the 1964–1968 Cyprus documents now had to go to the
                        CIA. Picker inquired whether the Portuguese desk had equity over documents
                        relating to Angola in the post-colonial era, and LaFantasie affirmed that it
                        did. Nina Noring (HDR) added that Portugal was also currently engaged in
                        mediation efforts in Angola.</p>
                    <p>Herring then turned to the Tibet issue, which, Kimball interjected, the
                        Committee had first raised more than 2 years ago. It too was a CIA question.
                        LaFantasie said that HO had formally appealed two documents that the
                        Committee felt very strongly about. Leffler remarked that the CIA denied
                        this appeal but was willing to talk to the Committee about it. The documents
                        were discussed with the CIA, but nothing further had happened. Kimball noted
                        that the CIA had not answered his letter on the question.</p>
                    <p>The subcommittee agreed to publish the China volume and the Tibet compilation
                        without the deletions in these two documents because the basic story is
                        intact. The deletions are such that the reader of the volume will be able to
                        see what is missing. Schwar interposed that the Tibet compilation
                        constitutes about 10–12 percent of the volume. Kimball added that the CIA
                        position forced on HO is ridiculous, because it fails <pb n="18"
                            xml:id="pg_18" facs="0021"/> to hide successfully what the CIA wants to
                        conceal. None of the Tibet documents was denied in entirety, and a document
                        cleared by CIA showed CIA involvement in Tibet. What the Agency seemed to
                        object to subsequently was certain specific references. In spite of the
                        excisions, the CIA’s role could still be gleaned if one compared these
                        documents to ones that had not been excised.</p>
                    <p>Herring and LaFantasie also noted that the subcommittee did not resolve the
                        issue of the wording in the preface. Herring said he was working on the
                        language, which the CIA would have to approve. When Picker asked why CIA
                        clearance was required, Herschler responded that problems of
                        declassification are described in the prefaces and have to be cleared by the
                        agencies involved. Slany said this was done as a “courtesy,” and the CIA had
                        not objected in the past to <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        prefaces. Kimball said the preface could not be the usual boilerplate, which
                        would not work in this case. Boilerplate language might be all right for
                        volumes that the Committee does not review, but the Committee has a hand in
                        clarifying the language of the prefaces for volumes it does review.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg hoped that the Tibet question could be entirely resolved before the
                        next meeting. All Committee members should also have a chance to look at the
                        excised documents on Japan and the draft prefaces. She wondered how long all
                        this would take. Kimball said he assumed that the Committee would be able to
                        comment on it again. LaFantasie said the China/Tibet volume was way off
                        schedule, and Slany added that the Committee could look at the volume in
                        May. Kimball suggested that all Committee members should look at the Tibet
                        compilation by noon tomorrow (Wednesday). The pages could then be typeset,
                        and the volume could proceed to publication. The preface could be added
                        later. The CIA should not worry as long as the preface was drafted
                        carefully.</p>
                    <p>Committee members expressed interest in reviewing the Tibet documents in the
                        meeting room, and Kimball agreed if it did not take up regular session time.
                        The Committee assented to Leffler’s suggestion that the Committee convene at
                        8:30 a.m. Wednesday. Kimball added that members could also inspect the
                        documents in the HO Office until 5:30 p.m. Tuesday. Hogan asked whether the
                        Committee could also review the three Japan documents. He and Michael
                        Schaller had not yet seen them. Slany and Herschler agreed that this too
                        could be arranged. Hogan then said that he would also like to see a sample
                        of the CIA “bullet” cards. Kimball agreed and asked HO people to bring over
                        “a reasonable sample” for a “peekaboo” session for interested Committee
                        members beginning Wednesday morning at 8:30 a.m.</p>
                    <p>Kimball went on to say that Ken McDonald would appear before the Committee on
                        Wednesday morning. He had heard that McDonald is retiring and would be
                        bringing his replacement with him. The Committee might go into executive
                        session to clear past problems and get off to a good start with Donald
                        Steury, McDonald’s successor.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="report-on-the-visit-to-the-national-security-council">
                    <head>Report on the Visit to the National Security Council</head>
                    <p>Leffler then described the meeting of the subcommittee at the National
                        Security Council. There was discussion of the small “institutional”
                        collection of pre-1969 NSC <pb n="19" xml:id="pg_19" facs="0022"/> documents
                        at the National Archives. Langbart said that this collection included only a
                        small part of the documents from the Kennedy and Johnson Presidencies. Davis
                        and Leffler said they were told there were 15 boxes of NSC material at NARA.
                        No guidelines existed to review the documents for declassification, and
                        there was a backlog of 3,000 FOIA requests at the NSC. Leffler said the NSC
                        told the subcommittee that NARA had not asked the NSC for guidelines.</p>
                    <p>Marvin Russell interjected that NARA had often requested guidelines from the
                        NSC, but after 15 years of non-response had given up. Davis added that Bill
                        Leary had only been at the NSC for one year and had previously been at NARA.
                        Leffler said the NSC had told the subcommittee that there could be no
                        declassification of “institutional” NSC records until there were guidelines.
                        Picker said the subcommittee was also told that even if the NSC was asked
                        for guidelines, it did not have the resources to develop them. Davis said it
                        was a Catch-22 problem, with Leary saying that there was no solution.</p>
                    <p>Smith proposed a joint NARA–State letter to the NSC requesting guidelines.
                        When Picker noted that there was a legal device whereby it was possible to
                        draft a “continuous request” letter, Davis affirmed that such a letter would
                        act like the redial button on telephones. Smith indicated that the NSC had
                        in effect responded that it was a question of insufficient resources.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg then asked whether the State guidelines could be the basis for NSC
                        guidelines. Of course, the NSC would have to approve them. Kimball noted
                        that the Committee had no jurisdiction over other agencies, but Picker
                        pointed out that the Committee could say that all the other agencies have
                        guidelines. Smith repeated that the NSC tells the Presidential Libraries to
                        send White House documents to the other agencies that have equities and not
                        to submit them for NSC review. The Libraries have done this, but the NSC
                        wants all “institutional” NSC documents (numbered NSAMs, memoranda, etc.) to
                        be submitted to the NSC. Russell added that the NARA staff does not have the
                        documents, only the numbers. Even the lists of documents had been taken away
                        from him.</p>
                    <p>Kimball then inquired whether even the numbers were classified, and whether
                        this problem has any effect on the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        series. Keefer said “no,” and heads shook around the room. Humphrey noted
                        that there were virtually no numbered NSC memoranda for the Johnson years.
                        Langbart added that for the JFK–LBJ Presidencies there were no background
                        files or interagency input to the NSC papers. When Leffler asked if NSAMs
                        still go back to the NSC for review, Regina Greenwell replied “yes,” but
                        only after other agencies had reviewed them. Leffler believed that if the
                        situation was good at the Presidential Libraries, then the Committee did not
                        have to worry. Smith said that when the NSC was asked for guidelines for the
                        Johnson Library documents, it was clear from Leary’s letter of 2 weeks ago
                        that the Library would get none for the NSAMs.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked whether the NSC might not scramble to give NARA guidelines for
                        declassification authority to all NSC materials when they see all the NSC
                        documents coming to the NSC for declassification review. Smith concluded
                        that the NSC still <pb n="20" xml:id="pg_20" facs="0023"/> wanted the NSC
                        “institutional” documents to go from the Presidential Libraries back to the
                        NSC, but that this was only a small portion of NSC materials.</p>
                    <p>Kimball inquired whether the DOD guidelines had been extended, and Rosenberg
                        replied that they were being worked on.</p>
                    <p>Slany then distributed to the Committee copies of the latest CD-ROM put out
                        by the PA Bureau, and he announced that the May disc will also include a <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume.</p>
                    <p>At 4:30 p.m., the Committee went into executive session.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="closed-session-february-15">
                <head>CLOSED SESSION, February 15</head>
                <div xml:id="comments-by-the-cia-historian-on-access-to-cia-records">
                    <head>Comments by the CIA Historian on Access to CIA Records</head>
                    <p>Kimball called the meeting to order at 9:15 a.m. He noted that the only item
                        on the agenda was the question of access to CIA records. He observed that
                        Ken McDonald and Donald Steury from the CIA History Staff were present and
                        invited McDonald to open with any remarks he wished.</p>
                    <p>McDonald noted that the Committee had expressed its concern over the
                        provenance issue at its luncheon meeting with CIA Executive Director Leo
                        Hazlewood. McDonald, commenting on proposals included in Slany’s January
                        1995 letter on the citations to CIA documents in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> volumes, stated that they had an agreement in principle
                        that <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> could include job numbers in
                        document provenance identifications, but he did not yet have a formal letter
                        on the subject signed by Hazlewood.</p>
                    <p>McDonald stated that his office had been working with HO on questions of
                        access. He stated that Don Steury will be taking over the responsibility
                        formerly held by Mary McAuliffe (former Deputy Chief of the History Staff)
                        of coordinating access for HO historians for <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> purposes. He noted that two senior Foreign Service
                        officers assigned to HO, William Marsh and Gerald Monroe, have been going
                        through the 1954 Guatemala documents. There is a massive amount of material.
                        He stated that HO historians have made copies of a portion of a card index
                        to agency records at the History Staff office, which he said was one of the
                        best finding aids to CIA records. He said that some of the information on
                        the cards was very sensitive, in spite of its age, and noted that people in
                        the Operations Directorate tend to think that age makes no difference in
                        determining sensitivity.</p>
                    <p>McDonald stated that he will be retiring in September. He will be with the
                        History Staff until May. His successor is not yet selected.</p>
                    <p>Kimball stated that the Committee recognized that McDonald was in an awkward
                        position between the Committee and the CIA leadership on matters of access
                        and stated that a lot of progress had been made in the last couple of
                        years.</p>
                    <p>McDonald stated that there was a practical problem of getting agency records
                        organized so the historians can get at them. CIA records were not organized
                        for purposes of historical research. We can’t resolve all problems of access
                        at any one time.</p>
                    <pb n="21" xml:id="pg_21" facs="0024"/>
                    <p>Leffler presented the report of the subcommittee on access, which had met
                        with HO staff members and senior FSOs Marsh and Monroe. He stated that Marsh
                        and Monroe had reported that they were going through 250 boxes of documents
                        on U.S. policy toward Guatemala in 1954, consisting largely of trivia. So
                        far they had found six documents which might be said to relate to policy.
                        They were using a study by Nick Cullather (former member of the CIA History
                        Staff), which was helpful, and using his citations. They had seen a document
                        from the station that said everything had been burned.</p>
                    <p>The subcommittee had also seen an HO memo reporting that CIA History Staff
                        had found the papers of Richard Bissell. When HO historians researched the
                        Bay of Pigs in 1992 and 1993, they had been assured that all records on that
                        subject had been made available. The subcommittee wondered how the newly
                        discovered Bissell papers could have been overlooked. What are the prospects
                        that other such collections might be discovered? What if HO gave the History
                        Staff a list of people who played important roles at CIA?</p>
                    <p>McDonald said this was the first he had heard about the Bissell papers. Who
                        had discovered them and where? It was explained that CIA staff historian
                        Mike Warner had found them. McDonald stated that a couple of years ago
                        Bissell was at the History Staff office. They had worked with him to try to
                        find his records but had not found them.</p>
                    <p>McDonald stated that the CIA has no central register of records. Each
                        directorate has its own system. Records were deliberately compartmentalized.
                        Plans (Operations) is most difficult, because they are most
                        compartmentalized. He was sure there were no boxes labeled “Bissell Papers.”
                        If Mike Warner has turned up the Bissell records, it was probably by rooting
                        through a lot of files. The chances of finding other such collections are
                        not good. McCone kept excellent records, but other DCIs on the whole have
                        not done so.</p>
                    <p>Leffler wondered if it might be useful for someone like Warner to come and
                        talk to the Committee about how he goes about locating records. One of the
                        things HO needs to do is to identify the subjects it is working on in ways
                        that are helpful to the History Staff. He didn’t think the index cards
                        looked very helpful.</p>
                    <p>McDonald agreed that it would be helpful if Warner were there. He thought the
                        index cards were helpful. He said that if a historian did a study on a
                        particular subject, the records he used were filed as a group. The cards are
                        indexed to the source documents.</p>
                    <p>Rosenberg asked if HO historians had access to the studies. McDonald said
                        yes. He stated that there are about 600 studies, including many station
                        histories and histories of CIA components. They vary greatly in quality and
                        were confined to the period of 1947 to 1967, although some extend further.
                        There are thousands of cards pointing to documents used in the studies.</p>
                    <p>Leffler asked if HO historians could see the documents? McDonald said yes, if
                        the documents can be found. Schwar asked whether the cards can be used to
                        locate the documents. McDonald said there were numbers on the upper right
                        hand corners of the cards that indicate the location.</p>
                    <pb n="22" xml:id="pg_22" facs="0025"/>
                    <p>Kimball asked if HO historians had access to the cards. A number of HO
                        historians indicated varying degrees of access.</p>
                    <p>Kimball suggested that the History Staff put together a list of finding aids.
                        McDonald agreed that a list would be useful. He stated that the more we
                        could deal with information systematically the better.</p>
                    <p>Kimball asked whether the History Staff had such information available for
                        use in training its own new historians.</p>
                    <p>McDonald replied that the staff is small. When a historian starts work on a
                        new project, he goes and talks to the Information Management office in that
                        directorate. He thought development of a cumulative list of sources was a
                        good idea. He stated that HO historians theoretically have access to all
                        records; it’s a matter of finding them. For any topic, you need specialized
                        information. The CIA historians are learning as they go along; with each new
                        topic they discover new records. The body of knowledge rests with the staff
                        historians.</p>
                    <p>Leffler asked if the History Staff records this information anywhere.
                        McDonald replied that they had not done so in the past, but that it might be
                        very useful.</p>
                    <p>Schwar asked if records schedules of CIA records might be helpful, whether
                        the History Staff has access to them, and whether HO historians could get
                        access to them. McDonald said they are helpful; they show job numbers. The
                        History Staff has access to them, and HO historians could get access to
                        them. Geyer asked if this would apply to files that are still active.
                        McDonald said they have records schedules for active files too. He thought
                        it unlikely that such files would be helpful to HO; operational offices
                        don’t keep files around for archival purposes.</p>
                    <p>Geyer asked if the index cards extended into the Nixon period. McDonald
                        replied that they extended very little into the Nixon period. He stated that
                        the CIA Executive Director from 1967 to 1973 had tasked all major offices
                        with producing histories of the period 1947–1967. When Colby became
                        Executive Director in 1973 he stopped the project. Therefore the card file
                        covers the 1947–1967 period but very little afterward. These histories are
                        mainly institutional histories, but there are station histories.</p>
                    <p>Howland asked if there was a central list of station histories. She referred
                        to one in which she had seen a reference but which Warner had been unable to
                        locate. McDonald said the histories were done in two copies. The original
                        went to the component, and in most cases, a copy went to the History Staff.
                        The History Staff does not have all the studies. Most of the ones it does
                        not have are from the Science and Technology Directorate. It could be that
                        the study in question was never completed.</p>
                    <p>At this point the session concluded, and the Committee went into executive
                        session to meet with HO staff members for off-the-record comments and to
                        consider its recommendations and actions for this meeting. The executive
                        session concluded at 1:20 p.m.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
