<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="complete">Telegram From the Embassy in Greece to the Department of State,
               August 2002</title>
            <title type="short">Telegram From Embassy Athens, 2002</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <date type="posted" when="2013-12-09">December 9, 2013</date>
             <date type="created" when="2002-08-19">August 19, 2002</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>A scan of the original document is available for download (<ref
                  target="2002-08-19-athens-02867.pdf">PDF</ref>, 208 KB, 5pp.)</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Source: Department of State, State Archiving System, 2002 ATHENS
               002867. The cable was sent Priority to the Department and for information to the
               Consulate in Thessaloniki and the Embassies in Nicosia and Ankara. The requested
               distribution included Grecinos, Gollner-Sweet, and R. Glover in EUR/SE; L. Schwartz
               and M. Toner in EUR/PA; J. Miller in H; and M. Makri in Thessaloniki PA.</hi></p>
         <p>Cited in <hi rend="italic">Toward “Thorough,
                  Accurate, and Reliable”: A History of the Foreign Relations of the United States
                  Series</hi>, Chapter 12, <ref target="../chapter-12#fn43">Footnote 43</ref></p>
         <div type="document">
            <head>Telegram From the Embassy in Greece to the Department of State</head>
            <dateline>Athens, August 19, 2002, 1425Z</dateline>
            <p>02867. Subject: Release of FRUS Volume Elicits Mild Media Interest and Questions
               About Lacunae</p>
            <p>1. Summary. The 15 August release of the Foreign Relations of the United States
               volume pertaining to Greece, Turkey and Cyprus in the period 1964-68 drew secondary
               attention from TV, radio and print media. All media noted that the USG was fully
               aware of possible coup attempts during this period of political ferment, but seemed
               to display “apathy and indifference” to then King Constantine's request for US
               military support for a coup of his own. The media noted that American authorities
               feared that Andreas Papandreou's political ascent would result in a more
               anti-American course, and said the documents showed then-US Ambassador Phillips
               Talbot unaware that the CIA station was in touch with the Greek colonels who plotted
               the successful coup d'etat in April, 1967. Despite this material, most media were
               rather disappointed by the contents of the volume, and seemed more intrigued by the
               USG bureaucratic in-fighting which delayed the release of a volume printed in 2000.
               All media asserted that the USG gave the go-ahead in the wake of recent arrests of
               members of the Greek terrorist group 17 November. End Summary.</p>
            <p>Who Knew What, and When</p>
            <p>2. The 777-page volume was released on a Greek holiday, so it took until Sunday and
               even Monday for most papers to sink their teeth into the contents. Radio and TV news
               bulletins carried highlights of the report as a secondary item in their Sunday
               bulletins, and noted the points cited above. The two largest TV stations, Mega and
               Antenna, ran voice-overs of “revelations” in the FRUS volume over historical photos
               from mid-1960s and the coup d'etat. Some reports noted that Talbot seemed to be
               expecting the King to engineer a coup in cooperation with the generals, and was
               somewhat shocked when it turned out to be the colonels who were responsible. All
               newspapers, including pro-government, anti-American Eleftherotypia and conservative,
               pro-main opposition Eleftheros Typos, pointed out that the documents show the CIA
               operated under no such misapprehension, and was “fully aware of what the colonels
               were going to do.” In a front-page story, independent, respected Kathimerini wrote
               that even those US officials blind-sided by the coup were reassured by the pro-US
               sympathies of Col. Papadopoulos, who had served as a liaison with DIA, and of Col.
               Pattakos, “who had relatives in the US Army.”</p>
            <p>Reasons for Delay</p>
            <p>3. All media devoted equal attention to the delay in the release of the volume. On
               Sunday 18 August, extensive inside reports in To Vima and Kathimerini claimed that
               CIA authorities had delayed release of the published volume in the fear that there
               would be reprisals against American officials currently in Greece. The two papers
               said there was considerable wrangling between the State Department, represented by
               then US Ambassador Burns and by historian Jim Miller, and the CIA over both what the
               volume should and should not contain, and the date of its release. Even though only
               0.04 [percent] of the declassified documents were censored, the 19 August edition of
               Eleftherotypia divined a suspicious number of holes in the account, and ran the
               sub-head “the Americans are hiding the role of their secret services.” To Vima noted
               that the volume's release had been carefully timed to coincide with the sleepiest
               time of the summer: August 15 is a holiday and traditionally the high point of the
               Greek summer, with most of the country at the beach.</p>
            <p>4. Most electronic and print media, still awash in non-stop coverage of the cases of
               the arrested terrorists belonging to the 17 November group, elided between the two
               stories, and claimed, on the basis of circumstantial evidence alone, that the CIA
               lifted its objections to the release of the report once the GOG had “broken” 17N.
               Thus ended a deadlock that began when the declassification project ended in 1999.</p>
            <p>Government Reaction</p>
            <p>5. Back from the beach and in typical form was government spokesman Christos
               Protopappas, who said “none of these revelations come as big news to us. It was
               well-known that the secret services of certain countries were involved in what
               happened during that time. It is no coincidence that President Clinton, on his visit
               here, apologized for the role those services played in creating and in sustaining the
               junta.” (Comment: this is a deliberate misreading of Clinton's far more nuanced
               statement in November, 1999.)</p>
            <p>Is That All There Is?</p>
            <p>6. Comment. Overall (and fortunately) there seemed to be a sense of disappointment at
               the contents of the FRUS. The two year delay in the volume's release and the
               conspiratorial bent of most Greek media had tempted readers to believe there would be
               new evidence of skullduggery and malfeasance. Instead, as an insightful op-ed piece
               in Kathimerini (8/19) noted, it showed the disorganization and vanity of the Greek
               political establishment, and that establishment's responsibility for allowing the
               junta to remain in power for seven years. “No one has ever accepted that the old
               regime collapsed because of the inability of the politicians who comprised it, given
               that all those who survived its collapse, with the exception of King Constantine,
               resurfaced to build the post-1974 political system,” wrote diplomatic editor Costas
               Iordanides.</p>
            <p>7. Indeed, in a country where paranoia is as rife as it is in Greece, it may be the
               wisest course of action to be as open as possible with the release of declassified,
               archival material. In this case, doing so allowed us to map out the limits of what US
               involvement in Greece's domestic affairs has been, and to advertise, by example, the
               openness of American political culture. Releasing the documents as promptly and as
               unabridged as possible helps us in our continuing campaign to “normalize” the
               Greek-US relationship and reduce the level of anti-Americanism based on suspicion of
               US policy interests in Greece. End Comment.</p>
            <p>Miller</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
