<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<event>
    <id>1</id>
    <title>Panel on FRUS and Responsible Transparency at American Historical Association (AHA) 2014
        Annual Meeting</title>
    <created>2013-12-09</created>
    <icon>
        <width>150px</width>
        <height>150px</height>
        <url>http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/aha-2014-logo.png</url>
        <alttext>Still image of AHA 2014 Annual Meeting Logo</alttext>
    </icon>
    <link>/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#aha-2014-frus-responsible-transparency</link>
    <link-alttext>More information about this event</link-alttext>
    <event-type>Public Presentation</event-type>
    <event-date>2014-01-04</event-date>
    <teaser>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#aha-2014-frus-responsible-transparency">“Historicizing the Debate about
                Responsible Transparency: The Past and Future of the <em>Foreign Relations of the
                    United States</em> Series”</a> (a panel at the American Historical Association
            Annual Meeting)</div>
    </teaser>
    <full-description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="aha-open-secrets">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="https://aha.confex.com/aha/2014/webprogram/Session10069.html" title="Link to AHA Annual Meeting homepage">
                <img width="150px" height="150px" style="border:1px black solid" src="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/aha-2014-logo.png" alt="AHA 2014 Annual Meeting Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="https://aha.confex.com/aha/2014/webprogram/Session10069.html">“Historicizing the Debate about Responsible
                    Transparency: The Past and Future of the <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em>
                    Series”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;">American Historical Association Annual
                Meeting<br/>January 4, 2014</p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Chair <ul>
                        <li>Stephen Randolph, U.S. Department of State</li>
                    </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Panel 
                        <ul>
                            <li>Steven Aftergood, Project on Government Secrecy, Federation of
                                American Scientists</li>
                            <li>Brian Balogh, University of Virginia</li>
                            <li>Joshua Botts, Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                            <li>Malcolm Byrne, National Security Archive, George Washington
                                University</li>
                            <li>Richard H. Immerman, Temple University</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>On January 4, 2014, Office of the Historian staff members will participate in a
                roundtable discussion at the American Historical Association Annual Meeting on
                “historicizing the debate about responsible transparency: the past and future of the
                Foreign Relations series.” Informed by new historical research, this discussion will
                provide an opportunity to consider the value ascribed to openness in government
                alongside the efforts made to protect sensitive information. Participants Steven
                Aftergood, Brian Balogh, Joshua Botts, Malcolm Byrne, Richard Immerman, and Stephen
                Randolph will comment upon the ways in which the history of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> clarifies our
                understanding of the debate about transparency and secrecy and illuminates broader
                themes in American history. Following these comments, the roundtable will engage the
                audience in a wider discussion about the past and future of responsible
                transparency.</p>
        </div>
    </full-description>
</event>