<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<event>
    <id>3</id>
    <title>Panels on Crisis and Change in FRUS at the Society for History in the Federal Government (SHFG) 2011 Annual
    Meeting</title>
    <created>2011-02-15</created>
    <icon>
        <width>150px</width>
        <height>36px</height>
        <url>http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/shfg-logo.jpg</url>
        <alttext>SHFG Logo</alttext>
    </icon>
    <link>/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#shfg-crisis-change</link>
    <link-alttext>Link to SHFG Annual Meeting homepage</link-alttext>
    <event-type>Conference</event-type>
    <event-date>2011-03-31</event-date>
    <teaser>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#shfg-crisis-change">“Crisis and Change in the <em>Foreign
                Relations of the United States</em> Series, 1861-2011”</a>
            <br/> (A panel at the Society for History in the Federal Government Annual
            Meeting)</div>
    </teaser>
    <full-description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="shfg-crisis-change">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://shfg.org/shfg/feature-archive/conference-registration/" title="Link to SHFG Annual Meeting homepage">
                <img width="150px" height="36px" style="border:1px black solid" src="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/shfg-logo.jpg" alt="SHFG Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://shfg.org/shfg/feature-archive/conference-registration/">“Crisis
                    and Change in the <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> Series,
                    1861-2011”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A panel at the Society
                for History in the Federal Government Annual Meeting<br/>March 31, 2011</p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Chair <ul>
                            <li>William B. McAllister, Ph.D. Special Projects Director, Office
                            of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Presenters <ul>
                            <li>Aaron Marrs, Ph.D., Research Historian, Office of the Historian,
                            U.S. Department of State</li>
                            <li>Peter Cozzens, Special Assistant to The Historian, Office of the
                            Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                            <li>Joshua Botts, Ph.D., Research Historian, Office of the
                            Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>The <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> (FRUS) series, the official
                documentary record of U.S. foreign policy, enters its 150th year of continuous
                publication in 2011. The Department of State’s Office of the Historian, which
                publishes the FRUS series, is conducting significant new research about the
                historical development of the series. To commemorate the FRUS sesquicentennial,
                we propose to share the most significant early results of this research at the
                2011 SHFG Annual Conference. This panel will shed important new light on
                multiple aspects of 18th through 20th century history and historiography,
                including pre-1861 releases of foreign policy documents, relations between the
                legislative and executive branches, conceptions about “openness in government”
                in a 19th century context, the growing professionalization of both historians
                and the Foreign Service, the tension between the rising status of the United
                States in world affairs and the desire to promote informed public debate through
                release of foreign policy documents, the international ramifications of
                revelations that have an impact on other governments, and evolving political
                factors that have shaped and continue to shape the compilation and publication
                of FRUS volumes. We also envision allotting sufficient time after the
                presentations to engage in question-and-answer and general discussion with the
                audience about issues of interest to them. </p>
        </div>
    </full-description>
</event>