<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<event>
    <id>4</id>
    <title>Panels on FRUS in the 19th and 20th Centuries at the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations (SHAFR) 2011 Annual
    Meeting</title>
    <created>2011-04-01</created>
    <icon>
        <width>150px</width>
        <height>116px</height>
        <url>http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/shafr-logo.gif</url>
        <alttext>SHAFR Logo</alttext>
    </icon>
    <link>/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#shafr-nineteenth</link>
    <link-alttext>More information about this event</link-alttext>
    <event-type>Conference</event-type>
    <event-date>2011-06-24</event-date>
    <teaser>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#shafr-nineteenth">“FRUS In The World, Part One: New
                        Research on the <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> series,
                        The Long Nineteenth Century”</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#shafr-twentieth">“FRUS In The World, Part Two: New
                        Research on the <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> series,
                        The Twentieth Century in Comparative Perspective”</a>
                </li>
            </ol> (Panels at the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations Annual
            Meeting) </div>
    </teaser>
    <full-description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="shafr-nineteenth">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://www.shafr.org/conferences/annual/2011-annual-meeting/" title="Link to SHFG Annual Meeting homepage">
                <img width="150px" height="116px" style="border:1px black solid" src="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/shafr-logo.gif" alt="SHAFR Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://www.shafr.org/conferences/annual/2011-annual-meeting/">“FRUS In
                    The World, Part One: New Research on the <em>Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</em> series, The Long Nineteenth Century”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A panel at the Society
                for Historians of American Foreign Relations Annual Meeting<br/>June 24, 2011 </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Chair <ul>
                            <li>William B. McAllister, Ph.D., Special Projects Director, Office
                            of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Presenters <ul>
                            <li>Aaron Marrs, Ph.D., Research Historian, Office of the Historian,
                            U.S. Department of State</li>
                            <li>Peter Cozzens, Special Assistant to The Historian, Office of the
                            Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Commentators <ul>
                            <li>Howard Jones, Ph.D., University of Alabama</li>
                            <li>J.C.A Stagg, Ph.D, University of Virginia</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>As part of the sesquicentennial commemoration of the FRUS series, the Office of
                the Historian has launched a major research initiative to examine numerous
                questions about the series that have remained unexamined for 150 years. The most
                significant results of this research will be revealed in the two sessions we
                propose to present at the 2011 SHAFR annual meeting. Why was the series launched
                in 1861, and how was it shaped by previous public releases of foreign policy
                documents? Why did the series continue after its ostensible reason for
                publication, the Civil War, ended? What controversies surrounded the compilation
                and publication of the series in the later 19th century? This panel will shed
                important new light on multiple aspects of 19th century U.S. history and
                historiography, including relations between the legislative and executive
                branches, conceptions about “openness in government” in a nineteenth-century
                context, issues of professional expertise and politicization involved in
                producing FRUS volumes, and important foreign policy issues of the era. In order
                to explore this topic thoroughly, we anticipate that each presenter will speak
                for 30 minutes, followed by substantial remarks from the two commentators, with
                sufficient time reserved for the audience to participate in a larger discussion
                of the issues raised. </p>
            <div>
                <h4>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus">“Publicizing Foreign
                        Relations in Time of War: The Foundation of the Foreign Relations of the
                        United States Series”</a>
                </h4>
                <p>Aaron W. Marrs</p>
                <p>An examination of early Foreign Relations of the United States volumes gives
                    us an opportunity to investigate how the federal government presented its
                    foreign policy to the American people, and how the populace reacted to
                    foreign policy. Using the volumes themselves, Department of State documents,
                    and private papers, this paper will demonstrate that FRUS was composed for a
                    domestic (not international) audience and constitutes an example of the
                    federal balance of powers. This paper will shed light on FRUS’s early
                    history, contrast the volumes with the ad hoc publications which preceded
                    them, and explore the contemporary implications of its publication. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <h4>“Charming Volumes for Summer Outings”: FRUS and the Transformation of
                    American Foreign Policy, 1870-1900</h4>
                <p>Peter Cozzens</p>
                <p>This paper will examine the role the FRUS series played during the
                    transformative years of American Foreign Policy from 1870-1900. It will
                    place especial emphasis on Congressional, public, and foreign reception of
                    the series and the series’ impact on American foreign policy and
                    transparency in government. Also examined will be the quality and
                    completeness of the volumes, particularly with respect to salient policy
                    issues and crises. The paper will be based on research principally in
                    government documents, private papers, and period newspapers. </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="shafr-twentieth">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://www.shafr.org/conferences/annual/2011-annual-meeting/" title="Link to SHFG Annual Meeting homepage">
                <img width="150px" height="116px" style="border:1px black solid" src="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/shafr-logo.gif" alt="SHAFR Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://www.shafr.org/conferences/annual/2011-annual-meeting/">“FRUS In
                    The World, Part Two: New Research on the <em>Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</em> series, The Twentieth Century in Comparative
                    Perspective”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A panel at the Society
                for Historians of American Foreign Relations Annual Meeting<br/>June 24,
                2011</p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Chair <ul>
                            <li>Michael Hogan, Ph.D., President of the University of
                            Illinois</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Presenters <ul>
                            <li>Joshua Botts, Ph.D., Research Historian, Office of the
                            Historian, U.S. Department of State</li>
                            <li>Sacha Zala Ph.D., Director, Diplomatic Documents of Switzerland,
                            Swiss Academy of Humanities and Social Sciences</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                    <li>Commentators <ul>
                            <li>Richard Immerman, Ph.D., Temple University</li>
                            <li>Elizabeth Cobbs Hoffman, Ph.D., San Diego State University</li>
                        </ul>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>As part of the sesquicentennial commemoration of the FRUS series, the Office of
                the Historian has launched a major research initiative to examine numerous
                questions about the series that have remained unexamined for 150 years. The most
                significant results of this research will be revealed in the two sessions we
                propose to present at the 2011 SHAFR annual meeting. This panel will shed
                important new light on multiple aspects of 20th century U.S. history, including
                the growing professionalization of both the historical profession and the
                Foreign Service, the tension between the rising status of the United States in
                world affairs and the desire to promote informed public debate through release
                of foreign policy documents, the international ramifications of revelations that
                impact other governments, and political factors that can shape the compilation
                and publication of FRUS volumes. This panel will also feature an important
                international comparative perspective by including the prominent Swiss scholar
                Sacha Zala, who has examined how several European governments have dealt with
                many of these same issues. In order to explore this topic thoroughly, we
                anticipate that each presenter will speak for 30 minutes, followed by
                substantial remarks from the two commentators, with sufficient time reserved for
                the audience to participate in a larger discussion of the issues raised. </p>
            <div>
                <h4>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/politics-of-the-yalta-frus">“Out of the Frying
                        Pan Into the Fire”: The Politics of the Yalta FRUS</a>
                </h4>
                <p>Joshua Botts</p>
                <p>This paper examines the origins, compilation, reception, and consequences of
                    the Yalta FRUS volume. The Yalta volume was notable for several reasons. It
                    not only sparked intense public controversy upon its 1955 release, but it
                    also represented the culmination of the professionalization of FRUS that
                    began in the 1920s and introduced methodological changes that transformed
                    the compilation and scope of the FRUS series during the postwar period. The
                    paper uses Department of State and Congressional records, personal
                    manuscript collections, and newspapers to examine issues of domestic and
                    bureaucratic politics, diplomacy, and national security as FRUS entered the
                    Cold War era. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <h4>“The War of Documents” and the Professionalization of the Editor’s Work: A
                    Comparative View</h4>
                <p>Sacha Zala</p>
                <p>This paper will place the FRUS series in comparative international
                    perspective by examining similar issues that have arisen in European
                    official publications of foreign policy documents. Topics will include how
                    the FRUS series impacted, and was impacted by, the “War Guilt Controversy”
                    of the 1920s; controversies surrounding the publication of FRUS volumes on
                    the Paris Peace Conferences; the use of captured German records as a Cold
                    War propaganda tool; and general observations about developing professional
                    standards for historians and government employees surrounding the use and
                    release of sensitive foreign policy documents. </p>
            </div>
        </div>
    </full-description>
</event>