<event>
    <id>5</id>
    <title>Public Presentations on FRUS at the New York Public Library (NYPL)</title>
    <created>2011-08-08</created>
    <icon>
        <width>150px</width>
        <height>96px</height>
        <url>http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/nypl-logo.jpg</url>
        <alttext>NYPL Logo</alttext>
    </icon>
    <link>/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#nypl</link>
    <link-alttext>More information about this event</link-alttext>
    <event-type>Public Presentation</event-type>
    <event-date>2011-10-12</event-date>
    <teaser>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#nypl-using-frus">“New Perspectives on Postcolonial
                        History: A Workshop on Using <em>FRUS</em> in the 21st Century”</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#nypl-cold-war">“Out of the Frying Pan Into the
                        Fire”: A Conversation about Security and Transparency in the Cold War
                        Era <em>Foreign Relations</em> Series”</a>
                </li>
            </ol> (Presentations at the New York Public Library) </div>
    </teaser>
    <full-description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="nypl-using-frus">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://www.nypl.org/events/classes/2011/10/12/new-perspectives-postcolonial-history-workshop-using-foreign-relations-uni?nref=62452" title="Link to NYPL event info">
                <img width="150px" height="96px" style="border:1px black solid" src="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/nypl-logo.jpg" alt="NYPL Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://www.nypl.org/events/classes/2011/10/12/new-perspectives-postcolonial-history-workshop-using-foreign-relations-uni?nref=62452">“New Perspectives on Postcolonial History: A Workshop on Using
                    <em>FRUS</em> in the 21st Century”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A presentation at the New
                York Public Library<br/>October 12, 2011, 3 p.m.</p>
            <p>This workshop on researching the postwar history of decolonization, nationalist
                struggles, and identity will demonstrate how to utilize the <em>Foreign
                    Relations of the United States</em> series for non-diplomatic history
                topics. Office of the Historian staff will also provide an overview of NARA and
                other available on-line resources, address more traditional uses of
                <em>FRUS</em>, and demonstrate the research capabilities of <a href="http://history.state.gov">history.state.gov</a>. Participants will
                have access to computers and will be encouraged to search/browse the site and
                consult with Office of the Historian staff regarding their research
                interests.</p>
        </div>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="nypl-cold-war">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://www.nypl.org/events/programs/2011/10/12/%E2%80%9Cout-frying-pan-fire%E2%80%9D-conversation-about-security-and-transparency-cold-w?nref=62451" title="Link to NYPL event info"/>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://www.nypl.org/events/programs/2011/10/12/%E2%80%9Cout-frying-pan-fire%E2%80%9D-conversation-about-security-and-transparency-cold-w?nref=62451">“Out of the Frying Pan Into the Fire”: A Conversation about Security and
                    Transparency in the Cold War Era <em>Foreign Relations</em> Series”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A presentation at the New
                York Public Library<br/>October 12, 2011, 6 p.m.</p>
            <p>The <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> series, the official
                documentary record of United States foreign policy and diplomatic activity, has
                embodied the Department of State’s commitment to responsible transparency since
                1861. The evolution of the series during the twentieth century, particularly
                debates in the 1950s surrounding the release of the 1945 Yalta Conference volume
                (and those covering other wartime conferences), illuminates historical debates
                within the United States Government over secrecy versus transparency in the
                realm of diplomacy and national security and tensions between Congress and the
                Executive Branch in conducting foreign policy. Dr. Josh Botts of the Department
                of State’s Office of the Historian and Susan Butler, distinguished historian and
                biographer, will discuss how the story of the Yalta <em>FRUS</em> volume
                reflected the interplay of partisan impulses, national security imperatives, and
                bureaucratic politics in the 1950s.</p>
            <p><span style="color: #911625; text-transform: uppercase;">Update</span>: An audio recording of this event is available from the <a
                href="http://www.nypl.org/audiovideo/out-frying-pan-fire%E2%80%9D-conversation-about-security-and-transparency-cold-war-era-foreign-re"
                >NYPL homepage</a>.</p>
        </div>
    </full-description>
</event>