<event>
    <id>7</id>
    <title>Panel Discussion on <em>FRUS</em> at the Wilson Center</title>
    <created>2011-11-07</created>
    <icon>
        <width>150px</width>
        <height>114px</height>
        <url>//s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus150/wilson-center-logo.png</url>
        <alttext>Wilson Center Logo</alttext>
    </icon>
    <link>/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#wilson-center</link>
    <link-alttext>More information about this event</link-alttext>
    <event-type>Public Presentation</event-type>
    <event-date>2012-02-02</event-date>
    <teaser>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a href="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/events#wilson-center">“<em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> Series: SALT I, 1969–1972”</a>
            <br/> (Panel Discussion at the Wilson Center) </div>
    </teaser>
    <full-description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" id="wilson-center">
            <a style="float:right" class="not-external" href="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/event/foreign-relations-the-united-states-series-salt-i-1969%E2%80%931972" title="Link to Wilson Center event info">
                <img width="150px" height="114px" style="border:1px black solid" src="//s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus150/wilson-center-logo.png" alt="Wilson Center Logo"/>
            </a>
            <h3>
                <a href="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/event/foreign-relations-the-united-states-series-salt-i-1969%E2%80%931972">“<em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> Series: SALT I, 1969–1972”</a>
            </h3>
            <p style="font-size: 0.825em; text-transform: uppercase;"> A panel discussion at the Wilson Center<br/>February 2, 2012, 3:30-5 p.m.</p>
            <p>The Nuclear Proliferation International History Project in collaboration with the
                U.S. Department of State's Office of the Historian presents a panel discussion on
                the latest volume in the <em>Foreign Relations of the United States</em> Series, 1969–1976,
                Volume XXXII, SALT I, 1969–1972. Speakers will include: Erin Mahan, chief historian
                of the Office of the Secretary of Defense, Michael Krepon, co-founder and senior
                associate at Stimson and Amb. Raymond L. Garthoff, senior fellow at the Brookings
                Institution, and former member of the SALT negotiating team.</p>
            <p>The Strategic Arms Limitation Talks produced a series of comprehensive arms control
                agreements between the United States and the Soviet Union that for the first time
                limited the deployment of ballistic missiles and anti-ballistic missile systems.
                Commonly referred to as “SALT I,” the agreements were signed by President Richard
                Nixon and the General Secretary of the Soviet Union Leonid Brezhnev at the Moscow
                Summit in May 1972. This volume documents the negotiations leading up to the
                agreement, the internal deliberations among U.S. policy makers, and reveals the play
                of political and national security considerations that factored into U.S.
                negotiating positions and policy decisions.</p>
            <p>Tim McDonnell, program associate in the Wilson Center's Nuclear Proliferation
                International History Project will chair the event.</p>
        </div>
    </full-description>
</event>