<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Secretary Kellogg’s “Principles to Guide the Editing of
                    ‘Foreign Relations’” and Cover Memoranda</title>
                <title type="short">“Principles to Guide the Editing of ‘Foreign Relations’”</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-27">October 27, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This document was released in conjunction with <ref
                    target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/eureka-the-1925-frus-order">“Eureka!: The 1925 <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Order (and Why You Should Be Nice to Archivists).”</ref>
                    A scan of the original text is available for download (<ref
                    target="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/1925-order.pdf">PDF</ref>, 499
                    KB, 8 pp.).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="document" xml:id="memo1">
                <head>Memorandum from Tyler Dennett to the Secretary of State<note n="1">Source:
                    Folder 55D606 OSS/PB-1, Box 35, Miscellaneous Office Files, 1910-1944, Record
                    Group 59, Archives II</note></head>
                <dateline><date when="1925-03-26">March 26, 1925</date>.</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Secretary:</p>
                <p>The attached memorandum addressed to yourself together with the appended
                    statement of the principles to guide the editing of “Foreign Relations” is
                    designed in such a way that it can, if it meets with your approval, be
                    mimeographed and used in answering inquiries from historical students as to the
                    principles which now govern the editing of diplomatic correspondence in the
                    Department.</p>
                <p>You may, therefore, wish to scrutinize the memorandum and draft with a view to
                    its possible circulation outside of the Department. It is an attempt to define
                    some of the aspects of the necessary limitations upon “open diplomacy”.</p>
                <p>TD</p>
                <p>I see no objection</p>
                <p>Kellogg</p>
                <p>Noted.-</p>
                <p>MacM.<note n="2">Handwritten initials “TD” added by Dr. Tyler Dennett, head of
                    the Division of Publications. Handwritten “I see no objection” and “Kellogg”
                    added by Frank Kellogg, Secretary of State. Handwritten “Noted.-" and “MacM."
                    added by John Van Antwerp MacMurray, Assistant Secretary of State.</note></p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="memo2">
                <head>Attached Memorandum</head>
                <dateline> <date when="1925-03-26">March 26, 1925</date>.</dateline>
                <p>Dear Mr. Secretary:</p>
                <p>At a recent conference of the Solicitor and the Chiefs of the geographical
                    divisions, called by Mr. MacMurray and held in his office, there was a thorough
                    discussion of the principles which ought to guide the editing of ‘Foreign
                    Relations”. As a result of this conference, the Chief of the Division of
                    Publications was requested to formulate the principles upon which those present
                    were agreed and to present them to the Secretary for his formal approval.</p>
                <p>I beg to call your attention to the fact that in the attached outline two
                    innovations are proposed. It is believed that “Foreign Relations” is the proper
                    place in which to publish the decisions of the Department on subjects of
                    international law which are of peculiar interest to students. Hitherto, material
                    of this nature has usually not been available for study. Also, the publication
                    of important documents concerning treaty negotiations ought greatly to increase
                    the value of “Foreign Relations” as a source-book of American history. This
                    proposed new material ought to contribute to the promotion of interest in
                    questions of foreign policy and <pb n="2"/> in turn assist in the maintenance of
                    an intelligent public opinion. The attached outline otherwise is important not
                    so much for new principles as because it sets up a uniform standard for the
                    guidance of the many officers of the Department who are related to the editing
                    of diplomatic correspondence.</p>
                <p>If this statement commends itself to your judgment, I shall he glad to have for
                    it your formal approval.</p>
                <p>Tyler Dennett</p>
                <p>A-M MacM. U J.C.G.<note n="3">Dennett’s signature is handwritten. MacMurray and
                    Joseph Grew, Undersecretary of State, initialed the document.</note> </p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="memo3">
                <head>Appended Statement of Principles</head>
                <p rend="center">Principles to Guide the Editing of “Foreign Relations”.</p>
                <p>Although the Secretary of State is not by law required to make an annual report,
                    it is recognized that a well-informed and intelligent public opinion is of the
                    utmost importance for the conduct of foreign relations.</p>
                <p>The publication of diplomatic correspondence relating to matters which are still
                    current often presents an insuperable obstacle to effective negotiation, but it
                    is obvious that after the completion of the business in hand as much of the
                    correspondence as is practicable ought to be made public. This object is
                    attained by the publication of “Foreign Relations” which presents, in a form
                    economical, compact, and easily, accessible, the documentary history of the
                    foreign relations of the United States. The editing of “Foreign Relations” must,
                    therefore, be recognized as an important part of the duties of the Department of
                    State.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>The Chief of the Division of Publications is charged with the preparation for
                    this purpose, as soon as practicable after the close of each year, of the
                    correspondence relating to all major policies and decisions of the Department in
                    the matter of foreign relations, together with the events which contributed to
                    the formulation of each decision or policy, and the facts incident to the
                    application of it. It is expected that the material thus assembled, aside from
                    the omission of trivial and inconsequential details, will be substantially
                    complete as regards the files of the Department.</p>
                <p>The development of the science of international law has become a matter of such
                    weight and general concern that it is recommended that the Chief of the Division
                    of Publications, with the help and counsel of the Solicitor, should <del
                    rend="strikethrough">be</del> give<del rend="strikethrough">n</del> special
                    attention to the publication of all important decisions made by the Department
                    relating to international law, with a view to making available for general study
                    and use, the annual contributions of the Department to this important branch of
                    jurisprudence. It is likewise believed that the Department may profitably
                    inaugurate the <pb n="3"/> practice of printing a record of treaty negotiations,
                    and it is, therefore, suggested that such material be added, beginning with
                    “Foreign Relations 1918”, which is now in the process of editing.</p>
                <p>When the documents on a given subject have been assembled in the Division of
                    Publications, they should be submitted to the Solicitor or to the Chief of the
                    appropriate division which has had immediate supervision of the topic. The
                    Solicitor, or the heads of these divisions, respectively, are charged with the
                    duty of reviewing the material thus assembled and indicating any omissions which
                    appear to be required. Omissions of the following kind are recognized as
                    legitimate and necessary:</p>
                <list>
                    <item> <label>(a)</label> matters which if published at the time would tend to
                        embarrass negotiations or other business;</item>
                    <item> <label>(b)</label> to condense the record and avoid needless
                        details;</item>
                    <item> <label>(c)</label> to preserve the confidence reposed in the Department
                        by other governments and by individuals;</item>
                    <item> <label>(d)</label> to avoid needless offense to other nationalities or
                        individuals by excising invidious comments not relevant or essential to the
                        subject; and,</item>
                    <pb n="4"/>
                    <item> <label>(e)</label> to suppress personal opinions presented in despatches
                        and not adopted by the Department. To this there is one qualification,
                        namely, that in major decisions it is desirable, where possible, to show the
                        choices presented to the Department when the decision was made.</item>
                </list>
                <p>On the other hand, there must be no alteration of the text, no deletions without
                    indicating the place in the text where the deletion is made, and no omission of
                    facts which were of major importance in reaching a decision. Nothing should be
                    omitted with a view to concealing or glossing over what might be regarded by
                    some as a defect of a policy.</p>
                <p>Where a document refers to two or more subjects, provided there are no other
                    objections, it should be printed in its entirety, and not divided for purposes
                    of more exact classification in editing. Great care must be taken to avoid the
                    mutilation of documents. On the other hand, when a foreign government, in giving
                    permission to use a communication, requests the deletion of any part of it, it
                    is usually preferable to publish the document in part rather than to omit it
                    entirely. A similar principle may be applied with reference to documents
                    originating with the American Government.</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>The chief of the Division of Publications is expected to initiate, through the
                    appropriate channels, the correspondence necessary to secure from a foreign
                    government permission to publish any document received from it and which it is
                    desired to publish as a part of the diplomatic correspondence of the United
                    States. Without such permission, the document in question must not be used. The
                    offices and divisions concerned in this process of editing may be expected to
                    cooperate heartily with a view to the preparation of an adequate and honest
                    record.</p>
                <p>Approved</p>
                <p>Frank B. Kellogg</p>
                <p>Approved FBK</p>
                <p>A-M MacM. E.E. E.E.Y. F.E. F.P.L. L.A. F.W. M.E. F.M.G. N.E. A.W.D.</p>
                <p>W.E. So. C.C.H. U. J.C.G.<note n="4">Kellogg’s approval and signature are
                    handwritten. An unidentified person added the “Approved” and “FBK” initials
                    beneath Kellogg’s signature. MacMurray, Evan E. Young (Chief of the Division of
                    Eastern European Affairs), Frank P. Lockhart (Acting Chief of the Division of
                    Far Eastern Affairs), Francis White (Chief of the Division of Latin-American
                    Affairs), Franklin Mott Gunther (Chief of the Division of Mexican Affairs),
                    Allen W. Dulles (Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs), Charles C. Hyde
                    (Solicitor), and Grew initialed the document. No initials appeared next to
                    “W.E." (Division of Western European Affairs).</note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
