<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Minutes of the Opening Session of the Historical Advisory
                    Committee</title>
                <title type="short">Minutes of the Opening Session of the Historical Advisory
                    Committee</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-08-11">August 11, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This document was released in conjunction with <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/formation-of-the-hac"
                        >"The Formation of the Historical Advisory Committee."</ref> A scan of the
                    original text is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus150/1957-hac-minutes-transcript.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 2.9 MB, 81 pp.).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON "FOREIGN RELATIONS OF THE UNITED STATES"</p>
            <p>PARTICIPANTS:</p>
            <p>Dr. G. Bernard Noble, Chief Historical Division, Department of State, presiding</p>
            <p>GUEST SPEAKERS:</p>
            <p>The Honorable John Foster Dulles, Secretary of State<lb/>Mr. Andrew H. Berding,
                Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs</p>
            <p>MEMBERS OF THE COMMITTEE:</p>
            <p>Dr. Thomas A. Bailey, Department of History, Stanford University<lb/>Dr. Clarence
                Arthur Berdahl, Professor of Political Science, University of Illinois<lb/>Dr.
                Leiand M. Goodrich, School of International Affairs, Columbia University<lb/>Dr.
                Richard W. Leopold, Department of History, Northwestern University<lb/>Dr. Dexter
                Perkins, Department of History, Cornell<lb/>Dr. Philip W. Thayer, School of Advanced
                International Studies, The Johns Hopkins University<lb/>Mr. Edgar Turlington,
                American Society of International Law</p>
            <p>STATE DEPARTMENT REPRESENTATIVES:</p>
            <p>Mr. Lampton Beery, NEA<lb/>Mr. William T. Briggs, OSA<lb/>Mr. Ralph N. Clough,
                CA<lb/>Mr. G. M. Richardson Dougall, HD<lb/>Mr. William M. Franklin, HD<lb/>Mr.
                Frederick W. Jandrey, EUR<lb/>Mr. Edwin M. Kretzmann, Jr., NEA<lb/>Mr. Gustave A.
                Nuermberger, HD<lb/>Mr. Ernest R. Perkins, HD<lb/>Mr. William P. Snow, ARA<lb/>Mr.
                J. Burke Wilkinson, Deputy Assistant Secretary</p>
            <p>Reported by: V.R. Voce</p>
            <p>TABLE OF CONTENTS</p>
            <p>Introductory Remarks: The Advisory Committee and the "Foreign Relations" Program</p>
            <p>The Process of Compiling and Editing "Foreign Relations". Explanatory Statements and
                Discussion.</p>
            <p>Scope and Coverage of "Foreign Relations"</p>
            <p>Remarks by Andrew Berding, Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs</p>
            <p>Discussion of Down-Grad1ng of Documents Selected for Publication in "Foreign
                Relations" Volumes</p>
            <p>Statistics on Distribution of Recent "Foreign Relations" Volumes</p>
            <p>Discussion of Use of "Foreign Relations" by Authoritative Writers</p>
            <p>Remarks by The Honorable John Foster Dulles, Secretary of State</p>
            <p>PROCEEDINGS</p>
            <p>[The meeting was convened at 10:00 a.m., Dr. Bernard Noble presiding.]</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I have a few introductory remarks to make.</p>
            <p>ITEM 1. INTRODUCTORY REMARKS: THE ADVISORY COMMITTEE AND THE "FOREIGN RELATIONS"
                PROGRAM.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We regard the appointment of this Committee as an important event in
                our foreign relations history, it was not set up on the basis of a snap judgment by
                any means. We had thought about this for some time. As a matter of fact, some eight
                or ten years ago we actually made some proposals along this line. But the Department
                at that time had not made up its mind about it. But the developments in the past few
                years have been fairly conclusive in our minds, in our judgment, as to the
                desirability of it, particularly since the world situation is so directly reflected
                in the "Foreign Relations" volumes.</p>
            <p>In the 19th Century, "Foreign Relations" were published generally in one volume after
                they were inaugurated in 1861. In the 1940's we were putting out seven volumes, much
                larger volumes than the average, per year, and, so far as the 1950's and 1960's are
                concerned, I'm talking about the "Foreign Relations" covering those years, it's
                difficult to forecast precisely what their proportions will be if we carry on the
                present basis of selection. In the 19th Century, I might say also, publication was
                done on a fairly current basis. The first volume was sent, along with the
                President's Message in December 1861.</p>
            <p>By 1914 there had developed a lag of about seven years, and in the 1930's that lag in
                publication became 15 years. And for the years in the 1940's and 1950's it is
                difficult to forecast just what it may be. I think you'll understand that more
                clearly, if you do not already, from what we have already written to you and from
                your other understanding of the problem. The reasons for this, of course, are fairly
                obvious, I think. That lag grew basically out of the growing volume of papers, the
                greater complexity and out of an increasing sensitivity of the papers which is due
                to the change of situation in the world politics.</p>
            <p>Our problem has been made somewhat more difficult in the past few years by reason of
                the request of several Senators, supported by the Senate Appropriations Committee,
                for the publication of two special series of documents and the acceleration of the
                publication of the regular series. And the point is to narrow the gap which was then
                about 18 years.</p>
            <p>You may recall the heated discussions in 1952 especially with regard to the Yalta
                conference and the demands that were made for the records to be disclosed. You may
                also recall the publication of the so-called "White Book on China" in 1949, and the
                criticism caused by that. And demands were later made that the full record of our
                relations with China during the 1940's be made public. And these two requests were
                incorporated in letters from leading Senators, and later supported by the Foreign
                Appropriations Committee. The Department responded to these requests by setting up a
                four-year program, a program to meet their requests as nearly as possible, but with
                the caution that the completion of the job would be contingent on getting clearance
                of papers as well as the availability of adequate staffing, etc.</p>
            <p>When we came to grips with these programs and in compiling the relevant documents, we
                ran into clearance difficulties at home and abroad. We had many difficulties in
                getting papers, and of course it's difficult from a staffing side also. This applied
                not only to the war time conferences but also to the China volumes. The compilation
                of these raised serious questions of clearance, which ultimately made it impossible
                to meet the schedule which we made up in 1954. And that, naturally, caused further
                adverse criticisms.</p>
            <p>In this over-all situation, it was felt by the Department that the counsel of a
                highly qualified group of scholars and citizens would be a good thing, and one of
                the best ways to secure a meeting of minds and an understanding between the
                Department and the public, at least the scholarly leaders of the public, those who
                teach and write books and influence thinking of public opinion. We looked at it as
                sort of a two-way operation. The Department could get a lot of help and advice, both
                in reflecting responsible opinion upon our problem and important editorial problems,
                and also such a group would be a kind of link with the public, especially with the
                scholarly professional public, in helping to understand the Department's problem in
                this area. So we approached the three leading national associations interested in
                this particular area, the American Historical Association, the American Political
                Science Association, and the American Society of International Law, all of whom I
                happen to be a member, as do a number of you others. So we approached these
                associations and asked them to make nominations. There was a great problem of how to
                set up this committee. Ultimately, of course, the Department had to take technical
                responsibility for appointing individuals, but we wanted to do it in complete
                understanding and agreement with the professional associations. So we asked the
                associations to make nominations on the basis of which the Department would make
                appointments. And we secured the very enthusiastic and sincere cooperation of the
                American Historical Association, the American Society of International Law, and the
                American Political Science Association, for which we are very grateful. And these
                appointments of individuals here are the result of it.</p>
            <p>I want to express my own personal and official gratification over the fact that all
                of you have accepted; and in fact it was very, I think, notable that you all were
                able to accept without any difficulty.</p>
            <p>There is just one more problem, which is more of a housekeeping detail, which I might
                mention. That is the question of the term. As you know, the appointment is for a
                three-year period. The question is when that term should begin and when it should
                end. Our suggestion is that it should begin, say, with September 1. I believe your
                appointments were made or confirmed sometime around July and August, so I suggest
                that the term shall begin on September 1. One advantage of that is that if we should
                want to change the time of meeting, it makes for a little bit more flexibility in
                the fall. I want to discuss that time of meeting with you before we adjourn—I hope
                we shan't forget it—so we can find time to your mutual convenience. I think we are
                very fortunate in being able to get you here at this time.</p>
            <p>My suggestion that the term should begin on September 1 doesn't mean that your
                service will necessarily be discontinued at the end of three years. We haven't any
                such presumptions in mind, but we will consult with the American Historical
                Association, the American Society of International Law, and the American Political
                Science Association before the expiration of that year.</p>
            <p>Now, as to the way this program shall be carried out, the conduct is suggested in the
                agenda of the meeting, which is the first document in your dossier. The way we carry
                this out is not prescribed and my own feeling is we have to play it somewhat by ear.
                But I will say in advance that I think we might bear in mind that it might be
                desirable to concentrate our discussion on problems of clearance this afternoon, by
                and large. I realize that things of that sort will come up all along the line, and
                there is no hard and fast rule.</p>
            <p>We have provided you here with a batch of materials relevant to this subject and if
                it's agreeable to you, we might just look through this somewhat casually at this
                point.</p>
            <p>First is the agenda, which you have all seen.</p>
            <p>The second item is the Regulations and Procedures bearing on the publication of
                "Foreign Relations" volumes. And you notice there the statement that it constitutes
                an official record; includes, subject to necessary security considerations, all
                documents needed to give a comprehensive record of the major foreign policy
                decisions within the range of the Department of State's responsibilities, etc.</p>
            <p>Then it provides for certain exceptions, certain omissions of obvious lines of
                documents which might, if published, interfere with current negotiations and give
                needless offense to other nationalities or individuals.</p>
            <p>The third item in your dossier is a statement of purposes of publication of "Foreign
                Relations", which Mr. Perkins drew up. It points out the dual purposes of the
                "Foreign Relations". It's useful, of course, to officials of the Department and in
                the Foreign Service particularly, where at all the major posts at least these are on
                file and constitute an indispensable record. And the second purpose is for public
                education, scholars, and so forth. I won't dwell on that unless there is some
                question.</p>
            <p>Then under item four there is the subject we will refer to from time to time, the
                status of the "Foreign Relations" volumes as of December 1. And you notice volumes
                on the left; the year of publication indicates that Volume "American Republics" is
                the only one left in 1939 that is not out. In 1940 there are still three that have
                not been published; four others in 1939 have been published and three in 1940. Is
                that correct?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Yes.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: In 1941, one has been published. You see, "X" marks the stage of
                advance of each one, whether galley proofed or clearance for foreign and domestic
                and indexing stage or waiting release.</p>
            <p>On the next page is the further status of volumes that are more or less in
                compilation. Some are in compilation, or compilation is completed. Six volumes are
                how in the process of compilation.</p>
            <p>The next one is the status of the "Foreign Relations" volumes of the special China
                series, 1942-43. We thought when we made our program schedule we didn't know course
                how many volumes there would be for a year and we suggested there might be one and
                there would be eight possibly from 1942 through '49 inclusive. It turns out, as you
                see, there were three for 1946 and 1949. You notice there the various stages of the
                pipeline leading to publication they are in.</p>
            <p>Page four covers the various conferences, the war time conferences, showing the
                Yalta-Malta volume published and the other important ones, Cairo, Tehran which will
                be one volume, are in the stage of clearance; and the second Cairo, also the Potsdam
                volume.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: That is the first Cairo-Tehran?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: And the second also.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: Those will be one volume, those three?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes, sir. Item 5 in your dossier is the status of the "Foreign
                Relations" projects requested by the Senate Committee on Appropriations beginning
                with the fiscal year 1954. I thought that would be very useful to you. We have said
                that the Malta-Yalta volumes are published; the Berlin (Potsdam) volume is in
                process and likewise the Cairo and Tehran volumes. Those are the most important
                ones. So we have given a little space there to ex plain the historic development of
                that, and I want a little later on to have Mr. Franklin say something about the
                compilation of the Yalta volume and Mr. Dougall to say something about Potsdam. But
                this simply gives the major stage in the development of the editing of them up to
                date. You might read that at your leisure. There is nothing urgent about it at this
                point.</p>
            <p>No. II, the special series on United States relations with China, that simply is a
                summary of the status of those volumes.</p>
            <p>And, finally, III, on the request from the Senate Appropriations Committee, refers to
                reducing the backlog of the regular volumes, and this section deals with that. I
                might just say that when that program was asked for, 26 volumes had been compiled
                and were in various stages of pipeline leading to publication. Since that time, 25
                volumes have been published, and at the present time there are 37 volumes which are
                compiled in the various stages of pipeline leading to publication.</p>
            <p>The next item is a presentation of the volumes published from 1954 to 1959 and with
                some reference to the next two years and what could be done in the next two years if
                various problems could be settled. Actually, the first year we put out nine volumes.
                We had hoped to put out ten. The second year we put out eight volumes. We had hoped
                to put out ten. And we fell down three, and this year we haven't actually put out
                any. But we hope that before the end of the year we shall be able to do so.</p>
            <p>ITEM 7. THE PROCESS OF COMPILING AND EDITING "FOREIGN RELATIONS". Explanatory
                Statements and Discussion.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Item seven in the dossier is a statement on the process of preparing
                "Foreign Relations" volumes. Mr. Perkins has made a statement there. Would you like
                to say something on that and have a little discussion on that also? In the process
                of compiling I think you have read something about it in the files we sent to you.
                Ralph, just the high points on that.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I think the details are giver in this statement, so I will not take
                time to repeat that.</p>
            <p> I just want to say that the compilation is a professional job. All the people come
                in under Civil Service status. They are professional historians or political
                scientists. And we have had a remarkable continuity down through the years in our
                staff. The turnover hasn't been large, so the same people have been compiling in
                some cases for a good many years. In fact, I have been here for 27 years myself and
                we have other people who have been here over ten years. It is strictly a
                professional job not linked up with policy considerations on the compilation
                end.</p>
            <p>The GPO annual volumes and the China series are done in the Foreign Relations Branch
                of the Historical Division because of the pressure of work, and for certain other
                reasons, the war time conferences were taken over by other men in the division and
                not in the regular Foreign Relations Branch. We had all we could handle with the
                regular Foreign Relations program and the China program. They had been working for
                us in the Department on the war time conferences, so it was quite natural that they
                should continue to edit the war time conferences.</p>
            <p> The compilations made by our professional staff all come to me for review and then
                after we agree on final compilations it is sent over to our Publications Services
                Division where they have a "Foreign Relations" editing branch that does the
                technical work of putting it in shape and they send it to the Government Printing
                Office. I think the written material we have given you really covers all that needs
                to be said.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any questions about this aspect of it? [None]</p>
            <p>The next item in your dossier is the "Yalta" volume I thought you might be interested
                in a few indications as to the way in which the "Yalta" volume was compiled, since
                that has been the subject of some discussion. Mr. Franklin prepared this and I will
                ask him to make any incidental comments he might bring out by way of illumination
                without trying to give all the content of this.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Well, there may be more questions after this is read. I suspect there
                may be. I don't know how far this goes in answering any questions that you do have
                in mind, but this points out a few of the characteristics of this particular volume.
                It explains why we brought it out first in the series, although it is neither first
                nor last chronologically. One reason was obvious public interest. The other reason
                was, as indicated by Mr. Perkins, that we already had a great deal of material in
                the files in the division on the important war time conferences from which, during
                the years, we had answered repeated questions coming from within the Department as
                to what took place at various war time conferences. And we were therefore actually
                in a better position to push the "Yalta" volume ahead since there had of course been
                more questions about that and we had been more active in collecting materials.</p>
            <p>However, we did find that our record on the military side of the conference was
                scrappy in the files of this Department and so we were confronted at the outset with
                making a rather large decision as to whether we would or would not include the
                entire military record. We decided that we would, and thereby entailed a great deal
                of work and difficulty because we had to obtain documents of the Joint and Combined
                Chiefs of Staff and these are not lightly released.</p>
            <p> We also found that since the "Yalta" volume is coming out in the middle of something
                of a desert of documents, we had to put in a large amount of background documents.
                This made for very difficult decisions as to what should be included. We had to
                identify subjects and go far back into the fields that would be covered and will be
                covered by five years of Foreign Relations in order to pick out those particular
                salient documents that would lead the reader to an understanding of the references
                made in the minutes at Yalta and the allusions to previous materials made in the
                minutes. This, of course, is open-ended and is necessarily not complete, but 455
                pages of the volume are designed to take the reader up to Yalta so he will know
                about the major subjects that were under discussion. </p>
            <p>Similarly, we put in some post conference documents, which had been the subject of a
                little misunderstanding. We did not endeavor to cover the aftermath of Yalta,
                naturally, but simply to put in those documents, or portions of documents in which
                participants at the conference subsequently said exactly what had happened at the
                conference.</p>
            <p>Then, on the conference records themselves, as I have indicated here, we tried very
                hard to lean over backwards putting in every scrap of paper that anyone wrote at I
                or about Yalta at the spot. So in many cases you will find not one set of minutes on
                a meeting but two or even three sets of minutes, notes, jottings, memos, however
                cryptic or informal. A few passages of side remarks were deleted, as I have
                indicated here; a few were also taken out for security reasons. None of these,
                however, interfered with the main burden of the story whatever.</p>
            <p>We did not include materials already published by participants, such as later
                messages of the President, other statements which came up subsequent to the
                conference but as a bonus to the reader we did put in a full list of all such
                references. We felt that it would be contrary to the general practice of "Foreign
                Relations" to include all that type of already published material, most of it
                officially published, and it would have, as you see, run us over into an extremely
                unwieldy volume, if not two volumes, to have included all that.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Bill, you're really referring to post conference documents now, aren't
                you?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes, post conference documents already published. But we also added, as
                you have probably noticed, some other innovations, maps, photographs, and stuck
                rather closer to literal printing of the documents than we ordinarily do just
                because of the extreme touchiness of the subject. Do you have any other
                questions?</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I have two questions. They both relate to different things. First of
                all, were there special considerations which led to your including in this volume
                scraps and scribblings and bits that you would normally, I take it, not include in a
                conference record?</p>
            <p>And, secondly, did you obtain clearance from all the Governments participating in the
                conference?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: With regard to the inclusion of scraps and bits, we did go further down
                the line than is normal "Foreign Relations" practice. That is true. I think,
                however, we shall have to go far down the line for all the war time conferences
                because, except for the consistent minutes kept by the Combined Chiefs of Staff and
                by Mr. Bohlen, for those meetings for which he was interpreter, or other
                interpreters, the rest of the record is extremely fragmentary and therefore every
                little scrap and bit and jotting becomes of great significance, perhaps not
                intrinsically but we don't dare leave them out when we have no consistent approved
                record of conversation. And with regard to many of the memos discussed, we will
                probably find in many conferences only an occasional carbon copy. Therefore, if
                there are any variants on any copies we will put them in.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: On that point, I just wonder what value these scribblings and scraps
                have. I know in the case of the San Francisco Conference. It was decided not to make
                the verbatim record of the technical committees public for the reason that they were
                incomplete. In one or two cases the stenographer was so situated that she couldn't
                hear what was going on, for example. I just wonder whether a scholar using this
                volume, is going to be any better informed as a result of having these Hiss
                scribblings? I just raise the question.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Well, Yalta had a secret agreement notoriously held for a year or so
                before it was released, and it had Mr. Stalin and it had Alger Hiss and we
                just—-</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: In other words, Alger Hiss was a reason for including them?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Obviously. But we did not restrict our jottings to Alger Hiss. So we
                simply decided, in view of this situation, we would go all the way down for anything
                that had any bearing pertinent to the subject. Some of the Hiss jottings, by the
                way, are extremely interesting. They are by no means junk. In a few places he picked
                up and heard some things which were not fully spelled out in the minutes.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: But do we know this Hiss record is reliable?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: There were no agreed minutes for any of these meetings except the
                agreed minutes for the Combined Chiefs of Staff.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think it is all very interesting I just raise the question if, in
                order to keep these volume within limits, something has to be eliminated if this
                doesn't suggest where the action can be used a little.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: I believe Yalta is probably the chief example of that type of material.
                I believe with the other conferences there will not be as much of that.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I was struck with what you said about the amount of background material
                you had to include in this volume. If you publish the other war time conference
                volumes out of order and it is not altogether clear, but I think some will be out of
                chronological order, you're going to run into the same problem, aren't you?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes, we shall.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I know it's beyond your control.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: I have another question. It was noticed when the volume came out there
                was a departure from the normal kind of editing, which I notice is mentioned in your
                statement here on page 3 next to the last paragraph the attribution to those who
                drafted or approved various Department of State papers. I don't raise this question
                for the purpose of discussing it here now, but it seems to me this might be an
                important matter that ought to be discussed perhaps.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes, indeed. I hope we shall discuss it, the principle of editing.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: One other point. I see an expression here that is in other
                connotations also, "giving needless offense to other nationalities or individuals".
                I wonder when offense is considered to be needful. </p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is a very good point. You know the definition of a gentleman is
                one who never insult an individual except intentionally. Are there any further
                questions on Yalta? [None] I want Mr. Dougall, who is Chief and immediate editor of
                the Potsdam (Berlin) volumes—and we say volumes because there will be three of
                them—to say something about the status and problems of the Potsdam volumes.</p>
            <p>MR. DOUGALL: One of the problems of Potsdam is that, unlike most of the other war
                time conferences that we are concerned with, it was a long conference. It lasted a
                lot longer and it was in a comparatively accessible place, so that people turned up
                who were not, so to speak, members of the central core of the conference and these
                discussions all got closely interwoven.</p>
            <p>The Polish delegation, for instance, was summoned and came and appeared. This did not
                happen at most of the other conferences, although at a few like Casablanca we had
                French representatives appearing. The length of the thing, plus the number of
                various committees and subcommittees, that were at work mean that there are a lot
                more minutes in that type of thing and the actual bulk of material is longer. The
                size of the delegations were enormous and the number of subjects which they
                discussed was pretty great. We have broken them down into 64 individual subjects,
                for instance, which we are dealing with and printing papers on, aside from the
                minutes.</p>
            <p>As Dr. Leopold pointed out, there is going to be a lot of pre conference material on
                this as well, more than on Yalta, because there are more subjects to cover. A whole
                volume, probably, and if we get the Potsdam volumes out in the reasonable future
                they will certainly be ahead in chronological order of the annual volumes of
                "Foreign Relations". So an entire volume will be devoted to what was going on
                immediately before the conference so that the general reader may have an idea of
                what the situation on each individual problem was when the conference opened.</p>
            <p>There will then be the minutes and perhaps in a volume by itself the physical
                breakdown which has not been arranged entirely. And then some 700 documents broken
                down by subject, which were either passed around at the conference, proposals of the
                individual delegations, or conference related papers of some sort, correspondence
                between our delegation at Potsdam and the State Department, this type of thing, or
                reports as to what was going on elsewhere which had an effect on the conference
                discussions. This is something again for which I think Potsdam will probably be
                unique, because it lasted so long the delegation could get reports of what was going
                on, say, in Iran or with respect to the Venezia Giula question or the Yugoslav
                demarche against Greece which they then dealt with at the conference. And if you
                don't have any documents of what was going on outside the conference, you really
                don't understand what they are talking about at the conference table. Potsdam was
                much less hermetically sealed, say, than Yalta. Even there there was some
                correspondence back and fro, but the communications were difficult. The conference
                was much shorter, so that there is this difference in the problem.</p>
            <p>We also had a much greater difficulty in some ways in getting the documentation
                together. As your summary on Yalta points out, they got scores, if not in the
                hundreds, of documents from the Roosevelt Library at Hyde Park. For Potsdam the
                Truman Library was not yet set up. It did not have control of the papers. They were
                in the personal control of Mr. Truman who, from the general setup of the speeding up
                of this publication, thought there were some politics involved and was in no awful
                hurry to cooperate on the matter. I must say that when he finally decided to, he did
                it very wholeheartedly, but there were a couple of years of delay in merely getting
                into his papers to fill out what we needed from them. And when we did get into them,
                we discovered that some subjects were discussed at Potsdam which we had had no
                evidence of before that they had actually been discussed. We knew that a paper was
                prepared, say, for the President and Mr., Byrnes on Palestine, but had no indication
                whatever that it had been discussed internationally at the conference. The evidence
                of this was in Mr. Truman's papers, which he had discussed with the British. So we
                then had to have another look at the State Department files to see what should be
                put into the volumes to enlighten people on this. </p>
            <p>Well, we had some other difficulties with finding files. Admiral Leahy's files, for
                instance, are in the Pentagon. But the Pentagon was blissfully unaware of this fact.
                They told us two or three times that they didn't have them, until we finally found
                one of the Admiral's Aides who could be quite specific as to where they were, and
                then we found them and we got quite a lot of material about that.</p>
            <p>The research on Potsdam is now all done and has been for some time. The problem is
                one of clearance now, which we will put off until this afternoon in the general
                clearance discussion. There aren't more than a few dozen-odd queries to clean up on
                footnotes to keep the volumes from going right along in the printing process, except
                for the clearance business. This means that the Department still has to make up its
                mind as to whether it's going to print the full story or whether it cannot print the
                full story, and if it can't, our opinion is that we had better hold off more or less
                indefinitely until it can all be told. That is it, Mr. Chairman.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are there any questions right now? </p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: I have a small one. In regard to papers held by the President and
                other high officials, would the Department like to see some legislation to limit the
                practice of taking papers away?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, as it actually works out, it isn't quite so bad as it might seem.
                You see, the Roosevelt papers had been set up at Hyde Park and the Truman papers had
                been set up out in Independence and they both have been turned over to the Archives,
                so that they are under official control. I don't think that the publication of those
                papers would be any different, if their presence were restricted in that matter,
                than they are now. We have had quite full access to the Roosevelt papers at Hyde
                Park, and when the Truman papers are organized properly at Independence—I understand
                that will be within a year—they would be accessible too.</p>
            <p>[At this point Mr. Andrew Berding, Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, joined the
                meeting.]</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I'd like to introduce Andrew Berding, Assistant Secretary of State for
                Public Affairs, who has been extremely helpful in promoting our program and has
                interested himself in helping us to get this committee established, which I think is
                certainly a landmark in our development. I want Mr. Berding to say a few words to
                you.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDING: It is certainly good to see you here; and with the same degree of
                emphasis, we need your help. It's simply stating the obvious to you when I tell you
                how the foreign affairs of the Government has grown even within the last few years.
                Obviously the statement of history connected with the growth of these foreign
                relations is of ever-widening importance and complexity. I am thinking, for
                instance, of the many conferences now that someday are going to appear in "Foreign
                Relations" volumes.</p>
            <p>Take in relation to myself. A year ago I was with the Secretary at a NATO conference
                in Paris. I just take this span of one year. The NATO conference in Paris was first.
                In March we were at Canberra, Australia, for the South East Asia Treaty conference.
                Two days after we got back we went to Bermuda for the Bermuda conference with the
                British. In May we were in Bonn for the next NATO conference. In July we were in
                London for the Disarmament Conference. Then, of course, we were up for a week at the
                General Assembly. Now we leave a week from today, probably the night before so we
                can get over there ahead, for this Heads of Government meeting in Paris. That is
                just a span of one year. That didn't used to be the case in the past, before the
                blessed, and not so blessed, advent of the airplane, but it certainly is the case
                now.</p>
            <p>We, likewise, have what we did not have before—the United Nations, and all our
                relationships with the United Nations. I was at the Secretary's staff meeting this
                morning and a good portion of the discussion concerned the present state of
                discussions in the United Nations. All that at some time will have to be taken into
                consideration in our "Foreign Relations" volumes. We weren't a member of the League
                of Nations in the old days. Now we are a member of this world organization.</p>
            <p>Then we have the fact that since the end of the war we have diplomatic relations now
                with a score of new nations, newly independent nations. They never appeared before,
                except occasionally as a reference to a dependency or colony. And now we have
                full-scale diplomatic relations with those countries. And we find that those new
                names will be now be appearing too. Who thought and who thinks now, in connection
                with our "Foreign Relations" volumes, of Ghana? But some day, sure as anything, our
                historians will be dealing with Ghana in our "Foreign Relations" volumes. It's
                simply one of many more, and there are other nations still going along that are
                newly independent that we will add to this number. </p>
            <p>The complexity of our foreign relations is further increased by such things as our
                mutual security program. We operate now to an infinitely greater degree in the
                economic field than was ever the case before the last war. In the last war we
                operated with the Government and before that, and since the last war, a great deal
                of American public investment which of course calls for treaty work, agreements and
                the like, all of which again have to be handled, to some degree at least, by the
                historians and have a record of these things.</p>
            <p>Our staff, of course, has grown a great deal to cover this complex work. I had the
                great pleasure, in writing the memoirs of Cordell Hull, of working with Secretary
                Hull. And I remember several years after he retired, he came back to the Department
                one day just to pay a courtesy call on Secretary Acheson. After they talked for a
                while, Secretary Acheson said, "Wouldn't you like to have me call in the Assistant
                Secretaries to meet you?" And he looked around this great big office and he said,
                "Do you think this room is large enough?" [Laughter]</p>
            <p>It's just a small illustration of how things have grown and, as I say, they certainly
                give us many, many problems and we therefore are most grateful to you gentlemen for
                agreeing to come here and be part of this, to us, very important Advisory Committee,
                and we will certainly work with you to the utmost. The Secretary is very interested.
                He will be in to talk with you at noon and we hope to have the very great benefit of
                your sage, wise advice and counsel.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Thank you. Are there any further questions about the Potsdam volume?
                [None]</p>
            <p>The next item on clearance of "Foreign Relations" I think we will leave over to this
                afternoon, since we are going to specialize on that problem now.</p>
            <p>The next small item is on down-grading of documents.</p>
            <p>DISCUSSION OF DOWN-GRADING OF DOCUMENTS SELECTED FOR PUBLICATION IN "FOREIGN
                RELATIONS" VOLUMES</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I will ask Mr. Nuermberger to stand up and say something about
                that.</p>
            <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: We have a brief statement on the down-grading. We primarily
                instituted that particularly to facilitate the handling of the material primarily
                with Mr. Clough's office. Mr. Osborn in your office has been very helpful on that,
                Mr. Clough.</p>
            <p>If we handle this as Top Secret, we would have any number of safes, and so forth, and
                extra charge to the GPO when it did get down there, if it is permissible to do so.
                We receive these documents and we instituted the practice that wherever possible we
                down-grade as far as we can go, primarily if we can go to Unclassified. We have been
                able to get Unclassified for a number of documents because a number have been found
                to be printed or the substance printed in various publications. Also on Top Secret
                telegrams—that is, where they were Top Secret in code—telegrams more than ten years
                old could be down-graded, and we have been able to do that.</p>
            <p>The procedure is for us to take the initiative and then take it up with the office
                that is primarily interested in the document. I believe, as I have listed there, we
                have been able to down-grade approximately 1,000 Top Secret documents, and from the
                overall picture that is just a drop in the bucket as far as Top Secret documents go,
                because during the war most documents were Top Secret. It has been a problem, but it
                has also been very helpful to us and we appreciate the cooperation that we have
                received both from within the Department and also the Defense Department in
                down-grading their documents. We have had no difficulty with them in
                down-grading.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Might I add something on that subject. The special difficulty in the
                war time conference volumes has been the large admixture of Defense documents of the
                Joint and Combined Chiefs of Staff, so that where the conferences at Malta-Yalta,
                Tehran and Potsdam are concerned, we have not been able to down-grade until a much
                later stage and we have had to operate with these large masses of manuscript add
                gaily proof Secret and Top Secret. It has acted like a anchor on the physical
                handling of safes and everything that goes with it.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: And, incidentally, the surcharges that go with the printing of
                documents on a Secret and Top Secret basis are much larger. </p>
            <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: I believe it runs around 20 percent higher. </p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It is more than that, isn't it? </p>
            <p>MR. NUERMBERGER: It's 20 or 25 percent. </p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Any questions on that? [None] The next item is on the statistics on
                distribution of recent "Foreign Relations" volumes, which you might be interested in
                looking at.</p>
            <p>STATISTICS ON DISTRIBUTION OF RECENT "FOREIGN RELATIONS" VOLUMES</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: There is a total of 4,000 copies printed. The House and Senate get
                1,620, Department of State 460 and Depository Libraries get 464 copies; while the
                Superintendent of Documents has 750 copies for sale, the Library of Congress 25
                copies, and other Government agencies get 535 copies and Foreign Exchange 106 copies
                with Press getting 40 copies.</p>
            <p>You notice next the statistics of sales with the Soviet Union getting, from 1933 to
                '39, very heavy distribution. Volumes of sold copies were very heavy and the
                Malta-Yalta volume was extremely heavy, I suppose surpassing any previous sales for
                the "Foreign Relations" volumes.</p>
            <p>But the "Foreign Relations" volumes, of course, are not printed from the point of
                view that they will be a profitable enterprise. They are distributed to the
                libraries and very few professors. I believe Professor Leopold has an enormous
                collection of them, but I don't know how many other have. But obviously they cannot
                be collected in the ordinary man's library, and so they have to be used in other
                libraries. Therefore, we cannot apply the test of sales to the "Foreign Relations"
                volumes. I think that becomes pretty obvious.</p>
            <p>The next brief item is what one of our staff thought up, showing the number of pages
                required in the "Foreign Relations" volumes from 1912 to 1941. You notice in 1919
                they jumped enormously because in those years some 29 volumes were printed,
                including the 13 covering the Paris Peace Conference; and now they are mounting up
                again down in the 1940-41 period, because they are not all printed yet. But they are
                in galley proof and the presumption is that that is an estimate on the galley proof. </p>
            <p>We thought it would be interesting for you to see, in the complexity of "Foreign
                Relations" as it is becoming now, some of the things that are not printed, not
                included normally in "Foreign Relations". Some reference is made to that in the item
                we sent you. You no doubt have an idea of the types of things that are ordinarily
                left out but we just took a rambling sample and asked the members of our staff to
                sit down and make a few notes covering a brief period, say, as to the specific
                items, the concrete things which were not included.</p>
            <p>Under the second heading you will see a great many things which you might offhand
                think should be included, but for reasons of relative importance they are left out.
                When you consider what we have to put out, taking the major aspects of our policies,
                this leaves a great deal of interesting information, particularly on the internal
                affairs of particular countries that a person can do valuable research on. As I say,
                these are random samples and do not purport to cover everything specifically. But
                they, I think, are suggestive and are interesting as to the sorts of things we have
                left out, and we covered something from each of the areas. There is one on
                Switzerland for the European area; and one on the Far East, not including China—not
                that we intended to exclude it but it just happened that these notes were so made—;
                one on the Near East; one on the Soviet Union; and one on the general area. And
                here's an illustration: the story on "The European Advisory Commission", this sort
                of thing. And on Argentina is one from the Latin American Republics area. You may
                want to ask questions about that later.</p>
            <p>DISCUSSION OF USE OF "FOREIGN RELATIONS" BY AUTHORITATIVE WRITERS</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Item 14 in your books is a list of the uses of "Foreign Relations" by
                authoritative writers and some of the writers are present here today. They find that
                reading of important books in international relations covering our diplomacy has a
                great many references to "Foreign Relations".</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I am sure that sometimes your group is asked what is the value of all
                this work you're doing, and I think in connection with this list there is a very
                nice correlation between the footnotes used in the volumes here and those years in
                which you published the greatest number of pages for the period of the World War and
                the Peace Conference.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is very interesting. I hadn't thought that through. On that
                question you raised about the value, you people are in a position to give us helpful
                advice, which we appreciate. I just called up a friend at the Library of Congress
                and asked him about the use there in the reference library on the next item, and I
                was quite interested in his reply. The Library receives at least 23 copies and they
                are in fairly constant use.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the last item in the dossier, the Indexing of Persons in "Foreign
                Relations" Volumes.</p>
            <p>I think we might leave that for discussion later. It's a matter which we had a good
                deal of concern about.</p>
            <p>[At this point Mr. Berding left the meeting room.]</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I suggest, gentlemen, that we might turn to the agenda, and we have
                covered Items 1 and 2, so we'll now come to the third item. </p>
            <p>ITEM III. THE SCOPE AND COVERAGE OF "FOREIGN RELATIONS"</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Item 3.a. raises the question which is: should coverage continue on as
                extensive a basis as in the past, in view of the increase in the mass of records? I
                might say, it's very difficult to get a precise indication of the increase in the
                mass of records. We are going to try to get a better indication than we now have.
                Records, of course, as a whole include a lot of things other than just the policy
                papers. The best evidence we have of the problem is a tendency now for the number of
                volumes of papers, that are deemed necessary to "Foreign Relations", to
                increase.</p>
            <p>As I say, in 1941 we had seven volumes at least that will be required in addition to
                the war time conferences of the time. And the presumption is, as Mr. Berding said,
                with the United Nations and the new countries it means that correspondence will be
                greatly increased. So we can assume that perhaps in the post war period the tendency
                to increase is even greater than during the war period, aside from the war
                conferences.</p>
            <p>Now is the time, gentlemen, for our Advisory Committee members to lead some
                discussion here on this subject. You have a brief summary here as to the situation
                and we would like very much to have your views on this question as to the scale on
                which we should compile and, the way in which the compilations should be made. Shall
                we go on increasing volumes following the present basis of selection? Or shall we
                change our basis of selection one way or another, regardless of the number of
                volumes that result? Of course I don't mean to say that we assume that 10, 15 or 20
                volumes would be ordinarily required, it probably won't be that. But there is a
                tendency to increase, so what should we look forward to in the way of
                compilation?</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: What is your budgetary situation?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, I want to say that we have had a somewhat varied experience in
                the budgetary side. Back in 1950 the appropriations for publishing "Foreign
                Relations" volumes was reduced to $28,000, which would have limited us to a little
                less than three volumes a year in terms of the cost of publishing a volume, which
                runs to about $11,200. This was in the spring of 1953 when the new program went into
                effect and we were requested to turn out more volumes. The appropriation the next
                year was increased to $112,000, making it possible to put out ten volumes. And that
                continued for another year, and then it was cut down to $84,000 and it has been
                $84,000, approximately, for the last two years. That would really make it possible
                to turn out eight volumes, but in the present situation that would be as many
                perhaps as we could actually manage to publish and clear.</p>
            <p>Of course we are going to face Congress soon on the appropriations question and one
                can't anticipate what the present discussions on defense, and so forth are, and the
                fact that at the present time we are not actually very productive so far as volumes
                flowing out of the pipeline is concerned. We hope that we will be able to make a
                little better showing before the end of the year has arrived. But at present it is
                not too promising.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Does this figure cover the next staff expansion?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That I gave?</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Yes. You have to look forward to staff expansion if you would continue on
                this same scale.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, our staff, I think, at present in the "Foreign Relations" side is
                reasonably adequate on the present scale. If the number if required to increase,
                then we have to have more staff. But at the present, the staff is divided into five
                or six sections — there is the general and five others, six sections of two
                professions each. And Mr. Perkins and Mr. Nuermberger do the reviewing. That is
                adequate at present. I think for the next few years the staff is reasonably adequate
                to turn out, say, eight volumes a year. Would you agree, Ralph?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Yes. And I would make this statement, if the situation changes so
                that we need extra staff there would be a lag between the publications and the
                staff. In other words, we have already compiled so much material in advance that if
                we found they were catching up on publication of what we have compiled, then we
                would have time to increase our staff immediately to bring up that problem. As long
                as we have so much material, already compiled that isn't coming out, I think we
                would have a rather poor case to ask for an increase of staff to compile more at
                present. I think we will need, as we get into the expansion of the post war period,
                perhaps extra staff, but not at the present time. It isn't a problem now.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Would you be able to find the same quality of person if you have to
                increase?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: If you professors turn over the product.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Then there is a great demand for of the Ph.D. in the academic world—a
                prospective demand.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: We find that competition with the universities is much greater now
                than it was a few year ago.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: In the year in which you were cut to $84,000, was that due in any respect
                to the fact that you were in need of fewer volumes, or did you ask for more?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We asked for a continuation of $84,000 because at that time we were
                still quite optimistic that we might be able to turn out the ten volumes, but it was
                cut.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: So that did result in leaving out material that otherwise might be
                included?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, it didn't result in any difference in our compilation. We still
                put in the same. It simply meant—well, it happened or concurred that we ran into
                difficulties in clearance, so we couldn't put out any more.</p>
            <p>MR. CLOUGH: There is another aspect of the cost of this. That is that it is a burden
                on the people who do the clearance. The more you have to put in the "Foreign
                Relations", the more you have to be cleared by the geographic office and this takes
                a substantial amount of time.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is quite correct. I don't know what the implications of that
                are.</p>
            <p>MR. CLOUGH: Well, the only point is that the Departmental budget as a whole would be
                affected because it takes more manhours to accomplish a particular job.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: We reach the point where we can't by any means assume finality in any
                respect. Sacrifices will have to be made, it seems to me, to have a program at
                all.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: But I think in conferences, for example, you still wish to turn out
                as many as you can. There must be further elimination of data in fields that are
                almost required by the situation at present.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It is either that or cutting down in the marginal documents on those
                subjects which we cover.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: That is what I mean, really, cutting down on the volume of documents
                except when we want a full record of a thing like the Potsdam Conference—would it by
                any chance be obtained as full as possible. But in the normal volumes, it seems to
                me, there is room for further reduction.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: As a matter of fact, I have two volumes here which Mr. Perkins went
                through and indicated documents which might be regarded as marginal documents, and
                if we had time—perhaps we will before the conference is over—I'd like to just go
                through that and point out; some of them and get your comments on that. This
                afternoon we will have your comments on some other things, but I think that would be
                a useful exercise if we could spend some time on that.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: It strikes me that this question of clearance rears its ugly head at
                every point in trying to decide what your future is going to be. This would depend
                upon clearance and what you can do.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is correct. And on that you want to concentrate your earnest
                attention this afternoon.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: And the more important the subject, the greater the difficulty of
                clearance.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: On the question of personnel, it might be added that the war time
                conferences have had to be done by folks in the Policy Studies Branch, and in the
                regular compiling "Foreign Relations" branch of the division, so some inroads have
                been made there and they have been at the expense of our other work done for the man
                within the Department very largely, so there has been an increment there in such
                instances and it might be that some additional staff in the "Foreign Relations"
                branch might be necessary to keep up that slack.</p>
            <p>MR. DOUGALL: There is also the fact that cutting down on publication does not
                necessarily mean that we won't eventually need more staff just to go through the
                papers, because there are certain categories of files you can set aside but the
                other categories which you have to go through to pick out the important papers
                mushrooming beginning about 1945 and they will have to be gone through.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is a very good point. Well, you know the old saying, that if you
                have to give a ten-minute speech it takes you longer to prepare it than if you had
                to give a 30-minute speech.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: As I understand it, we are not qualified to discuss the entire foreign
                policies program of the State Department. It seems to me it's a budgetary problem
                for the series of "Foreign Relations"; it does become a general problem of
                publication, doesn't it? I mean, if we get a certain amount of money, it's the
                distribution of that money—whether it is distributed wisely. That is the point. I
                have sat in earlier previous years with some other special groups that have been
                called to discuss other phases of the publications program.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Sometimes the Congress acts to restrict or specify what it can spend
                for a particular purpose and sometimes it doesn't.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: That brings up the question about current publications, as to the
                extent they are repeated in the Foreign Service Bulletin, and you have the
                T.I.S.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Of course the T.I.S.—</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: In some of the older volumes of "Foreign Relations" they requested us
                to print the texts of treaties and drafts, etc. But I think the problem is more on
                the bulletins, as far as I know. There are many documents of considerable historical
                importance that are published in the Bulletin currently.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I would assume so, but Mr. Perkins can discuss that.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: The repetition of documents published in the Bulletin would not be
                an important fact in cutting down. Occasionally, on short key documents, we feel
                it's better to put in "Foreign Relations" rattier than send the person to find the
                Bulletin which perhaps he can't find. But the Bulletin is of a rather different
                nature. The great majority of our documents in "Foreign Relations" exchanges of
                telegrams between the Department and our missions and memoranda of conversations
                with officials, etc., etc., the nature of the documents is quite different. We have,
                in recent years, been adopting a policy of leaving out more documents that can be
                cited to a good official source where people can find them elsewhere.</p>
            <p>As you know, we have left out treaties and we are leaving out executive agreements.
                In some cases, though, you are right, we have printed drafts to show you can't very
                well have the correspondence on how a treaty was arrived at without presenting the
                drafts which were discussed. But we do not reproduce much <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bulletin</hi> material. </p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: You will be helped, won't you, as you get past '45 of the new
                publication of the documents on the period 1945-55, so far as treaties and those
                official texts will relieve you? Because I think there will be an authoritative
                volume of the State Department to which you can send yours.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: You wouldn't accept the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> text?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: No, not for a thing of that kind.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: I was thinking in terms of a cross reference.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: We are not supposed to show partiality between private
                publications, but in cases where we give citations, say, to the New York Times, it
                would be in some public speech or public statement by somebody that is not in any
                good official source. It may refer to a speech made by a certain person—well, that
                speech, is reproduced in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> and we might cite
                the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> in a case of that kind.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Has any thought been given to eliminating marginal countries completely,
                like Liberia?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, thought has been given to it. It is indicated in here [Indicating
                dossier]. </p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: Shouldn't we address ourselves to the questions raised on page 2?
                There are four points made here. I don't see that my views are crystallized on that,
                but I must say that points 1, 2 and 3 seem to me of a somewhat hierarchical order. I
                would think that one is the one to do first. I should dislike to see 4 done, if
                anything else could be done.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, we would dislike that very much too.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: In between that, my reaction—and I am willing to listen to other
                points of view—is that one, two and three represent a kind of hierarchical order. </p>
            <p>One is the simplest thing to do. I think two might be well considered. I am not so
                hot about three and I don't care at all about four. That is the way it goes with me. </p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Perhaps one word of explanation is needed. In putting these items
                down there is no suggestion that we recommend these. These were ideas that have come
                to us of what might be done and we put them in as possibilities, not as things that
                we recommend.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I would like to second Mr. Perkins' feeling, particularly about three
                and four—although my views are not crystallized on them either. But I feel as
                strongly about keeping three as I do about keeping four.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: It does tie up with the financial problem and the clearance problem.
                You can't discuss in the absolute sense without thinking about both. You agree in
                general with what I have been saying?</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I do.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: I am thoroughly in sympathy with the thought that Mr. Perkins expressed.
                If we assume that something has to be cut, that we can't continue to amplify to the
                extent that has been done, it seems to me that number one is a very sensible
                thought, that number two is a corollary which may be equally sensible, but numbers
                three and four should be thrown out entirely.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would agree completely with that, and it seems to me that if we are
                going to think in terms of the criteria that would be applied in tightening up on
                the selection, then that in my mind raises the question as to what the purpose or
                purposes of the "Foreign Relations" volumes are.</p>
            <p>Now, I take it that one purpose is to serve the interests of the Department and the
                Foreign Service. But so far as scholars are concerned, it seems to me that you can
                distinguish between more general interests of scholars in the history of "Foreign
                Relations" and the interpretation and application of "Foreign Relations" and the
                more specialized interests and the detailed story with regard to some fairly
                specific issue. And on the assumption that anyone can go to the Archives for all the
                detail he wants, I think that you might apply the principle of excluding documents
                that would be of interest only to the few who might be invested in a very detailed
                study of that particular question. Now, I don't know how that appeals to the
                diplomatic historians, I'm sure.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Has any investigation been made as to who uses this publication? Is it
                possible to achieve that as a corollary?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We have given some consideration to that, but it's very difficult to
                get a satisfactory analysis of it, I think. Of course people like yourselves are
                among those who are best able to tell us. I had this little item from the Library of
                Congress which is used in the Embassies. But from the public side, we might
                circulate a questionnaire—it might be a project which we ought to undertake, and
                with your approval and upon your suggestion, but; we have figures here as to the use
                that has been made of them in writings. As to how full the professors in this field
                require the use of "Foreign Relations" by their students is something we would like
                to know. I believe you would have to tell us.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think there is one thing to keep in mind in connection with what Mr.
                Bailey said, and that is the difference between, say, the use given to a volume in
                your series for 1934 today and in the last few years and what might be given 20
                years from now, coming back to the list of selections you made. The words of many of
                those volumes in that item are only now being written, but they are dealing with the
                period 1917-18, 1920-21.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: I go along with you, Mr. Perkins, on, that. I have a feeling we might be
                governed in the long run by Congress.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: What is the date they go to the National Archives now?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Actually, for the period 1930-39, they are there now. But during those
                years it is not fully open. It's fully open at 1930 without question under the rules
                of the Archives not the State Department. From 1930 to '41, inclusive, they are open
                under a semi-restricted basis, shall we say. And those restrictions are imposed by
                the Department; that is to say, anyone can apply and can have the privilege of using
                the files, subject to the clearance of his notes and possibly the review of his
                manuscript. We prefer just to clear notes, to avoid any possibility of so-called
                censorship of interpretation. But those are the restrictions with regard to that
                period, down through 1941.</p>
            <p>From 1941 down to the present, they are so-called closed and general access is not
                given except under the roost exceptional circumstances.</p>
            <p>MR. P. PERKINS: That means more than ever, it seems to me, that we have to establish
                criteria of what is really of most use because most students could not go to the
                Archives. I think, we are right in the way in which you arranged the possible means
                of elimination.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: On the question of the use of volumes, so far as our school is concerned,
                every student in the school is encouraged to use and, so far as I know, discuss
                these volumes in the preparation of term papers and their essays of that kind. There
                is a very general use, in other words.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It is quite impressive to me that the Library of Congress supplies 19
                volumes for general use and they are used extensively.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: Could I have a clarification on number three? Coverage of
                multilateral conferences, for example, on a year-by-year basis—how is that done? In
                other words, you don't wait for that month to be concluded before you report it, you
                just report what progress has been made for all the multilateral conferences done
                during the year, or what?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Ralph, you might discuss that. I will say in general that the coverage
                is on a year-by-year basis.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: That doesn't mean current, right after the thing has been
                published. It means our regular annual volumes are issued, so many volumes, for each
                year with the exception of one volume for 1939, for example, there were five
                volumes, four of which have come out and then of 1941 there are seven volumes, one
                of which has been published. It simply means that we would cover all these important
                subjects on a year-by-year basis and concentrate on things of major importance, a
                comprehensive coverage of all areas in all departments. In other words, if
                conferences are of minor importance, there we would not cover it, there are various
                policies which we would not consider of special importance, we would leave out large
                sections that were not of major importance.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: That is true now?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: No, a comprehensive coverage of all areas in all departments of
                general subjects and concentrate efforts on subjects or problems of major
                importance. For example, there is a difference between importance and major
                importance. We leave out lots of minor things now. But anything we need to cover the
                diplomatic activities, the diplomatic activities of the Department for a year, we
                put in. Under this three, we would omit a large number of the minor things and
                concentrate on getting the record on certain major subjects. That clearance is
                always bobbing up, of course, as you have noticed. There is one drawback to that. If
                you abandon the across-the-board coverage of all important subjects and just
                concentrate say on major subjects, we would always be told this subject you can
                abandon until sometime later, the clearance is easy on it.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: Perspective would change then too, and it's pretty dangerous to try
                to make the elimination cut very deep there.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: What I'm trying to get at is if you publish 16 years after the event
                a considerable record of multilateral conferences, you may not have anything that in
                new at all. There is not too much sensitivity. I suppose generally in multilateral
                conferences and a current publication on a multilateral conference might just
                anticipate the need for mentioning it in detail in the volume published 16 years
                later.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: To some extent, of course, you're right. And of course it would be
                true in discussions in the Assembly and all the discussions at the United Nations,
                the official discussions, are done in the open and those records are published and
                we would not reproduce, of course, those records. What we would print would be lots
                of documentation of what goes on behind the scenes. </p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: You mean behind the scenes so as the American Delegation to the
                Assembly is concerned—position papers and private conversations, and records of
                conversations with other delegations, that sort of thing? </p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: That kind of thing. </p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: That would supplement the printed record that is made available
                currently?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Of course we haven't really explored the post war period at all,
                except in the China series where we have compiled down through 1939.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: But you would expect future volumes of "Foreign Relations" to have
                United Nations subjects?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I don't know as we would have a subject "United Nations ". Of
                course we would have to explore that as we entered the field. But presumably we
                would do as we do now—we treat by subjects. And if a subject were brought up at the
                United Nations we would treat that phase along with other phases of the
                old-fashioned diplomacy going on outside. </p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Under the so-called general heading? </p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Well, it would depend on what the topic was. If it were something
                like disarmament, a multilateral subject, a general subject, it would be under a
                general heading. If it were something in Palestine or Syria, it would be under the
                heading, even though discussed at the United Nations.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: Coming back to the printing of documents already printed somewhere else,
                would you consider the collection of documents in which Leland Goodrich has joined
                in editing for the past for the Peace Foundations is an appropriate source to cite
                for the documents without necessarily reprinting them? This is in a sense a private
                source, of course.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I believe those documents mostly have been reproduced from official
                documents.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: No, sometimes they are reproductions of the <hi rend="italic">New York
                    Times</hi> texts and you obviously wouldn't accept those.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: No.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I wouldn't think the State Department would want to accept that as a
                substitute, but I think, it would be desirable to avoid duplicating, so far as
                possible documents already published by the Department.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: We have done that more and more as we have felt the need of
                tightening up on selection and cite too other cases. However, often where a document
                is not very long and has lots of references to it, it would be very inconvenient to
                have readers go out and find it from another source which they might not be able to
                find. But we definitely do consider the space problem on that.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: What bothers me is how you get the proper correlation between your
                conference documents and your year-by-year volumes on "Foreign Relations".</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Aside from this special war time series, we expect to treat the
                other conferences as we come to them in the regular course of "Foreign Relations".
                You see, in that case this problem that Mr. Dougall mentioned, of putting in lots of
                background documents, will not arise—I mean in the conference.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: Suppose you have a top-level conference sometime in the near future on
                the unification of Germany and in connection with that there will be a lot of
                communication between participating governments as well as the actual discussions
                that take place at the conference. Now, is that documentation going to be repeated
                in the year by-year volumes?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Perhaps I can say a word on that. We have made an effort, that you may
                have noticed, during the past ten years to bring out a large amount of
                documentation, all that could be released, currently on top-level conferences—you
                know, our volume on the Paris Peace Conference in '46, the volume on the conferences
                In Berlin, Geneva, and so on. These little booklets contain most all that can be
                released at the time and will help, I think, to take the pressure off "Foreign
                Relations" and I am sure Ralph would not contemplate reprinting those. That is what
                he meant when he referred before to having good official collections to which
                reference can be made. Then, however, he would for those conferences cover the
                background position papers, the formulation of United States policy, behind the
                scenes, and so on.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: But then you may have what has happened in connection with China. You
                had a single volume on the development of the China policy and then when the
                Republicans took over that wasn't enough, they wanted the full story to be told. Now
                you have 15 volumes on China. That is not a good example, but suppose this is a
                conference and you put into the conference record all the documentation. What do you
                do when you come to the year—just refer to that? I would think that is the logical
                thing to do.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: I might say on the China volumes, the method of compilation is very
                much the same as for the annual volumes, only we jumped ahead on China. But
                otherwise that same material would have been picked up in normal course. I think
                that, due however to a great interest in China, we did put in a great deal
                additional back-ground material that would otherwise not be put in, and there is one
                very good reason for that historically. A great deal of the discussion of our China
                policy has centered around a charge that the United States lost China. The other
                people say, as the Secretary said in his preface to the White Book, that nothing we
                did could have changed the picture, the final result. That, you see, concentrates
                interest on what went on in China, and you have to dig real into the picture of the
                Revolution in China much more than you normally would in the internal affairs of
                another country. And that probably would have arisen whether we did it in the
                regular course of the annual volumes or in a special series. </p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: At the moment, while we are making some progress, I think, as to how you
                solve your problem of cutting down the size, I raise now the question—it may be
                irrelevant— of how you have tried to save some space in the past and to take just a
                quick look. I have in mind one thing. In some of the supplements—correct me if I am
                wrong on this—for the World War series, or I think in some of the special
                conferences of the past, there was a list of people participating which might take
                only a page or two which was of tremendous assistance to even the specialists in the
                field—it was all there. You have this material in your present volumes in footnotes.
                I think the help that is given in the China volumes and in others is superb, but you
                have to dig and keep going. I wonder if this is the sort of thing we can perhaps put
                back as the series expands. That is the sort of thing I mean, and I believe it's
                missing from the regular years now. I do not believe there is one for the China
                volume for '42.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: No.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Just one other thing. I understand perfectly the reasons for omitting
                the digest, which I think goes back to the 1932-33 year, where you used to have the
                compilation at the start.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I wonder whether you thought there was any compromise between the
                omission and the very lengthy, maybe a hundred pages in each volume that you used to
                have; that is, that digest in the first hundred pages was very useful. It was very
                costly and space-consuming. I wonder whether there was any thought given to
                that.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Would that be helpful to give just a little of the documents?</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I don't know. It had occurred to me you are under constant pressure to
                reduce the size of the volume, which we appreciate, but even with the reduction in
                the size of the volume we are going to run apparently for each year seven volumes
                and this imposes on even the specialists a certain difficulty in any finding of
                aides or anything of that sort.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Would you give some consideration to that question? </p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: May I just speak to one point briefly?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: On this list of persons, we indexing and on have a section here/on
                indexing persons. If we index all people except those just given trivial reference,
                then a person can turn in the index and, while we would not put in all his
                positions, he might hold two or three positions during the year; if he is indexed
                you don't know who the man is so you turn to the first reference and he would be
                identified. We have thought that might meet that situation.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: That applies to the problem of precis too. You might do that by the
                index too.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Of course they serve two different purposes. The list of papers gives a
                guide into the volume and we have discussed this many times, but they do have their
                separate purposes.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, the question of whether the list of persons that you suggest
                would be as good as or better than including persons in the index—now, that is
                something we are beginning now and we would like very much to have your advice on
                that. Do you think it's desirable to have a list of persons, say, in the beginning
                of the book? Do you think it's also desirable, or alternatively desirable, to have
                persons listed in the index as we are now beginning at least?</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: In this volume we have both. This is indexed by name and also a
                list.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: If you have the index by person, it will be simply a page, there will be
                no breakdown beyond that but simply the number of the pages on which that man's name
                appears.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: No. There will be a breakdown.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: All of these things are desirable from the standpoint of the person using
                the volumes.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Well, are they sufficiently urgent to cause you to recommend them very
                strongly?</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I would think for a conference volume it would be very helpful to have
                at the beginning the list of participants, but for a normal volume I don't see any
                reason to have a list of persons at the beginning.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: In undertaking the names of the persons, I just learned that it raises
                the price per page of indexing quite a bit. I think it is $1.10 or something like
                that, and now it's $1.65 per page to include the names. I was surprised and somewhat
                shocked.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: It costs more to index by name than subject.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: For example, in the Yalta volume, Mr. Acheson is not in the index
                though he is mentioned several times.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes, we weren't too happy about that. The index was done hurriedly and
                it was our first departure from our regular practice so we said to go ahead and pick
                up all proper names and to use the list we gave him for the identification purposes.
                But it was not done meticulously.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: It is more complicated than one might think at first glance because
                the index is a specialized job and he was not completely familiar with the whole
                subject and, instead of referring to a person by name, he often said, "The Foreign
                Minister"—well, now in indexing the reference to the Foreign Minister is just as
                important as though he were mentioned by name. And in the index you have to be able
                to pick up those references: "The Ambassador", "The Foreign Minister", this, that
                and the other, have got to be picked up by office as well as by name. </p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: This is where the indexer needs a list of persons to begin with.
                Otherwise he is lost.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: Mr. Chairman, I'd like to suggest a point for consideration rattier
                than a point to be insisted upon. There may be a divergence between the interests of
                the two groups for which "Foreign Relations" is prepared. The Departmental and
                Foreign Service people may have a very different interest from that of the
                historical scholars. That might be pertinent in our consideration.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: Shall we try to serve both, or could there perhaps be a different
                print made available much earlier. Five to ten years earlier for the Departmental
                people? And to scholars whose brains might be considered to be adequate and secure.
                [Laughter]</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Our feeling, of course, is that even if we can't publish, say, for 15
                or 20 years that we can still go on compiling and we should go on compiling for the
                Department officers, you see, and others. Perhaps you would want to consider these
                questions: the list of persons, the including of names in the index along with the
                subjects, and then the matter of the list of papers. I wonder, have we done as much
                as we should in the way of considering this question of cutting down, if we have to
                cut down, the subjects? It is your preference, I gather, that it should be on the
                basis of including the same subjects, including countries, I take it.</p>
            <p>MR. BAILEY: Well, I come back to the point that I have raised but I don't seem to
                receive much support, namely, that we could give serious thought to dropping out
                certain countries for certain years, for example, Liberia, for instance, in a
                certain year might not contribute, too much.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: A good illustration of that was a protest we had from Professor
                Bemis once because we didn't have Argentina in "Foreign Relations" for a certain
                year. Actually, we did have Argentina in as a participant in the Pan-American
                Conference, but it just happened that for that year in bilateral relations between
                the United States and Argentina there was nothing of sufficient importance to cover.
                We do not make a practice of trying to get every country in. If there is nothing in
                any one year of sufficient importance in relation to that country, we omit it and
                you notice in there you go down the list of minor countries often and you will find
                countries are not listed for a certain year.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: Isn't that covered by one and two really?</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: All areas doesn't mean all countries. </p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Do you feel that we have adequately covered this question? If so, may
                we go on to "c" and we might have time to approach that before the Secretary comes
                in, as to the policy with regard to including documents from other agencies. You
                have a little note here which indicates the problem. Mr. Franklin and Mr. Dougall
                have pointed out the importance, as far as the war time conferences are concerned,
                to get the military. We all know how much more important the military has become
                since 1940; with the setting up of the National Security Council we know how much
                its importance is written into the process of reaching decisions of a high character
                and quality.</p>
            <p>The question is, how much of an effort we should make in normal circumstances to get
                the papers of, say, Defense and Treasury, for example, particularly Defense. It's
                obvious that it is not an easy matter to get them. We have a great deal of
                difficulty in getting clearance and getting access. Our people can't go in and go
                through their files and we couldn't do it for administrative reasons even if we were
                permitted on other grounds.</p>
            <p>Ralph, would you like to speak to that, as to the military papers which we normally
                get in ordinary diplomatic correspondence and in order to fill out a particular
                subject it might be necessary to go to Defense for additional papers.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: We do not try to cover strictly military subjects in "Foreign
                Relations", but obviously military subjects become diplomatic in nature at times.
                For example, you may have the question of withdrawing the Marines from China. Now,
                that is a military question, also a diplomatic question which the Department of
                State has a definite responsibility for. And naturally in our own files we have a
                great deal of correspondence presenting the side of the Department of the Navy on
                that subject. However, you may run into references to other important documents on
                the subject which we do not have in our files and in this case we may go to the
                Navy, say, for it.</p>
            <p>I remember a case, to go back and not take any current things, years ago during World
                War I where we set up a radio station in France. That was handled by the Navy. Then
                the question came up about terminating American control of that radio station, turn
                it back to France. We didn't have it in our files. They were talking about the
                agreement with France for that station, but we didn't have it in our files, yet we
                had discussions on the subject. We went to the Navy Department to get that agreement
                they had made with France for that naval radio station. That would be the kind of
                thing we would handle, you see.</p>
            <p>We do definitely try to, in our regular volumes, keep to the subjects in which the
                State Department has a very definite responsibility, not go wandering off into
                subjects even though they are international In scope that are primarily the
                responsibility of the military or of the Treasure Department, for example. Those are
                the two we run into most, Defense and Treasury.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Any comments on this?</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: Maybe I am out of line here, but I was struck by I think it was your
                statement, Mr. Chairman, about the difficulties of getting access to materials, I
                assume in the Department of Defense or either the Army or Navy, the difficulty of
                getting access and that there is an administrative difficulty even if you get
                them.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: As far as we are concerned, the limitation of our staff and going to do
                researchings in their files.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: That is, you wouldn't have the personnel?</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That's right.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: What about the Executive Offices and the President?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Of course the period we have worked on so far has been the period
                up through the Roosevelt Administration where we have had access to the papers at
                the Franklin Roosevelt Library at Hyde Park and we have had members of our staff and
                I myself have gone up several times to Hyde Park and made searches up there for
                supplementary records. Often those, however, are definite! State Department records
                which, have gotten mixed in with the Presidential papers.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: You would include in the subjects of which the State Department has
                responsibility the subjects handled by Heads of Government?</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: Well, the Heads of Government often take action, sometimes even
                without consulting the State Department. That may be true. But generally the
                subjects dealt with are within the scope of the State Department's responsibility
                and we definitely do need to supplement the State Department record with the action
                that is being taken up above.</p>
            <p>MR. DOUGALL: This is where the war time conference volumes had to go a slightly
                separate way from the annual volumes. At Potsdam, for instance, the problem of
                Soviet participation in the war against Japan was an import-ant subject. Mr. Truman,
                in writing about it afterwards, said that it was the reason why he went to Potsdam.
                The State Department was not in on those discussions at all. It was entirely at the
                Presidential level or when below it it was at the military level. Now, here we
                scrounged around for military papers, the Yalta papers, of which we didn't find very
                much, but on some we did. Mr. Stimson was in on this and we got some enlightening
                information from his papers on it. Nothing in the State Department papers.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Are you suggesting that those should not have been included in the
                "Foreign Relations" volumes?</p>
            <p>MR. DOUGALL: Oh, I think definitely they have got to go in when you're dealing with
                the Heads of Government conferences. And it's such a centrally important
                subject.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: This all came up to us when we first dug into Malta-Yalta. We have it
                in an even more acute form with regard to the conferences at Cairo and Tehran which
                you haven't heard about yet but which are also in galley stage and which I have been
                working on with the assistance of several others. This is the payoff on this
                particular problem because, of course, at Yalta-Malta we had Mr. Stettinius at least
                there. The Department was utterly unrepresented at the two Cairo and Tehran
                conferences, absolutely unrepresented, and only one paper was actually prepared in
                the Department of State, and the people who prepared it did not know what it was
                for, except they did learn that it was taken to Tehran. That is all.</p>
            <p>So, in doing a series on the war time conferences, there is no problem at all. We say
                on the back-strips of "Foreign Relations of the United States", we will go after
                documents wherever they might be, whether pertinent to United States Treasury, Hyde
                Park, Defense in all its categories, the whole works. But these are all the
                documents that fit the President. It just so happens he so chose not to use the
                Department of State but he used other agencies, private and official.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: But you are thinking really of what we would call loosely "official"
                documents that come before the President. The point that Mr. Dougall made about
                which side of the fence he is on comes up, it seems to me, very acutely as to how
                far you're going to pursue this policy of material that was never in the State
                Department files and how far into private collections, it seems to me, some of the
                criticisms of the Yalta-Malta volumes were, that you didn't go far enough.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Yes. You can see on what basis we started from. And we went about 500
                percent farther than we had ever gone before or than Ralph could ordinarily conceive
                of doing for every annual volume.</p>
            <p>MR. DOUGALL: It is terribly time-consuming.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: I don't think we should take those conferences as a precedent for our
                regular program.</p>
            <p>There are two reasons. For one reason, because of expansion; and, second, on
                theoretical consideration that after all the Department of State is not responsible
                for publishing the records of other agencies on things for which it does not assume
                responsibility.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: There will be a real problem, however, with regard to papers of the
                National Security Council. That will be our chief upcoming problem in the
                approachable years.</p>
            <p>MR. D. PERKINS: That won't arise for some time though.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: Not until '47. We have two to choose from, whether to stay in the
                Department or go afield.</p>
            <p>MR. GOODRICH: I think you have to go afield.</p>
            <p>MR. E.R. PERKINS: That is a different case because the State Department, of course,
                is represented on the Security Council.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: We have already dipped into it briefly because of the China volumes of
                '48 and '49 and we have already learned the extreme sensitivity of the National
                Security Council to make any reference which would indicate that it was an NSC
                document. In a number of cases, in other words, we can publish papers maybe, but
                with restrictions on identifying that it strictly wouldn't be very serious.</p>
            <p>MR. FRANKLIN: If the problem arises, we can publish papers submitted to the NSC by
                the Department of State. The question then arises on how far afield should we go to
                print other papers to give a broader knowledge of the papers submitted by the other
                departments, individuals, and agencies.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: The question is whether we can say the statement is a paper submitted
                by the Department to the NSC. Do we have a consensus, gentlemen, on this question? I
                have a feeling there is consensus here that there is a limit in which we should not
                go in trying to dig out the papers from other agencies, that the State Department
                has responsibilities to follow through on that but not beyond things which the State
                Department has important responsibility. Is that a fair statement?</p>
            <p>MR. BERBAHL: It seems to me that what you're doing is really discussing the exact
                application of the points the four points involved there. And it's very easy to
                agree, I think, on those four points on the disposition, but the application of
                those points is obviously a very difficult thing. You still have the problem of
                interpretation of these documents. So point one I suppose ought to read not only
                tighten up but loosen up occasionally. Such as approaching the other departments for
                significant documents that must by all means be included if we possibly can.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: Under Part 2 of the compilation, the Regulations and Procedures, it
                starts out by saying "The publication of Foreign Relations of the United States,
                Diplomatic Papers, constitutes the official record of the Foreign policy of the
                United States." It would seem to me to follow from that that you have got to chase
                down significant documents wherever you have to go to get them.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Particularly if they are NSC.</p>
            <p>MR. THAYER: Particularly if they are NSC.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: So far as that is the crux, so far as vital decisions are
                concerned.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: Yes, Treasury, Defense, Labor certainly concern themselves with "Foreign
                Relations". In dealing with ILO, certainly you have to get a hold of Department of
                Labor documents.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Don't you think that in most cases the matter of vital foreign policy
                interest there would be some State Department papers en the matter which would give
                us a lead into the other agency and on occasion Mr. Perkin has said we follow
                through where that seems to be called for. But not to approach the Labor Department
                or any other agency and to search his files separately.</p>
            <p>MR. TURLINGTON: The China problem was 1949, only eight years ago, different from the
                ordinary l6-year problem</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: That is correct, and we haven't published the papers yet.</p>
            <p>MR. LEOPOLD: I think this brings us back to the point to avoid criticism, not only at
                the Congressional level but even at the scholarly level, that it's imperative to
                make clear, as I know you have been trying to make clear, in the introductions of
                the individual volumes, just what is your policy of searching out material beyond
                what is actually in the State Department files. I feel that many of the critics of
                the Malta-Yalta volume expected you to do something that could not possibly be
                done.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: It's amazing too, there was a very honest conviction on the part of
                many people, of course, including the members of both Houses of Congress, that you
                could really put out these volumes in three or four or five years after the event.
                And anything under ten years of a classified document would require
                paraphrasing.</p>
            <p>You couldn't give the document in the clear under ten years because of the code,
                cryptographic material.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: There is a rule to this effect.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Yes. There is a gradual change in the code from year to year, but they
                don't feel entirely safe for ten years.</p>
            <p>MR. BERDAHL: There is not much danger of us catching up to ten years for a long
                period of time.</p>
            <p>[At 12:10 p.m., The Honorable John Foster Dulles, Secretary of State, Joined the
                Committee meeting.]</p>
            <p>SECRETARY DULLES: I wanted, actually, first of all, to express my very great
                appreciation for your coming down and helping us in what is a quite difficult
                problem.</p>
            <p>The publication of these "Foreign Affairs" volumes raises each year increased
                problems. As United States responsibilities become greater in the world, the volume
                of our diplomatic activity increases, and its sensitivity increases with our playing
                a more central part in world affairs than we did formerly.</p>
            <p>I was given, just before I came here, a first volume that was published in
                1861—almost a hundredth anniversary—and if you're interested in a small volume, you
                may be familiar with it. The first two documents are circulars to all Ministers of
                the United States. Of course in those days we didn't have any Ambassadors. The first
                one is by Mr. Black and the second is by Mr. Seward, dealing with the Civil War or
                the war between the States — whichever you choose to call it—and appealing to our
                Ministers to try to prevent any foreign interference in the struggle. There is fine
                language in it: [Reading]</p>
            <p> "We feel free to assume that it is the general conviction of men, not only here but
                in all other countries, that this federal union affords a better system than any
                other that could be contrived to assure the safety, the peace, the prosperity, the
                welfare, and the happiness of all the States of which it is composed. . . .</p>
            <p> "Nor do we think we exaggerate our national importance when we claim that any
                political disaster that should befall us, and introduce discord or anarchy among the
                States that have so "long constituted one great pacific, prosperous nation, under a
                form of government which has approved itself to the respect and confidence of
                mankind, might tend by its influence to disturb and unsettle the existing systems of
                government in other parts of the world, and arrest that progress of improvement and
                civilization which marks the era in which we live. "</p>
            <p>It's a little more high-flown than I write nowadays, but I approve the sentiment.</p>
            <p>Of course the volume has grown immensely. I think in '41, which is the last one, is
                it not, there were seven volumes of about a thousand pages each. As we get on to the
                war years, the Second World War years, and the post-war problems, we get into great
                difficulty as to what can be appropriately published without serious damage to
                existing relations. A lot of these problems remained unresolved for quite a while.
                Take the problem of the reunification of Germany, which goes back to the war
                conferences, the Potsdam Conference perhaps most particularly, and where today the
                complete revelation of what took place there might have very bad consequences upon
                our problems of today and afford the Communists ammunition which they would use
                against us in Germany. </p>
            <p>We have a special mandate, I think, from the Congress. We got together quite a lot of
                work on the Potsdam papers. It is designed to be a special publication, along with
                the Malta-Yalta volume, I think, but we haven't yet been able to bring ourselves to
                publish the papers on Potsdam because of adverse political consequences that might
                result from that. Those, I suppose, will be the types of problems that you gentlemen
                will deal with.</p>
            <p>I hope that in dealing with that problem you will take account of some other things
                that we are doing which, while they do not technically meet the conventional
                requirements of our "Foreign Affairs" volumes, do go quite a ways toward meeting the
                needs of scholars. One of these is to get up these volumes which Dr. Noble is
                working on. This is the first of two volumes on American Foreign Policy from 1950 to
                '55, from pages 1 to 1700. There will be a second volume from pages 1700 to
                approximately 3500 or thereabouts; which will include a great deal of the
                significant diplomatic history of those years. And you are, I think, planning to try
                to get that on more or less of an annual basis. You are trying to get out one for
                the next two years and then pick it up from then on on an annual basis for the
                documents so that the documents will be coming out fairly promptly after the close
                of each year. Is that your program, Dr. Noble?</p>
            <p>MR. NOBLE: Yes, sir, that's right.</p>
            <p>SECRETARY DULLES: Nowadays, while this reflects only non-classified documentation,
                the pressure for knowledge about documents which comes from the press and the
                Congress, and so forth, is so great that there is included actually now in a volume
                like this a great deal of material which normally or in the past would have been
                kept classified and only appear in the "Foreign Relations" volumes.</p>
            <p>Then we also have adopted the practice, in the interest of information for the
                scholars, of publishing special pamphlets or booklets dealing with international
                conferences or periods of special concern. We have got out a series of books on the
                Berlin Conference with the Russians in '54, the conferences which led up to the
                bringing of Germany into NATO and the conference of the London-Paris Accords of '54,
                the "Summit" Conference, the Conference of Foreign Ministers that followed the
                "Summit" Conference, the documentation with reference to the Suez Conferences that
                were held in London, and then the documents with reference to the subsequent
                evolution of that into the crises that began with the Israeli and the British and
                French attack of a year ago in October or November, along through that period.</p>
            <p>Those publications do include a considerable amount of information which, in that
                particular form at least, was classified at the time but which was subsequently
                released with the consent of the governments concerned, and constitutes another
                important addition to the information available to scholars and is pretty much
                current. We have been able to get those volumes out within a few weeks after the
                closing events which they dealt with. So that we are making a very considerable
                effort to make available to students and scholars, and those interested in public
                affairs, a very large amount of material which partially at least covers what
                normally would be covered by the "Foreign Affairs" volumes.</p>
            <p>That doesn't mean that there is not a very considerable additional amount which at
                some time or other should come out in "Foreign Affairs" volumes. It does indicate
                that we are attempting to compensate in terms of making available in convenient form
                quickly such material as can be made available in that form, and that is a great
                deal, to compensate for the embarrassments we are under in not being able to bring
                out a complete record of all our correspondence because of the extremely sensitive
                character of much of what we are now doing.</p>
            <p>In the past days, particularly up to the end of the Second World War or the middle of
                the Second World War, the United States relationship with these events was rather
                peripheral. The leading part was played by what were then called the Great Powers.
                We were not among them, although we began to become that in the First World War,
                until we achieved a dominant position in the world at the end of the Second World
                War. So that prior to that time, you gentlemen know far better than I do, the really
                important decisions, the highly secret decisions, highly sensitive decisions were
                taken by other governments than ours. And we, as I say, were somewhat peripheral in
                our attitude toward those matters.</p>
            <p>Now the center has shifted here and it is our action which becomes central and in a
                way most sensitive and, furthermore, we are engaged in a so-called "cold war" which
                has gotten pretty hot at times, where there is an extremely well-organized
                propaganda machine which is ready to seize any events whatsoever and use them
                against us. And when you get into problems like the Arab-Israel problem, well, I
                suppose it would be catastrophic to our position in the whole free world in the
                Middle East if there should be a complete revelation of what took place, going back
                into and preceding the creation of the State of Israel. We sent some of that
                material up to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee when they were going to have a
                hearing on the subject and they dropped it like a hot cake. And you [indicating Mr.
                Noble] worked and did a terrific job on that. We got this material up there and when
                they began to see what was in it they decided they would discontinue that particular
                inquiry.</p>
            <p>The problem that you have undertaken to help us with is one of very, very great
                difficulty and where we need the best guidance that we can get. You have offered to
                give it to us, and I think you would be rendering a real service to your country in
                its various aspects of responsibility as you study the problem and tell us how you
                think it can be resolved.</p>
            <p>I guess that is all I have to say. Do any of you gentlemen have any questions you
                would like to put to me?</p>
            <p>MR. NOBLE: I am sure they must be teeming with questions.</p>
            <p>SECRETARY DULLES: Well, we think that we have a very extremely conscientious and able
                person in you, Dr. Noble, in charge of this work here. I find whenever I have called
                on you I get very quickly very comprehensive and totally impartial reports.</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: I have a very good staff. Thank you very much, Mr. Secretary.</p>
            <p>[At 12:29 p.m. the Secretary left the meeting room.]</p>
            <p>THE CHAIRMAN: Any remarks or comments? [None]</p>
            <p>Would it be agreeable to you to meet back here at 2:30 for approximately two hours?
                And then meet tomorrow morning at 10? [Agreed]</p>
            <p>[Whereupon the meeting was recessed at 12:30 p.m. to reconvene at 2:30 p.m.]</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
