<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“No Policy Issue Can Be of Comparable Importance”: The 1980
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Re-Review</title>
                <title type="short">The 1980 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Re-Review</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-12-09">December 9, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Between the spring and fall of 1980, Department of State officials debated the
                    proper balance between security and transparency as they argued about the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) series. In the spring of 1980, as U.S. policymakers grappled
                    with the frenzied aftermath of the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and the
                    Iranian revolution, plans to modernize U.S. intermediate nuclear forces based in
                    Western Europe, and Josip Tito’s death in Yugoslavia, a combination of
                    institutional reform of declassification procedures within the Department and
                    anxieties held by some Department officials inspired a re-review of already
                    cleared <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compilations. In response, David Trask, the
                    head of the Office of the Historian (HO), used the official “dissent channel” to
                    appeal the re-review decision to the highest levels of the Department. Trask’s
                    appeal was denied and the re-review delayed, for several years, the release of
                    many <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes covering the first half of the 1950s.
                    More importantly, however, the 1980 debate over <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    exposed sensitivities to releasing Cold War secrets that continued to plague the
                    series – eventually with sensational consequences – throughout the remainder of
                    the decade.</p>
                <p>The 1980 re-review was an ironic consequence of institutional reform that was
                    designed to streamline and liberalize Department declassification procedures. In
                    response to President Jimmy Carter’s Executive Order 12065 on classification and
                    declassification policies in 1978,<note n="1">Jimmy Carter, “National Security
                        Information,” Executive Order 12065, June 28, 1978 available at <ref target="http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-12065.htm">http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-12065.htm</ref> (accessed December
                        2, 2011).</note> Under Secretary of State for Management Ben Read determined
                    that “declassification activities are a permanent and major function and the
                    Department must organize itself to handle them on a permanent basis.” To
                    implement Carter’s directive, Read established “a unified Department-wide
                    structure governing all aspects of records release.” The
                    Classification/Declassification Center (CDC) replaced an ad hoc process of
                    clearances by desk officers in the geographic and functional bureaus whose
                    prioritization of operational responsibilities sometimes led to tardy or
                    arbitrary decisions about protecting or releasing information. The transition to
                    CDC authority was supposed to be gradual, with the existing process remaining in
                    place for records from 1950-1954 and the new system responsible for records from
                    1955 onward.<note n="2">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d1">Ben Read
                            memorandum to all Assistant Secretaries, Special Assistants, and Office
                            Heads, November 20, 1978 and Department notice,
                            “Classification/Declassification Center,” November 24, 1978</ref> in
                        Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S.
                        Department of State, Washington, DC (henceforth “Dissent Channel
                        Package”).</note>
                </p>
                <p>In 1980, this plan for a gradual, orderly bureaucratic transition fell apart
                    after Department officials protested that the old declassification process led
                    to flawed clearances for several <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes that were
                    near publication. On March 19, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Clayton
                    McManaway (who was in charge of the CDC) informed HO and its parent Bureau of
                    Public Affairs (PA) that the CDC was assuming responsibility for reviewing
                    pre-1955 records, especially those regarding relations with the British. Two
                    major concerns held by officials in the Bureau of European Affairs (EUR) and CDC
                    animated the initiation of the re-review. The first was that previous reviewers
                    had made poor assessments of the sensitivity of foreign government information
                    in U.S. documents and that existing Department procedures were inadequate for
                    protecting such information.<note n="3">Long-standing <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> clearance practices had made foreign government consent
                        necessary for publishing foreign government-originated documents, but
                        Department historians had repeatedly resisted submitting all U.S.-originated
                        documents to foreign governments for clearance in the past. During the
                        1950s, partial exceptions were made for wartime conference volumes that
                        printed U.S. minutes of Allied summit meetings, but these minutes were sent
                        to the British Government for “information only” – not for clearance. See
                        Morrison Giffen memorandum to Wilder Spaulding, June 4, 1935, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/866 and William Phillips instruction to Joseph Grew, July 15,
                        1935, 026 Foreign Relations/878 in Department of State Central Decimal
                        Files, 1930-1939, RG 59, NARA II; “Clearance with the British Government” in
                        “Briefing Papers prepared for the Secretary’s discussion with the Senate
                        Foreign Relations Committee on April [19],” [April 14, 1955?], Folder “Malta
                        and Yalta Conferences 1955,” Box 3; William Franklin memorandum to Bernard
                        Noble, November 29, 1956 and Richardson Dougall memorandum to Bernard Noble,
                        December 4, 1956 in Folder “November-December 1956,” in Box 6; and
                        Richardson Dougall memorandum for the files, December 2, 1957, Folder
                        “November-December 1957” and Andrew Berding memorandum to Burke Elbrick,
                        January 14, 1958 in Folder “January-February 1958” in Box 7 in Records
                        Relating to the Compilation of the World War II Conference Volumes of the
                        Publication “Foreign Relations of the United States,” Lot File 83 D 222, RG
                        59, NARA II; and Robert Woodward memorandum to Alexis Johnson, December 4,
                        1961, 023.1/12-461; Roger Tubby memorandum to Alexis Johnson, January 3,
                        1962, 023.1/1-362; and Edwin Martin memorandum to Alexis Johnson, July 20,
                        1962 and Mark Lissfelt memorandum to Edwin Martin and Robert Manning, July
                        31, 1962 in 023.1/7-2062 in Department of State Central Decimal Files,
                        1960-1963, RG 59, NARA II.</note> The second was that information had become
                    re-sensitized between desk officer clearance and preparation of volume
                    manuscripts for publication.<note n="4">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d2">Clayton
                            McManaway memorandum to William Blair, March 19, 1980</ref>; David Trask
                        memorandum to William Blair, March 26, 1980; and <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d3">memorandum of
                            conversation (March 27, 1980) between Clayton McManaway, et al., April
                            2, 1980</ref> in “Dissent Channel Package”; memorandum of conversation
                        between Laurence Pickering and David Baehler, April 4, 1980, Folder
                        “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954
                        (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC
                        (henceforth “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign
                        Relations”).</note> On April 11, Assistant Secretary of State George Vest,
                    who headed EUR, formally withdrew his bureau’s clearances of all unreleased <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compilations. The same day, Under Secretary Read
                    affirmed that CDC would re-review almost two dozen compilations that had already
                    completed or nearly completed clearances under the old declassification
                        procedures.<note n="5">
                            <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d4">George Vest
                                memorandum to Ben Read, April 11, 1980</ref> and <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d5">Ben Read
                            memorandum to all Assistant Secretaries, April 11, 1980</ref> in
                        “Dissent Channel Package.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>At first, Trask and other historians in HO cooperated with the re-review in the
                    hope that it could be limited in scope and completed quickly, thus minimizing
                    delays for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publication. These hopes faded quickly
                    after April 11. Over the next month and a half, HO attempted to persuade key
                    officials that the re-review and proposals to expand the scope of foreign
                    government clearances were unnecessary and counterproductive. On April 11, Trask
                    argued that “no sovereign state should compromise in any way its freedom of
                    action to dispose of its records as it chooses” and that “only the United States
                    can bear responsibility for a report of foreign-government information in an
                    American document.”<note n="6">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d6">David Trask
                            memorandum for the record, April 11, 1980,</ref> “Dissent Channel
                        Package.”</note> He also tried to reassure Vest that HO followed careful
                    procedures to “minimize untoward stories or embarrassment for missions overseas”
                    when <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes were published.<note n="7">David Trask
                        memorandum to George Vest, April 14, 1980, “Dissent Channel Package.”</note>
                    On April 28, Trask rejected a CDC suggestion that “the 30-year publication line
                    is more sensible than the 20-year line,” characterizing “delaying the series” as
                    “overkill of the first magnitude.”<note n="8">David Trask memorandum to William
                        Dyess, April 28, 1980, “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign
                        Relations.”</note> On May 2, Trask added that “at no point in the
                    publication of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series have
                    untoward consequences resulted from the traditional practice of avoiding
                    discussions with foreign governments concerning publication of their information
                    in American documents.” Moreover, he warned that, even if “consultation with
                    foreign governments is primarily being considered with reference to the UK and
                    other Commonwealth countries,” “drawing distinctions between foreign countries
                    in terms of their right to prepublication review could create misunderstandings
                    and tensions.”<note n="9">Hodding Carter draft memorandum to Ben Read (tab 7 of
                        David Trask memorandum to Hodding Carter), May 2, 1980, “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Trask also emphasized the damaging effects that the re-review would have on the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. Though Under Secretary Read
                    was the key decision-maker in the re-review, Trask had to enlist Hodding Carter
                    III, the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs, to support HO’s case
                    before going up the bureaucratic chain of command. On May 2, Trask sent a
                    memorandum to Carter urging the Assistant Secretary to take up HO’s case by
                    forwarding a slew of memos addressed to Read and McManaway that affirmed the
                    value of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> for the Department, described the
                    difficulties engendered by the re-review and CDC’s actions, rejected the
                    re-review of some volumes, insisted upon a rapid timetable for others, and
                    pressed for the retention of existing policies for clearing foreign government
                    information in U.S. documents. Carter declined to support HO’s bureaucratic
                        appeals.<note n="10">
                            <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d9">David Trask
                            memorandum to Hodding Carter (with attached draft memoranda), May 2,
                            1980,</ref> “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign
                        Relations.”</note> By May 22, Trask had “come to the firmest conclusion that
                    decisive action should be taken immediately to stop all tampering with
                    unpublished volumes.”<note n="11">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d11">David Trask
                            memorandum to William Dyess, May 22, 1980,</ref> “Dissent Channel
                        Package.”</note> On June 11, 1980, Trask used the dissent channel to bypass
                    the CDC, his superiors in PA, and Under Secretary Read and appeal the re-review
                    directly to the highest levels of the Department. He argued that, “if the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series is compromised, so is the
                    Department’s commitment to open government. Given the fundamental importance of
                    information in the function of a democratic society, no policy issue can be of
                    comparable importance.”<note n="12">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d13">David Trask
                            memoranda to Anthony Lake, June 11, 1980,</ref> “Dissent Channel
                        Package.” Despite Trask’s request to restrict distribution of the dissent
                        channel appeal from M and the CDC, Lake’s office included those officials as
                        recipients later in June. See Anthony Lake memorandum to David Trask, June
                        30, 1980, “Dissent Channel Package.” For background on the dissent channel,
                        see Hannah Gurman, “The Other Plumbers Unit: The Dissent Channel of the U.S.
                        Department of State,” <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic History</hi> (April
                        2011), pp. 321-349.</note> He also informed the <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/formation-of-the-hac">Historical Advisory
                        Committee</ref>, comprised of leading scholars representing academic
                    stakeholders, about the re-review and HO’s efforts to uphold previous
                        clearances.<note n="13">David Trask memorandum to members of the Advisory
                        Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation, June 11, 1980, “Dissent
                        Channel Package.” Word of the re-review and concerns over the clearance of
                        foreign government information had already reached the academic community in
                        May. See Lloyd Gardner letter to George McGovern and Frank Church, May 6,
                        1980; David Trask memorandum to Hodding Carter, May 12, 1980; and George
                        McGovern letter to Brian Atwood, May 14, 1980 in “Dissent Channel
                        Package.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Even before the dissent channel appeal was underway, the re-review commenced. In
                    anticipation of a June 5 meeting of the Department’s Oversight Committee
                    responsible for implementing President Carter’s executive order, Trask still
                    hoped that the re-review could be avoided.<note n="14">David Trask memorandum to
                        William Dyess, May 23, 1980, “Dissent Channel Package.”</note> On May 27,
                    however, McManaway reported that “the results achieved thus far more than
                    justify the undertaking of the re-review. The protection of materials relating
                    to Yugoslavia, Iran, and to several of our European allies have been of great
                        importance.”<note n="15">Clayton McManaway memorandum to Oversight Committee
                        for the Department’s Information Security Program (E.O. 12065) [henceforth
                        Oversight Committee], May 27, 1980, “Dissent Channel Package.”</note> Trask
                    pressed the case against the re-review at the June 5 meeting. He had support
                    from William Dyess, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, who noted
                    “the implications” of the re-review debate “went well beyond publication of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> to the whole question of sincerity about openness in
                    government.” Robert Miller, the Director of Management Operations, argued that
                    “the publication of post-World War II records would lead to many more [foreign
                    policy] difficulties than had the publication of earlier records … because there
                    is continuity between the early postwar years and the institutions that
                    developed the[n] and the present.” David Baehler, HO’s Declassification Advisor,
                    countered that the Department had “yet to hear a peep of protests from foreign
                    governments reflecting foreign policy difficulties” even though it had “been
                    publishing postwar documents for fifteen years now.” Similarly, after Dyess
                    pointed out that “no political repercussions have arisen from re-sensitization
                    of already published records,” he suggested that “it was unclear why they should
                    arise from records about to be published.” Miller was unconvinced. He claimed
                    that “the act of publication can be construed abroad as a political statement on
                    the part of the US government.” With assurances from the Government Printing
                    Office that re-reviewed manuscripts could be “fast-tracked” for early
                    publication, the Bureau of Management (M) and CDC dismissed HO’s warnings of
                    significant delays in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Despite Trask’s criticism of
                    the decision-making process that led to the re-review, his warnings of looming
                    “image problems” with the academic community, and his projection of the high
                    cost of the re-review, M and the CDC rejected HO’s arguments and proceeded with
                    the re-review.<note n="16">“Decisions, Undertakings, and Understandings Reached
                        at the Oversight Meeting of June 5, 1980,” [no date] and <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d12">memorandum of
                            conversation (June 5, 1980) between Robert Miller, et al., June 9,
                            1980</ref> in “Dissent Channel Package.”</note> By June 27, just days
                    before Trask’s dissent channel message was distributed to M or CDC, McManaway
                    reported that the re-review was on schedule and that a total of nine <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes were on track to be printed between
                    September 15 and December 15, 1980.<note n="17">Clayton McManaway memorandum to
                        Oversight Committee, June 27, 1980, “Dissent Channel Package.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Over the next few months, HO pursued dual tracks within the Department
                    bureaucracy. Trask and his colleagues remained fully engaged in the re-review
                    process. On July 23, McManaway reported that CDC had completed its re-review of
                    half of the 19 volumes affected and that “there should be no difficulty in
                    meeting the established deadlines.”<note n="18">Clayton McManaway memorandum to
                        Oversight Committee, July 23, 1980, “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of
                        Foreign Relations.”</note> On September 15, McManaway reiterated his
                    optimism that “all [volumes] are scheduled to be completed on or before November
                    1, 1980.”<note n="19">Clayton McManaway memorandum to Oversight Committee,
                        September 15, 1980, “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign
                        Relations.”</note> Despite CDC’s assurances, Trask was pessimistic that the
                    bureaucracy would meet the re-review targets since HO and CDC could not even
                    agree on what constituted a “complete” re-review.<note n="20">David Trask
                        memorandum to Terry McNamara, September 23, 1980, “Documents Relating to the
                        Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>At the same time, Trask peppered Elaine Morton, who was assigned to coordinate
                    the dissent channel response from the Policy Planning Staff, with memoranda
                    criticizing the re-review.<note n="21">David Trask memorandum to Felix Vargas
                        and Elaine Morton, July 3, 1980 and David Trask memorandum to Elaine Morton,
                        July 7, 1980 in “Dissent Channel Package.” To the latter memo, Trask
                        attached the various documents contained in the “Dissent Channel Package”
                        folder cited above.</note> On July 18, Trask pointed out that
                    “fast-tracking” re-reviewed volumes for early publication, even if successful,
                    would so disrupt the production process that subsequent volumes would be
                        delayed.<note n="22">David Trask memorandum to Elaine Morton, July 18, 1980,
                        “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note> On August
                    28, he criticized re-sensitization as a justification for re-reviewing
                    documents. He pointed out that the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume that had
                    initially alarmed the CDC and EUR back in April had been released to “not one
                    jot or tittle of reaction” and explained that HO “editorial practice works
                    against sensationalism.” He dismissed “concern about ‘resensitization’” as “an
                    aspect of ‘nervous nellyism’ that can prevail in government during periods of
                    stress” and characterized fears that Cold War-related documentation would be
                    more susceptible to re-sensitization as “just plain stupid.” Trask closed his
                    argument by claiming that he had “observed a lot of smoke screens in my time,
                    but ... none as patently ridiculous as this one.”<note n="23">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d14">David Trask
                            memorandum to Elaine Morton, August 28, 1980,</ref> “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Finally, on September 9, Trask responded to allegations of foreign concern about
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. He traced these anxieties to “’nervous
                    nellyism’ and clientism in the Department” and conflations of foreign government
                    apprehensions about the Freedom of Information Act with <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. After dismissing “fears that somehow, someway, great disasters
                    will flow from publication of the truth many years after the event,” Trask
                    insisted that “even if on some future occasion a row materializes, we have to
                    weigh some slight evanescent inconvenience against our responsibility to report
                    the truth at an appropriate time without fear or favor. If we stray from that
                    principle in publishing our foreign affairs record objectively at a reasonable
                    remove from currency, we will be throwing away one of our strong and undeniable
                    assets in dealing with the rest of the world and informing our own people.”
                    Trask’s memorandum concluded with an assertion that “it is of great importance
                    that nervous nellies are not allowed to use international concern about
                    unauthorized leaks or authorized Freedom of Information releases to injure the
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series, about which no
                    comparable body of concern has ever been manifest.”<note n="24">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d15">David Trask
                            memorandum to Elaine Morton, September 9, 1980,</ref> “Documents
                        Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>HO’s battle against re-review reached its apogee in early October 1980. In a
                    meeting chaired by David Newsom, the Under Secretary of State for Political
                    Affairs, Trask, Vest, and Laurence Pickering from CDC debated HO’s appeal of
                    re-review excisions from the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compilation for
                    European security in 1951. Newsom focused on two basic questions: “what are our
                    obligations to our allies and to NATO?” and how should the “possible damage of
                    release to national security ... be weighed against the right of the public to
                    the information”? Newsom pressed all three officials. The Under Secretary asked
                    Trask pointed questions about clearing foreign government information and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s role in the overall declassification process. He
                    queried Vest about the continued sensitivities of NATO military planning and
                    documents relating to Greece and Turkey’s admission to NATO. Laurence Pickering
                    intervened in the discussion at several points to clarify CDC views on
                    declassification procedures and authorities. Ultimately, Newsom upheld the
                    continued secrecy of documents referencing Yugoslavia and those relating to
                    Greek and Turkish entrance into NATO. Action to implement Newsom’s agreement
                    with HO that NATO military planning documents could be released was deferred
                    until the CDC could consult with the NSC. Though Newsom upheld existing
                    procedures for reviewing foreign government information in U.S. documents and he
                    explicitly endorsed Trask’s formulation of a balancing test between security and
                    transparency, he accepted most of EUR and CDC’s arguments about where such a
                    line should be drawn in 1980.<note n="25">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d16">Memorandum of
                            conversation between David Newsom, et al., October 9, 1980 and David
                            Baehler memorandum for the record, October 9, 1980,</ref> “Documents
                        Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Policy Planning Staff Director Anthony Lake’s response to Trask’s dissent channel
                    appeal echoed Newsom’s stance at the re-review appeal meeting. Lake agreed with
                    Trask that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was “central to the Department’s
                    adherence to the principle of open government.” He also agreed with the CDC that
                    “the decentralized nature of previous reviews of the 1950-1954 material and
                    events transpiring during the relatively long period of time that elapsed
                    between some of the initial declassification actions and the dates of planned
                    publication combined to allow material to be authorized for publication, the
                    release of which would either: (1) tend to impede current diplomatic
                    negotiations or other business; (2) fail to preserve the confidence reposed in
                    the Department by individuals and by foreign governments; (3) give needless
                    offense to other nationalities or individuals; or (4) reflect personal opinions
                    presented in internal communications and not acted upon by the Department.”
                    Given the possible “negative impact upon our ability to conduct an effective
                    diplomacy,” Lake described the decision to undertake the re-review as “proper.”
                    He also echoed the CDC’s optimistic projections for completing the re-review and
                    publishing the affected <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes and reaffirmed the
                    adequacy of the Department’s existing policies and procedures for “balancing
                    national security concerns and the public’s right to know about the history of
                    our foreign policy.” Lake’s response amounted to a total rejection of Trask’s
                        appeal.<note n="26">
                            <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d17">Anthony Lake
                            memorandum to David Trask, October 14, 1980,</ref> “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.” The language that Lake used to
                        justify the re-review came directly from the 1925 Order that formalized FRUS
                        editorial methodologies and defined acceptable grounds for excisions. See
                            <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1925-order">http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1925-order</ref> (accessed
                        December 2, 2011).</note>
                </p>
                <p>The re-review controversy fueled academic community concerns about both the
                    timeliness and the comprehensiveness of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Within days
                    of Lake’s response, Trask, Baehler, and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> General
                    Editor William Slany met with Professors (and former HAC members) Walter LaFeber
                    and Lloyd Gardner to discuss Department of State declassification
                        procedures.<note n="27">LaFeber and Gardner were prominent historians of
                        U.S. foreign relations and members of an Organization of American Historians
                        ad hoc committee on declassification practices and access to
                        documents.</note> LaFeber and Gardner both exhibited concern that the
                    empowerment of the CDC would slow declassification and result in more documents
                    being withheld from release. After Gardner proposed withholding “any volume that
                    proved to be less than complete on any important issue,” Slany “pointed out that
                    HO’s lack of access to other agencies’ files compromised this principle, quite
                    apart from unfavorable declassification actions. He said that access was the
                    other half of the declassification coin.” As the meeting concluded, “Gardner
                    closed by reiterating his concern that HO not sacrifice the comprehensiveness of
                    the series in the effort to attain the twenty year line.” Trask replied that “HO
                    desired both to maintain – indeed to enhance – the comprehensiveness of the
                    volumes and to attain the twenty year line.”<note n="28">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript#d18">David Baehler
                            memorandum for the record, October 17, 1980,</ref> “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations.” The 20-year publication line had
                        been established by Richard Nixon in a March 8, 1972 memorandum attached to
                        Executive Order 11652. See <ref target="http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-11652.htm">http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-11652.htm</ref> (accessed August
                        9, 2011).</note>
                </p>
                <p>By early November, the re-review had already fallen behind schedule. In a report
                    to Newsom, Dyess pointed out that only two of the 18 compilations being
                    re-reviewed (two others relating to Iran had been deferred indefinitely) had
                    “run the full course preparatory to publication.” While HO had received
                    information about 4 other manuscripts, it still had no response from CDC
                    concerning two thirds of the re-review workload that was supposed to have been
                    completed entirely by November 1.<note n="29">William Dyess memorandum to David
                        Newsom, November 4, 1980, “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign
                        Relations.”</note> In mid-November, the annual HAC meeting focused on the
                    re-review and its implications. The HAC’s report warned that, with the creation
                    of the CDC and the tightening of declassification guidelines, “a critical
                    situation has developed, one which threatens the integrity of the Foreign
                    Relations series.”<note n="30">Betty Unterberger, “1980 Report of the Advisory
                        Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation,” <hi rend="italic">PS:
                            Political Science and Politics</hi> (Spring 1981), pp. 274-281. Quote
                        from p. 280.</note> HO and HAC concerns about the re-review were realized as
                    the series fell further behind its official goal of a 20-year publication line
                    in the 1980s. Of the nine “fast-tracked” volumes scheduled to be published in
                    1980, one was published in 1981, two in 1982, three in 1983, two in 1984, and
                    one (after being split into two volumes) in 1987 and 1989.<note n="31">The
                        “fast-tracked” volumes were: European Security and the German Question
                        (1951, Vol. III), Korea and China (1951, Vol. VII), General Political and
                        Economic (1952-1954, <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v01p1">Vol. I</ref>), American Republics (1952-1954, Vol. IV); West European
                        Security (1952-1954, <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1952-54v05p1">Vol. V</ref>), Africa and South Asia (1952-1954, Vol. XI), Indochina
                        (1952-1954, Vol. XIII), Geneva Conference (1952-1954, Vol. XVI), and Africa
                        and South Asia (1955-1957, Vols <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1955-57v08">VIII</ref> and <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1955-57v18">XVIII</ref>).</note> The
                    1980 re-review, the delays that it entailed for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, and
                    the CDC-led declassification process that initiated it were all major
                    contributors to mounting academic concerns over timeliness and comprehensiveness
                    that plagued the series throughout the decade before exploding into controversy
                    in 1990 and 1991.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Read <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview-transcript">recently declassified documents on the 1980 re-review</ref>, or
                        download the <ref target="http://static.history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/1980-rereview-documents.pdf">PDF</ref>, 2.2 MB, 61 pp.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>