<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Documents Relating to the 1980 Re-Review of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>
                </title>
                <title type="short">1980 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Re-Review Documents</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-12-09">December 9, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>These documents were released in conjunction with <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview">“The 1980
                            <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Re-Review."</ref> A scan of the original
                    documents is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus150/1980-rereview-documents.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 2.2 MB, 61 pp.).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d1">
                <head>1. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State for Management (Ben Read) to
                    All Assistant Secretaries, Special Assistants, and Office Heads<note n="1"
                        >Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114,
                        U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1978-11-20">November 20, 1978</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Classification/Declassification System</p>
                <p>As you know, we have been studying for some months how the Department can best
                    organize itself to respond to the new Executive Order on Classification and
                    Declassification policy (E.O. 12065)<note n="2">Jimmy Carter, “National Security
                        Information,” Executive Order 12065, June 28, 1978 available at <ref
                            target="http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-12065.htm"
                            >http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-12065.htm</ref> (accessed December
                        2, 2011).</note>. A major conclusion we have reached is that these
                    activities, in particular the declassification activities are a permanent and
                    major function and the Department must organize itself to handle them on a
                    permanent basis.</p>
                <p>I have decided, after considering all of the memoranda and representations
                        made,<note n="3">Not located.</note> that we should now institute several
                    reorganization moves to bring the Department into compliance with Executive
                    Order 12065, to continue compliance with legislation governing the release of
                    information to the public (Freedom of Information Act, Privacy Act, etc.) and to
                    establish a unified Department-wide structure governing all aspects of records
                    release. Section 5-404 (a), (b), and (c) of E.O. 12065 requires agencies to
                    assign responsibilities for operations, appeals, and oversight of all specified
                    Classification/ Declassification matters. Accordingly, the following structure
                    and procedures will be established:</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <hi rend="underline">Classification/Declassification Center (A/CDC)</hi>
                        <lb/> A new Deputy Assistant Secretary will be appointed in A to be in
                        charge of a new Classification/Declassification Center (A/CDC). The Center
                        will be co-located with FADRC on the first floor. <list>
                            <item>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Responsibilities</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>1.</label> Operation of Departmental classification
                                        and declassification systems;</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>2.</label> Deciding declassification, release, and
                                        denial issues in the first instance (under mandatory review
                                        provisions of the E.O., FOI, Privacy Act and any other
                                        relevant legislation or executive orders);</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>3.</label> Assuring systematic review for
                                        declassification of Departmental records at 20 years and
                                        thereafter as required by the E.O.;</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>4.</label> Providing guidelines, after full
                                        consultations with the concerned regional and functional
                                        bureaus, for classification, declassification and systematic
                                        review as required;</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>5.</label> Providing all Department reports and
                                        information required by the Information Security Committee;
                                        and</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>6.</label> Representing the Department, with L when
                                        appropriate, on the Interagency Security Committee;
                                        and</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <label>7.</label> Conducting an educational program on the
                                        new Executive Order.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Staff</hi>
                                <lb/> The staff of the center will include: Up to six new positions,
                                including that for the new DAS; a portion of the current A staff
                                dealing with Privacy Act matters; part of the FOI staff which will
                                be transferred from PA<note n="4">Two positions will remain in PA to
                                    staff appeals. The remaining positions will be transferred to
                                    the A Bureau and apportioned between FADRC for request
                                    processing, and the Classification/Declassification Center.
                                    (Footnote in original.)</note>; at some <pb n="3"/> point in the
                                future an indeterminate number of positions presently used primarily
                                for FOI declassification review purposes to be transferred gradually
                                from the regional and functional bureaus; and an indeterminate
                                number of retired Foreign Service Officers who may work on a
                                split-day shift or other part-time arrangements. The retirees will
                                conduct the actual review of documents for declassification. The
                                selection of these retired officers will be done in close
                                coordination with the bureaus.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Coordination</hi>
                                <lb/> The DAS in charge of the Center will operate in a
                                quasi-autonomous manner in accordance with guidelines and policies
                                to be developed by a Coordination Committee of representatives of
                                the concerned regional and functional bureaus, including PA, chaired
                                by the DAS. Policy differences which cannot be reconciled will be
                                settled by the Oversight Committee (see below). The DAS will
                                promulgate the final directives.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <hi rend="underline">Declassification and Release Procedures</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Systematic Declassification Review</hi>
                                <note n="5">Under the E.O., systematic review of material othan than
                                    foreign government information must be <hi rend="underline">
                                        reviewed for declassification</hi> at 20 years; agencies are
                                    required to reach this standard within 10 years. The CDC will be
                                    charged with achieving this objective as early as possible, and
                                    no later than the end of 1985. (Footnote in original.
                                    Underlining added to original.)</note>
                                <lb/> The DAS for operations will identify and assemble as required
                                all records subject to declassification review at 20 years. The
                                DAS/CDC will devise and oversee <hi rend="underline">procedures,
                                    with the concurrence of the Historical Office (PA/HO)</hi>
                                <note n="6">Underlining added to original.</note> and involving
                                DAS/O and regional bureaus as appropriate, to select records from
                                each year’s files to facilitate both: (1) <hi rend="underline"
                                    >review by the CDC for the purpose of drafting declassification
                                    guidelines and (2) selection and editing by HO of materials for
                                    publication in the “Foreign Relations” volumes.</hi>
                                <note n="7">Underlining added to original.</note> On the basis of
                                this review, the CDC will draft declassification guidelines for
                                approval in close consultation with the bureaus concerned. Following
                                final approval of the guidelines, the total permanent record for the
                                period concerned will be transferred to the National Archives for
                                declassification review in accordance with those guidelines.</item>
                            <pb n="4"/>
                            <item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Requests under the FOI Act, the Privacy Act,
                                    and the Mandatory Review Provisions of the Executive Order</hi>
                                <lb/> Records relevant to all other disclosure requests will be
                                identified by the Deputy for Operations (FADRC) and forwarded to the
                                Classification/Declassification Center for review and decision as to
                                declassification and/or release. As indicated above, the actual
                                review will be done primarily by experienced retired officers
                                working as consultants. They will conduct their reviews under
                                guidelines. The Bureaus will be requested to prepare and propose the
                                initial guidelines, which, because of the greater sensitivity in
                                many cases of these documents, will need to be more specific than
                                those governing systematic review of twenty year old documents. The
                                bureaus will submit their proposed guidelines to the DAS/CDC for
                                review and approval. Policy disagreements will be referred to the
                                Oversight Committee. In the event of any uncertainty concerning the
                                application of the guidelines in specific cases, or in the event of
                                especially sensitive cases, the relevant bureau(s) will be consulted
                                by the CDC before a decision is taken.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <hi rend="underline">Record-keeping</hi>
                                <lb/> The Deputy for Operations (FADRC) will assure in both cases
                                (A. and B. above) that documents once processed for possible
                                declassification and/or release under these procedures are marked
                                    <hi rend="underline">or</hi>
                                <note n="8">Underlining added to original.</note> otherwise recorded
                                so that review is not repeated in the event of another, later
                                request. Resources to accomplish these functions (A., B. and C.)
                                will include up to 9 part-time positions. To insure integrity of the
                                record, the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Operations will deal
                                directly with the public and governmental users of information, both
                                to receive requests and respond to them after processing.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <hi rend="underline">Appeals</hi>
                        <lb/> The Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs will be responsible for
                        Department action on appeals from CDC decisions and will chair appeals
                        panels, usually consisting of three members including the Chairman, drawn
                        from a list <pb n="5"/>of senior representatives of other bureaus. The DAS
                        for the Center will serve as an ex-officio, non-voting member of such
                        panels. In the event that the original decision to deny was taken on the
                        insistence of a bureau, a representative of that bureau may participate for
                        the purpose of explaining the rationale for the denial. The panels will
                        decide <hi rend="underline">all appeals</hi>
                        <note n="9">Underlining added to original.</note> from the rulings of the
                        Center <hi rend="underline">on declassification and release of
                            information</hi>
                        <note n="10">Underlining added to original.</note> as well as appeals to
                        amend personal information under the Privacy Act. Two of the current PA/FOI
                        positions will be retained in PA to staff the appeals function.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <hi rend="underline">Oversight</hi>
                        <lb/> The Under Secretary for Management will serve as the “senior agency
                        official” to chair a Department Oversight Committee “with authority to act
                        on all suggestions and complaints” with respect to the agency’s overall
                        administration of the Executive Order, as specified in Section 5-404(b). The
                        Committee will consist of representatives of <hi rend="underline">A, L, and
                            PA</hi>
                        <note n="11">Underlining added to original.</note>. The Committee may
                        request periodic reports from the DAS in charge of the
                        Classification/Declassification Center and from the Chairman of the appeals
                        panels. The Committee will decide policy issues which cannot be resolved at
                        bureau levels, other than appeals which relate to the denial of information
                        requested under statutory or Executive Order authority. One of its concerns
                        will be the adequacy of resources and <hi rend="underline">procedures
                            employed</hi>
                        <note n="12">Underlining added to original.</note> to carry out the purposes
                        of the Order.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Transitional Aspects</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is much to be done before the new system will be fully operational and the
                    new center can take over the review process from the bureaus. In the interim,
                    and until the new Center is <hi rend="underline">fully operational</hi>
                    <note n="13">Underlining added to original.</note>, the current system will
                    continue in effect and preparations now being made by the Council on
                    Classification Policy and its member bureaus for implementing the new E.O.
                    should continue.</p>
                <p>Procedures already approved by the Council on Classification Policy for review
                    and declassification of 1950-54 records should be pursued and completed at the
                    earliest possible date. The new system will be applied beginning with the 1955
                    records. The phasing in of the CDC operations will be gradual. Every effort <pb
                        n="6"/>will be made to avoid confusion. We must avoid disruption of the
                    current system before the new one is in place. The cooperation of all will be
                    essential. Modifications and the transition will be implemented by the new DAS
                    using the Coordination Committee mentioned in Paragraph 1 c, above. In that
                    connection, all bureaus and offices have been requested to nominate a
                    representative to that Committee at the Deputy Assistant Secretary level.
                    Nominations should be made to M.</p>
                <p>All other existing Department organizational units dealing with classification
                    and declassification matters specified above, including the Council on
                    Classification Policy and the Freedom of Information Staff (PA/FOI), will cease
                    to exist when the procedures outlined herein are effected and the Center is in
                    full operation.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d2">
                <head>2. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for the
                    Classification/Declassification Center (Clayton McManaway) to the Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs (William Blair)<note n="14"
                        >Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114,
                        U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-03-19">March 19, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: CDC Role in Foreign Relations Series Prior to 1955-57</p>
                <p>As you know, I have been considering on an urgent basis the question of the
                    extent to which it will be necessary for the Classification/ Declassification
                    Center to play a role in the process of clearing materials for publication in
                    the Foreign Relations of the United States series for years prior to the 1955-57
                    triennium, i.e., material which was in the clearance process when the Center was
                    established.</p>
                <p>As part of this process, we have looked at material of this sort pertaining to
                    selected countries.</p>
                <p>In our judgment, which is concurred in by the Bureau of European Affairs, the
                    1952-54 material concerning our relations with the U.K. contains a number of
                    documents which should remain classified in whole or in part. It contains other
                    documents which should be declassified only after clearance with the U.K. The
                    latter category relates directly to our internal discussions concerning policy
                    with respect to foreign government information provided to us by Commonwealth
                    governments. Our ultimate decision concerning documents in this category should
                    await the outcome of these discussions, which will be known in the near
                    future.</p>
                <p>Questions have also been raised concerning material related to certain other
                    countries, questions sufficiently serious to require that they be taken up with
                    the geographic bureaus concerned.</p>
                <p>In light of the above, I have decided that the Office of Systematic Review must
                    go over those materials already in the pipeline but not yet advanced to the
                    page-proof stage. It is my understanding that this would comprise:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>From the 1951 Series - Vols. IV (Europe) &amp; VII (Korea &amp;
                        China)</item>
                    <item>From the 1952 - 54 Series - All Volumes except Vol. III</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>We will make every effort to accomplish this review so as not to interfere with
                    maintenance of your current publication schedule. Thus, we will give first
                    priority to the review of the volumes in the 1951 series and Volume V of the
                    1952-54 series. Other priorities will be established in relation to your
                    schedule. Reviewers are available to begin (in some cases to continue) this task
                    and I believe it can be accomplished rapidly enough so as to have little or no
                    effect on your schedule.</p>
                <p>Please take the necessary steps to assure that the materials involved are handled
                    in such a way as not to preclude making effective the results of our review.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <head>3. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="15">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel
                        Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State,
                        Washington, DC. Drafted within PA/HO. An unatributed marginal notation reads
                        “Are these cleared minutes?”</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-02">April 2, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Meeting on Re-review of Unpublished <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Volumes by the CDC for the Years 1951-54, March 27, 1980</p>
                <p>Participants</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Clayton McManaway</item>
                    <item>William Blair</item>
                    <item>Laurence Pickering</item>
                    <item>David Trask</item>
                    <item>David Baehler</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Blair noted that the inclusion of certain material in the European volumes
                    for 1952-54, already cleared for release, has aroused concern. What was the
                    rationale for re-review of all unpublished volumes for the entire period? Mr.
                    McManaway said that the genesis of the re-review was accidental, arising mostly
                    from Mr. Galloway’s reading the UK compilation for 1952-54 and a resultant
                    inquiry to the desk, asking how much of the material contained therein should be
                    published without consultation with the concerned government. He also observed
                    that concern expressed upon completion of the review of the volume on Indochina.
                    Mr. Pickering said that specifically the CDC was concerned about some
                    third-country involvement in bilateral relations between the US and other
                    countries, such as Swedish intermediary action in US relations with Korea. There
                    is no evidence, he said, that such third country involvement was cleared either
                    with the desk having responsibility or with the third country.</p>
                <p>Mr. McManaway said that the CDC’s concern about the adequacy of the review
                    coincides with concern about the adequacy of the 1950-54 guidelines. He went on
                    to say that delays in the FRUS publication would not be a problem because there
                    is not enough material to slow the process significantly. He gave assurances
                    that the CDC would start with 1951, v. VII and continue with 1952-54, v. V.
                    Finally, he assured those present that the CDC did not relish the prospect of
                    re-review because it delayed somewhat its review of 1955-57 material. Mr.
                    Pickering said he expected few or no additional deletions from most volumes. Mr.
                    Trask said that one of HO’s concerns was with the delays the re-review might
                    cause. Mr. Pickering assured Mr. Trask that the<pb n="2"/> re-review would take
                    place in the order that HO requested. Mr. Trask noted that even a small delay at
                    the front end can multiply later on, particularly if the re-review is de novo
                    and if it should require appeals to different authorities than those now
                    involved in the process. Mr. Pickering doubted that this would present much of a
                    problem, since the only area that is likely to become an issue is the UK. Mr.
                    McManaway agreed with Mr. Pickering. He also gave assurances that the CDC would
                    not make additional objections unless it had already checked with the concerned
                    bureau. This should reduce additional objections to a minimum, thus minimizing
                    delays, and since the publication dates for most of the concerned volumes are so
                    far off anyway, it was hard to see how CDC action could entail any appreciable
                    delays.</p>
                <p>Mr. Blair said he agreed with the concern expressed about UK and certain
                    Indochina material, but wondered whether this concern justified jettisoning all
                    bureau reviews on all volumes for the period. Mr. McManaway said that they in
                    the CDC went through a similar thought process, but concluded that we could not
                    be certain whether other problems existed unless the CDC looked at everything.
                        <hi rend="underline">Mr. Pickering pointed out the seriousness of the
                        problem by saying that the UK desk felt that some of the documents
                        previously cleared should not even be shown to the UK government, let alone
                        published.</hi>
                    <note n="16">This sentence is emphasized in the margin and accompanied by an
                        unatributed marginal notation that reads “Who on the desk? [unclear] What is
                        the material?”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Trask inquired about the procedure used to inaugurate re-review of the
                    1951-54 volumes. He suggested an alternative that might have been used. Ben Read
                    had established the original division of labor by which the CDC began its review
                    with the 1955 records. PA was supposed to complete work on the records through
                    1954. For this reason, given CDC interest, CDC and HO might have returned to Mr.
                    Read jointly with arguments as to why or why not the 1951-54 records destined
                    for publication required re-review. If Mr. Read decided in favor of re-review,
                    the CDC would have made the initial examination and could have consulted with HO
                    on its conclusions. At that point, the CDC and HO could jointly or individually
                    consult the bureaus about proposed deletions or about reversals of deletions
                    made earlier. Mr. McManaway said that the procedure Mr. Trask had outlined was
                    about what the CDC has envisioned in any event.</p>
                <p>Pursuing the question of procedure, Mr. Trask asked whether HO and the CDC had
                    the same understanding of <hi rend="underline">de novo</hi> review. Mr.
                    Pickering described his conception of <hi rend="underline">de novo</hi> review.
                    His reviewers would conduct a review of all of the volumes without reference to
                    the actions the bureaus had taken earlier.<pb n="3"/> Only after that review was
                    complete would the reviewers compare their actions against actions previously
                    taken as reflected in the HO galleys. In the event of divergence between desk
                    and CDC actions, the CDC would discuss the question with the bureaus. Mr. Trask
                    said that it sounded from Mr. Pickering’s presentation that HO would suffer from
                    the worst of both the old and new worlds under the contemplated re-review
                    procedures. It appeared that all the old denials would remain intact, while the
                    results of the CDC re-review would simply be an add-on to earlier decisions. He
                    said he thought that the CDC should take full responsibility for all
                    withholdings directed in the course of re-review. In undertaking the re-review,
                    the CDC was in effect telling the bureaus that their initial examination was
                    inadequately done. If that is in fact the case, HO expected CDC to declare the
                    bureaus’ review invalid. The procedure described by Mr. Pickering did not
                    explicitly provide for that.</p>
                <p>Mr. McManaway said in effect that Mr. Trask drew a false distinction between
                    bureau and CDC review. The CDC, as the bureaus’ agent, will not make any changes
                    either way -- negatively or positively -- without consulting the bureaus. Mr.
                    Trask agreed that the CDC acted as the bureaus’ agent. He only wanted to be sure
                    that the CDC related to the bureaus in the re-review of the 1951-54 records in
                    the same way that it will relate to them on records for 1955 and later. It did
                    not appear that the CDC planned to do that. Mr. Blair disagreed with Mr. Trask,
                    stating that it seemed to him that the CDC and HO were of one mind on the ground
                    rules for re-review.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then listed three characteristics of de novo review as HO understands
                    the term and asked whether the CDC had the same understanding: <list>
                        <item>
                            <label>1.</label> The prior bureau review was suspended.</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <add>The CDC would</add> accept full responsibility for actions under
                            the new review; i.e., HO would deal directly with CDC in all matters
                            relating to the re-review such as appeals.</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>3.</label> Re-review might result in release of material withheld
                            under previous examination as well as denial of material released
                            previously.</item>
                    </list> Messrs. McManaway and Pickering indicated agreement. The CDC would
                    conduct the review without prior knowledge of bureau actions; it would consult
                    with HO after the review was completed to determine whether there was any
                    compelling reason for withholding certain material; and it would return to the
                    bureaus in order to resolve<pb n="4"/> disagreed items. The CDC would assume
                    full responsibility for all deletions, always recognizing that it functions as
                    an agent of the bureaus that originated classified information. Mr. Blair
                    concluded with the observation that PA was present to defend the principles of
                    openness; he hoped that the CDC would recognize that role.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said that his concern in re-review was not the amount of material that
                    the CDC might deny. He believed that the object should be to insure that all
                    desensitized material be declassified and that legitimate sensitive information
                    remain classified at the appropriate level. Mr. Blair said that the CDC and HO
                    seemed to be close on general principles of re-review and asked that Mr. Trask
                    proceed to specifics.</p>
                <p>At this point Mr. Trask asked that volumes VII, 1951, and V, 1952-54, be exempted
                    from re-review on the following grounds: <list>
                        <item>
                            <label>1.</label> Re-review could entail considerable expense.</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>2.</label> Re-review could cause significant delay in
                            publication.</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>3.</label> The volumes have already been fully cleared.</item>
                    </list> Mr. McManaway replied that the CDC was already mostly finished with
                    1951, v. VII, and it did not appear that many significant changes would be
                    necessary. As for the rest of the material, it was not possible to determine
                    what deletions would be necessary prior to review, but a review would in any
                    case be necessary. Mr. Pickering pointed out one passage that the CDC found
                    sensitive in its review of 1951, VII, by way of illustrating what a review of
                    the aforementioned volumes might turn up. Mr. Trask noted that the passage dealt
                    with foreign-government information in a U.S. document and sought to clarify
                    HO’s position on the treatment of FGI. He pointed out that the general
                    guidelines call for withholding such information contained in US documents only
                    if the reviewers find it still sensitive. Mr. McManaway thought this point
                    irrelevant in the case of the UK desk officer who reviewed the UK compilation
                    previously. Guidelines did not then exist. Besides, it was CDC’s view that the
                    desk officer did not adequately take account of sensitive documents in his
                    review. Mr. Trask asked if Mr. McManaway thought the UK desk officer’s review
                    was incompetent. Mr. McManaway said he did think so, and that is the reason for
                    the CDC’s returning to the desk at this point to determine what is
                    sensitive.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask then asked to rehearse the reasons why HO thought the re-review
                    unnecessary for the purpose of placing those views on the record. Mr. McManaway
                    suggested that he do this with<pb n="5"/> Mr. Pickering. Mr. Trask said he
                    preferred to do it during the meeting in progress. Mr. Blair asked how long it
                    would take. Mr. Trask said it would take about 3 minutes, whereupon permission
                    was granted. The first point, he said was that no showing had been made that a
                    re-review was necessary. The CDC had not presented a good case to demonstrate
                    that the bureaus’ review was incompetent. <hi rend="underline">Mr. McManaway
                        asked if PA wanted to take responsibility for release of something damaging
                        in the event that a part of the review was incompetent. Mr. Blair said that
                        ultimately Hodding Carter would have to take responsibility, and that in
                        practical terms PA would not be able to show that such a re-review was
                        unnecessary.</hi>
                    <note n="17">These sentences are emphasized in the margin.</note> He told Mr.
                    Trask that he disagreed with this criticism of re-review by HO. Mr. Pickering
                    then read a portion of a telegram cleared for publication with the purpose of
                    showing that the passage in question raised serious questions about the adequacy
                    of the initial review. Mr. Trask asked whether HO had previously been consulted
                    about this passage to see whether the information contained in it was already in
                    the public domain and thus desensitized. Mr. McManaway said that the CDC had not
                    so consulted and regretted not having done so.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask’s second point in objecting to the re-review was that delays in
                    publication and in the CDC’s review of 1955-57 (which would result in later
                    publication delays) was unavoidable, as previously noted, and that re-review
                    would entail considerable expense, and should be avoided unless the need for it
                    was fully demonstrated, something that CDC had not yet done. Mr. McManaway
                    promised to avoid delays if at all possible. He also reiterated that the CDC
                    would not ask HO to withhold publication of material (which could result in
                    delays for the purpose of appealing the decision) unless the bureaus have
                    already agreed in advance with the CDC decision. At this point Mr. Blair asked
                    for a brief discussion of the agreement mentioned in Mr. Meyers’ memorandum<note
                        n="18">Not located.</note> about a meeting with representatives of the
                    British Embassy. He stated that PA would have to insist on consulting about any
                    such arrangement and would oppose granting a foreign government a veto over
                    publication of such information. Mr. McManaway said that, first of all, no one
                    had made a decision on how the US would handle such information. Secondly, when
                    a decision is made by Mr. Read on the question, the material submitted to him
                    will specifically exclude the possibility that any foreign government will have
                    the right to exercise a veto right over such information. Thirdly, he assured
                    those present that HO is already on the ground floor of the decision process and
                    that HO will continue to be involved in it. Mr. Trask asked that the Meyers’
                    memo be revised to include the word “consultation” in place of the word “review”
                    on the grounds that the latter implies that the government concerned has the
                    right to exercise a veto over information contained in a US document. For the
                    same reason, he proposed that the word “clearance” be removed from the memo and
                    that a specific statement be included to indicate<pb n="6"/> that any
                    arrangement would not diminish the right of the originating government to
                    dispose of its own documents. Mr. Pickering noted that the memo did not reflect
                    a formal proposal. Mr. McManaway saw no reason to alter the memcon. Mr. Blair
                    agreed with Mr. McManaway.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask said in conclusion that HO was opposed not only to the way the matter
                    was handled procedurally, but also to the substance of the proposal discussed at
                    the meeting. In this connection, he handed Mr. McManaway a memorandum of Nov. 3,
                    1958 by Mr. Noble on the subject of clearing FGI in US documents with the
                    government originating that information. (This memorandum strongly opposed any
                    form of consultation with other governments on FGI in US documents, except in
                    the case of direct quotations. A copy is appended.)<note n="19">Bernard Noble’s
                        memorandum was not attached and has not been located.</note> Mr. Blair said
                    he wished Mr. Trask had given him a copy of the memo. Mr. McManaway said that he
                    was conscious that the FGI discussion could represent a change in policy. He
                    would be sure to include HO in discussions of the proposed change.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d4">
                <head>4. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs
                    (George Vest) to the Under Secretary of State for Management (Ben Read)<note
                        n="20">Source: Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot
                        File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC. Copies of the
                        memorandum were also sent to Hodding Carter and Clayton McManaway. David
                        Trask received a copy on April 16, 1980.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-11">April 11, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: EUR Clearance of Material for the FRUS, 1950-54</p>
                <p>The issuance of FRUS Volume 1, 1951, containing material which I would have
                    preferred not be released, has brought home to me the EUR clearance problem. As
                    a result of this experience, I think it is important to ensure no
                    repetition.</p>
                <p>I feel obligated to withdraw EUR clearances for the FRUS documents and volumes
                    not yet published. I request that all this material be reviewed again by the
                    CDC, consulting as advisable with me and other officers in EUR. During this
                    review, I request that foreign government information proposed for publication
                    in the FRUS that might require consultation with the governments concerned, if
                    it is to be published at all, be specifically identified to me or my staff.</p>
                <p>After the experience of last week, it is especially important to have a sensitive
                    review procedure. The staff you have assembled in CDC has the background and
                    sensitivity. I and my Deputies and Office Directors will be ready to work to
                    ensure orderly and expeditious publication -- but now is the time to ensure the
                    procedure.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <head>5. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State for Management (Ben Read) to
                    All Assistant Secretaries<note n="21">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package
                        (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington,
                        DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-11">April 11, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Re-review of Materials for Publication in the Foreign Relations of the
                    US: 1950-1954</p>
                <p>We have recently discovered problems with some of the material previously cleared
                    by the bureaus for publication in the FRUS covering the years 1950-1954. In
                    addition, some of these earlier reviews were conducted as long as three years
                    ago, and circumstances have changed substantially in some cases in the
                    interim.</p>
                <p>Consequently, I have directed the CDC to conduct a fresh review of all the
                    unpublished materials previously cleared for the FRUS covering 1950-1954. This
                    will be a <hi rend="underline">de novo</hi> review including, also, material
                    previously withheld.</p>
                <p>The re-review must be done <hi rend="underline">as expeditiously as
                        possible</hi>.<note n="22">Underlining added to original. A hand-written
                        message reads “Hodding - Clay tells me [unclear] his people will complete
                        their review of the next vol by the end of next week. Ben 4/11”</note> The
                    CDC will need to consult with the bureaus, as appropriate, and your cooperation
                    will be appreciated.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d6">
                <head>6. Memorandum for the Record<note n="23">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel
                        Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State,
                        Washington, DC. Drafted by David Trask.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-11"/>April 11, 1980</dateline>
                <p>Subject: Reasons Why the Office of the Historian Opposes All Forms of Dealings
                    with Other Governments on United States Documents that Include Foreign
                    Government Information</p>
                <p>The case against any such proceeding has been extant for a long time, and it has
                    been adhered to in the past. A good number of the reasons for this view, firmly
                    held in HO, are listed in a memorandum on the subject that G. Bernard Noble, the
                    former head of HO, prepared in 1958. A copy of this document is appended.<note
                        n="24">Not located.</note> I attach also a relevant memorandum on the
                    subject that HO made available to the CDC. Arthur Kogan prepared it.<note n="25"
                        >Not located.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The basic expediential reason to avoid any exchanges is that any form of
                    discussion, with other governments, even mere consultation, on U.S. documents
                    containing foreign government information is that the disadvantages would far
                    outweigh any conceivable advantages.</p>
                <p>A question of fundamental principle also obtains; no sovereign state should
                    compromise in any way its freedom of action to dispose of its records as it
                    chooses.</p>
                <p>Below find a systematic listing of the several specific reasons for opposition to
                    discussing U.S. documents, most of them mentioned in Mr. Noble’s memorandum:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> Only the United States can bear responsibility for a
                        report of foreign-government information in an American document, other than
                        a direct quotation. Any such report is by definition an American official’s
                        interpretation of another government’s views not information owned by the
                        other government.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> Review of American documents or consultation about them
                        may place information in the hands of another government to which it has no
                        right. Moreover, delivery of such information might not be in the national
                        interest.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> Foreign governments might use review or consultation as an
                        opening to permit censorship of information other than that submitted to
                        them for consideration.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> Publication of a document that excluded foreign-government
                        information might distort its meaning.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>5.</label> If asked to consent to publication of certain types of
                        information a foreign government might well feel the need to oppose
                        publication, but it might have no objection at all to a unilateral action by
                        the United States.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>6.</label> Real difficulties could develop with a foreign government,
                        should it object to publication of certain passages that the United States
                        government later felt compelled to publish anyway.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>7.</label> In almost every case of foreign-government information
                        found in U.S. documents historians and others in the Department of State can
                        make an accurate estimate of the sensitivity of foreign-government
                        information in the other nation and take that estimate into consideration in
                        considering declassification and publication. In other words, only in very
                        rare instances would the United States learn through consultation with a
                        foreign government what it could not learn by other means.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>8.</label> Reviews or consultations would pose certain legal and
                        administrative problems that would unduly complicate matters, leading to
                        unacceptable expense and delay.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d7">
                <head>7. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
                    (Hodding Carter III) to the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs
                    (George Vest)<note n="26">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box
                        3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-17">April 17, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>Subject: EUR Clearance of Material for the FRUS, 1950-54 </p>
                <p>Ref: Your Memorandum to Ben Read, April 11, 1980, with a copy to me</p>
                <p>George,</p>
                <p>Your withdrawal of EUR clearances for unpublished FRUS volumes covering 1950-54
                    is surprising and disappointing. As a matter of priority, please send to me a
                    copy of all material contained in FRUS Volume I which you would have preferred
                    not to be released, which you cite as your reason for withdrawing clearances for
                    the 1950-54 volumes. I understand that you sent a copy of FRUS Volume I 1951 to
                    the British Embassy with an apology for publishing the material in question. I
                    request also a copy of your communication to the British Embassy. None of us
                    want to publish material that will be detrimental to the national interest, but
                    that interest has to be defined and interpreted to include the public’s right to
                    access. You know well the battles that have been fought over where to draw the
                    line. I am concerned that in our effort to open the historical record we are
                    evidently moving backward, taking steps that could lend substance to a charge
                    that the present Administration is less committed to the goal than either of its
                    two immediate predecessors.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d8">
                <head>8. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs
                    (George Vest) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs (Hodding
                    Carter III)<note n="27">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3,
                        Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-04-18">April 18, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: EUR Clearance of Material for FRUS 1950-1954</p>
                <p>I know that my reservation on the clearances causes a problem, but I stress that
                    I don’t want to cause a slow-down and only to make assurance doubly sure. As for
                    the material in the 1951 volume that left me uneasy, Bill Galloway brought it to
                    my attention and could identify the worrisome sections. As for the British
                    Embassy, I did not send them a copy with an apology for publishing material. In
                    the course of the DCM’s call on business, I handed him a copy and suggested that
                    they might want to look through the Table of Contents to be on the alert in case
                    the distribution led to newspaper stories. There was therefore no communication
                    to the British Embassy.</p>
                <p>Again, I don’t want to move the historical effort backward, and I’m prepared to
                    take the time and to call on my key Deputies to get a move on, with care.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <head>9. Memorandum From the Historian (David Trask) to the Assistant Secretary of
                    State for Public Affairs (Hodding Carter III)<note n="28">Source: Folder
                        “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954
                        (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington,
                        DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-05-02">May 2, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Actions Concerning Foreign Relations of the United States</p>
                <p>On April 15, 1980, at your instruction, I sent you a package of materials<note
                        n="29">See David Trask memorandum to Hodding Carter (with tabbed
                        attachements), April 15, 1980, Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box
                        3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                    concerning proposed reactions to re-review of unpublished volumes in the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series (FRUS). Events having
                    markedly altered the general situation, HO wishes to substitute this package of
                    recommendations for the earlier one. The most important of the new elements is
                    the arrival of a request from the Central Intelligence Agency for the right to
                    re-review all unpublished volumes. This request covers the items covered in Mr.
                    Read’s directive.</p>
                <p>HO’s view is that PA should resist re-review, given the consequent delay and
                    expense, unless a convincing case is made for re-review in writing.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>In this connection HO proposes that you send the draft memorandum to Mr.
                        White of the CIA attached as Tab 2.<note n="30">Not printed.</note> The
                        latter rejects the CIA request for re-review.</item>
                    <item>HO suggests further that you send an action memorandum to Mr. Read
                        requiring the CDC to cease interfering with HO’s pursuit of declassification
                        decisions in other agencies. This draft is attached as Tab 3.<note n="31"
                            >This attachment is labeled Tab 6. Printed as Document 10.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>HO also proposes that you send a memorandum to Mr. McManaway concerning
                        the schedule of re-review. This draft memorandum is attached as Tab 4.<note
                            n="32">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>In addition to these actions, which follow logically from prior activities at the
                    CDC-bureau level, HO recommends certain initiatives before the Oversight
                    Committee that was created to monitor and to control the workings of the new
                    system of central declassification review in the Department. Pursuit of these
                    initiatives is called for at the present time because the principle<pb n="2"/>
                    of openness is likely to carry greater weight at that level than in dealings
                    with the CDC or the bureaus and because PA can then regain the initiative in
                    discussions relating to FRUS. HO does not propose to stop actions at lower
                    levels; rather, it proposes that PA act simultaneously at another higher level.
                    Failure to act now at the higher level might render efforts at lower levels
                    nugatory.</p>
                <p>Specifically, HO proposes four initiatives to be undertaken in the Oversight
                    Committee:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>A briefing of the Oversight Committee to acquaint it with the function of
                        the Foreign Relations series and its present circumstances. Attached as Tab
                        5 is a brief summary of the information that might be communicated to the
                        Oversight Committee.<note n="33">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>Discussion of numerous weaknesses in the Department’s efforts to undertake
                        centralized declassification review. The system has not been fully
                        implemented, especially those aspects of it designed to insure that all
                        interested parties have an opportunity to contribute to the determination of
                        policies and procedures relating to classification and declassification.
                        Moreover, the Classification/ Declassification Center (CDC) has undertaken a
                        number of initiatives on its own motion without appropriate prior
                        discussions. Attached as Tab 6 is a memorandum outlining the weaknesses of
                        the system at present.<note n="34">This attachment is labeled Tab 3. Not
                            printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>Presentation of a proposal to reaffirm the Department’s traditional
                        opposition to presentation of US documents containing foreign government
                        information (FGI) to other nations for any purpose, whether consultation or
                        review. HO’s views on FGI are attached as Tab 7.<note n="35">Not
                            printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>Discussion of a proposed revision of 2 FAM 1350 intended to take recent
                        changes in policy and procedure into consideration. The proposed revision is
                        attached as Tab 8.<note n="36">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>HO believes that delay in taking this integrated package of actions works to the
                    disadvantage of PA; it urges an early decision. I am eager to discuss these
                    matters with you at your earliest convenience.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
                    (Hodding Carter III) to the Under Secretary of State for Management (Ben
                        Read)<note n="37">Source: Folder “Documents Relating to the Re-Review of
                        Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S.
                        Department of State, Washington, DC. Attached, as Tab 6, to David Trask
                        memorandum to Hodding Carter, May 2, 1980, Folder “Documents Relating to the
                        Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114,
                        U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC. A handwritten notation, “Not
                        sent,” presumably written by Trask, appears at the top of the first page of
                        the memorandum. Although this copy of the memorandum is dated May 2, another
                        copy (that also has a handwritten “Not sent” notation), in Folder “Dissent
                        Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State,
                        Washington, DC, is dated May 6. In addition, David Trask memorandum to
                        Elaine Morton, July 7, 1980, Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3,
                        Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC includes a
                        description of the same memorandum and gives the date as May 6.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-05-02">May 2, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: CDC, the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series, and the
                    Declassification Muddle</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">BACKGROUND</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Since 1978 PA and HO vigorously supported a centralized declassification program
                    in A/CDC. We played the leading role in shaping the design of the institution to
                    allow the Department to implement E.O. 12065. HO has worked to select the
                    documentary sample from which the CDC is to frame Department declassification
                    guidelines. HO prepared detailed, classified guidelines to be used to permit
                    transfer of 1950-1954 Department records to the National Archives and arranged
                    their clearance in the Department. PA and HO reluctantly agreed to retroactive
                    review of documents already carefully declassified under previous policies and
                    procedures. HO met all of CDC’s requests for re- sources to expedite retroactive
                    review in the hope of mitigating the impact upon the ongoing <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> publication program. HO has tried to
                    work closely with the CDC in establishing appropriate security handling
                    procedures for historical documents in order to permit prompt, orderly
                    processing of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series.</p>
                <p>So far, PA’s efforts to assure timely and proper adherence to E.O. 12065 have
                    been largely unavailing. The primary obstacle is a series of extemporized steps
                    taken by CDC that (a) have brought production of the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series to a halt; (b) thrown publication plans for
                    1980, 1981 and 1982 into confusion, and (c) seriously compromised the
                    Department’s ability to attain a twenty-year line in declassification.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Halt in Production of the Foreign Relations Series</hi>
                </p>
                <p>All thirty <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for the period
                    1950-54 have been carefully reviewed for declassification in the Department,
                    following time-tested procedures. Other agencies and governments have cleared
                    several of them. No other agency or foreign government has objected to these
                    procedures, but the CDC unilaterally decided that previous review of the 1950-54
                    material was inadequate. Although no showing of inadequacy was forthcoming, PA
                    acquiesced in the re-review of volumes not yet fully reviewed by all concerned
                    parties.</p>
                <p>Since that re-review was initiated the CDC has expanded its scope, again
                    unilaterally and without a showing of need, to include re-review of <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes that are already fully
                    declassified and nearing publication. The result has been a halt in issuance of
                    one of the major products of this Bureau. The result will cast serious doubt on
                    the readiness of this Department to carry out the will of this Administration
                    concerning open government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Disruption of publication plans for 1980, 1981 and
                        1982</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Partly because of the CDC’s unilateral decision to reinvent the wheel in
                    declassifying 1950-54 materials, and partly because of the CDC’s decision to
                    delay review of the post-1954 material, PA’s publication plans for the next
                    three years have been thrown into confusion. The CDC’s recommendation that one
                    volume on the verge of publication be withheld not only prevents public access
                    to it, but also must necessarily result in delays in re-review of later material
                    because the relevant documentation is thirty years old and must be presented to
                    the secretary for certification before further withholding can legally occur.
                    Re-review of materials already declassified by the State Department means that
                    this Bureau will have to halt review on volumes already in progress at the NSC,
                    since the NSC will act only on materials that have already been finally acted
                    upon by the constituent <pb n="3"/>agencies. Other volumes poised for
                    transmission for NSC declassification review must be held back. Finally,
                    activity on 1955-57 materials now in the CDC is necessarily scaled back and held
                    up pending a review of the earlier material.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">The Department’s Goal of Attaining the 20-Year
                        Declassification Line</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Your directive of November 20, 1978 stipulated that the Department attain a
                    twenty-year line in declassification as soon as possible but in no case later
                    than the end of 1985. Five and a half years before the deadline, the CDC is
                    still reviewing documents dated as early as 1950. I do not deny that attainment
                    of the goal is possible, but a determined effort is clearly called for--a much
                    more determined effort than has been made so far.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">DISCUSSION</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department’s declassification effort in the area of systematic review is
                    seriously flawed as presently constituted.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The CDC has disrupted the existing declassification
                        system. <list>
                            <item>
                                <label>a.</label> The CDC has failed to formulate a rationale for
                                the need to re-review previously declassified materials. Earlier
                                action, though far from perfect, was conducted under a clear set of
                                guidelines defining the goals and purposes of the <hi
                                    rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series and of systematic
                                review generally. In conducting a re-review, the CDC has dispensed
                                with those guidelines and has substituted nothing for them.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>b.</label> The CDC has also failed to follow the procedures
                                defined in your enabling memorandum of November 20, 1978. Had the
                                CDC followed your directive, there might have been a more sober
                                assessment of the need for re-review. To the best of my knowledge,
                                no meeting of either the Coordination Committee or the Oversight
                                Committee, both intended to represent all concerned parties and to
                                    <pb n="4"/>provide the policy guidance so lacking in recent CDC
                                decisions, has occurred in the last few months. If one or both of
                                these committees had met, basic issues concerning systematic review
                                and the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series could
                                have been debated by all concerned parties.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>c.</label> The CDC has demolished existing procedures
                                relating to review of foreign government information but has failed
                                to devise a new method for dealing with declassification of such
                                material. During the past several months the CDC has signalled to
                                the British Commonwealth countries its willingness to abandon
                                decades of prior practice by permitting those countries to review
                                American documents scheduled for inclusion <hi rend="underline">in
                                    the Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. This review was to be
                                undertaken on the pretext that it was an appropriate means of
                                applying the “foreign government information” clauses of E.O. 12065.
                                Attempted revision of procedures was begun without the benefit of
                                consultation either through established mechanisms in the Department
                                or through the Office of the Historian, whose work it directly
                                affects. It was advanced to Commonwealth representatives on the most
                                misguided of premises--that Commonwealth anxieties about the FOI
                                impact on recent intelligence information given to the US in
                                confidence could be extrapolated to cover thirty-year-old historical
                                documents scheduled for publication in <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>. Available evidence suggests that unsolicited
                                proposals from US officials to reverse long-standing and well-tested
                                clearance procedures for <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                                documents have caused puzzlement among representatives of the
                                Commonwealth countries. It is highly improbable that the
                                Commonwealth countries will adopt a reciprocal policy in response to
                                these proposals.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>d.</label> The CDC has delayed transfer of 1950-54 records to
                                the National Archives. Although guidelines for systematic review at
                                Archives of the 1950-54 materials have been completed and approved
                                in the Bureaus for several months, the CDC has delayed their
                                transmission, pending a test of their adequacy. While this is part
                                and parcel of the re-review to which this Bureau has already
                                acquiesced, further delay will postpone transfer of records to
                                Archives until 1981. Besides the obvious<pb n="5"/> retrogression in
                                the Department’s efforts to project a more open image, this
                                postponement will require the Secretary to certify the withholding
                                of thousands of pages of thirty-year-old documents that earlier
                                reviewers judged releasable.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>e.</label> The CDC has interfered with procedures for
                                acquiring other-agency clearances on documents destined for
                                publication in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                                series. Previous practices, sanctioned by Department regulations,
                                whereby HO assumes responsibility for acquiring declassification
                                action from other agencies have never elicited the slightest protest
                                from elsewhere in the government. For reasons unknown the CDC,
                                reversing a position taken in its formative stages, has recently
                                involved itself in declassification activities of other agencies on
                                    <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> materials. The
                                result, wholly unfavorable, has been confusion over who has
                                authority in this domain.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> The CDC has yet to replace the disrupted declassification
                        system with a viable substitute. <list>
                            <item>
                                <label>a.</label> The CDC has failed to activate a fully centralized
                                system for declassification. Despite your memorandum of November 20,
                                1978, no detailed guidance for review of historical documentation
                                selected for inclusion in <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi> and the documentary sample has been developed
                                through authorized channels.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>b.</label> The CDC has yet to develop through authorized
                                channels a full definition of the term “foreign government
                                information” as expressed in E.O. 12065.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>c.</label> The CDC has yet to transfer a single document to
                                the Archives’ custody under guidelines developed by means of the
                                review.</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>d.</label> The CDC has yet to complete systematic review
                                declassification on a single <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi> volume for the 1955-60 period, despite having
                                been in existence and at least partly staffed for nearly a year.
                                Start-up delays in such a complex system are inevitable, but the
                                projected schedule for review for the 1955-57 period has<pb n="6"/>
                                slipped badly and no work at all has been done on the 1958-60
                                documentation. HO has committed two work years toward meeting its
                                agreed goal of gathering a representative sample of documents from
                                the period 1958- 1960 for CDC review, a sign of its commitment to
                                centralized declassification review.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Downgrading of Historical Documentation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Related to the delay problem is the question of HO’s handling of classified
                    information. In preparing the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series, HO maintains at any given time some 1,500,000 pages of documents that
                    are twenty to thirty years old. <hi rend="underline">HO transmits in the average
                        year at least 50,000 pages of classified documents twenty to thirty years
                        old. Much of this material is Top Secret. All but a small fraction of it is
                        eventually declassified. For many years SY has recognized this documentation
                        as historical and eligible for handling as Confidential. Since 1961 HO has
                        operated under a formal waiver permitting the handling of all historical
                        documentation collected for preparation of Foreign Relations to be handled
                        as Confidential.</hi>
                    <note n="38">These sentences are emphasized in the margin.</note> Early this
                    year HO made an effort to bring its procedures more into line with the
                    Department’s new classification and declassification program. It sought from SY
                    an extension and reaffirmation of the waiver for historical documents. SY
                    referred the request to the CDC, which has yet to respond. The absence of denial
                    of the waiver will have a disastrous effect upon the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> program. Approximately sixteen volumes in linotype
                    at the GPO would have to be stored in a special handling facility that may not
                    even be available and would surely be astronomically expensive. Twelve volumes
                    in manuscript would have to be held in the Department in appropriate storage
                    facilities, pending long-delayed CDC declassification action. Some $50,000 in
                    outside editing contracts let by A/FAIM/PS would have to be suspended because
                    these commercial editing firms do not have top secret clearance and would not
                    attempt to obtain it. An additional $50,000 in feasibility contracts for
                    commercial word processing of <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes would also have to be suspended in the absence of either cleared
                    manuscript or handling waivers. These production delays<pb n="7"/> would be
                    compounded because of massive reassignment of HO resources to identifying,
                    labelling, storing, and listing at least 500,000 pages of Top Secret documents
                    from twenty to thirty years old. The <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    publication would be effectively ended; it would be impossible to resume
                    publication prior to 1982.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">RECOMMENDATIONS</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Effective declassification and foreign policy publication programs are essential
                    to the overall operation of the Department of State. Disarray and delay in
                    either of these programs will harm the Department in its dealings with Congress,
                    in its efficient internal operations, and in its relationships with key public
                    constituencies. A fully operational centralized declassification system must be
                    brought to bear at the earliest possible moment. It is no less important that
                    long-established and widely respected Department official publication <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> continues to be
                    published on a timely and efficient basis. In order to achieve these twin goals,
                    I recommend that you authorize or direct the following actions:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> That HO and CDC work out an accelerated review schedule
                        for the declassification evaluation of materials for <hi rend="underline"
                            >Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for 1955-1957 by the end of 1980.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> Convene regular meetings of the Coordination Committee of
                        CDC to assure building-wide understanding of an participation in the main
                        lines of the new Department centralized declassification program.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> Carry forward the retroactive review of previously
                        declassified Foreign Relations volumes but confine that review to the 1952-
                        1954 volumes; create a special task force of CDC, HO, and the Bureaus to
                        oversee the review and establish guidelines for it.</item>
                    <pb n="8"/>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> Charge the Office of the Historian with the responsibility
                        for securing declassification of other agency documents proposed for
                        publication in the official <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        volumes; procedures will be established to assure that CDC is kept fully
                        informed of declassification decisions by other agencies as well as to
                        permit reference by CDC to HO of documents with other agency equity.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>5.</label> Suspend negotiations with foreign governments regarding
                        the application of foreign government information criteria as it applies to
                        the declassification of documentation intended for publication in the
                        official Foreign Relations record; assure that HO will be a principal
                        Department participant in any renewal of such negotiations; place the
                        question of foreign government information on the agenda of the Coordinating
                        Committee and the Oversight Committee.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>6.</label> Give final approval to the Department’s classified
                        declassification guidelines for 1950-1954 which were drafted by HO and
                        reviewed and cleared by the Bureaus; make the earliest possible arrangements
                        for the transfer of the 1950-1954 record block, subject to National Archives
                        approval of the classified guidelines; encourage CDC to monitor this record
                        block closely and make in-depth spot checks as appropriate; encourage CDC
                        and FAIM to work expeditiously on this matter in order to obviate violation
                        of the E.O. 12065 on thirty-year-old documents and to minimize the need for
                        the Secretary to confirm their protection.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>7.</label> Direct CDC to provide HO with the necessary waiver
                        expeditiously for the handling of Top Secret documents as
                        confidential.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <head>11. Memorandum From the Historian (David Trask) to the Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary of State for Public Affairs (William Dyess)<note n="39">Source: Folder
                        “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department
                        of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-05-22">May 22, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Delay in Publication of FRUS Volumes, 1950-1954</p>
                <p>After careful consultation and reflection, I have come to the firmest conclusion
                    that decisive action should be taken immediately to stop all tampering with
                    unpublished volumes in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series,
                    1950-1954, both within the Department and at the Central Intelligence
                    Agency.</p>
                <p>I should like to meet with you at your earliest convenience to discuss this
                    matter. If we can agree upon a course of action, I would urge that it be
                    proposed to Mr. Carter as soon as possible. Should we differ, I would hope that
                    we could meet very soon with Mr. Carter to deliberate further.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Analysis</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Revocation of clearances and re-review of all unpublished volumes entails
                    extensive delays in publication, considerable extra expenditure, and a
                    catastrophic setback for open government. Given these considerations re-review
                    should obviously not occur unless excellent reasons are adduced to justify it.
                    The Office of the Historian has yet to receive any such justifications, either
                    from within the Department or from other agencies. Vague generalizations and
                    unsystematic impressions do not constitute “sound justification.”</p>
                <p>Re-review has effectively aborted publication of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Given delays resulting from the process of re-review,
                    only one volume can conceivably be published during the remainder of 1980. Even
                    this book, the fourth volume in the set for 1950, had been held up, although it
                    was already cleared, printed, and bound. If re-review leads ultimately to
                    revocation of clearances, the process of reprinting and rebinding will preclude
                    its release before next year at the earliest, despite the fact that the material
                    in it is already 30 years old. In all probability few if any volumes will be
                    ready for publication during 1981 because of the delays that will result from
                    re-review. (For additional details see note below.)</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>The longer PA postpones its reaction against re-review, the less likely it is
                    that the bureau can head off a catastrophe for the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Unjustified delay suborns the Administration’s policy
                    of open government. Academic users of the series and others will shortly
                    register strong complaints, some of them to the Congress, unless the Department
                    corrects its error. In the present circumstances the Department gives the
                    appearance of scuttling the series. Members of the academic community have
                    already begun to express this view.</p>
                <p>In the absence of convincing justification for further delay, we propose to
                    reverse the Department’s order to re-review the unpublished volumes for
                    1950-1954 and to oppose any such suggestion by other agencies.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Action</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The Historian should immediately inform the Advisory
                        Committee about circumstances that have halted publication of the Foreign
                        Relations series. Garbled versions are already circulating. To correct
                        misapprehension and to avoid the charge of seeking to cover up an
                        unjustified action such notice should be authorized as soon as possible. A
                        draft of such a letter is appended at Tab 1.<note n="40">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> The Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs should
                        immediately write to Mr. White at the CIA, rejecting the proposal of
                        re-review from CIA. Attached as Tab 2 is copy of a draft of such a letter
                        submitted earlier.<note n="41">Not printed.</note> This letter could emanate
                        directly from the Office of the Historian, but response from the Bureau
                        would presumably carry more weight.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> The Assistant Secretary should immediately send a
                        memorandum to Mr. Vest concerning the contents of volume IV for 1950. This
                        volume was supposed to appear at the end of April but was delayed without a
                        showing of the need to hold it up. Attached as Tab 3 is a draft of such a
                        memorandum submitted earlier.<note n="42">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> The Assistant Secretary should immediately request a
                        meeting of the Oversight Committee. The Committee would be asked to consider
                        the suspension of re-review within the Department. See Tab 4.<note n="43"
                            >Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label>5.</label> The Assistant Secretary at the appropriate time would ask
                        for further meetings of the Oversight Committee to consider:<pb n="3"/>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <label>(a)</label> a proposal concerning foreign government
                                information submitted earlier (Tab 5)<note n="44">Not
                                    printed.</note>;</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>(b)</label> a proposal to revise 2 FAM 1350, a draft of which
                                was submitted earlier (Tab 6)<note n="45">Not
                                printed.</note>;</item>
                            <item>
                                <label>(c)</label> a proposal to insure that the arrangements for
                                centralized declassification review are followed to the letter. A
                                memorandum noting deficiencies in this regard was submitted earlier
                                (Tab 7)<note n="46">Not printed.</note>.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The measures that should be presented to the Oversight Committee would do much to
                    correct abuse of the system of centralized declassification review. It has
                    broken down because it hasn’t been operated according to the directive issued by
                    M. The Office of the Historian does not oppose centralized declassification
                    review as such. It insists that the process has been terribly mismanaged and
                    that drastic action must be taken to avoid further damage. The Oversight
                    Committee was set up precisely to deal with the type of complaints that have
                    surfaced in recent weeks.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">NOTE</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There follows a discussion of the delays that will result from re-review of
                    unpublished volumes in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                        covering 1950-1954 includes thirty volumes. Of these six have been published
                        for 1950, three for 1951, and one for 1952-1954, a total of ten. Twenty
                        volumes are in various stages of production.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> Four volumes have reached the page-proof stage. These are
                        IV-1950; III-1951; V-1951; V-1952-1954. The Office of the Historian planned
                        to release these volumes between April and October 1980.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> At least eight volumes have reached the galley-proof stage
                        and clearances have been completed or nearly completed. These are VII-1951;
                        IV-1951; I-1952-1954; IV-1952-1954; IX- 1952-1954; XI-1952-1954; XIII,
                        1952-1954; XVI-1952-1954. The Office of the Historian planned to release
                        these volumes during 1981.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Re-review has thrown this schedule into complete disarray. Delay results
                    from:</p>
                <pb n="4"/>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The time required for CDC to complete the re-review. No
                        re-review of any unpublished volumes has yet been completed, despite the
                        passage of two months.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> When denials are reported to the Office of the Historian,
                        it will appeal certain of them, a process that could take several months or
                        longer. This procedure might entail reference of some materials to other
                        agencies.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> If bound volumes have to be altered as a consequence of
                        re-review, a lengthy and expensive handicraft process must be used to
                        correct 4000 individual books.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> If printed pages must be corrected, it becomes necessary
                        to reprint entire “signatures” (usually thirty-two pages) or even larger
                        segments. Reworking of volumes in page proofs will require a minimum of four
                        months to a maximum of a year. Volumes in galley proofs will require at
                        least a year of processing after completion of clearance.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Re-review insures that only one volume can conceivably be published in 1980,
                    namely IV-1950. It is already bound. If revisions are required, It is most
                    unlikely that the changes could be completed in time to permit publication
                    before 1981.</p>
                <p>Two other volumes in page proofs (III-1951 and V-1952-1954) might conceivably be
                    releasable in 1981, but the prospect appears dim at this time.</p>
                <p>Another volume (V-1951) contains information relating to Iran and may be in limbo
                    for an indeterminate time.</p>
                <p>It is most unlikely that any volume now in galley proofs can be published before
                    1982, given the delays that will result from re-review.</p>
                <p>The best possible situation would permit publication of one volume in 1980 and
                    three volumes in 1981.</p>
                <p>The worst possible case would be no volumes in 1980 and only one to three volumes
                    in 1981.</p>
                <p>If the best possible outcome occurs, the rate of publication over the period
                    1977-1981 would be:<pb n="5"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <label>1977</label> 9 volumes</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>1978</label> 2 volumes</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>1979</label> 2 volumes</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>1980</label> 2 volumes (instead of 5)</item>
                        <item>
                            <label>1981</label> 3 volumes (instead of 8)</item>
                    </list> In the best possible case publication during the current Administration
                    will have fallen from 26-27 years behind currency to 30-31 years behind
                    currency. In contrast compilation will have improved from 25-23 years behind
                    currency to approximately 20 years behind currency.</p>
                <p>Delays in the publication of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series now result principally from slowness in declassification. If re-review
                    takes place, the Office of the Historian could conceivably have as many as
                    forty-eight completed but unpublished manuscripts in various stages of
                    production (20 for 1950-54; 12 for 1955-1957; 16 for 1958-1960) on its hands by
                    April 1981.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d12">
                <head>12. Minutes of the Oversight Committee Meeting<note n="47">Source: Folder
                        “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department
                        of State, Washington, DC. The meeting was held on June 5, 1980.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-06-09">June 9, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> Re-review</p>
                <p>PRESENT:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Robert Killer, M/MO, Chairman</item>
                    <item>Samuel Gammon, M</item>
                    <item>Clayton McManaway, A/CDC</item>
                    <item>Laurence Pickering, A/CDC</item>
                    <item>Paul Washington, PS</item>
                    <item>William J. Dyess, PA</item>
                    <item>David F. Trask, PA/HO</item>
                    <item>William Z. Slany, PA/HO</item>
                    <item>David M. Baehler, PA/HO</item>
                </list>
                <p>Agenda item 1.A.: Role of CDC -- status, schedule</p>
                <p>Mr. McManaway opened the discussion by passing out a schedule for re-review
                    according to which the CDC would be completed with <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>, 1951 -54, by November 1, 1980. He emphasized that the CDC
                    did not welcome the re-review task because it cost the CDC a lot of valuable
                    reviewer time. But he felt re-review was essential because the Archives has
                    indicated dissatisfaction with the 1950-54 guidelines. Mr. Manaway said that
                    these guidelines were inadequate not because of a deficiency in the HO drafting
                    of them but because the bureaus’ reviews of the volumes for this period were
                    deficient. Because of this deficiency, the CDC will redraft the guidelines on
                    the basis of the re-review. CDC is exploring the use of contractors for this
                    purpose. Some discussion ensured over this proposal.</p>
                <p>Having had the opportunity to examine the schedule Mr. McManaway passed out, Mr.
                    Gammon raised the question of how much longer 1950, v. IV, would have to be
                    withheld from publication on account of the Yugoslav material, now that Tito has
                    died and the Soviets have yet to invade the country. Mr. McManaway said that he
                    would raise the issue with Mr. Vest during a meeting they were to have on 1951,
                    v. III, on Friday, June 6. Mr. Dyess said that he had looked at the questioned
                    material and failed to find anything sensitive about it. He asked to go along
                    with Mr. McManaway to the meeting with Mr. Vest. Mr. McManaway agreed, said he
                    doubted that Mr. Vest would change his mind about 1950, IV, on Friday, but
                    promised to keep after Mr. Vest on at least a monthly basis. Mr. Gammon and Mr.
                    Miller both emphasized the urgency of this question.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>A more general discussion ensued about how material deemed desensitized in the
                    initial review can become re-sensitized under the pressure of new events. Mr.
                    Dyess said that applied equally to volumes already published. No political
                    repercussions have arisen from re-sensitization of already published records and
                    it was unclear why they should arise from records about to be published. Mr.
                    Miller responded with the observation that the act of publication can be
                    construed abroad as a political statement on the part of the US government. Dr.
                    Dyess then suggested that the schedule for CDC’s completion of the review and
                    subsequent publication was very important because the implications went well
                    beyond publication of FRUS to the whole question of sincerity about openness in
                    government.</p>
                <p>At that point Mr. Washington indicated that delays should not be a problem
                    because someone in authority at GPO promised a 10-12 week turnaround from
                    submission of cleared manuscript to published volumes. The HO representatives
                    expressed great astonishment, asked if he meant 10-12 weeks for binding alone,
                    and indicated past experience told us to expect a 10-12 month turnaround even
                    after clearance of the galleys. It later turned out that Mr. Washington was
                    talking about GPO capabilities, using its latest technology. It was noted that
                    nearly all of the volumes in question were begun using the old technology, and
                    the turnaround time under these circumstances was lengthening rather than
                    improving.</p>
                <p>Noting that Mr. Washington has referred to cleared material in making his
                    projection, Mr. Trask asked for clarification on the classification status of
                    cleared but still unpublished <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    volumes. Does declassification occur at the point of clearance or at the point
                    of publication? If the former, wouldn’t any FOI requester have the right to the
                    already cleared galleys, creating the possibility of privileged access? If the
                    latter, wouldn’t GPO have to continue its slow method of typesetting, using only
                    cleared operators who must work on overtime? One suggestion was that the
                    Department could consider the documents declassified at the point of clearance
                    and still continue to deny them to FOI requesters on the ground that they are
                    working papers. The consensus was that the CDC and PA should seek a written
                    legal opinion from L on the question.</p>
                <p>In a final comment, Mr. Trask alluded to the statement on the schedule that Mr.
                    McManaway had passed out that re-review of certain volumes was “completed.” He
                    said it could not be considered complete until HO received from CDC a formal
                    listing of denials in the volumes in question. After some discussion about the
                    desirability of informal talks, it was agreed that written denials would be the
                    final step in the re-review process. Only upon receipt of these would HO
                    initiate appeals.</p>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <p>Agenda item 1. B.: CIA reclearance issue.</p>
                <p>Mr. Dyess recommended that CDC flag anything that it thinks should undergo
                    re-review at CIA but that HO in accordance with regulations should continue to
                    be responsible for communicating with CIA about any such material. Neither Mr.
                    McManaway nor Mr. Miller saw the reason for using this channel, since CDC is in
                    regular contact with CIA on other clearance questions in any case. Mr. McManaway
                    proposed that CDC flag the appropriate records, then call someone over from CIA
                    to have a look at them. Mr. Gammon thought that instead we should stick with the
                    regulations and let HO handle the liaison with CIA on <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> materials, despite Mr. McManaway’s claim that he had
                    responsibility for all declassification activities in the Department. Mr. Miller
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>Agenda item 1. C.: Rule of HO -- plans, schedule</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask presented the case against re-review, noting that delays would be
                    extensive and costs would be astronomical. A schedule was circulated projecting
                    HO’s specific volume publication dates under various conditions created by CDC’s
                        re-review.<note n="48">Not located.</note> Mr. Trask thought the total cost
                    of reviewing the 20 volumes in question would be upwards of $1 million. In view
                    of these factors and the lack of a systematic justification for re-review, he
                    stated that the decision to do so should be revoked.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gammon and Mr. Miller rejected this proposal and said that re-review would
                    continue.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask stated that the whole procedure has been decided on in a haphazard
                    manner. He cited as an example the lack of thought given to any provision for
                    appealing CDC decisions arrived at in the course of re-review. After some
                    discussion a consensus emerged that the Oversight Committee would not serve as
                    an appeals panel; rather, appeals would go through the normal chain of command:
                    bureaus, under secretary for political affairs, deputy secretary, secretary. In
                    this connection Mr. Trask noted that the E.O. called for the secretary’s
                    certification of withholding 30 year old documents, that this requirement
                    already applied to the material in 1950, v. IV, and that it soon would apply to
                    vast amount of documentation awaiting submission to Archives. Mr. McManaway
                    interrupted with the statement that this certification provision only meant the
                    secretary had to certify withholding categories of documents, not individual
                    documents.</p>
                <p>Returning to the question of delay, Mr. Pickering thought that the CDC could meet
                    HO’s original publication schedule after it completed the first few volumes
                    scheduled for re-review. He and Mr. McManaway failed to understand how HO could
                    justify the publication schedule just passed around. Mr. Slany explained it in
                        terms<pb n="4"/> of the delay caused by removing volumes from the clearance
                    and production pipeline and then, after CDC re-review, trying to get them back
                    on track. The sense of urgency that HO has sought to instill in agencies on the
                    need for clearance is also lost by this “loop” within the cycle. Mr. McManaway
                    agreed to help re-instill this sense of urgency, although he claimed that the
                    NSC, for one, did not even know that the State Department was conducting a
                    re-review. On the production question it was agreed that HO, CDC, and PS would
                    jointly work out a schedule based on the 12 week GPO turnaround that Mr.
                    Washington had claimed was possible.</p>
                <p>Adverting to the cost question, Mr. McManaway thought that $1 million was far too
                    high a figure for review costs. In any case, Mr. Miller thought that $1 million
                    would not be too high even in a period of budget stringency if it saved us some
                    foreign policy difficulties. He thought that publication of post-World War II
                    records would lead to many more such difficulties than had publication of
                    earlier records. This is because there is continuity between the early postwar
                    years and the institutions that developed then and the present. Mr. Baehler said
                    that logically what Mr. Miller said stands up, but that HO has been publishing
                    postwar documents for fifteen years now and has yet to hear a peep of protest
                    from foreign governments reflecting foreign policy difficulties. Until we do, we
                    remain unconvinced of the materials’ sensitivity.</p>
                <p>Agenda item 2.A.: cost problems -- PBR, HO</p>
                <p>All agreed that this point had already been covered.</p>
                <p>Agenda item 2.B.: Image problems</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask pointed out that the scholarly community was starting to learn of the
                    re-review and the incumbent delays, albeit in a distorted fashion. He explained
                    that this group’s influence on the Hill is out of proportion to its size, that
                    its contacts with the right Representatives and Senators on openness issues
                    could make political trouble for President Carter, and that such contacts at the
                    least could cause invoking consultations under the McGovern Amendment.<note
                        n="49">Section 120 of the FY 1979 authorization for the Department of State
                        states “(a) The Congress finds that the Department of State publication
                        ‘Foreign Relations of the United States’ plays an important role in making
                        the documentary record of the United States foreign relations avilable to
                        the Congress and the American public. (b) The Secretary of State shall
                        therefore insure that publication of the ‘Foreign Relations of the United
                        States’ volume is continued in such a manner as will maintain high standard
                        of comprehensive documentation already established by past volumes.” Trask
                        described the amendment as the result of lobbying undertaken by academic
                        historians to “preclude adoption of microform supplements as a means of
                        adding to the amount of publication.” See “Briefing Paper #8: McGovern
                        Amendment (David F. Trask),” [no date], Folder “Foreign Relations 2,” Box 2,
                        Arthur D. Kogan Papers, Lot 83 D 230, RG 59, NARA II.</note> From a more
                    general standpoint, re-review threatens to put the US behind the UK in opening
                    records to the public. Mr. Gammon thought that this outcome would be disastrous.
                    In order to halt distorted views from spreading through the scholarly community,
                    Mr. Trask emphasized, there was urgent need to inform the Advisory Committee of
                    exactly what was happening. No one demurred. Mr. Trask also noted that the
                    Department can use the opportunity of the SHAFR meeting in August to inform the
                    profession of the status of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series and of the 1950-54 record block.</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>Mr. Gammon and Mr. Miller thought it would be a good idea to use Mr. Read’s talk
                    at the SHAFR meeting to present a common Departmental position on the re-review
                    question. Once the text of the talk is drafted and agreed to within the
                    Department, we can draw on it to inform the Advisory Committee, to respond to
                    the Gardner inquiry,<note n="50">See Lloyd Gardner letter to George McGovern and
                        Frank Church, May 6, 1980 and George McGovern letter to Brian Atwood, May
                        14, 1980 in Folder “Dissent Channel Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D
                        114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note> and to answer other
                    questions about the rationale for re-review. The exact procedures for devising a
                    common position were left unclear. Mr. Miller noted that HO had action on the
                    Gardner letter, implying that the draft might serve as a starting point for the
                    rationale. Mr. Trask thought the Gardner letter would have to be an <hi
                        rend="underline">ad hoc</hi> response. Mr. Dyess said that the rationale
                    should be cleared in M and L. Who would draft the rationale was left unclear.
                    Regardless of who drafts it, the meeting scheduled at the Department on August
                    14 for the SHAFR attendees would be another good opportunity to present the
                    Department’s rationale.</p>
                <p>Agenda item III: Other issues.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask identified two areas he wanted to discuss:</p>
                <p>1. Problems of delay - Mr. Trask described the 1955-onward review. In response to
                    Mr. McManaway’s question as to what he was getting at, he said the problem is
                    that CDC is seriously behind in reviewing post-1954 records. Mr. McManaway
                    disagreed, saying that it will not be long until the CDC is well ahead of HO. He
                    repeated that CDC did not want to do the re-review but that he was unable to
                    accept responsibility for release of material at Archives under the guidelines
                    developed from the initial review. He recounted that he had so informed Mr.
                    Blair and had asked him if PA wanted to accept responsibility. When Mr. Blair
                    said no, Mr. McManaway had no choice but to conduct a re-review.</p>
                <p>2. Modes of consultation - Mr. Trask noted that the effects of re-review,
                    previously described, might have been avoided if CDC had adhered to the
                    procedures devised for consultation on all policy issues before taking the
                    re-review decision. Consultation bodies included the Coordination Committee and
                    the Oversight Committee. Mr. McManaway replied angrily that the Coordination
                    Committee had been set up only to ease the transition from the old to the new
                    declassification system and that he should know since he wrote the
                        directive.<note n="51">the Directive in question establishes the
                        Coordination Committee as a permanent body. (Footnote in original.)</note>
                    Mr. Trask said that even if he accepted Mr. McManaway’s interpretation, there
                    was a perception extant that the CDC had acted in a very cavalier manner in
                    reaching the re-review decision. Mr. Trask concluded with an expression of
                    concern that the Oversight Committee also had not previously met to discuss the
                    issue. The meeting then adjourned.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d13">
                <head>13. Memorandum From the Historian (David Trask) to the Director of the Policy
                    Planning Staff (Anthony Lake)<note n="52">Source: Folder “Dissent Channel
                        Package (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State,
                        Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-06-11">June 11, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Use of Dissent Channel: Objection to the Policy of Re-reviewing
                    Classified Information Previously Cleared for Publication in <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I make use of the dissent channel to appeal the Department’s decision to revoke
                    all declassification actions previously taken on twenty unpublished volumes of
                    the series <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> and
                    to re-review all such actions. Such a policy has no precedent. It can be
                    justified only in the most extraordinary circumstances. I do not believe that
                    those circumstances exist. I take action only after pursuing the matter through
                    all the normal channels.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series is the keystone of the
                    Department’s adherence to the principle of open government. Its preparation and
                    publication presents an authoritative, official, and objective record of the
                    nation’s foreign policy. It also triggers deposit of the Department’s records at
                    the National Archives, where they are opened to the public. If the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series is compromised, so is the
                    Department’s commitment to open government. Given the fundamental importance of
                    information in the function of a democratic society, no policy issue can be of
                    comparable importance.</p>
                <p>The Department’s decision to order re-review is stated in a memorandum dated
                    April 11 from Mr. Read to all assistant secretaries: “We have recently
                    discovered problems with some of the material previously cleared by the bureaus
                    for publication in the FRUS covering the years 1950-1954.” Also, “some of these
                    earlier reviews were conducted as long as three years ago, and circumstances
                    have changed substantially in some cases in the interim.” No other rationale was
                    offered.</p>
                <p>Given the consequences of re-review one would assume that such an action would
                    take place only after the most serious consideration by all concerned parties
                    and the preparation of a comprehensive rationale for the decision. No such
                    consideration occurred and nothing backs up the stated reasons for re-review
                    except unsupported allegations.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>Re-review contravenes this Administration’s policy of “openness.” It entails
                    substantial delays in the publication of the foreign policy record and the
                    transfer of the Department’s record block for 1950- 1954 to the National
                    Archives. It means that Great Britain, adhering to a “thirty-year rule,” will
                    release its foreign policy record for public inspection sooner than the United
                    States. The order to re-review will certainly lead to extensive protests on the
                    part of those who make use of the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series and the records of the Department deposited at the Archives. It will
                    certainly arouse grave concern in Congress because re-review may violate the
                    McGovern Amendment to the Department’s Authorization Act for 1979.</p>
                <p>These considerations lead me to take the extraordinary step of appealing this
                    policy decision through the dissent channel. I act with the unanimous support of
                    all senior supervisors in the Office of the Historian. I act in the conviction
                    that this step will enjoy universal approbation among other staff members of the
                    Office.</p>
                <p>I propose the following:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>that the Secretary of State immediately suspend the order to
                        re-review.</item>
                    <item>that the Secretary of State immediately arrange an <hi rend="underline"
                            >independent</hi> review of the entire issue, one that takes place
                        outside of the administrative channels already exhausted in this
                        situation.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Upon request the Office of the Historian is prepared to present detailed support
                    for its contention that a most careful rationale for re-review must exist before
                    the Department can reconcile re-review with public policy as reflected in EO
                    12065, FAM regulations relating to the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and the Office of the Historian, and various
                    legislative prescriptions such as the McGovern Amendment.</p>
                <p>Should the investigation uphold the policy of re-review, I propose that the
                    Secretary issue a detailed explanation of the reasons for adopting it so that
                    the Department may respond properly to public concern.</p>
                <p>If the investigation does not uphold re-review, I propose that the Secretary of
                    State revoke the order to re-review permanently.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d14">
                <head>14. Memorandum From the Historian (David Trask) to Member of the Policy
                    Planning Staff (Elaine Morton)<note n="53">Source: Folder “Documents Relating to
                        the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D
                        114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-08-28">August 28, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT : Resensitization as a Rationale for Re-Review</p>
                <p>In theory information that has previously been declassified for publication in
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> could
                    resensitize during the lapse of time between declassification and
                    publication.</p>
                <p>In practice this resensitization rarely happens. HO is not aware of
                    resensitization having ever caused difficulties across the long history of the
                        <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series and does not believe that
                    it has occured in connection with the set for 1950-1954.</p>
                <p>No problems have arisen in the past for a number of good reasons:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> Our editorial practice works against
                        sensationalism.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> Our modes of releasing the volume work against surprise
                        and publicity, in part to avoid irresponsible use of information in the
                        series.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> Mandatory declassification reviews under the Freedom of
                        Information Act and EO 12055 and revelations in memoirs and journalistic
                        accounts very often desensitize areas sufficiently so that resensitization
                        is most unlikely.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> Even in the event of some resensitization continued
                        declassification would very often be justified because of the balancing
                        clause in EO 12065 requiring that the sensitivity of material, especially as
                        it ages, be weighed against the public interest in its release.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In April the CDC became alarmed that information in Vol. I for 1951 would cause
                    great troubles if published. An attempt to abort publication of this volume
                    failed when it became clear that the process of release had gotten beyond the
                    point of no return. It is most instructive to note that not one jot or tittle of
                    reaction to Volume I for 1951 has as yet occurred. We deem it most unlikely that
                    such reactions will occur, and we hold the same view of other volumes as yet
                    unpublished in the 1950-1954 sequence. The burden of proof concerning
                    resensitization should lie with those who argue the case. All prior experience
                    argues that in the cases at issue the likelihood is all but infinitesmal.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>Concern about “resensitition” is almost always an aspect of “nervous nellyism”
                    that can prevail in government during periods of stress. It ought to be the
                    function of responsible agencies to resist “nervous nellyism.” One way to do
                    this is to insist upon the most comprehensive rationale for any specific claim
                    of resensitization. The Department ought not to allow incantation of formulas to
                    decide cases in which resensitization is alleged. It ought to insist on careful
                    data before it accepts a claim of resensitization. HO has not seen such careful
                    data in the cases being alleged at the moment. The most useful step that the
                    Department could take to guard against resensitization is to do all in its power
                    to expedite publication of FRUS, once declassification actions are
                    completed.</p>
                <p>One final word. It is argued that resensitization is much more likely to occur at
                    present and in the future than in the past because of changes in the nature of
                    our foreign relations during the years since 1945. This argument is just plain
                    stupid. It fails to take into account:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>a.</label> The fact that the gap now existing between events and our
                        publication of them is far greater than in earlier times.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>b.</label> The fact that our role in foreign affairs has come under
                        much more scrutiny since World War II than in earlier years so that public
                        knowledge of all aspects of our foreign relations is quite extensive.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>c.</label> The fact that all kinds of open-government practices have
                        prepared the way for fully authoritative and responsible coverage of events
                        that might have been extremely sensitive at a closer remove from
                        currency.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>d.</label> The fact that the editors of the Foreign Relations series
                        take appropriate steps to guard against problems of this sort not taken in
                        earlier years.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have observed a lot of smoke screens in my time, but I recall none as patently
                    ridiculous as this one.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <head>15. Memorandum From the Historian (David Trask) to Member of the Policy
                    Planning Staff (Elaine Morton)<note n="54">Source: Folder “Documents Relating to
                        the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D
                        114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-09-09">September 9, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: Allegations of Foreign Concern About the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Series</p>
                <p>In connection with my Dissent Channel message I should like to add the following
                    to the information that I have made available to you.</p>
                <p>Increasingly allegations are made that foreign governments are very much
                    concerned about release of information in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series. Concern is said to emanate primarily from Great
                    Britain and the Commonwealth countries, although a few other countries are
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>For whatever reasons those who air such concern have not chosen to present the
                    evidence for such allegations. I believe this is because no substantial evidence
                    exists. Let me note the following:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The Office of the Historian knows of no such concern
                        elsewhere about release of information in the <hi rend="underline">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> series.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> The Office of the Historian believes that concern about
                        the release of information emanating from other countries does not relate to
                        the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series but rather to other
                        types of release, namely, unauthorized leaks of sensitive information and
                        authorized release of relatively recent information obtained through the
                        workings of the Freedom of Information Act and analogous procedures.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> The Office of the Historian believes that “nervous
                        nellyism” and clientism in the Department could stimulate unreasonable
                        concern elsewhere, and it hopes that steps will be taken to insure that
                        well-meaning but entirely undesirable prompting of other countries will not
                        take place. Ari ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I respectfully note that on occasion nervous envoys have assumed that some great
                    disaster would befall the United States, should we release certain kinds of
                    information about the nation to which they are accredited. Such a situation
                    arose some years ago in connection with<pb n="2"/> planned release of
                    information about certain of our activities just after World War II in Italy.
                    The Office of the Historian has very elaborate procedures to insure against
                    sensationalizing of our volumes. These procedures, since improved, insured that
                    no trouble actually stemmed from the release of the information in Italy. The
                    ambassador was entirely in error in his predictions of doomsday. The point of
                    this story is that the Department keeps reinventing the wheel in terms of fears
                    that somehow, someway, great disasters will flow from publication of the truth
                    many years after the event. Uniformly, after irruptions of such concern, no
                    trouble materializes.</p>
                <p>In any event, even if on some future occasion a row materializes, we have to
                    weigh some slight evanescent inconvenience against our responsibility to report
                    the truth at an appropriate time without fear or favor. If we stray from that
                    principle in publishing our foreign-affairs record objectively at a reasonable
                    remove from currency, we will be throwing away one of our strong and undeniable
                    assets in dealing with the rest of the world and informing our own people.</p>
                <p>It is of great importance that nervous nellies are not allowed to use
                    international concern about unauthorized leaks or authorized Freedom of
                    Information releases to injure the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series, about which no comparable body of concern has ever been manifest.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <head>16. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="55">Source: Folder “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04
                        D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC. Drafted by David
                        Baehler.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-10-09">October 9, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>MEETING ON THE APPEAL OF DOCUMENTS IN FRUS, 1951, V. III</p>
                <p>Participants:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Mr. Newsom - P</item>
                    <item>Ms. Patterson</item>
                    <item>Mr. Vest - EUR</item>
                    <item>Mr. Holmes</item>
                    <item>Mr. Tracy - A</item>
                    <item>Mr. Pickering - A/CDC</item>
                    <item>Mr. Malmborg - L</item>
                    <item>Mr. Gammon - M</item>
                    <item>Ms. Morton - S/P</item>
                    <item>Mr. Dyess - PA</item>
                    <item>Mr. McNarnara</item>
                    <item>Mr. Trask - PA/HO</item>
                    <item>Mr. Baehler </item>
                </list>
                <p>The meeting commenced at 11:40 a.m.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom stated at the outset that his purpose in calling the meeting was to
                    discuss the appeals package,<note n="56">Not located.</note> which he noted had
                    occasioned considerable interest and heat, on documents denied by CDC in FRUS,
                    1951, v. III. His purpose was not to question the declassification review
                    mechanism embodied in the existence of the CDC and in its relations with the
                    geographic bureaus. Nor was it to question the appeals channel that had been
                    established to resolve disagreements. Speaking of his own role, he said it was
                    natural that he should be called on to resolve differences when basic policy
                    issues arose. Otherwise, when basic policy issues were not involved, he felt the
                    resolution of appeals should occur at the geographic bureau level. He thought
                    that the chain of command was the correct channel for resolving appeals.</p>
                <p>He wished to talk about the appeals package for 1951, v. III, which he had read
                    with interest. His first question was: what are our obligations to our allies
                    and to NATO with regard to the release of documents of interest to them? He
                    noted that by 1951, we have a real problem in this respect. He asked Mr.
                    Malmborg to explicate the definition of foreign government information as a
                    means of arriving at an answer to the question.</p>
                <p>Mr. Malmborg said the Executive Order defined foreign government information not
                    only as information in other governments’ documents, but also as such
                    information in US documents.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked if that was HO’s view. Mr. Trask said it was. At Mr. Newsom’s
                    behest, Mr. Trask elaborated HO’s view, to the following effect: HO has no
                    quarrel with the definition. HO stands on the set of general guidelines signed
                    by the Secretary governing systematic review at Archives. This set provides that
                    foreign government information given orally, reported in US documents, and no
                    longer sensitive is to be released at 20 years. Sensitivity thus becomes the
                    sole criterion for declassification review of such FRUS material.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Ms. Morton, Mr. Trask said that FRUS review is
                    neither systematic nor mandatory review. It is a special administrative review,
                    analogous to mandatory review. He said that CDC’s review is also not systematic
                    review. It is intended to provide the basis for guidelines to be used to perform
                    systematic review at Archives.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked who does systematic review. Mr. Trask said that an Archives
                    staff does it by examining the records page by page against Department
                    guidelines. If a given document seems to fall within the guidelines for
                    continued classification, the Archives staff sets it aside and asks for further
                    review by the Department. If the Department then decides to deny
                    declassification, the Secretary must certify the continued withholding of the
                    document for an appropriate period.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pickering said that he agreed with everything Mr. Trask said except for his
                    description of the need for the Secretary’s certification. He felt that the
                    Secretary had to certify only the guidelines on the basis of which the document
                    is withheld initially, and that authority to withhold individual documents can
                    then be delegated to lower levels in the Department. Mr. McNamara disagreed,
                    stating that PA had an oral opinion from L stating that such authority could not
                    be delegated. Mr. Newsom asked Mr. Malmborg what he thought. Mr. Malmborg did
                    not know. Mr. Newsom thought it would be a good idea to resolve the matter. In
                    the course of this colloquy, Mr. Pickering said that Mr. McManaway had been
                    operating on the basis of the legal view that Mr. Pickering had propounded.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom then asked Mr. Trask how FRUS fits into the systematic review scheme
                    he had outlined. Mr. Trask explained that the declassification review of FRUS
                    was the basis on which CDC drafted the guidelines that Archives would use to
                    conduct systematic review. It seemed to Mr. Newsom that, according to Mr.
                    Trask’s conception, the Secretary would have to certify the withholding of FRUS
                    materials. Mr. Trask said that this was his personal view, but as indicated,
                    FRUS review was not systematic review and the certification provisions of the
                    Executive Order did therefore not directly apply. He was uncertain in what way
                    the Department would resolve this issue.</p>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <p>Mr. Newsom then returned to his original question: what are our obligations to
                    our allies and to NATO? Mr. Trask, referring to the general guidelines, drew the
                    distinction between foreign government documents, which HO clears and will
                    continue to clear with foreign governments, and information in US documents,
                    which HO does not believe the US should clear with foreign governments. Mr.
                    Newsom said that he understood that there was an issue involved in one of the
                    documents in the appeal as to whether to clear it with the French. Mr. Baehler
                    replied that the case was one of a French document that was quoted in part in an
                    American document. HO had excised the quoted portion in response to a French
                    request. The American document containing it did not reveal the same information
                    denied by the French in their own document. Accordingly, HO did not regard as
                    justified the CDC’s denial of the US document. At this point, Mr. Vest agreed
                    with Mr. Trask’s earlier assertion that the only issue involved was the
                    sensitivity of the foreign government information in US documents.</p>
                <p>At this point, Mr. Gammon noted that HO had recognized the sensitivity of the
                    kind of information under discussion in the past and had agreed not to release
                    it even though legally the US could have done so.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked if EUR thought that some of the NATO military planning reflected
                    in the denied material was still sensitive. Messrs. Vest and Holmes indicated
                    that it remained sensitive because it portrayed the evolution of NATO planning;
                    from this information enemies of the US could extrapolate present plans existing
                    in NATO. Mr. Dyess asked if EUR was concerned with delivering the same sort of
                    message as that allegedly transmitted by the Acheson statement in early 1950
                    asserting that Korea was outside the containment perimeter, a statement that
                    allegedly led to the Korean War. Both Mr. Vest and Mr. Holmes indicated that
                    this was it precisely. Mr. Newsom then asked if what Messrs. Vest and Holmes
                    were saying was that publication in FRUS gives the documents a status of such
                    magnitude that the information could be read by an enemy to be a signal or an
                    official US government statement. Again, Messrs. Vest and Holmes agreed that
                    this was their meaning.</p>
                <p>At this point, Mr. Pickering broached the issue of the secrecy agreement made in
                    NATO concerning admission of Greece and Turkey to NATO in 1951. Mr. Newsom said
                    he had planned to come to this. Mr. Newsom inquired about the content of the
                    agreement. Mr. Pickering said it was contained in a document under appeal and
                    that it constituted unanimous assent to keep records of NATO discussion of the
                    issue from Greece and Turkey. Mr. Newsom asked if the agreement had included
                    keeping secret the records of the discussion maintained by individual countries
                    or if Mr. Pickering was “extrapolating” this interpretation from the agreement.
                    Mr. Pickering said it was an extrapolation.</p>
                <pb n="4"/>
                <p>Reverting to the sensitivity question (as opposed to the foreign government
                    information arguments) Mr. Newsom asked Mr. Vest for an objective answer to the
                    question of whether he really thought there was a good possibility the release
                    through FRUS of the records relating to admission of Greece and Turkey to NATO
                    would end up in Greek and Turkish newspapers and would as a consequence present
                    our negotiators with a problem. Mr. Vest replied that he thought there was a
                    high probability of this happening because the Greek press was given to
                    sensationalism on the subject and because the Turkish press was given to
                    distorting the issue at the slightest pretext. Mr. Newsom asked how long it
                    would be before the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> volume in
                    question is published if deletions were made that required a revision of the
                    volume. Mr. Trask replied that it would be six or eight months at the
                    earliest.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked if the problem would be resolved once the reintegration
                    negotiations are completed. Mr. Vest thought not. The sensitivities on the
                    subject transcended the issue of whether to reintegrate Greece into NATO. Mr.
                    Newsom asked, in view of that, when they could be released. Mr. Pickering said
                    that the CDC sets an automatic re-review date of ten years from the initial
                    denial and that the Department would take another look at that point. Mr. Newsom
                    then asked if the documents relating to Greek and Turkish admission to NATO
                    would be withheld under FOI. Mr. Pickering said that they would be withheld. Mr.
                    Newsom asked if the denial would be sustainable in court. Mr. Pickering said it
                    would be.</p>
                <p>Mr. Vest then offered the view that any discussion of Yugoslavia in the NATO
                    forum would be very sensitive now because of the instability of the Belgrade
                    government.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom then rendered a decision: Given the Greek and Turkish problems that
                    currently exist for US policy, he would recommend withholding the material on
                    Greek and Turkish admission to NATO until after the reintegration negotiations
                    have been completed. The decision to withhold would be re-examined at that time.
                    He further recommended that the references to Yugoslavia in the NATO context
                    should be withheld pending the stabilization of the situation in that country.
                    He recommended that the materials relating to NATO military planning in the
                    event of war be released as no longer sensitive.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pickering objected to the final decision on the grounds that it is still
                    sensitive information. He thought the sensitivity could be reduced if the exact
                    language were deleted and a footnote substituted for it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked Mr. Trask if this was a possibility.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask responded that the information should be released for three
                    reasons:</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The plans referred to in the documents were short-term
                        plans that became obsolete within a short period. They are accordingly no
                        longer sensitive.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> The presentation of the information in its full context
                        minimizes the chance that others might misunderstand the US reasons for
                        publishing it. The series has been published for 120 years and foreign
                        governments understand that its purposes are other than for delivering a
                        political message. Its goal is to inform the American public of its
                        government’s activities in the foreign policy area.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> As the documents become older, the balancing test must
                        become more and more prominent in deciding whether to release. The possible
                        damage of release to national security must be weighed against the right of
                        the public to the information.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Newsom explicitly recognized the validity of the last point, noting that it
                    would be wise to consider whether angering the scholarly community would be
                    worth withholding the information on national security grounds. With that, Mr.
                    Newsom confirmed his earlier recommendations. He then asked whether Mr. Trask
                    thought the Secretary had to certify the withholding of the documents for Mr.
                    Newsom’s recommendations to have legal validity.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask offered the opinion that the Secretary did not at this point have to
                    certify the withholding of FRUS material for the following reasons: 1) There
                    presently exists uncertainty about whether materials older than 20 years have to
                    be certified for withholding during the ten-year period allowed agencies by the
                    Executive Order to reach the 20 year systematic review line; and 2) FRUS
                    declassification is requested as a special administrative action and is not in
                    any case covered during the ten-year catch-up period by the certification
                    provisions of the Executive Order. He indicated that HO’s only interest was to
                    obtain a high-level hearing. He was satisfied that the material in question had
                    received a high-level and serious review. He felt that the burden of deciding
                    appeals should be transferred to an independent appeals panel.</p>
                <p>Mr. Newsom thought that it was not yet the time for establishing such a panel. He
                    confirmed his opinion that the present appeals system was workable.</p>
                <p>Mr. Pickering returned to Mr. Newsom’s decision to release NATO military plans
                    material. He stated that Mr. McManaway was currently discussing with the NSC a
                    policy on releasing materials on military planning. He wished to defer a
                    decision until such time as Mr. McManaway could work out a policy on the
                    issue.</p>
                <pb n="6"/>
                <p>Mr. Newsom asked whether this proposal was all right with Mr. Trask. Mr. Trask
                    responded that it was.</p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned at 12:25 p.m.</p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d17">
                <head>17. Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (Anthony Lake)
                    to the Historian (David Trask)<note n="57">Source: Folder “Documents Relating to
                        the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04 D
                        114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC. Limited Official Use; Dissent
                        Channel.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-10-14">October 14, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>SUBJECT: <hi rend="underline">Re-Review of 1950-54 Material for Publication in
                        Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As you know, your dissent to the Department’s April 1980 decision to re-review
                    the sensitivity of material scheduled for publication in <hi rend="underline"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> for the years 1950-54 has
                    received very careful and detailed consideration. The issues you raise are
                    important. That you elected to raise them at the highest levels of the
                    Department has served to sharpen the focus of those concerned on the dual role
                    that the Department performs: it is responsible both for conducting the
                    diplomacy of the United States and for helping to preserve and meet the public’s
                    right to know about the foreign affairs of their nation.</p>
                <p>I agree with you that the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series is
                    central to the Department’s adherence to the principle of open government. The
                    specific decision you question, however, was justified, in our view, when it
                    became apparent that the decentralized nature of previous reviews of the 1950-54
                    material and events transpiring during the relatively long period of time that
                    elapsed between some of the initial declassification actions and the dates of
                    planned publication combined to allow material to be authorized for publication,
                    the release of which would either:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>
                        <label>1.</label> tend to impede current diplomatic negotiations or other
                        business;</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>2.</label> fail to preserve the confidence reposed in the Department
                        by individuals and by foreign governments;</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>3.</label> give needless offense to other nationalities or
                        individuals; or</item>
                    <item>
                        <label>4.</label> reflect personal opinions presented in internal
                        communications and not acted upon by the Department.</item>
                </list>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>Although the number of similar instances of inappropriately cleared material
                    expected to be revealed by the re-review was small, their negative impact upon
                    our ability to conduct an effective diplomacy was properly deemed large enough
                    to warrant the time and effort necessary to identify and remove them from the
                    galleys of the 20 volumes of <hi rend="underline">FRUS</hi> that had not yet
                    been published for the years 1950-54.</p>
                <p>Your concern about the adverse public impact of any significant delay in the
                    scheduled publication of <hi rend="underline">FRUS</hi> is one that we share. As
                    you know, the 20 volumes in question were in various stages of the
                    previously-mandated clearance process when re-review was initiated. In order to
                    expedite publication in keeping with our public affairs responsibilities and the
                    recent E.O. 12065 injunction to declassify foreign affairs information as early
                    as national security considerations permit, the Department undertook measures
                    designed to insure that re-review and publication of the 1950-54 <hi
                        rend="underline">FRUS</hi> material proceed as rapidly as possible.</p>
                <p>The cooperative efforts of HO, CDC, and the regional bureaus in this endeavor
                    have been crucial. We are informed that re—review by CDC has yet to be completed
                    on only 6 of the 20 volumes in question.<note n="58">See Clayton McManaway
                        memorandum to Oversight Committee, September 15, 1980, Folder “Documents
                        Relating to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3,
                        Lot File 04 D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC.</note> In
                    addition, measures have been taken on an experimental basis to expedite
                    publication by declassifying galley proofs in the final stages of publication so
                    that more people can work on them. CDC anticipates that their part of the
                    re-review effort will be completed by November 1, 1980.</p>
                <p>The major remaining sources of publication delay appear to fall within two areas.
                    First, there is the process necessary to adjudicate specific classification/
                    declassification decisions contested by CDC and the regional bureaus on one hand
                    and PA representing HO on the other. Mr. Newsom has been working on this problem
                    with those concerned. Second, there is competition for the provision of central
                    services needed to expedite the publication process. I understand the Department
                    is working on this as well.</p>
                <p>Finally, I agree with you that the importance and inherent difficulty of reaching
                    decisions that balance national security concerns against the public’s right
                        to<pb n="3"/> know about the history of our foreign policy is such that it
                    is incumbent upon all of us in the Department who deal with such matters to
                    follow scrupulously the procedures designed to insure that policy decisions in
                    these matters are carefully weighed. In this regard, the Oversight Committee and
                    the Coordination Committee established by Mr. Read’s memorandum of November 20,
                    1978 setting up the Department’s Classification/Declassification system should
                    be used to their fullest extent, with regularly scheduled meetings in addition
                    to special meetings, as necessary, at the request of PA, CDC, or interested
                    regional bureaus. In particular, the Oversight Committee should be convened
                    whenever a request is made to re-review material previously declas¬sified in
                    accordance with FAM 1350.</p>
                <p>Let me again express appreciation for your provocative and useful dissent
                    message. </p>
            </div>
            <milestone unit="section" rend="hr"/>
            <div type="document" xml:id="d18">
                <head>18. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="59">Source: Folder “Documents Relating
                        to the Re-Review of Foreign Relations, 1950-1954 (1980),” Box 3, Lot File 04
                        D 114, U.S. Department of State, Washington, DC. Drafted by David
                        Baehler.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date when="1980-10-17">October 17, 1980</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>MEETING WITH AD HOC COMMITTEE OF OAH ON FOREIGN RELATIONS</p>
                <p>Participants:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Walter LaFeber</item>
                    <item>Lloyd Gardner</item>
                    <item>David Trask</item>
                    <item>William Slany</item>
                    <item>David Baehler</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber opened the meeting by stating that the Committee’s mandate was to
                    examine the effects of current declassification practices on FOI and the <hi
                        rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series. They particularly wanted to
                    talk about the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi> series, HO’s
                    relations with the CDC, and the status of the volumes undergoing re-review.</p>
                <p>Mr. Trask described the earlier system of review, which was characterized by
                    decentralization, and the origins of the CDC, which came into existence as part
                    of the Department’s effort to implement the new Executive Order on
                    declassification. He then described the CDC as divided into a mandatory review
                    staff and a systematic review staff that examines the material HO presents.</p>
                <p>At that point Mr. LaFeber asked whether there were any historians on the CDC
                    staff. Mr. Trask replied that there were not and resumed his description of the
                    CDC. Its main purpose, he said, was to develop guidelines to be used at Archives
                    in the course of systematic review. HO assists in that process by providing a
                    sample of documents from which the <hi rend="underline">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series for that period was compiled and that includes the documents incorporated
                    in the compilation. The sample is large because the Department considered it
                    necessary to derive the guidelines from a substantial representative portion of
                    the Department’s files and because it will be in the interest of HO to
                    declassify a large body of material when it adopts a microform supplement to the
                    FRUS volumes.</p>
                <p>In clarification of a point, Mr. Gardner asked whether the act of
                    declassification within the CDC had the effect of declassifying any documents
                    outside of the sample. Mr. Trask replied that it did not.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber then asked who was doing the re-review of the 1950-54 volumes. In
                    reply, Mr. Trask noted that his description of the CDC’s procedures applied to
                    the 1955 and later records and that the re-review was a special case. To answer
                    the question posed by Mr. LaFeber, Mr. Trask described the transfer of records
                    to Archives and noted that the Archives demanded guidelines from the
                    transferring agency before it would accept the records. He stated that HO
                    assisted by formulating a<pb n="2"/> set of “general guidelines” that all
                    bureaus approved and the Secretary of State sent to Archives. In addition to
                    these, there was required a supplementary set of “special guidelines” that HO
                    also drafted for the 1950-54 period based on the bureau actions and submitted to
                    the CDC for its and the bureau’s approval. That set was derived from the
                    declassification actions that the bureaus had taken in the course of their
                    reviews of the 1950-54 FR volumes. The CDC determined that these special
                    guidelines failed to cover adequately the areas of sensitivity with which the
                    Archives would be confronted when the declassification staff there conducted its
                    systematic review. The CDC made this determination on two bases: the initial
                    bureau review had been inadequate, and the material in the period since that
                    review had become resensitized. Mr. Trask noted that HO was not involved in this
                    determination because HO is not responsible for either declassification or
                    transfer of records to Archives. He noted finally that the decision to conduct
                    re-review had been taken and confirmed at the highest levels of the Department,
                    including Mr. Newsom, by virtue of his activities in connection with appeals of
                    certain negative re-review decisions.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber then said that two things bothered him about the existence of the new
                    declassification system in the Department. First, why are there no historians on
                    the CDC staff? Second, does not the new system amount to bureaucratic layering,
                    since the bureaus seem to have the final say on what is declassified in any
                    case? Mr. Trask replied that, with regard to the first question, HO had no say
                    on how the CDC would be staffed. Mr. Slany added that there would exist a
                    conflict of interest if historians from HO were made part of the CDC. Mr.
                    LaFeber indicated that he did not mean to imply that the historians would have
                    to come from HO. He went on to say, with regard to his second point, that the
                    Office had better luck obtaining declassification decisions when it dealt
                    directly with the desk officers than it now does in dealing with the CDC as an
                    intermediary.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner asked if the only mechanism for appealing negative decisions was to
                    appeal directly to Mr. Newsom. Mr. Trask replied that it was not. In fact, three
                    levels of appeal existed: (1) the CDC; (2) the assistant secretaries concerned;
                    and (3) Mr. Newsom.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber pursued the point by inquiring whether the decisions taken by the CDC
                    and through the appeals mechanism would have the effect of setting precedents
                    for the 1955 and later records. He went on to say that he feared the guidelines
                    derived from re-review would set in concrete the same denial principles for all
                    later periods. Mr. Trask replied that he was not prepared to go into specifics,
                    but was able to say that HO appealed as a matter of principle all deletions
                    deemed to be in error that would have a precedent-setting effect.</p>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <p>Mr. Gardner then asked if Mr. Trask could quantify the results of re-review in
                    comparison with the actions that the bureaus and desks had taken earlier. Mr.
                    Trask said that he could not because it was too early in the process to tell.
                    Mr. Gardner replied that someone in the State Department was able to do so,
                    because that person had responded to a letter he had written to Senator McGovern
                    by asserting that somewhat less than 1% of the records would be withheld by the
                    CDC. He stated that his original information to the effect that 20% of all
                    materials was being withheld by the CDC had been reconfirmed by his sources. Mr.
                    Trask replied that Mr. Gardner had probably received a grossly inflated
                    estimate, based on our experiences so far with the CDC. Mr. Gardner then
                    suggested a modification of the claim that 20% of the documents might be
                    withheld, and asked whether HO would agree to it: Is it possible that 20% of a
                    given compilation, such as, hypothetically, the Saudi Arabia compilation, might
                    be withheld and would such action effectively cut out the heart of the
                    compilation? Mr. Trask responded that this was hypothetically possible but that
                    we had not received any indication that such a thing had in fact happened. Mr.
                    Slany said that the same thing could happen if even only 1% of a given
                    compilation was withheld.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked if everything had been declassified for the 1950-54 period
                    before re-review occurred. Mr. Baehler replied that this was by no means the
                    case, although it is true that virtually everything had been through the
                    clearance prior to the inception of re-review.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner then returned to the issue of whether the results of re-review would
                    have the effect of setting a bad precedent. He claimed that re-review was
                    initiated on the premise that more would be withheld from publication than would
                    have occurred under the first review. He asked whether he could quote Mr. Trask
                    to that effect. Mr. Trask replied that he could not because it is too early from
                    the standpoint of CDC returns to tell how much would be withheld. Mr. Slany
                    noted that the process is at this point one of constant give and take and that
                    there have been probably forty meetings between representatives of CDC and HO to
                    work out understandings on withholding documents.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked what role HO had on elaborating the general guide- lines that
                    would be used at Archives for systematic review. Mr. Trask replied that HO’s
                    only role was advisory. Responding to Mr. LaFeber’s view that the general
                    guidelines would permit such restrictiveness in Archives review as to render
                    nugatory the intent of the Executive Order, Mr. Trask said that these guidelines
                    established sensitivity as the only criterion for withholding material under
                    systematic review. He pointed specifically to the foreign government information
                    provision in the guidelines: These provide that such material in US documents
                    over 20 years old should be released unless it remains sensitive. HO in the<pb
                        n="4"/> course of the re-review process is insisting that sensitivity is the
                    sole criterion for withholding material from the FR series.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany noted that in view of the fact that we have no basis on which to judge
                    the substantive results of re-review the sole visible effect of re-review at
                    this point is that it occasions considerable delay in the publication of
                    volumes. Heretofore, only one volume of the twenty undergoing re-review has run
                    its full course and is at GPO for printing. HO had expected that by this time
                    several more would be at that stage.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner said that he had a suggestion to make regarding a way to get around
                    the problems that CDC was presenting for the FR series. In view of the series’
                    mandate to present a comprehensive account of the history of American foreign
                    relations, he thought that the best means of resolving any issues presented by
                    re-review would <add>be</add> simply withholding from publication any volume
                    that proved to be less than complete on any important issue. He would recommend
                    such a course of action if, for example, 10-20% of the Saudi Arabia compilation
                    were denied in the declassification process. Mr. Trask assured him that if
                    important coverages were omitted as a result of declassification action, HO’s
                    policy would in fact be to withhold the volume. Mr. Gardner asked whether HO was
                    planning to remove documents in order to publish the volumes. Mr. Trask replied
                    that there were various expedients for dealing with this problem ranging from
                    simply removing documents if they were not important through substituting other
                    documents for the deleted material to withholding the volume from publication
                    until the documents were declassified.</p>
                <p>Mr. Slany replied to Mr. Gardner’s affirmation of comprehensiveness as the prime
                    criterion guiding the FR series by pointing out that HO’s lack of access to
                    other agencies’ files compromised this principle, quite apart from unfavorable
                    declassification actions. He said that access was the other half of the
                    declassification coin. Mr. Gardner said that he recognized this.</p>
                <p>Mr. LaFeber asked what triggered the change in the declassification system. Was
                    it complaints from foreign governments, he asked? Mr. Trask replied that this
                    was a more appropriate question for the CDC, but that he was not aware of any
                    foreign government complaints regarding publication of documents in the FR
                    series. Mr. LaFeber continued that if the change was not induced by foreign
                    government complaints, then it must be internally generated. Mr. Trask replied
                    that the CDC came into existence as part of the Department’s response to the new
                    Executive Order on classification. He noted that there were concerns within the
                    Department regarding foreign government information and explicated once again
                    the manner in which such information is to be handled.</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>Mr. Gardner stated that the new Executive Order flagged foreign government
                    information contained in US documents and said that, even if the State
                    Department was handling it sensibly, other agencies seemed not to be doing so.
                    Pursuing the point, Mr. LaFeber referred to the 30 year foreign government
                    information guidelines that in his opinion would make it even harder for HO to
                    release the information that was previously routinely released under the old
                    Executive Order. Mr. Baehler noted that these 30 year foreign government
                    information guidelines do not apply to the work done by HO because HO requests
                    declassification earlier and under special procedures to which the systematic
                    review of 30 year old information does not apply. Mr. LaFeber had not realized
                    this, but thought that the existence of restrictive guidelines for systematic
                    review at thirty years would make the release of material under other reviews
                    even more difficult prior to thirty years. Mr. Trask drew the distinction
                    between systematic review and the review that FR undergoes and said that
                    whatever provisions exist for systematic review do not affect review of FR. He
                    said that the presumption of the Executive Order and particularly of the
                    balancing test provision contained in it is that more material is going to be
                    released earlier.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner responded that in theory this made sense but in fact the Executive
                    Order has not resulted in the release of more material and that it would be
                    wrong to assume that the guidelines currently existing for systematic review
                    will not affect the amount of material that is released in FR. Mr. Trask replied
                    that he was unwilling to confirm the point of view expressed by Mr. Gardner.</p>
                <p>In closing, Mr. Trask emphasized that HO itself did not undertake
                    declassification or transfer of records and that the representatives should talk
                    with CDC and FAIM to get a first-hand account of their actions and the reasons
                    for them. Mr. Gardner assured Mr. Trask that they intended to do so. Mr. Gardner
                    indicated that the committee needed certain information from HO and that this
                    was the reason for the present discussion. As an afterthought, Mr. LaFeber
                    having left the room, Mr. Gardner asked how many volumes have been through
                    re-review. Mr. Baehler replied that there are several stages in the process,
                    but, as indicated earlier, one volume had run the full cycle. Five other volumes
                    were in the appeals stage, which meant that the CDC was effectively finished
                    with its review work. The remaining 14 volumes were nearing completion. Mr.
                    Trask suggested that Mr. Gardner talk with the CDC, which would give him a
                    different version of how much has been completed. Mr. Gardner also asked how
                    long it would take to complete the appeals. Mr. Trask replied that he did not
                    know because it depends on how expeditiously the CDC submits the results and how
                    acceptable those results are. Mr. Slany interjected that the CDC is seeking ways
                    to <pb n="6"/>minimize the delay occasioned by the re-review in the area of
                    technical production of the volumes. It remains to be seen how successful these
                    efforts will be.</p>
                <p>Mr. Gardner closed by reiterating his concern that HO not sacrifice the
                    comprehensiveness of the series in the effort to attain the twenty year line.
                    Mr. Trask replied that HO desired both to maintain -- indeed to enhance -- the
                    comprehensiveness of the volumes and to attain the twenty year line. He thought
                    that in the long run the existence of the CDC would abet reaching the latter
                    goal.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
