<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">A Good Year’s Work</title>
                <title type="short">A Good Year’s Work</title>
                <author>William B. McAllister</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2012-02-08">February 8, 2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>As you can see from our <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history"><hi
                            rend="italic">FRUS</hi> sesquicentennial page</ref>, we have had a busy
                    year, producing online postings, podcasts, articles, conferences, presentations
                    at academic sessions, and public addresses. We invite you to peruse our
                    discoveries and conclusions about the history of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>)
                    series.</p>
                <p>We have a new understanding about the evolution and uses of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> in the 19th century. Periodic executive branch releases to
                    congress predated the advent of formal <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes by
                    several decades, based on a longstanding mutual agreement that certain documents
                    could be withheld if the executive believed it necessary to protect national
                    security. We now know that in addition to the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes that began regular publication in 1861, the State Department submitted
                    to congress additional records that doubled the total number of documents
                    released. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes also played an important role in
                    Department operations, serving as an “active file” of important issues and as a
                    policy guide to U.S. diplomats. And we now know that highly-experienced
                    Department staff compiled the volumes with care, expertise, and rational
                    selection criteria.</p>
                <p>In the twentieth century the release of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes
                    presented increasingly thorny declassification problems. As America’s role on
                    the world stage became more prominent, calculations about what information was
                    safe to release changed dramatically. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> became, and
                    remains, a crucial declassification outlet for government documents. On several
                    occasions, we have discovered, the continued existence of the series was in
                    jeopardy. But in every instance <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> not only survived,
                    but also often emerged with a renewed mandate to disseminate vital foreign
                    policy information to elected officials and the public. In a few cases those
                    revelations caused some short-term consternation among diplomats, policy makers,
                    or allies. Overall, however, sharing key documents about how past decisions were
                    made and implemented has not only proved illuminating for politicians and the
                    public, but also exemplified how Americans value governmental transparency.</p>
                <p>We now see that the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                    series represents an important negotiation vehicle through which to debate the
                    balance between the need to know and the need to protect. <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> acknowledges United States foreign policy decisions to Americans
                    and the world, formally and officially. What secrets should the U.S. government
                    keep from its own citizens, and for how long? How does a democracy function in
                    an information-restricted environment? There are no permanent answers to those
                    questions—they must be reconsidered regularly in light of current circumstances
                    and the longstanding desire for Americans to have the most open government
                    possible. We may never be fully satisfied with the answers, but constantly
                    reconsidering such questions is vital, and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> plays a
                    crucial part in that national conversation.</p>
                <p>Most importantly, we have learned that both specialists and the general public
                    are interested in the issues raised by our in-depth study of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. Although our “official” commemorations of the 150th birthday of
                    the series end with the <ref
                        target="/conferences/2012-national-security-policy-salt">Williams College
                        conference</ref> in March 2012, we intend to continue our investigations and
                    share our findings with you. Specifically, we are writing a book-length
                    manuscript encompassing not only the last 150 years, but also the significant
                    pre-1861 story of Americans’ debate about the value, and values, of openness.
                    When the research, writing, editing, and peer review is complete, we will
                    publish a book of interest to both academics and a wider audience. We are also
                    compiling substantial appendices to the book that will list the hundreds of
                    releases of documents to congress in addition formal <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes, totaling thousands of pages in the 19th century. We believe a fuller
                    accounting of the formal communications between the executive and legislative
                    branches concerning foreign policy will enrich the work of those interested in a
                    variety of topics. Finally, we intend to make presentations across the country
                    about our findings and advance the conversation about the significance they hold
                    for issues confronting Americans in the 21st century. We will use this website
                    to provide updates, so watch this space for announcements about our future
                    activities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
