<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Amateurs Need Not Apply</title>
                <title type="short">Amateurs Need Not Apply</title>
                <author>Peter Cozzens</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-11-22">November 22, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In researching the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi>) series of the Gilded Age (1869-1897), I was particularly struck with
                    the high level of attention it received in the State Department. Unlike the
                    series today, which is prepared by professional historians in an office well
                    removed from the regional and functional bureaus, the nineteenth century <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> reflected the combined efforts of the key officers of
                    the Department.  The fact that the documents published in <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi> were contemporaneous and often reflected both the direction of
                    American foreign policy and Department actions on most of the key issues of the
                    day made such scrutiny imperative. With Congress as the intended consumer of <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, the last thing the Department needed was to submit
                    correspondence assembled randomly or without a nuanced understanding of
                    policy.</p>
                <p>The Second Assistant Secretary of State (the equivalent of today’s Under
                    Secretary for Political Affairs) supervised the annual <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi> volumes and reviewed every document in them. The Second Assistant
                    Secretary was both the supervisor of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    and the principal policy advisor to the Secretary of State, making him uniquely
                    qualified to determine the contents of the series. First Assistant Secretaries
                    of State were political appointees. They came and went every year or two and
                    never served beyond the term of the president. But from 1866 to 1924 there were
                    only two second assistant secretaries: <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/hunter-william">William Hunter</ref>
                    (1866-1886) and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adee-alvey-augustus"
                    >Alvey A. Adee</ref> (1886-1924).</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="adee-alvey-a.png"/>
                    <head>Alvey A. Adee, Second Assistant Secretary of State, 1886-1924 (Photo
                        credit Library of Congress)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As career officials of outstanding ability who enjoyed the confidence of
                    secretaries of state of both parties, Hunter and Adee brought to <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> highly professional and nonpartisan oversight and an
                    important element of continuity. William Hunter entered the Department of State
                    in 1829 and spent fifty-seven years there under twenty-one Secretaries of State.
                    He was so valuable to the Department that in 1866 the office of Second Assistant
                    Secretary was created especially for him, to be held by Hunter until his death.
                    Hunter was “the original draftsmen of many of the most important papers of the
                    Secretary of State,” recalled <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/moore-john-bassett">John Bassett Moore</ref>,
                    Third Assistant Secretary of State (the fourth ranking position in the
                    Department) in the late 1880s and Acting Secretary during part of the Spanish-American
                    War.</p>
                <p>During his thirty-eight year tenure, Adee played the same role as Hunter. Like
                    Hunter, he had a phenomenal memory. A stickler for correct style and usage, Adee
                    drafted most outgoing instructions for the Secretary of State’s signature.<note
                    n="1">John Bassett Moore Memoirs, 43-48, Container 217, J. C. Bancroft Davis
                    Papers, Library of Congress; Katharine Crane, <hi rend="italic">Mr. Carr of
                    State: Forty-Seven Years of in the Department of State</hi> (New York: St.
                    Martin’s Press, 1960), 39-47ff; Peter Bridge, “An Appreciation of Alvey A.
                    Adee,” <ref
                    target="http://www.unc.edu/depts/diplomat/archives_roll/2001_10-12/bridges_adee/bridges_adee.html"
                    >http://www.unc.edu/depts/diplomat/archives_roll/2001_10-12/bridges_adee/bridges_adee.html</ref>;
                    Peter Bridge, “Some Man Named Hunter,” <ref
                    target="http://www.unc.edu/depts/diplomat/item/2005/1012/brid/bridges_hunter.html"
                    >http://www.unc.edu/depts/diplomat/item/2005/1012/brid/bridges_hunter.html</ref></note></p>
                <p>The task of selecting and compiling correspondence for <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi> from among the 3,000 or more incoming despatches or outgoing letters
                    of instruction that the Secretary of State and U.S. ministers generated
                    annually fell to the six to ten clerks of the Diplomatic Bureau. Clerks were not
                    menials. Rather, they were the career officials with keen substantive knowledge
                    who were assigned geographical portfolios. Diplomatic Bureau clerks drafted
                    responses to incoming despatches on behalf of Department principals, and they
                    also submitted reports to them on issues of importance. They were the equivalent
                    of today’s country desk officers. The Diplomatic Bureau director or one of the
                    three division chiefs reviewed <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> page
                    proofs before they went to Hunter or Adee.</p>
                <p>It truly can be said that Hunter, Adee, and the Diplomatic Bureau staff who
                    worked on the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series under their
                    supervision, were among the world’s first professional documentary editors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
