<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">An Outburst of Pamphlets: Public Debate about <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> during the Civil War</title>
                <title type="short">An Outburst of Pamphlets</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-12-05">December 5, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus">a
                        research paper</ref> posted to this site on June 24, 2011, I wrote about the
                    domestic reaction to the first <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) volume [<ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-first-volume"
                        >text</ref> and <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/marrs-on-the-first-volume"
                        >video</ref>] published in 1861. That paper focused primarily on the
                    positive reaction of Northern newspapers. Tracking coverage of the first <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume in the press allows us to see how <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was received throughout the Union. Historians have
                    other options for learning about public reaction. In 1863, a brief flurry of
                    pamphlets sprung up after the publication of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volume covering 1862. In these pamphlets, we can see contemporaries debate the
                    propriety of publishing state papers.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="1862-northern-man-cover.png"/>
                    <head>Cover of <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Year: Being a Review of Mr.
                            Seward’s Foreign Correspondence of 1862</hi> (Photo credit Google
                        Books)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The first to take on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in that year gave himself the
                    pen name “A Northern Man” (although one of his opponents revealed his identity,
                    as we’ll see below). His pamphlet was entitled <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic
                        Year: Being a Review of Mr. Seward’s Foreign Correspondence of
                        1862</hi>.<note n="1"><ref
                            target="http://books.google.com/books?id=5VYMAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=The%20Diplomatic%20Year%3A%20Being%20a%20Review%20of%20Mr.%20Seward%E2%80%99s%20Foreign%20Correspondence%20of%201862&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                            >A Northern Man, <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Year: Being a Review
                                of Mr. Seward’s Foreign Correspondence of 1862</hi></ref>
                        (Philadelphia: n.p., 1863).</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Year</hi> had many targets, from President
                    Abraham Lincoln and Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William Henry
                        Seward</ref> to the very concept of publishing diplomatic
                    correspondence.</p>
                <p>The anonymous author argued that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was the result of
                    mere political intrigue. In 1862, Samuel Sullivan Cox (D-Ohio) submitted a call
                    for the release of documents. A Northern Man charged that, though Cox was a
                    Democrat, he was “closer in affinities to the Secretary than some of his party
                    friends, or certainly than the Chairman of the Senate Committee.” Thus, A
                    Northern Man averred, such a resolution never would have been offered up unless
                    there had been a “prompting” by or “concurrence of” the Department of State; the
                    request for the documentation did not truly stem from Congress.<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Year</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://books.google.com/books?id=5VYMAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=The%20Diplomatic%20Year%3A%20Being%20a%20Review%20of%20Mr.%20Seward%E2%80%99s%20Foreign%20Correspondence%20of%201862&amp;pg=PA12#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                            >12-13</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A Northern Man also denounced the contents of the published volume. Seward’s
                    writing was blasted as lacking a “dignity of style,” as being “pretentious,”
                    “stilted,” and “obscure.” A Northern Man was deeply disturbed that the volume
                    contained “Mr. Adams’s private movements and conversations in relation to the
                    French operations in Mexico, and his exultation at the disappointments which
                    seemed to attend them.”&#160; He stated that a series of documents relating to
                    the Spanish and French “ought not, unless offence was intended or foreign war
                    desired—to have been authoritatively published.”<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Diplomatic Year</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://books.google.com/books?id=5VYMAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=The%20Diplomatic%20Year%3A%20Being%20a%20Review%20of%20Mr.%20Seward%E2%80%99s%20Foreign%20Correspondence%20of%201862&amp;pg=PA22#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                            >22</ref>.</note> These and other revelations, feared A Northern Man,
                    would cause “irreparable” harm.<note n="4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic Year</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://books.google.com/books?id=5VYMAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=The%20Diplomatic%20Year%3A%20Being%20a%20Review%20of%20Mr.%20Seward%E2%80%99s%20Foreign%20Correspondence%20of%201862&amp;pg=PA27#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                            >27</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A Northern Man’s screed prompted at least two equally anonymous responses. One,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">A Diplomat on Diplomacy</hi>, castigated A Northern
                    Man’s writing as “ponderous” and scoffed that the pamphlet has “not attracted
                    attention adequate to the industry with which it has been circulated.”<note
                        n="5">
                        <hi rend="italic">A Diplomat on Diplomacy</hi> (n.p.: n.d.), 1. The Library
                        of Congress catalog lists the author of this pamphlet as <ref
                            target="http://lccn.loc.gov/44028315">Joseph Nunes</ref>.</note> The
                    author outed A Northern Man as “the late distinguished Commissioner to the most
                    imperial court of China.” Based on this description, it can be surmised that A
                    Northern Man was <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/reed-william-bradford"
                        >William Bradford Reed</ref>, President James Buchanan’s representative to
                    China. Reed’s anonymous opponent had little use for the complaints that Reed
                    made about publication, noting that “even in China,” Reed should have learned
                    that “the publication of a diplomatic correspondence may be highly improper at
                    one period of time, and eminently proper at another.”<note n="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Diplomat on Diplomacy</hi>, 2.</note> In sum, this author
                    believed that the Secretary of State and President could be trusted to determine
                    if the publication of confidential documents would serve national interests
                    rather than jeopardize them.</p>
                <p>The other response was the pseudonymous Dr. Syntax, Jr.’s <hi rend="italic">A New
                        “Sartor Resartus,” Being a Critical Analysis of a Pamphlet Entitled “A
                        Review of Mr. Seward’s Diplomacy.”</hi>
                    <note n="7">
                        <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/loc.ark:/13960/t6252dn8w"><hi
                                rend="italic">A New “Sartor Resartus,” Being a Critical Analysis of
                                a Pamphlet Entitled “A Review of Mr. Seward’s Diplomacy”</hi></ref>
                        (n.p.: n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Sartor Resartus</hi> is a satirical work by
                        Thomas Carlyle; the title means “the tailor re-tailored.” The Library of
                        Congress gives the author of <ref target="http://lccn.loc.gov/01013021"><hi
                                rend="italic">A New “Sartor Resartus”</hi></ref> as S.
                        Kimber.</note> Dr. Syntax presumably published his pamphlet after <hi
                        rend="italic">A Diplomat on Diplomacy</hi>, for he noted that <hi
                        rend="italic">The Diplomatic Year</hi> “has already been reviewed, and that
                    not in the kindest spirit.” Dr. Syntax agreed that the author was Reed, noting
                    that the pamphlet was “universally attributed to a prominent member of the
                    Philadelphia Bar; who was charged with an important foreign mission, under the
                    late Administration, and who has ever since been supposed to enjoy the especial
                    confidence of its Chief.”<note n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">A New “Sartor Resartus,”</hi>&#0160;<ref
                            target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/loc.ark:/13960/t6252dn8w?urlappend=%3Bseq=7"
                            >3</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is not clear if the implication should be that Buchanan himself approved of
                    the pamphlet, or merely that such a connection afforded Reed’s opinions more
                    respect than he might otherwise deserve. Dr. Syntax spent most of his pamphlet
                    on, as his name suggests, Reed’s language, picking apart his grammatical errors.
                    Dr. Syntax felt that the political opinions expressed in <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> needed no defense since they were lauded elsewhere.<note n="9">
                        <hi rend="italic">A New “Sartor Resartus,”</hi>&#0160;<ref
                            target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/loc.ark:/13960/t6252dn8w?urlappend=%3Bseq=8"
                            >4</ref>.</note> The author noted that the United States was hardly
                    alone in publishing correspondence.<note n="10">
                        <hi rend="italic">A New “Sartor Resartus,”</hi>&#0160;<ref
                            target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/loc.ark:/13960/t6252dn8w?urlappend=%3Bseq=20"
                            >16-17</ref>.</note> Britain produced its Blue Book of diplomatic
                    correspondence, as Dr. Syntax reminded his audience, and under the Buchanan
                    administration a “ponderous volume of Chinese dispatches was published;
                    unveiling many delicate secrets.” Dr. Syntax concluded, much as the anonymous
                    author of <hi rend="italic">A Diplomat on Diplomacy</hi> did, by arguing that it
                    was the role of “principals,” be they a merchant instructing a clerk or the
                    Secretary of State instructing a diplomat, to decide when interests “confided to
                    these servants, will be best promoted by a publication of the previously
                    confidential instructions under which they had acted.” He felt it was
                    “sophistry” to argue that once “subordinate agents” were under an “injunction of
                    secrecy” that those in charge of foreign affairs could never expose this
                        information.<note n="11">
                        <hi rend="italic"> A New “Sartor Resartus,”</hi>&#0160;<ref
                            target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/loc.ark:/13960/t6252dn8w?urlappend=%3Bseq=21"
                            >17, 18</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>What should we make over this outburst of pamphleteering in 1863? Reed’s
                    motivations remain a mystery, although his Democratic politics may help explain
                    part of his opposition to the Lincoln administration. Beyond partisan politics,
                    his objections were that publication of documentation would harm U.S. interests
                    abroad. As I explained <ref target="/research/constitutional-basis-of-frus">in
                        another post</ref>, Charles Francis Adams had similar concerns—which Seward
                    dismissed. These pamphlets demonstrate that a similar debate played out in
                    public, not just inside the government. Reed’s two opponents show us the other
                    side of the debate: they pointed out that publication of documentation was
                    routine and that the prerogative of releasing documents rightfully rested with
                    the leaders of the government, not those who wrote the documents. While
                    contemporary debates about the release over government documentation don’t
                    usually have the same personal tone that A Northern Man’s attacks did, it is
                    clear that issues such as striking a balance between openness and secrecy and
                    determining who has the right to release information have a long history in this
                    country.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
