<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> Series: An Orientation</title>
                <title type="short">The <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Series: An Orientation</title>
                <author>Edward Brynn</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-09-29">September 29, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                    <!-- Start of Brightcove Player -->
                    <div style="display:none"/>
                    <!--By use of this code snippet, I agree to the Brightcove Publisher T and C found at https://accounts.brightcove.com/en/terms-and-conditions/. -->
                    <script type="text/javascript"
                        src="http://admin.brightcove.com/js/BrightcoveExperiences.js"/>
                    <object id="myExperience1176174173001" class="BrightcoveExperience">
                        <param name="bgcolor" value="#FFFFFF"/>
                        <param name="width" value="486"/>
                        <param name="height" value="412"/>
                        <param name="playerID" value="642900215001"/>
                        <param name="playerKey"
                            value="AQ~~,AAAAAGWqYgE~,KxHPzbPALrGbr42hNpx45lOyQ1a-Nw88"/>
                        <param name="isVid" value="true"/>
                        <param name="dynamicStreaming" value="true"/>
                        <param name="@videoPlayer" value="1176174173001"/>
                    </object>
                    <!-- This script tag will cause the Brightcove Players defined above it to be created as soonas the line is read by the browser. If you wish to have the player instantiated only afterthe rest of the HTML is processed and the page load is complete, remove the line.-->
                    <script type="text/javascript">brightcove.createExperiences();</script>
                    <!-- End of Brightcove Player -->
                </div>
                <p rend="italic">A brief video with accompanying transcript of Ambassador Edward
                    Brynn speaking about the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> series—its history, evolution, and continuing significance.</p>
                <p>Hello, I am Edward Brynn, The Historian for the Department of State.</p>
                <p>The U.S. Government is committed to responsible transparency. As a U.S. diplomat
                    argued in 2002, after the Department of State released a collection of
                    historical documents in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> series that had been the subject of particularly contentious
                    clearance debates, “it may be the wisest course of action to be as open as
                    possible with the release of declassified, archival material.” He claimed that
                    doing so gave the United States the opportunity “to advertise, by example, the
                    openness of American political culture.” Over the past 150 years, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series—often
                    referred to as <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>—has exemplified both the durability
                    of the U.S. Government’s commitment to responsible transparency as well as the
                    evolving ways that this commitment has been met.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> celebrates <ref
                        target="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history">its
                        sesquicentennial anniversary</ref> in December 2011. Since the first <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume was published in December 1861, the U.S.
                    Department of State has released nearly 500 volumes of documents illuminating
                    the country’s diplomacy and its national security policies. These volumes have
                    changed rather significantly in that time. In 1861, it took 313 documents in a
                    420 page volume to illustrate <ref
                        target="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus"
                        >the Union’s diplomatic efforts to ensure that the Confederacy did not gain
                        international support during the Civil War</ref>. Today, the Office of the
                    Historian is approaching the end of its <ref
                        target="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/nixon-ford">efforts to
                        document the Nixon and Ford administrations’ foreign policies</ref>. The 40
                    volumes released thus far for the Nixon and Ford years contain 13,323 documents
                    in 46,708 pages—and there are still more than a dozen volumes remaining in the
                    pipeline! Clearly, the scope of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s task has grown
                    considerably in the years since the series began.</p>
                <p>In part, the expanded scope of recent <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes
                    reflects the much larger role that the United States plays in the world today
                    compared to 150 years ago. But it also reflects some fundamental changes in what
                    the series has been designed to do over time. In 1861, <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> was released to inform Congress of the Lincoln administration’s
                    efforts on a relatively narrow range of highly important priorities. In 1925,
                    Secretary of State Frank Kellogg ordered that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    provide comprehensive documentation on U.S. foreign relations from the State
                    Department files. In 1991, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> became, by law, “the
                    official documentary historical record of major foreign policy decisions and
                    significant diplomatic activity of the United States Government.”</p>
                <p>What exactly does this mean? It means that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> is the
                    primary way that the U.S. Government acknowledges its own past actions,
                    including its most sensitive historical covert operations. It means that
                    historians in the Department of State scour the historical records of all the
                    various parts of the U.S. Government that played a role in making or executing
                    foreign policy, including the National Security Council, the Department of
                    Defense, and intelligence agencies, so the series can provide the
                    legally-mandated “thorough, accurate, and reliable” documentation. This, in
                    turn, means that the Department of State must work with the rest of the
                    government to review all the selected documents for declassification. Sometimes,
                    this can take years as officials weigh the benefits of historical accountability
                    and promoting open government against whatever risks might still exist in
                    releasing highly classified documents.</p>
                <p>This balancing act between security and transparency has shaped the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series from the very beginning. Even during the
                    Civil War, the U.S. Government withheld information that could jeopardize its
                    efforts to preserve the Union. In the aftermath of the Civil War, U.S. diplomats
                    sometimes complained that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> made the U.S. Government
                    too transparent and their jobs more difficult. In the 1930s, the historians who
                    worked on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> debated clearances on documents concerning
                    Iran with their colleagues within the Department of State. They also faced
                    opposition from the Japanese and French governments to releasing 15 year-old
                    documents that were not “dead,” diplomatically speaking. During World War II,
                    President Roosevelt and the British blocked the State Department’s efforts to
                    publish the records of the post-World War I Paris Peace Conference. Throughout
                    the Cold War, national security concerns posed challenges to <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. Indeed, in the 1980s, these concerns made it impossible for
                    Department of State historians to compile and declassify comprehensive volumes
                    covering the 1950s. When the Department released volumes on Guatemala and Iran
                    that omitted documentation about well-known covert operations, it faced
                    criticism from the media, the academic community, and from Congress that
                    ultimately led to the 1991 law that now defines the purpose and scope of the
                    series.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> serves an important role in providing a responsible
                    way of ensuring that the public, both inside and outside the United States, has
                    the information they need to make judgments about the past. As part of the
                    commemoration of the 150<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, the Office of the Historian is fulfilling this
                    ongoing commitment, not only with more <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes, but
                    also by engaging in a research and outreach initiative to explore the history of
                    the series and share that history with the public. I invite you to visit the
                    Office of the Historian’s website, <ref target="https://history.state.gov/"
                        >history.state.gov</ref>, to discover for yourself the rich trove of
                    historical records that are available in <ref
                        target="https://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/">the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series</ref> and to learn
                    more about what the history of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> can tell us about
                    important issues in America’s past.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
