<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">The Constitutional Basis of <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi></title>
                <title type="short">The Constitutional Basis of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi></title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-24">October 24, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In these blog posts, we have been sharing the fruits of our ongoing research into
                    the history of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                    series. As our investigation continues, our knowledge about the series grows and
                    evolves. In this post, I’ll discuss how new findings shed light on some
                    long-standing questions about the series.</p>
                <p>One of the frustrating aspects of researching Civil War-era <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> tomes is that documentation from the nineteenth century tells us
                    very little about the actual mechanics of how the volumes were assembled. We
                    don’t know much about how the documents were selected or who did the selecting
                    (although, in <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/those-asterisks">my
                        previous post</ref> I showed that we can learn something by looking at the
                    material left out of the volume). The philosophical impetus behind releasing
                    documentation has represented another gap in our knowledge. We’ve never known
                    how fully involved Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William Henry
                        Seward</ref> was in the creation of the series or what purpose he believed
                    the series had (if any).</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="adams-charles-francis.jpg"/>
                    <head>Charles Francis Adams, Minister to the United Kingdom</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Recent sleuthing at the National Archives has uncovered more of the story,
                    illuminating Seward’s ideas concerning the utility of releasing foreign
                    relations documentation. (Hearty thanks are due to Forrest Barnum for conducting
                    the original research and to David Langbart of the National Archives for
                    generously providing the images of the original document.) In 1864, Seward
                    defended the practice to his minister in London, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles Francis
                        Adams</ref>, and in so doing laid out some principles which undoubtedly
                    guided the compilation of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> during the war years.
                    Let’s take a look at the documents.</p>
                <p>On February 11, 1864, Adams complained to Seward about the publication of his
                    correspondence in a previous year’s edition of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> (see
                        <ref
                        target="http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?id=FRUS.FRUS1864p1"
                        >the full text of Adams’s despatch</ref>). Adams noted that “the publication
                    of the diplomatic papers … has elicited much comment in Parliament and in the
                    newspapers,” and attached a clipping from the <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>
                    (London) which described debates in the House of Lords and House of Commons.
                    Adams expressed his disappointment that “when you decided on publishing those
                    instructions, you did not at the same time” publish another despatch which would
                    have made his actions more understandable to the British. Because of the uneven
                    publication of the record, Adams contended, he was now perceived by the British
                    government to have “suppress[ed]” information back in 1863.</p>
                <p>Seward responded on March 2, 1864. His response was not published in <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, but can be found in manuscript form (see <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/seward-letter">here</ref>
                    for the transcript and PDF scan) at the <ref target="http://www.archives.gov/"
                        >National Archives</ref> in College Park, Maryland.<note n="1">Instruction
                        No. 859 from the Department of State, March 2, 1864, Instructions from the
                        Department of State, 2nd Series, volume XIV, Embassy Great Britain, RG 84,
                        National Archives. Thanks to Forrest Barnum for conducting this
                        research.</note> Seward quickly dispensed with Adams’s complaint,
                    particularly since Adams himself admitted in his despatch that no “particular
                    injury” had resulted from the publication of the documentation. Seward then
                    embarked on a lengthy defense of the publication of diplomatic correspondence.
                    Since this document constitutes what little evidence we have of the
                    administration’s intent, I think that it is worth quoting at some length here.
                    Here’s how Seward began his defense of the publication:</p>
                <q rend="blockquote">“The Constitution of the United States requires the President,
                    from time to time, to give to Congress information concerning the state of the
                    Union. In the beginning of our government a practice obtained according to which
                    the President communicated this information on the assembling of Congress in a
                    full and comprehensive annual speech or message, to which are appended all the
                    important reports and documents which have been placed by the Heads of
                    Departments before the President as the sources and evidences of the information
                    to be by him submitted to Congress. It is hardly necessary to say that the
                    interest of Congress and of the people of the United States in the transactions
                    of the Executive Department, always earnest, became intensified with the
                    breaking out of the civil war.”</q>
                <p>For Seward, then, informing Congress had a Constitutional basis. Seward was
                    referring to <ref
                        target="http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution_transcript.html"
                        >Article II, Section 3</ref>, which states that the President shall “from
                    time to time give to the Congress Information of the State of the Union.”
                    Clearly, Seward understood providing information to Congress to be a duty rather
                    than an option; that responsibility had only intensified during the Civil War.
                    Seward then noted that the President considered it to be “more satisfactory” to
                    fulfill this obligation “with all possible fullness at the beginning of each
                    meeting of Congress, rather than to await their special calls for it in
                    particular cases.” As I have noted elsewhere <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-first-volume">in this
                        article</ref> and <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/marrs-on-the-first-volume"
                        >video</ref>, Congress requested and received diplomatic documentation since
                    the earliest years of the republic. Now, however, Lincoln felt it was
                    appropriate to supply the information without waiting to be asked by
                    Congress.</p>
                <p>Seward noted that in a democracy, the people deserve to have information since
                    they are the source of the government’s power:</p>
                <q rend="blockquote">“The Government constantly depends on the support of Congress
                    and the People, and that support can be expected only on the condition of
                    keeping them thoroughly and truthfully informed of the manner in which the
                    powers derived from them are executed. Mutual confidence between the People and
                    the Government is a condition of our national life.”</q>
                <p>Seward then turned from an explanation of why materials could be excluded from
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> (and thus, why the materials Adams was worried
                    about should be included). Speaking again of Congress, Seward wrote:</p>
                <q rend="blockquote">“They had the same right to see my dispatch to you of the 11th
                    of July, 1863, that they had to see any other parts of the Executive
                    correspondence concerning foreign affairs. This history would be incomplete
                    without that document. It was the President’s duty to communicate it, unless
                    special reasons of a public nature existed for withholding it. Only two such
                    special reasons could be allowed, namely, one, that the publication would be
                    incompatible with the public interests by affecting a friendly negotiation on an
                    existing question. But the question which had called out the dispatch had been
                    for a time put at rest; and mutually satisfactory explanations between the two
                    Governments had been made. The other reason was that the publication might give
                    offence to Great Britain. But the document was a communication from this
                    Government not to Her Majesty’s Government, but to its own agent; and the paper
                    was believed to be as respectful to the British Government as it manifestly was
                    earnest and sincere. On the other hand, to withhold so important a portion of
                    the Executive correspondence would have seemed to imply a confession that it was
                    improper in itself, while to practice reserve on so great a question would be
                    liable to be deemed an abuse of the confidence which Congress and the people had
                    so freely reposed in the Government.”</q>
                <p>Here, Seward made clear that there were only two reasons for excluding material:
                    if it was affecting negotiations or would give offense to another power. In the
                    course of the entire response, Seward set out the complete case of why it was
                    important to release the documentation. The President had a Constitutional
                    obligation to communicate with Congress. The American people, through their
                    Congress, had the right to be informed since the power of the government was
                    derived from the people. There were very few reasons why documents deserved to
                    be excluded from publication. Indeed, the exclusion of documents could itself
                    raise questions about the reliability of the government.</p>
                <p>As we know from <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/those-asterisks">my past
                        post</ref>, material was sometimes excluded for what appeared to be very
                    different reasons (such as pointing out the embarrassment of Union defeat at
                    Bull Run). Nevertheless, Seward’s statement to Adams in 1864 presents a strong
                    case for what the administration believed it accomplished with the release of
                    these volumes. The need for transparency was explicitly linked to our form of
                    government and the obligations created by the Constitution which the Union was
                    fighting so hard to preserve.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Read <ref
                            target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/seward-letter">the
                            text of Seward's statement to Adams</ref>, or download the <ref
                            target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus150/seward-letter.pdf"
                            >PDF</ref>, 1 MB, 9 pp.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
