<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Sharing the Emancipation Proclamation with the World</title>
                <title type="short">Sharing the Emancipation Proclamation with the World</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2012-09-20">September 20, 2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="AWM" role="editor">
                        <persName>Aaron W. Marrs</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#AWM" when="2012-09-20">Drafted text.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Sharing the Emancipation Proclamation with the World</head>
                <p>This year, we celebrate the sesquicentennial of the <ref
                        target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/alhtml/almintr.html">Emancipation
                        Proclamation</ref>, first announced to the U.S. public on September 22,
                    1862. While the story of the Proclamation’s domestic impact is well known, there
                    was also a foreign dimension to this story.</p>
                <p>The idea of Emancipation had been gestating during the summer of 1862; Lincoln
                    drafted a preliminary proclamation in July. The timing for releasing the
                    proclamation to the general public, however, was not right until after the
                    Union’s successful repelling of Confederate forces at Antietam in September.</p>
                <p>The same day that the proclamation was released to the U.S. public, Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                        Seward</ref> released the text “to the diplomatic and consular officers of
                    the United States in foreign countries.”</p>
                <p>The 1862 edition of <title level="s">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</title> prints Seward’s note to Charles Francis Adams, the U.S.
                    Minister in London. We’ve reproduced his text below; you can also click <ref
                        target="http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=goto&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1862v01&amp;isize=M&amp;page=195"
                        >here</ref> to see the version as it was originally published. Similar texts
                    were sent to other representatives abroad. Seward had <ref
                        target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/12/01/lincolns-p-r-coup/"
                        >long identified slavery</ref> as the cause of the war in his correspondence
                    with U.S. diplomats. Lincoln’s proclamation gave him the opportunity to tell our
                    diplomatic representatives that “it is the Union, and not slavery that must be
                    maintained and preserved.”</p>
                <p>Adams wrote back on October 10, 1862, and noted that the effect of the
                    proclamation was “to draw the line with greater distinctness between those
                    persons really friendly to the United States and the remainder of the community,
                    and to test the extent of the genuine anti-slavery feeling left in this
                    country.” The Proclamation’s intent and effect was immediately apparent, and
                        <title level="s">FRUS</title> gives us a glimpse into how the rest of the
                    world was informed of this landmark act.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Department of State Circular</head>
                <p>Mr. Seward to Mr. Adams.</p>
                <p>[Circular.]</p>
                <p>DEPARTMENT OF STATE,</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Washington, September</hi> 22, 1862.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">To the diplomatic and consular officers of the United States in
                        foreign countries:</hi></p>
                <p>GENTLEMEN: You will receive by the post which conveys this despatch evidences
                    that the aggressive movement of the insurgents against the loyal States is
                    arrested, and that the renewed and reinvigorated forces of the Union are again
                    prepared for a new and comprehensive campaign. If you consult the public
                    journals you will easily learn that the financial strength of the insurrection
                    is rapidly declining, and that its ability to bring soldiers into the field has
                    been already taxed to its utmost. You will perceive, on the other hand, that the
                    fiscal condition of the country is sound, and that the response to the calls for
                    new levies is being made promptly, without drawing seriously upon the physical
                    strength of the people.</p>
                <p>I have heretofore indicated to our representatives abroad the approach of a
                    change in the organization of society in the insurrectionary States. That change
                    continues to reveal itself more distinctly every day. In the judgment of the
                    President the time has come for setting forth the great fact distinctly for the
                    serious consideration of the people in those States, and for giving them to
                    understand that if they will persist in forcing upon the country a choice
                    between the dissolution of this necessary and beneficent government or a
                    relinquishment of the protection of slavery, it is the Union, and not slavery,
                    that must be maintained and preserved. With this view the President has issued a
                    proclamation in which he gives notice that slavery will be no longer recognized
                    in any State which shall be found in armed rebellion on the first of January
                    next. While good and wise men of all nations will confess that this is just and
                    proper as a military proceeding for the relief of the country from a desolating
                    and exhausting civil war, they will at the same time acknowledge the moderation
                    and magnanimity with which the government proceeds in a transaction of such
                    great solemnity and importance.</p>
                <p>I am, gentlemen, your obedient servant,</p>
                <p>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">By the President of the United States of America.</hi></p>
                <p>A PROCLAMATION.</p>
                <p>I, Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States of America, and
                    commander-in-chief of the army and navy thereof, do hereby proclaim and declare
                    that hereafter, as heretofore, the war will be prosecuted for the object of
                    practically restoring the constitutional relation between the United States and
                    each of the States and the people thereof, in which States that relation is or
                    may be suspended or disturbed.</p>
                <p>That it is my purpose, upon the next meeting of Congress, to again recommend the
                    adoption of a practical measure tendering pecuniary aid to the free acceptance
                    or rejection of all slave States, so called, the people whereof may not then be
                    in rebellion against the United States, and which States may then have
                    voluntarily adopted, or thereafter may voluntarily adopt, immediate or gradual
                    abolishment of slavery within their respective limits; and that the effort to
                    colonize persons of African descent with their consent upon this continent or
                    elsewhere, with the previously obtained consent of the governments existing
                    there, will be continued.</p>
                <p>That on the first day of January, in the year of our Lord one thousand eight
                    hundred and sixty-three, all persons held as slaves within any State or
                    designated part of a State, the people whereof shall then be in rebellion
                    against the United States, shall be then, thenceforward, and forever free; and
                    the executive government of the United States, including the military and naval
                    authority thereof, will recognize and maintain the freedom of such persons, and
                    will do no act or acts to repress such persons, or any of them, in any efforts
                    they may make for their actual freedom.</p>
                <p>That the Executive will, on the first day of January aforesaid, by proclamation,
                    designate the States and parts of States, if any, in which the people thereof,
                    respectively, shall then be in rebellion against the United States; and the fact
                    that any State; or the people thereof, shall on that day be, in good faith,
                    represented in the Congress of the United States by members chosen thereto at
                    elections wherein a majority of the qualified voters of such State shall have
                    participated, shall, in the absence of strong countervailing testimony, be
                    deemed conclusive evidence that such State, and the people thereof, are not then
                    in rebellion against the United States.</p>
                <p>That attention is hereby called to an act of Congress entitled “An act to make an
                    additional article of war,” approved March 13, 1862, and which act is in the
                    words and figure following:</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of
                        the United States of America in Congress assembled</hi>, That hereafter the
                    following shall be promulgated as an additional article of war for the
                    government of the army of the United States, and shall be obeyed and observed as
                    such:</p>
                <p>“ARTICLE-. All officers or persons in the military or naval service of the United
                    States are prohibited from employing any of the forces under their respective
                    commands for the purpose of returning fugitives from service or labor who may
                    have escaped from any persons to whom such service or labor is claimed to be
                    due, and any officer who shall be found guilty by a court-martial of violating
                    this article shall be dismissed from the service.”</p>
                <p>“SEC. 2. <hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>, That this act shall
                    take effect from and after its passage.”</p>
                <p>Also to the ninth and tenth sections of an act entitled “An act to suppress
                    insurrection, to punish treason and rebellion, to seize and confiscate property
                    of rebels, and for other purposes,” approved July 17, 1862, and which sections
                    are in the words and figures following:</p>
                <p>“SEC. 9. <hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>, That all slaves of
                    persons who shall hereafter be engaged in rebellion against the government of
                    the United States, or who shall in any way give aid or comfort thereto, escaping
                    from such persons and taking refuge within the lines of the army; and all slaves
                    captured from such persons or deserted by them, and coming under the control of
                    the government of the United States; and all slaves of such persons found <hi
                        rend="italic">on</hi> [or] being within any place occupied by rebel forces
                    and afterwards occupied by the forces of the United States, shall be deemed
                    captives of war, and shall be forever free of their servitude, and not again
                    held as slaves.</p>
                <p>“SEC. 10. <hi rend="italic">And be it further enacted</hi>, That no slave
                    escaping into any State, Territory, or the District of Columbia, from any other
                    State, shall be delivered up, or in any way impeded or hindered of his liberty,
                    except for crime, or some offence against the laws, unless the person claiming
                    said fugitive shall first make oath that the person to whom the labor or service
                    of such fugitive is alleged to be due is his lawful owner, and has not borne
                    arms against the United States in the present rebellion, nor in any way given
                    aid and comfort thereto; and no person engaged in the military or naval service
                    of the United States shall, under any pretence whatever, assume to decide on the
                    validity of the claim of any person to the service or labor of any other person,
                    or surrender up any such person to the claimant, on pain of being dismissed from
                    the service.”</p>
                <p>And I do hereby enjoin upon and order all persons engaged in the military and
                    naval service of the United States to observe, obey, and enforce, within their
                    respective spheres of service, the act and sections above recited.</p>
                <p>And the Executive will in due time recommend that all citizens of the United
                    States who shall have remained loyal thereto throughout the rebellion shall
                    (upon the restoration of the constitutional relation between the United States
                    and their respective States and people, if that relation shall have been
                    suspended or disturbed) be compensated for all losses by acts of the United
                    States, including the loss of slaves.</p>
                <p>In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand, and caused the seal of the
                    United States to be affixed. Done at the city of Washington this twenty-second
                    day of September, in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
                    sixty-two, and of the Independence of the United States the eighty-seventh.</p>
                <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN</p>
                <p>By the President:</p>
                <p>WLLLIAM H. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
