<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Eureka!: The 1925 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Order (and Why
                    You Should Be Nice to Archivists)</title>
                <title type="short">The 1925 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Order</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-27">October 27, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>One of the most frustrating experiences for a historian occurs when you know that
                    something happened but you can’t find contemporary sources to shed light on how
                    it happened, or why it happened the way that it did. For the <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi> sesquicentennial project, the Departmental Order of March 26, 1925,
                    which for the first time explicitly defined principles for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Foreign Relations</hi> series, has been a source of exactly this kind of angst.
                    After hours of digging through the Department of State’s central files for the
                    period 1910-1929 in search of the Order – which had been reprinted in a 1928 <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume<note n="1"><ref
                    target="http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1914Supp.p0007&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1914Supp&amp;isize=M"
                    ><hi rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United
                    States, 1914 Supplement: The World War</hi> (Washington, DC: Government Printing
                    Office, 1928), pp. iii-iv</ref>.</note> and referenced repeatedly as an
                    important milestone for the series – the best I could come up with was a 45-page
                    memorandum written in 1937 that summarized its origins to refute criticism of
                    later <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes.<note n="2">Cyril Wynne, “Memorandum
                    on the subject of Dr. D. C. Poole’s letter of June 21, 1937, which includes a
                    statement giving the background of the present system of preparing the Foreign
                    Relations volumes,” July 13, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1210, Department of
                    State Central Decimal File, 1930-1939, Record Group 59 (henceforth RG 59),
                    Archives II, College Park, MD (henceforth Archives II), pp. 4-22.</note> While
                    the 1937 memo provided a great deal of interesting information about the Order
                    and the major players in its creation, it was a poor substitute for primary
                    source documentation from 1925 embodying contemporary, rather than
                    retrospective, accounts of the effort to formalize the principles behind the <hi
                    rend="italic">Foreign Relations </hi> series.</p>
                <p>Luckily for me and the rest of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> sesquicentennial
                    research team, the person who is probably more familiar with the archived
                    records of the Department of State than anyone else in the world was also
                    determined to track down the 1925 Departmental Order. David Langbart is an
                    archivist at the National Archives and Records Administration. In the past, he
                    was responsible for assessing the historic value of Department of State records
                    (and those of other agencies) to ensure that significant archival materials are
                    preserved; he now has responsibilities for describing those records and
                    providing assistance to researchers interested in using them. For many years,
                    the Office of the Historian has worked closely with Langbart to conduct research
                    in recently-retired Department of State files for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    compilation. As we began looking more systematically at the history of <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> this year, we quickly discovered that he already knew
                    where a lot of the skeletons were buried (so to speak). Well before we began
                    investigating the history of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, Langbart’s success in
                    preserving important records from the production of the wartime conference <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes in the 1950s proved essential to investigating
                    <ptr
                    target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/politics-of-the-yalta-frus"
                    />the origins, controversies, and effects of the Yalta volume. He helped us
                    track down original copies of several important instructions and despatches
                    printed in nineteenth century <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes so that the
                    full and excised versions of the texts could be compared. He secured a
                    high-quality digital copy of an 1864 instruction from Secretary of State William
                    Seward to Minister to London Charles Francis Adams that contained the earliest
                    authoritative explanation for and defense of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi> series yet found. Most recently, Langbart’s discovery of where
                    records related to the 1925 Departmental Order were hiding within the vast array
                    of Department of State files proved instrumental to my research.</p>
                <p>The documents that Langbart found shed new light on the motivations behind the
                    1925 Order and clarified the key players who established a firm foundation for
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s future. The original version of the editorial
                    principles drafted by head of the Division of Publications Tyler Dennett and
                    approved by <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kellogg-frank-billings"
                    >Secretary of State Frank Kellogg</ref> included an opening one-sentence
                    paragraph omitted from the version published in 1928: “Although the Secretary of
                    State is not by law required to make an annual report, it is recognized that a
                    well-informed and intelligent public opinion is of the utmost importance for the
                    conduct of foreign relations.” This justification for <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi> also appears in documents that describe internal discussions among
                    top Department of State officials. Dennett’s covering memorandum to the
                    Secretary transmitting the Order for Kellogg’s approval explained that <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> “ought to contribute to the promotion of interest in
                    questions of foreign policy and in turn assist in the maintenance of an
                    intelligent public opinion.” In short, the Department intended for <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> to serve an important public affairs function in
                    addition to satisfying demands from the academic community.<note n="3">
                    “Principles to Guide the Editing of ‘Foreign Relations,’” attachment to Tyler
                    Dennett memorandum to Secretary of State, March 26, 1925, Folder “55D606
                    OSS/PB-1,” Box 35, Miscellaneous Office Files, 1910-1944, RG 59, Archives II, p.
                    1 and Dennett memorandum to Secretary of State, pp. 1-2.</note> </p>
                <p>These papers also illustrate that many Department officials were engaged in the
                    formulation of the 1925 Order. Dennett, who took charge of the Division of
                    Publications – and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> – in late 1924, was the central
                    figure in determining the future the series, but he had crucial allies in the
                    top ranks of the Department. <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/macmurray-john-van-antwerp">Assistant
                    Secretary of State John Van Antwerp MacMurray</ref> convened a high-level
                    meeting in his own office where the Department Solicitor (bureaucratically
                    ranked just below the Assistant Secretary) and the heads of the geographical
                    divisions (including Allen Dulles, future Director of the Central Intelligence
                    Agency) held “a thorough discussion of the principles which ought to guide the
                    editing of ‘Foreign Relations.’” MacMurray also commented on Dennett’s
                    subsequent drafts of the Order before they were submitted to Kellogg for his
                    approval.<note n="4">Dennett memorandum to Secretary of State, p. 1 and John
                    V.A. MacMurray note to Tyler Dennett (with attached annotated draft), March 24,
                    1925 in Folder “55D606 OSS/PB-1,” Box 35, Miscellaneous Office Files, 1910-1944.
                    </note> <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/grew-joseph-clark">Undersecretary
                    of State Joseph Grew</ref> (the second-highest ranked official in the
                    Department) endorsed Dennett’s initiatives as well.<note n="5">Grew initialed
                    his approval on both Dennett’s March 26, 1925 memorandum transmitting the Order
                    to Kellogg as well as the actual “Principles to Guide the Editing of ‘Foreign
                    Relations’” document.</note> Since its inception, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    received high-level attention. However, this is the earliest documentation
                    illustrating systematic consideration of the series’ purpose and principles
                    among top Department officials that we’ve encountered so far.</p>
                <p>The insights about the evolution of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> gleaned from the
                    1925 Departmental Order and the surrounding correspondence that David Langbart
                    found in the National Archives demonstrate that there’s no substitute for
                    primary source documents. They also provide a useful reminder for all
                    researchers seeking to understand the past: it’s a good idea to be nice to
                    archivists!</p>
                <p> <hi rend="italic">Read the text of the original <ref
                    target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1925-order">“Principles to Guide the Editing of
                    ‘Foreign Relations’” and Tyler Dennett’s covering memoranda to Secretary of
                    State Frank Kellogg</ref>, or download the <ref
                    target="http://static.history.state.gov/frus150/1925-order.pdf">PDF</ref>, 499
                    KB, 8 pp.</hi> </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
