<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“The problem that you have undertaken to help us with is one
                    of very, very great difficulty”: The Formation of the Historical Advisory
                    Committee and the First HAC Meeting, December 1957</title>
                <title type="short">The Formation of the Historical Advisory Committee</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-08-11">August 11, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>If you read my previous post on <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/politics-of-the-yalta-frus"
                        >the story of “the Yalta papers,”</ref> you’ll see that one of the most
                    consequential legacies of the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was the creation
                    of a Historical Advisory Committee (HAC) in 1957. The formation of the HAC
                    marked an important transition for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of
                        the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) series, formalizing the
                    critical role that academic and professional organizations had played in the
                    evolution of the series since the 1920s and insulating <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> from the partisan political pressures that had been so
                    significant in the first half of the 1950s. The HAC was one of a series of
                    changes in the way that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was planned, produced,
                    declassified, and released that took place in the 1950s. </p>
                <p>The HAC was a direct consequence of the controversies engendered by the release
                    of the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume. Scholars had become
                    increasingly significant consumers of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series since the 1920s and they were alarmed when it became
                    entangled in partisan debate between 1953 and 1955. They were suspicious of the
                    unorthodox scheduling of the wartime conference and China volumes, which were to
                    be released in advance of the regular annual volumes that could establish the
                    context for these controversial facets of U.S. foreign policy in the 1940s. They
                    were also alarmed by allegations of censorship raised by conservative critics of
                    the Yalta volume. When two Department of State historians were dismissed for
                    insubordination in the fall of 1955, some members of the American Historical
                    Association (AHA) – most notably Howard Beale – insisted on an investigation of
                    the Historical Division to determine whether political considerations were
                    undermining the integrity of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        series.<note n="1">See Donald Dozer press release, October 22, 1955;
                        Professor Howard Beale letter to American Historical Association Executive
                        Secretary Boyd Shafer, November 3, 1955; Shafer letter to Beale, November 9,
                        1955; Shafer letter to Professor Wood Gray, November 15, 1955; Beale letter
                        to Shafer, November 30, 1955; Shafer letter to American Historical
                        Association Executive Committee (with attached draft letter to Beale),
                        December 6, 1955; Professor Sidney [Painter?] letter to Shafer, December 7,
                        1955; Professor Edward Kirkland letter to Shafer, December 10, 1955; Shafer
                        letter to Beale, December 12, 1955; Shafer letter to Kirkland, December 13,
                        1955; Professor Arthur Bestor letter to Shafer, December 13, 1955; Professor
                        Dexter Perkins letter to Shafer, December 15, 1955; Beale letter to Shafer,
                        December 16, 1955; and Shafer letter to Bestor, December 20, 1955 in
                        “Historians &amp; the Federal Government 1955,” Box 188, American Historical
                        Association Papers, Manuscript Division, Library of Congress (subsequently
                        AHA Papers).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Over the course of 1956, the head of the Historical Division (HD) at the
                    Department of State, Bernard Noble, and his superiors in the Bureau of Public
                    Affairs worked with the leadership of academic organizations like the AHA, the
                    American Society of International Lawyers, and the American Political Science
                    Association to translate simmering discontent over the Yalta volume into an
                    institutionalization of the relationship between the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and academia. <note n="2">See Shafer letter to
                        Professors Samuel Bemis, Thomas Bailey, and Richard Leopold, January 3, 1956
                        and Beale letter to Shafer, January 18, 1956 in “American Historical
                        Association – Committee on the Historian and the Federal Government,” Box
                        444, AHA Papers; Gray memorandum to the Committee on the Historian and the
                        Federal Government, January 28, 1956, [no folder], Box 444, AHA Papers;
                        Shafer letter to Professor Edward Younger, March 5, 1956 and Younger letter
                        to Kent Greenfield, March 16, 1956, “American Historical Association –
                        Committee on the Historian and the Federal Government,” Box 444, AHA Papers;
                        Bernard Noble letter to Shafer (with enclosed letter to Perkins, April 30,
                        1956), May 3, 1956, “Historians and the Federal Government 1956,” Box 477,
                        AHA Papers; Minutes of May 19, 1956 Meeting of the Committee on the
                        Historian and the Federal Government (with Chairman’s [Younger’s] subsequent
                        draft of resolutions and submission to AHA Council), June 18, 1956; and
                        Bemis letter to Shafer, June 9, 1956 in “American Historical Association –
                        Committee on the Historian and the Federal Government,” Box 444, AHA Papers;
                        Shafer letter to Younger, September 6, 1956 and Deputy Assistant Secretary
                        of State Burke Wilkinson letter to Shafer, December 3, 1956 in “Historians
                        and the Federal Government 1956,” Box 477, AHA Papers.</note> Of particular
                    note was Noble’s confession to Professor Dexter Perkins, then President of the
                    AHA, that he hoped that the academic community’s engagement with the
                    controversies surrounding HD and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> might result in the
                    formation of a permanent advisory committee. Noble explained that “in this day
                    and time, when the number of diplomatic papers has reached such gigantic
                    proportions, the task of compiling ‘Foreign Relations’ has become inordinately
                    complicated.” He elaborated that the Historical Division “would welcome highly
                    qualified professional advice from the outside” on “a number of problems
                    involving the scope of the selection of the papers, the nature of the contents
                    of the volumes, and the inadequacy of State Department files to cover the
                    subject of our foreign relations.”<note n="3">Noble letter to Perkins, April 30,
                        1956, “Historians and the Federal Government 1956,” Box 477, AHA Papers, p.
                        2.</note> In the year following the release of the Yalta <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>, Noble tried to devise an alternative to Congressional (and
                    partisan) oversight over and guidance for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series that would enhance its quality as it entered the Cold
                    War era and protect HD from mounting academic criticism. </p>
                <p>In 1957, after months of coordination and clarification of authorities within the
                    academic community and between the academic community and the Department of
                        State,<note n="4">For the AHA, see Shafer letter to Younger, January 14,
                        1957; Younger letter to Shafer, January 23, 1957; Shafer letter to
                        Wilkinson, February 25, 1957; Younger letter to Shafer, June 10, 1957;
                        Assistant Secretary of State Andrew Berding letter to Bemis, July 26, 1957;
                        Bemis letter to Shafer, July 30, 1957; Noble letter to Shafer, August 7,
                        1957; Bemis letter to Berding, August 12, 1957; and Noble letter to Shafer,
                        October 31, 1957 in “Historian and the Federal Govt – 1957,” Box 482, AHA
                        Papers and Berding letter to Perkins, et al., August 21, 1957, 023.1/8-2157;
                        Noble letter to Professor Thomas Bailey, November 15, 1957, 023.1/11-1557;
                        and Noble letter to Bailey, November 29, 1957, 023.1/11-2957 in Department
                        of State Central Decimal File 1955-1959, RG 59, Archives II, College Park,
                        Maryland.</note> the first meeting of the HAC was held on December 6 and 7.
                    HD staffers and Department officials briefed the seven assembled historians,
                    political scientists, and international law scholars on the <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> production process, including new challenges related to access to
                    significant non-State Department documents and interagency clearance decisions,
                    and asked them for guidance on the preferences of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s
                    academic consumers. Participants at this meeting – as they would at HAC meetings
                    throughout the ensuing decades – struggled to reconcile competing priorities.
                    Scholars wanted complete volumes, but comprehensiveness entailed significant
                    delays for access and clearance. Secretary of State John Foster Dulles stopped
                    by to thank the committee for assisting the Department in dealing with a problem
                    “of very, very great difficulty.”<note n="5">Minutes of Meeting of the Advisory
                        Committee on “Foreign Relations of the United States,” “1957 – HAC – Annual
                        Meeting,” Lot File 03 D130, Department of State, Washington, DC.</note> This
                    first meeting of the Historical Advisory Committee marked a milestone in the
                    evolution of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and the beginning of an ongoing
                    collaboration between the Department of State and the academic community to
                    ensure that the fullest possible array of documents is published in as timely a
                    manner as responsibly and practically feasible.</p>
                <p>To learn more about this first meeting of the HAC, you can read the text of the
                    <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1957-hac-minutes-transcript">the minutes of
                        the opening session</ref> (<ref
                        target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/frus150/1957-hac-minutes-transcript.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 2.9 MB, 81 pp.).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
