<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Publicizing Foreign Relations in Time of War: The Foundation
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                    Series</title>
                <title type="short">The Foundation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi> Series</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-06-24">June 24, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>After the start of the Civil War, the Union faced a series of challenges related
                    to foreign relations. One immediate challenge was to prevent the fledgling
                    Confederate government from gaining recognition from foreign powers. In the
                    summer of 1861, the Lincoln government received calls from Congress to
                    demonstrate and explain the steps being taken to prevent such recognition from
                    taking place. Thus, in addition to the challenge overseas, the administration
                    had to respond to domestic demands for information about foreign policy. The
                    administration responded to these demands by releasing several hundred pages of
                    foreign affairs-related documentation with the President’s annual message in
                    December 1861. Although the documents were released in direct response to a
                    Congressional demand, they also served a public relations function. This paper
                    will explore the creation of the first volume of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series and suggest some general conclusions about the
                    significance of this volume.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, many of the circumstances surrounding the creation of the first
                    volume are shrouded in mystery. There are few relevant Department records from
                    the era, and Lincoln’s and Seward’s personal papers contain nothing pertinent to
                    the topic. Early histories of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> also shed precious
                    little light on the history of the series.<note n="1">See, for example, Clarence
                        E. Carter, “The United States and Documentary Historical Publication,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi> 25 (June 1938):
                        3-24; E. R. Perkins, “ ‘Foreign Relations of the United States’: 91 Years of
                        American Foreign Policy,” Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin
                        </hi>(December 22, 1952): 1002-1006; Robert Wilson, “A Hundred Years of
                        ‘Foreign Relations,’ ” <hi rend="italic">American Journal of International
                            Law</hi> 55 (October 1961): 947-950; Richard W. Leopold, “The <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Series: A Centennial Estimate,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mississippi Valley Historical Review</hi> 49 (March 1963):
                        595-612; William M. Franklin, “The Future of the ‘Foreign Relations’
                        Series,” Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi> (September 15,
                        1969): 247-251. One exception to this trend is Rick Moss’s useful, “Public
                        Diplomacy and the First <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>: The Origins of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> Series,” fall
                        2001, unpublished paper in author’s possession. Moss uncovered the
                        resolutions in the House of Representatives which sparked the 1861 volume
                        and also developed the idea of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> representing
                        checks and balances.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although it is difficult to know with any certainty how deeply Lincoln and Seward
                    were involved in the decision to publish this volume, it is equally difficult to
                    imagine documents of this importance being released without Seward’s
                    concurrence. What we can learn from existing evidence is the degree to which
                    Congress was responsible for the publication. The impetus for the volume came
                    from a request from Congress. Thus, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> represents an
                    example of the checks and balances of federal government: the executive branch
                    carried out foreign policy, but the legislative branch demanded the right to
                    monitor that policy via these requests for documentation. In the summer of 1861,
                    resolutions in Congress included the following: “<hi rend="italic"
                    >Resolved</hi>, That the President be requested, if not, in his opinion,
                    incompatible with the public interest, to submit to this House all
                    correspondence between this Government and foreign Powers on the subject of the
                    existing insurrection in the United States.”<note n="2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Congressional Globe</hi>, 37th Congress, 1st Session,
                        129.</note> The House resolutions came from Democrats and the Senate
                    resolution from a Republican, suggesting bipartisan interest in this issue.</p>
                <p>Congress had to wait until December for satisfaction. When the volume was
                    released, it displayed for the public the administration’s actions in the first
                    months of the war. Staving off Confederate agents was key. To the minister to
                    Spain, Carl Schurz, Seward wrote that preventing the Confederacy from gaining
                    recognition was “your chief duty, and no more important one was ever devolved by
                    the United States upon any representative whom they have sent abroad.”<note
                        n="3">Letter from Seward to Schurz, April 27, 1861, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Message of the President of the United States to the Two Houses of
                            Congress at the Commencement of the Second Session of the Thirty-Seventh
                            Congress</hi> (Washington: Government Printing Office, 1861) [hereafter
                            <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>], 257.</note> Even in countries of lesser
                    import, ministers were urged to be on the watch. Although Seward did not believe
                    that the Confederates would attempt to gain recognition immediately from
                    Denmark, he wrote to our representative there that “political action even of the
                    more commanding or more active States is influenced by a general opinion that is
                    formed imperceptibly in all parts of the Eastern continent. Every representative
                    of the United States in Europe has, therefore, a responsibility to see that no
                    effort on his part is wanting to make that opinion just, so far as the true
                    position of affairs is in his own country is concerned.”<note n="4">Letter from
                        Seward to Wood, May 1, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 311.</note>
                    Likewise to the minister to Switzerland: “You are in a region where men of
                    inquiring mind and active habit seek a temporary respite from severe studies and
                    exhausting labors. The world’s affairs are discussed freely, and the sentiments
                    and opinions which influence the conduct and affect the prospects of nations are
                    very often formed in the mountains and dells of Switzerland.”<note n="5">Letter
                        from Seward to Fogg, May 15, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>,
                        329.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The letters encouraged ministers to not let discouraging news from America cloud
                    foreigners’ perceptions of the war effort. “You will hear of a reverse of our
                    arms in Virginia,” Seward wrote to Charles Francis Adams in London after the
                    Battle of Bull Run. He encouraged the minister to think little of it: “The vigor
                    of the government will be increased, and the ultimate result will be a triumph
                    of the Constitution. Do not be misled by panic reports of danger apprehended for
                    the capital.”<note n="6">Letter from Seward to Adams, July 29, 1861, <hi
                            rend="italic">Message</hi>, 124.</note> He likewise wrote to William
                    Lewis Dayton in France: “Treason was emboldened by its partial success at
                    Manassas, but the Union now grows manifestly stronger every day.”<note n="7"
                        >Letter from Seward to Dayton, August 17, 1861, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Message</hi>, 240.</note> Foreigners could get their news from any
                    number of sources, and ministers had to stand ready to put a positive spin on
                    events.</p>
                <p>The volume also printed letters from ministers abroad. Some shared good news of
                    the response from foreign governments. From Belgium, Henry Shelton Sanford
                    reported that the Confederate government would “receive no sanction by any act
                    of Belgium” because it would violate the Belgian policy of “strict
                        neutrality.”<note n="8">Letter from Sanford to Seward, May 26, 1861, <hi
                            rend="italic">Message</hi>, 55-56.</note> From Great Britain, George
                    Mifflin Dallas reported that “there was not the slightest disposition in the
                    British government to grasp at any advantage which might be supposed to arise
                    from unpleasant domestic differences in the United States.”<note n="9">Letter
                        from Dallas to Seward, April 9, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 81.
                        Seward found the British response inadequate, see letter from Seward to
                        Adams, April 27, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 83.</note> From
                    Austria, Jehu Glancy Jones noted that the country “hoped to see us re-united”
                    and “was not inclined to recognize <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> governments
                        anywhere.”<note n="10">Letter from Jones to Seward, April 15, 1861, <hi
                            rend="italic">Message</hi>, 188.</note> In Turkey, the minister of
                    foreign affairs assured the American representative of “the most friendly
                    sentiments towards the government of the United States, and expressions of warm
                    sympathy” for the country.<note n="11">Letter from Brown to Seward, June 11,
                        1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 389.</note> Some of the initial
                    reports, then, were positive.</p>
                <p>Other countries had to hedge. Mexico occupied a unique position since the nascent
                    Confederacy was a potential neighbor. Thomas Corwin reported that the government
                    was “well affected towards us in our present difficulties” but would be
                    “unwilling to enter into any engagement which might produce war with the south,
                    unless protected by promise of aid from the United States.”<note n="12">Letter
                        from Corwin to Seward, May 29, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>,
                        70.</note> From France, Dayton reported that while the French government was
                    “not in the habit of acting hastily upon such questions” as recognizing <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> governments such as the Confederacy claimed to
                    be, the French representative was “equally bound to say that the practice and
                    usage of the present century had fully established the right of <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> governments to recognition when a proper case
                    was made out for the decision of foreign powers.”<note n="13">Letter from
                        Faulkner to Seward, April 15, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>,
                        205.</note> In Venezuela, Edward A. Turpin was only able to convince the
                    President that Confederate ships should not be allowed in Venezuela in any case
                    other than distress; “I could not obtain from him their complete denunciation as
                    pirates,” he wrote.<note n="14">Letter from Turpin to Seward, July 27, 1861, <hi
                            rend="italic">Message</hi>, 427.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Other ministers shared news from the foreign public or other statesmen. In
                    Berlin, Joseph Albert White reported that he was “in the receipt of hundreds of
                    letters and personal calls seeking positions in the American army, and asking
                    for means of conveyance to our shores. So numerous, indeed, are the
                    applications, that I have been compelled to place on the doors of the legation a
                    notice to the purport that ‘This is the legation of the United States, and not a
                    recruiting office.’ ”<note n="15">Letter from Wright to Seward, May 26, 1861,
                            <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 40.</note> Dallas forwarded newspaper
                    clippings from the London press featuring debates on the war.<note n="16">Letter
                        from Dallas to Seward, May 2, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>,
                        83-85.</note> From Sweden, Benjamin Franklin Angel noted that “so far as my
                    reading and observations extend, the better informed European statesmen express
                    the opinion that those charged with the administration of public affairs have
                    acted with the greatest moderation” and that the Union “will have the sympathy
                    and best wishes of all conservatives on this side the Atlantic.”<note n="17"
                        >Letter from Angel to Seward, June 10, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>,
                        396.</note> One month later, James Samils Haldeman noted that “quite a
                    change is visible in diplomatic circles,” and that diplomats in Sweden “speak
                    out openly that the government of the United States should act vigorously and
                    efficiently” and that the “rebellion should be annihilated by force and not by
                        compromise.”<note n="18">Letter from Haldeman to Seward, July 28, 1861, <hi
                            rend="italic">Message</hi>, 399.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The volume also outlined to the frustration the Union felt over Britain’s
                    willingness to treat the Confederates as belligerent powers (and thus with the
                    attendant rights, even if it fell short of full recognition).<note n="19"
                        >According to Howard Jones, the British “adhered to international law in
                        equating a civil war with a war between nations and then assuming a position
                        of neutrality.” Through belligerent status, the Confederates gained
                        “credibility,” their raids on Union ships were not considered piracy by the
                        British, and Confederates could do business with British merchants. Jones,
                            <hi rend="italic">Blue and Gray Diplomacy: A History of Union and
                            Confederate Foreign Relations</hi> (Chapel Hill: University of North
                        Carolina Press, 2010), 51-52.</note> Such documents exposed British actions
                    to American citizens. Adams reported to the British that the Americans were
                    “irritated” by the Queen’s proclamation which was seen as “designed to aid the
                    insurgents by raising them to the rank of a belligerent state.” Although Adams
                    demurred that he himself did not feel that this was British intent, he went on
                    to point out that the presence of “pseudo commissioners” from the Confederates
                    was a continued aggravation. The British responded that “it had been the custom
                    both in France and here to receive such persons unofficially for a long time
                    back. Poles, Hungarians, Italians, &amp;c., &amp;c., had been allowed
                    interviews, to hear what they had to say. But this did not imply recognition in
                    their case any more than in ours.”<note n="20">Letter from Adams to Seward, June
                        14, 1861, <hi rend="italic">Message</hi>, 104.</note> Publishing this
                    exchange demonstrated to Americans the dangerous position Great Britain was
                    taking.</p>
                <p>As the above quotations demonstrate, there was a great deal in the volume for a
                    domestic audience. The volume serves as a good representative of what the
                    Lincoln administration wanted the public to know about its foreign relations
                    efforts during the first months of the war. In that effect, the volume tells
                    some clear stories. Seward immediately wrote to representatives abroad and
                    instructed them on no uncertain terms to resist the efforts of Confederate
                    agents to secure recognition and demand that countries refuse Confederate ships
                    succor at their ports. Readers of the correspondence were treated to a range of
                    responses from around the globe: some declared their support for the Union,
                    others pledged a neutrality which partially legitimized the Confederates. The
                    documentation from the ministers illustrated the arguments used to sway foreign
                    governments.</p>
                <p>The Department clearly felt that the volumes had some value for telling the
                    government’s story, because they ordered two thousand copies for their own use.
                    The Department ordered 1,000 copies on November 29, and then an additional 1,000
                    copies on December 12. This is far in excess of the number of foreign posts
                    maintained by the United States, so it is unclear what use was made of these
                        volumes.<note n="21">Letter from William Seward to John D. Defrees, November
                        29, 1861, page 520, volume 55, reel 52, microfilm publication M40 (Domestic
                        Letters, 1784-1906), RG 59, National Archives; letter from Frederic Seward
                        to John D. Defrees, December 12, 1861, page 22, volume 56, reel 53,
                        microfilm publication M40 (Domestic Letters, 1784-1906), RG 59, National
                        Archives.</note> Perhaps copies were distributed to Congressmen, since they
                    requested the documents. But we know for certain that copies found their way
                    into the hands of journalists. It was surely through wide distribution through
                    newspapers that most Americans learned about the documentation and the work the
                    Department was doing to shore up U.S. interests abroad.</p>
                <p>Prior to the publication of the annual message, newspapers speculated about the
                    coverage of foreign affairs to be included in the message; both the <hi
                        rend="italic">New York Herald</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">New York
                        Times</hi> anticipated that the message would include material on the <hi
                        rend="italic">Trent</hi> affair.<note n="22">
                        <hi rend="italic">New York</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>, December 2, 1861; <hi rend="italic">New York
                            Times</hi>, December 4, 1861. On November 8, 1861, the USS <hi
                            rend="italic">San Jacinto</hi> seized Confederate ministers James Mason
                        and John Slidell from the British ship HMS <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi>,
                        violating British neutrality (Jones, <hi rend="italic">Blue and Gray</hi>,
                        chap. 3).</note> In this hope they would be disappointed, but newspapers
                    along the Eastern seaboard published accounts of the correspondence just a few
                    days after the message and documents were released to the public. On December 6,
                    three New York newspapers (the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Commercial Advertiser</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Herald Tribune</hi>),
                    three Philadelphia newspapers (the <hi rend="italic">Public Ledger</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">North American</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Inquirer</hi>) and
                    the Baltimore <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi> published essentially similar accounts,
                    each reporting on the number pages of documentation released and highlighting
                    some of the documentation. The next day, the <hi rend="italic">Albany Evening
                        Journal</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Boston Daily Advertiser</hi> printed long
                    synopses of the papers. In Connecticut, the <hi rend="italic">Norwich Morning
                        Bulletin</hi> printed a much shorter item, and praised the publication: “The
                    diplomatic correspondence submitted to Congress by President Lincoln, reveals as
                    favorable a condition of our relations with foreign Powers as could have been
                    anticipated. This is doubtless owing in a great degree to the firm and decided
                    position maintained by Secretary Seward in his official intercourse with these
                        Governments.”<note n="23">
                        <hi rend="italic">Albany Evening Journal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Boston
                            Daily Advertiser</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Norwich Morning Bulletin</hi>,
                        all December 7, 1861. On December 9, the <hi rend="italic">Hartford Daily
                            Courant</hi> published a similar synopsis to the lengthy ones published
                        on December 6 and 7 by other papers.</note> The publication continued to
                    make the news in the following weeks.<note n="24">The District of Columbia <hi
                            rend="italic">Daily National Intelligencer</hi> published a range of
                        documentation over several days in the end of December, for example.</note>
                    Newspapers began to publish additional documents, particularly those relative to
                    relations with France.<note n="25">Correspondence with France was published or
                        summarized by the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> (December 9, 1861),
                        the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hartford Daily
                            Courant</hi>, Pennsylvania <hi rend="italic">Public Ledger</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Boston Daily Advertiser</hi> (all December 11), <hi
                            rend="italic">Boston Daily Advertiser</hi>, Philadelphia <hi
                            rend="italic">North American</hi>, Keene <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire
                            Sentinel</hi> (all December 12), and the <hi rend="italic">Cincinnati
                            Daily Enquirer</hi> (December 14).</note>
                    <hi rend="bold"/>
                </p>
                <p>If it was intended as a public relations measure, the publication of the volume
                    was a success in Northern newspapers. The Baltimore <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi>
                    reported on December 9 that the correspondence was “receiving that close
                    attention from persons skilled in diplomacy and public law which belongs to its
                    distinguished source and the magnitude of the subject in question.” Papers
                    praised the publication of the correspondence and the contents of the documents.
                    The Keene <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi> reported that “in the
                    whole of this correspondence, the Secretary of State exhibits marked ability as
                    a statesman and diplomatist.”<note n="26">
                        <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Sentinel</hi>, December 12, 1861.</note>
                    Others took heart from the correspondence that Seward would continue to act
                    appropriately in the future. “The masterly ability which Gov. SEWARD has shown
                    in his instructions to our Foreign Ministers,” opined the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Albany Evening Journal</hi>, “induce strong confidence that he will conduct
                    the correspondence likely to grow out of the MASON and SLIDELL affair, to a
                    successful and satisfactory issue.”<note n="27">
                        <hi rend="italic">Albany Evening Journal</hi>, December 18, 1861.</note> By
                    January 1862, the correspondence had reached the West Coast; the <hi
                        rend="italic">San Francisco Bulletin</hi> reported that the diplomatic
                    correspondence was “quite voluminous” and “highly interesting.” Seward again
                    came in for praise, his “high-toned” and “courteous” messages were “as nearly
                    perfect models of diplomatic correspondence as are to be found on the pages of
                    modern history.” The correspondence with Adams and Dayton “have swept to the
                    winds all the aspersions of those who have accused him of favoring a timid and
                    wavering policy in dealing with the rebels.”<note n="28">
                        <hi rend="italic">San Francisco Bulletin</hi>, January 9, 1862. The paper
                        published additional items on January 10, 13, 14, and 31.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Other newspapers hoped that the publication of the correspondence would improve
                    the standing of the United States abroad. The <hi rend="italic">New York
                        Herald-Tribune</hi> hoped that British newspapers which had shown Seward in
                    an unfavorable light “would be surprised if the contents of this volume could be
                    fairly laid before them. In vain would they turn page after page in eager quest
                    of the passages whereon the criminations of their favorite journals were based;
                    they do not appear because they do not exist.” The paper praised Seward for his
                    “assured and firm” tone and his faith that the country, “reunited, will be
                    stronger and more prosperous than ever before.”<note n="29">
                        <hi rend="italic">New York Herald-Tribune</hi>, December 18, 1861.</note>
                    Among these newspapers, at least, Seward acquitted himself well.<note n="30">For
                        more praise, see the <hi rend="italic">Trenton State Gazette</hi>, December
                        20, 1861.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The publication of the correspondence even attracted notice in the
                        Confederacy.<note n="31">See, for example, <hi rend="italic">Macon
                            Telegraph</hi>, January 7, 1862.</note> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Columbus</hi> [Georgia] <hi rend="italic">Daily Enquirer</hi> discussed the
                    correspondence with France, under the headline “Whom the Gods Wish to Destroy,
                    They First Make Mad.” Naturally, the paper put a different spin on the
                    correspondence; rather than noting Seward standing strong in the face of an
                    unfavorable British and French response, the paper focused on the response
                    itself: “It will thus be seen that the relations between the United States and
                    Great Britain and France were far from being securely amicable before the arrest
                    of Mason and Slidell, that there were issues between them of great irritation
                    and danger, and that Great Britain and France are united in the policy to be
                    pursued in reference to political troubles on this continent.”<note n="32">
                        <hi rend="italic">Columbus Daily Enquirer</hi>, December 23, 1861.</note>
                    Likewise, the New Orleans <hi rend="italic">Times-Picayune</hi> sneered at the
                    correspondence with France from June 1861, noting that it came from a time when
                    “arrogant confidence” about a speedy end to the war was “universally felt at the
                    North,” before “the fervor of the Southern passion for independence” and the
                    subsequent “holy war” had been fully experienced.<note n="33">New Orleans <hi
                            rend="italic">Times-Picayune</hi>, December 25, 1861.</note> In these
                    documents, Southerner saw hope that their cause was not lost in Europe, and that
                    Union leaders were grasping at straws.</p>
                <p>The extent of newspaper response illustrates the important domestic function that
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> served. Newspapers across the country—including
                    the West Coast—printed the correspondence directly (or analysis of it), and many
                    papers praised Seward, the decision to publish the correspondence, and the
                    contents of the publication. The volume was created in response to a request
                    from Congress, and it retained its domestic character upon release by being
                    widely debated and discussed in the country. While we cannot know exactly how
                    many of the complete volumes were distributed across the country or precisely
                    how it happened, the newspaper distribution serves as a good proxy for studying
                    how Americans reacted to the publication of this correspondence.</p>
                <p>This brief investigation of the first volume suggests a few general conclusions.
                    First, the project was not conceived in the executive branch. Rather, the
                    process of sharing information represents the checks and balances of the
                    branches of government: the executive executes foreign policy, and the
                    legislative ensures that the policy is being honestly carried out.</p>
                <p>The second broad conclusion is that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> had a significant
                    domestic audience. It is clear from the correspondence written by the Secretary
                    of State in 1861 and subsequent debates in Congress over the cost of printing
                    that the Department intended the volume as a public relations tool in foreign
                    lands. And yet, there was a definitive domestic audience for the volumes as
                    well. We know that Congress wanted thousands of copies for its own distribution.
                    And newspapers across the country also watched with interest when the volumes
                    came out.</p>
                <p>This conclusion suggests the third broad conclusion: that even if these volumes
                    may not tell us everything that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> might wish to know
                    about foreign relations during the Civil War era, they do give us a good picture
                    of what the federal <hi rend="italic">government</hi>wanted its citizens to
                    know. The early volumes are not “scholarly” in the way that today’s <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes are. We do not know anything about the
                    clerks who compiled them, whereas today’s volumes are produced by trained
                    historians. Of course, it is anachronistic to castigate the early volumes for
                    not being scholarly when the historians in America had yet to
                        professionalize.<note n="34">For example, the American Historical
                        Association was not founded until 1884, 23 years after publication of the
                        first volume.</note> Yet the volumes remain valuable for what they tell us
                    about what the government wanted citizens to know. The picture emerges from the
                    first volume of Seward firing off long letters around the world, instructing our
                    ministers abroad to fend off Confederate advances in other lands. The documents
                    exposed the willingness of England and France to treat the Confederates as
                    legitimate belligerents. There was a public relations value to exposing this
                    type of information.</p>
                <p>Waging war against the Confederacy required not only fighting Confederates on the
                    battlefields but also combating their envoys in foreign lands. The first volume
                    of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was not the first publication of diplomatic
                    correspondence. Yet it marked an important stage in the evolution of publishing
                    diplomatic correspondence. The anonymous clerks who created the first volume
                    probably could not have envisioned the massive undertaking that <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> has become, but hopefully they would be sympathetic
                    to its shared mission: to create a record of U.S. foreign policy, laid out for
                    citizens to freely assess the work of their government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
