<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> at War: Appeasement, Alliance Politics, and the
                    Paris Peace Conference Volumes </title>
                <title type="short">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> at War</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-20">October 20, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The first potentially paralyzing clearance battle waged for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series came in the late 1930s. When preparing the
                    regular annual volumes, Department of State historians—or other officials—could
                    simply omit materials that posed insolvable clearance problems. This in fact
                    occurred in 1936, in response to opposition within the Department and from the
                    Iranian government to publishing records from 1922 concerning a financial
                    mission to Tehran and negotiations for an oil concession. The annual volumes
                    covering 1922 simply skipped over Iran entirely, though the omissions did not
                    diminish the value of the remainder of the compilation.<note n="1">See Wallace
                        Murray memorandum to Cyril Wynne, November 21, 1936 and Cyril Wynne
                        memorandum to Wallace Murray, November 23, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1118;
                        Gordon Merriam despatch to Secretary of State, December 10, 1936, 026
                        Foreign Relations/1134; Cyril Wynne memorandum to Wallace Murray, November
                        30, 1936; Wallace Murray memorandum to Cyril Wynne, December 3, 1936; Cyril
                        Wynne memorandum to Wallace Murray, December 5, 1936; Wallace Murray letter
                        to R. Walton Moore, December 10, 1936; Cyril Wynne memorandum to Acting
                        Secretary, December 14, 1936; Wallace Murray memorandum to Cyril Wynne,
                        December 16, 1936; and Cyril Wynne memorandum to Acting Secretary, December
                        31, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1138; R. Walton Moore instruction to Gordon
                        Merriam, January 7, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1139; R. Walton Moore letter
                        to Gordon Merriam, January 7, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1140; Gordon
                        Merriam despatch to Secretary of State, March 10, 1937, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1155; Gordon Merriam telegram to Secretary of State, March 17,
                        1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1152 in Department of State Central Decimal
                        Files 1930-1939, Record Group 59, Archives II, College Park, Maryland
                        (henceforth DoS CDF 1930-1939).</note> The Paris Peace Conference volumes
                    posed a much different challenge because foreign government clearances would be
                    required to publish the jointly “owned” formal minutes of conference proceedings
                    and since the conference record had to be substantially complete to be coherent.
                    If any of the foreign governments that played a major role at the 1919 Paris
                    Peace Conference objected to publishing the records of the conference
                    discussions, Department of State historians would have to put the subseries
                    publication plan on hold until they changed their minds.</p>
                <p>In March 1938, the Department sought permission from the governments of France,
                    Great Britain, and Italy to publish documents from the 1919 peace
                        conference.<note n="2">George Messersmith instruction to Edwin Wilson, March
                        8, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/1; George Messersmith instruction
                        to William Phillips, March 8, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/1A;
                        and George Messersmith instruction to Joseph Kennedy, March 8, 1938, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/1B in DoS CDF 1930-1939 .</note> Although
                    Italy and Great Britain gave the desired preliminary approvals in June and
                    September, France proved much more hostile to the project.<note n="3">Note
                        verbale, June 24, 1938 enclosed with Edward Reed despatch to Secretary of
                        State, June 27, 1938, 026 Foreign relations (P.C. 1919)/8 and Stephen
                        Gaselee letter to Herschel Johnson, September 23, 1938 enclosed with
                        Herschel Johnson despatch to Secretary of State, September 30, 1938, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/16 in DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note> The French
                    Foreign Ministry was aghast at the proposal to publish politically sensitive
                    records of the negotiation of the controversial Treaty of Versailles in the
                    midst of domestic political and social strife, heightened international
                    tensions, and fears of war. When Director of Political Affairs at the French
                    Foreign Ministry Renè Massigli met with Edwin Wilson, the Counselor of the U.S.
                    Embassy in Paris, to discuss the issue, he argued that “Europe was today in a
                    highly dangerous situation, perilously near war, and every effort was being made
                    by those in responsible positions to prevent war, to save civilization, and with
                    that end in view to appease conflicts and remove so far as possible every
                    pretext for misunderstanding.” Wilson explained to officials in Washington that
                    Massigli “was frankly terrified at the thought of how publication of the secret
                    documents of the Peace Conference could be seized upon by people who want to
                    promote trouble and misunderstanding. As between the embarrassment … by being
                    put in the position of objecting to the publication of these documents, and the
                    danger of adding fuel to the flames of international controversies, he much
                    preferred the former.” Even delayed publication “might merely prejudice the work
                    of appeasement which might have been done in the meanwhile.” Wilson’s
                    conversation with Massigli ended with the latter concluding that “if during the
                    next month things take a turn for the worse, our thoughts may look forward to
                    the next peace conference rather than to the question of publishing the
                    documents of the last one.”<note n="4">Memorandum of conversation between Edwin
                        Wilson and M. Massigli, August 26, 1938 enclosed with Edwin Wilson despatch
                        to Secretary of State, August 27, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C.
                        1919)/13, DoS CDF 1930-1939. See also William Bullitt telegram to Secretary
                        of State, July 2, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/7, DoS CDF
                        1930-1939.</note> After a “sweep” of the French Foreign Ministry removed
                    Massigli in the fall, Wilson felt the French would be more amenable to the
                        project.<note n="5">Edwin Wilson letter to Pierrepont Moffat, November 30,
                        1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/18.5, DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note> He
                    was right. The French Government agreed to the Peace Conference volumes in late
                    December 1938, allowing Cyril Wynne (chief of the Division of Research and
                    Publication) to announce the project at the American Political Science
                    Association’s annual meeting on December 29, 1938. <note n="6">Edwin Wilson
                        telegram to Secretary of State, December 27, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations
                        (P.C. 1919)/19 ; and Alexis Leger note to William Bullitt, December 24, 1938
                        and Cyril Wynne address to American Political Science Association meeting at
                        Columbus, Ohio, December 29, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/20 in
                        DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note></p>
                <p>The first Peace Conference volumes appeared in 1942, and a total of five volumes
                    were released during World War II. The fall of France and hostilities with Italy
                    left Great Britain as the lone holder of foreign equities for the most crucial
                    documents of the Paris Peace Conference volumes, the minutes to the discussions
                    of the Council of Four. While Britain acceded to U.S. requests to print most of
                    the Peace Conference records,<note n="7">H. Freeman Matthews despatch to
                        Secretary of State, June 16, 1942, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/66 and
                        John Winant telegram to Secretary of State, December 30, 1943, 026 Foreign
                        Relations (P.C. 1919)/98 in DoS CDF 1940-1944.</note> Winston Churchill and
                    Anthony Eden balked in July of 1943 when the U.S. asked for permission to
                    publish Council of Four discussions during the war. Eden explained that “the
                    publication in particular of the minutes of the Council of Four would have a
                    cramping effect upon any similar confidential discussions which it may be
                    necessary to hold after the present war.” He also worried that printing the
                    Council of Four minutes might “provide hostile propagandists with welcome
                    material.” Finally, Eden objected to the publication of “rough workings kept for
                    the convenience of the statesmen concerned” while one of those statesmen—David
                    Lloyd George—was still alive.<note n="8">John Winant telegram to Secretary of
                        State, July 12, 1943, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/87 and Anthony Eden
                        note to John Winant, July 9, 1943, enclosed in W aldemar Gallman despatch to
                        Secretary of State, July 12, 1943, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/88 in
                        DoS CDF 1940-1944. For the U.S. request for British permission to print the
                        Council of Four minutes, which requests supplementary documents from British
                        records, see Ernest Perkins letter to Wilder Spaulding, March 31, 1943, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/77 and G. Howland Shaw instruction to John
                        Winant, April 10, 1943, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/77a in DoS CDF
                        1940-1944. British skittishness about these particular records should not
                        have been a surprise. Previous British clearances had been expressly limited
                        to a narrow slice of the overall record of the Paris Peace Conference
                        records and the British objected when the preface for the first couple
                        volumes pledged that the rest of the Paris Conference documentation would be
                        released. See Stephen Gaselee letter to W aldemar Gallman, March 25, 1943
                        enclosed in W aldemar Gallman despatch to Secretary of State, April 2, 1943,
                        026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/77, DoS CDF 1940-1944.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="big-four.jpg"/>
                    <head>The Big Four of the Allies chat while gathering in Versailles for the
                        Treaty of Versailles, which officially ended World War I, in this 1919
                        photo. They are, left to right, David Lloyd George, of Great Britain,
                        Vittorio Orlando, of Italy, Georges Clemenceau, of France, and Woodrow
                        Wilson, United States President. (AP Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Department asked the British government to reconsider its position in early
                    August 1943,<note n="9">Cordell Hull airgram to John Winant, August 6, 1943, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/87, DoS CDF 1940-1944.</note> but soon faced
                    opposition from another source: President Franklin Roosevelt. In preparation for
                    a summit with Churchill at Hyde Park in September, Roosevelt asked <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Secretary of State Cordell
                        Hull</ref> to explain why the U.S. Government was trying to publish the
                    Council of Four minutes. The President expressed “distinct hesitation… because
                    notes of these conversations ought not to have been taken down anyway.”<note
                        n="10"><ref
                            target="http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=goto&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1943&amp;isize=M&amp;submit=Go+to+page&amp;page=1334"
                            >F[ranklin] R[oosevelt], “Memorandum for Hon. Cordell Hull,” September
                            7, 1943, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States: The
                                Conferences at Washington and Quebec, 1943</hi> (Washington, DC:
                            Government Printing Office, 1970), p. 1334.</ref></note> Roosevelt’s
                    “hesitation” prompted a spate of memo-writing within the Division of Research
                    and Publication. Staff historian Philip Burnett surmised that the “real reason”
                    for the President’s attitude was the “wretchedly shortsighted” impulse to avoid
                    releasing any information that could potentially be used to criticize the coming
                    peace settlement.<note n="11">Philip Burnett memorandum to Ernest Perkins,
                        September 9, 1943 attached to M. F. Axton memorandum to Ernest Perkins,
                        August 27, 1945, 026 Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/8-2745, DoS CDF
                        1945-1949.</note> Hull’s response to Roosevelt echoed the Department’s
                    arguments to the British Government, emphasizing the pressure from academics and
                    Congress for publishing the full record of the Paris Peace Conference and the
                    extent of already-published information about the Council of Four
                        discussions.<note n="12">Cordell Hull memorandum for President, September 9,
                        1943, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States: The
                            Conferences at Washington and Quebec, 1943</hi>, pp. 1334-1335. See also
                        Wilder Spaulding memorandum to Secretary of State (with attached draft
                        Secretary of State memorandum to President), September 9, 1943 attached to
                        M. F. Axton memorandum to Ernest Perkins, August 27, 1945, 026 Foreign
                        Relations (P.C. 1919)/8-2745, DoS CDF 1945-1949.</note></p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fdr-and-churchill.jpg"/>
                    <head>Franklin D. Roosevelt and Winston Churchill in “Shangri-la,” May 14, 1943.
                        They agreed to keep the Council of Four discussions under wraps several
                        months later. (Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, New York)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Roosevelt remained unconvinced. He told Hull that publication “would probably
                    result in wholly unwarranted sensational articles” from “hostile sources.” He
                    also explained that “no notes should have been kept. Four people cannot be
                    conversationally frank with each other if someone is taking down notes for
                    future publication.” Roosevelt “felt very strongly about this” and, during his
                    meeting with Churchill at Hyde Park, vetoed publication of the Council of Four
                    minutes for the duration of the war.<note n="13"><ref
                            target="http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=goto&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1943&amp;isize=M&amp;submit=Go+to+page&amp;page=1338"
                            >W[inston] C[hurchill] [telegram?] to Anthony Eden, September 13, 1943,
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States: The
                                Conferences at Washington and Quebec, 1943</hi>, p. 1338.</ref> See
                        also Hull telegram to American Embassy London, September 20, 1943, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/87, DoS CDF 1940-1944. </note> Only in
                    November of 1945, after Lloyd George and Roosevelt had died and Churchill and
                    Eden had lost their government posts, did the Department renew its efforts to
                    secure British permission to publish the Council of Four minutes.<note n="14"
                        >Ernest Perkins memorandum to Wilder Spaulding, November 6, 1945, 026
                        Foreign Relations (P.C. 1919)/ 11-645, DoS CDF 1945-1949.</note> The volumes
                    appeared the next year and Roosevelt’s intervention in the series was itself
                    included in a <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume published in 1970.</p>
                <p>The special <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> subseries on the Paris Peace Conference
                    marked the culmination of one era for the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations
                    </hi> series while foreshadowing some of the difficulties that would greet
                    Department of State historians during the Cold War era. During the interwar
                    period, clearance with foreign governments posed the most serious obstacles to
                    publishing comprehensive annual volumes on schedule. Because most of the
                    documentation came from Department of State files, interagency coordination for
                    research and declassification of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    compilations was virtually nonexistent. Although the Paris Peace Conference
                    volumes did require an unprecedented amount of research beyond Department
                        files,<note n="15">Wilder Spaulding memorandum to Breckinridge Long, March
                        15, 1940, 026 Foreign Relations/1456.5 and Breckinridge Long memorandum to
                        Wilder Spaulding, March 16, 1940, 026 Foreign Relations/1458.25 in DoS CDF
                        1940-1944. </note> it was not until the 1950s, <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/politics-of-the-yalta-frus"
                        >when the U.S. Senate demanded that the Department of State publish the
                        “Yalta papers,”</ref> that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> historians confronted
                    the documentary consequences of the rise of the national security state during
                    and after World War II. Then, in the context of intense partisan scrutiny,
                    determined bureaucratic resistance, and familiar British objections, <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> truly entered the Cold War era.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
