<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s Brush With Death</title>
                <title type="short">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s Brush With Death</title>
                <author>Peter Cozzens</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2012-01-23">January 23, 2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>When Hamilton Fish took office as Secretary of State on March 17, 1869, he
                    inherited both a political and administrative mess. Relations with Congress were
                    terrible. Recently inaugurated President Ulysses S. Grant loathed the powerful
                    Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Charles Sumner. For his
                    part, Sumner quickly became an implacable opponent of the new president’s
                    foreign policy and insinuated himself and his committee into State Department
                    business whenever possible.</p>
                <p>By year’s end, Fish was disgusted with what he considered the Senate’s blatant
                    overstepping of its prerogatives. “The Senate, in fact Congress, but especially
                    the Senate, [has] encroached largely beyond the former line of demarcation
                    between their powers and those of the Executive,” Fish complained to a friend.
                    “They still claim the same extent of power; they wish, practically, to dictate
                    nominations not merely to ‘advise and consult.’ The constitutional power of the
                    Senate is limited to yea or nay upon the names submitted to them.”<note n="1"
                        >Fish to Webb, January 1, 1870, Fish Papers, Container 277, Letters Sent,
                        DLC; Michael J. Devine, “Hamilton Fish,” in Edward S. Mihalkanin, editor,
                            <hi rend="italic">American Statesmen: Secretaries of State from John Jay
                            to Colin Powell</hi> (Westport: Greenwood Press, 2004), 192–93.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although he and Sumner were on cordial terms, Fish had no intention of giving
                    Congress any more information on foreign relations than was absolutely
                    necessary. But first he had to control what Grant revealed about underlying
                    policy in his forthcoming annual message to Congress. On November 22, 1869, he
                    handed President Grant a confidential abstract on foreign relations featuring
                    both a candid appraisal of thorny issues — particularly Cuban belligerency and
                    Spanish colonial rule—and advice as to how Grant should address them. In
                    particular, Fish thought that the Cuban insurrection had run its course and
                    wanted the president to raise no expectations of United States recognition of
                    Cuban belligerency. “I had great sympathy for Cuba, but the Cubans are
                    inefficient and have done nothing for themselves,” he wrote a friend. “They have
                    been all the time crying to Hercules, without putting their own shoulder to the
                    wheel. You cannot help those who will not help themselves.”<note n="2">Fish
                        Diary, November 22, 26 and 27, 1869, to Webb, January 10, 1870, Roll 277;
                        Moore Files, Container 369; and Fish to Charles Sumner, November 26, 1869,
                        Container 188, Letters Sent, all in Fish Papers, LC; Alan Nevins, <hi
                            rend="italic">Hamilton Fish, The Inner Workings of the Grant
                            Administration</hi> (New York: Dodd, Mead, and Company, 1937),
                        294–95.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Grant accepted Fish’s advice but softened the tone of his message. “The people
                    and government of the United States entertain warm feelings and sympathies for
                    the people of Cuba,” he told Congress in his December 6 message, “but the
                    contest has at no time assumed the conditions…sufficient to justify recognition
                    of belligerency.” Moreover, Grant said, the United States had “no disposition to
                    interfere with the existing relations of Spain to her colonial possessions on
                    this continent.”<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic">Message of the President of the United States with the
                            Reports of the Postmaster General and of the Secretary of the Navy</hi>,
                        41st Cong., 2d Sess., H. Ex. Doc. 1, pt. 1 (serial 1445), 7.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On foreign policy, the president’s words stood alone. No State Department
                    correspondence accompanied his annual message; Congress and the nation would
                    have to accept the president’s unsubstantiated appraisal of the Cuban
                        situation.<note n="4">Preceding the report of the Postmaster General and the
                        Secretary of the Navy were two short foreign policy related documents from
                        the State Department: <hi rend="hi">Opinion and Award of the Commissioner
                            under the Treaty of July 1, 1863 between Great Britain and the United
                            States, for the Final Settlement of the Claims of the Hudson’s Bay and
                            Puget Sound Agricultural Companies, Pronounced September 10, 1869</hi>,
                        41st Cong, 2d Sess. H. Ex. Doc. 1, pt. 2 (serial 1411), xxii-xxxviii, and
                            <hi rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Concession for a Submarine
                            Cable, Made by the French Government to the Baron Erlanger and Mr.
                            Julius Reuter</hi>, 41st Cong., 2d Sess., H. Ex. Doc.1, pt. 6 (serial
                        1411), xl-liv. In 1932, the State Department Division of Research and
                        Publication described the manner of their publication as “a return to the
                        practice of 1860 and earlier.” E. Wilder Spaulding to N. Andrew Cleven, July
                        26, 1932, 026 Foreign Relations/592, Department of State Decimal File,
                        1930–1939, RG 59, NA.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Perhaps to deflect possible Congressional complaints about the absence of the
                    yearly <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume, on December 6, 1869,
                    (the date of the president’s annual message), Fish responded to a nine-month old
                    Congressional request for a report on the clerical force of the Department that
                    had been gathering dust. Fish reminded Speaker of the House James G. Blaine
                    that, in 1868, Congress slashed the number of Department clerks from forty-eight
                    to thirty-one. “No [further] reduction in the number or compensation of the
                    clerks now employed is compatible with the public interests,” Fish told Blaine,
                    adding pointedly, “With so large a reduction the business of the Department is
                    already seriously embarrassed.” Congressional parsimony came at a cost.<note
                        n="5">Hamilton Fish to James G. Blaine, December 6, 1869, in “Reports of the
                        Secretary to the President and Congress,” Volume 10, page 198, Miscellaneous
                        Correspondence of the Department of State, 1784–1906, RG 59, NA; <hi
                            rend="italic">Clerks in the State Department</hi>, 41st Cong. 2d Sess.,
                        H. Ex. Doc 9 (serial 1416), 1–2.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Fish always maintained that staff cuts and the reshuffling of ministers
                    occasioned by a new administration had precluded preparation of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> for 1869. Three years later, when House
                    Foreign Affairs Committee Chairman Nathaniel P. Banks asked him why there had
                    been no <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> 1869, Fish reminded him “that
                    the period alluded to embraces that in which many changes in the diplomatic
                    agents of the government were made. The clerical force in the Department was
                    small and much occupied at the close of the year, and for these reasons no
                    publication was made.” Fish might have added that his staff was cleaning up
                    behind former Secretary of State William F. Seward, preparing <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> 1868 for a tardy submission to Congress with Grant’s
                    December 1869 annual message.<note n="6">Hamilton Fish to Nathaniel P. Banks,
                        May 18, 1872, in “Reports of the Secretary to the President and Congress,”
                        Volume 11, page 199, Miscellaneous Correspondence of the Department of
                        State, 1784–1906. RG 59, NA. Staff shortages plagued the Department
                        throughout the remainder of the nineteenth century as it sought to balance
                        preparation of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes and
                        responses to Congressional requests for correspondence with other work.
                        Referring to a Senate call for correspondence in March 1888, Secretary of
                        State Thomas F. Bayard told the chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee
                        that “this Department is now actively engaged in preparing an answer to this
                        resolution, which will require much clerical labor as the papers asked for
                        have increased to a considerable volume since 1871.” Thomas F. Bayard to
                        George F. Edmunds, March 27, 1888, <hi rend="italic">Reports of the
                            Secretary and President to Congress</hi>, A1, Entry 145, Volume 17, 141,
                        RG 59, NA</note>
                </p>
                <p>Historians writing on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> have wrongly
                    attributed the break in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> to Hamilton
                    Fish, when in fact Seward halted the series in 1868. That year, outgoing
                    President Andrew Johnson transmitted no diplomatic correspondence with his last
                    annual message to Congress. This should come as no surprise. Relations between
                    the executive and legislative branches were frosty at best. From February 1868,
                    when the House of Representatives impeached him, until May 1868, when the Senate
                    acquitted him by one vote, Johnson was locked in a death struggle with Congress.
                    Secretary Seward staunchly supported Johnson. Between March and November 1868,
                    he sent no formal correspondence to Congress, not even on the most routine
                        matters.<note n="7">“Reports of the Secretary to the President and
                        Congress,” Volume 10, Misc. Correspondence of the Department of State,
                        1784–1906, RG 59, NA.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Staff constraints and the press of other Congressionally-mandated business may
                    also partly explain why the Johnson administration did not transmit diplomatic
                    correspondence to Congress with the president’s 1868 message. The preceding
                    December, the Senate adopted resolutions calling for the State Department to
                    provide all correspondence pertaining to the Alabama claims case. The most
                    pressing and potentially explosive diplomatic issue of the day, the Alabama
                    claims case pitted the United States against Great Britain in a dispute over the
                    British government’s liability for losses to Union merchant vessels suffered at
                    the hands of the Confederate commerce raider Alabama during the Civil War.
                    Completing work begun under Seward, Secretary Fish submitted the Alabama
                    correspondence, which ran to four volumes totaling three thousand pages, a month
                    into the Grant administration. Undoubtedly the clerks who normally would have
                    compiled <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> had their hands full with the
                    Alabama papers.<note n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Correspondence Concerning Claims against Great
                            Britain</hi>, 41st Cong. 1st Sess. S. Ex. Doc. 11 (serial 1440), 4; <hi
                            rend="italic">Register of the Department of State</hi> (Washington:
                        Government Publishing Office, 1870), 8.</note>
                </p>
                <p>When the two-volume <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> 1868 appeared in
                    December 1869, it was met with silence: the press ignored it,<note n="9">All
                        conclusions regarding U. S. newspaper coverage of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> in this paper are based on a search of the one
                        thousand-plus contemporaneous newspapers contained in <ref
                            target="http://www.newspaperarchives.com"
                            >http://www.newspaperarchives.com</ref>, together with those contained
                        in the Library of Congress project <hi rend="italic">Chronicling America:
                            American Historic Newspapers</hi>, <ref
                            target="http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/"
                            >http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/</ref>
                    </note> and Congress did not question its late appearance.</p>
                <p>But Congress did want more than the simple recounting of Grant’s foreign policy
                    priorities—particularly with respect to Cuba. On December 8, 1869, the Senate
                    requested—with the usual caveat “if not incompatible with the public
                    interest”—any information [Fish] may have in regard to the progress of the
                    revolution and the political and civil condition of the island [of Cuba].”<note
                        n="10">Normally Congress simply requested any correspondence that the
                        Department might have on a subject; in this case the request was directed to
                        Fish by name.</note> Five days later, the House passed a similar resolution.
                    When Fish tried to pigeonhole the resolutions, the hostile but influential New
                    York Herald Tribune demanded Fish produce the Cuba correspondence and implored
                    Congress to take no “steps in the dark regarding our foreign relations.”<note
                        n="11">Hamilton Fish to Ulysses S. Grant, December 14, 1869, in “Reports of
                        the Secretary to the President and Congress,” Volume 10, 208, Misc.
                        Correspondence., Entry 145, RG 59, NA; <hi rend="italic">New York Herald
                            Tribune</hi>, December 9, 1869</note>
                </p>
                <p>Congress had no such intention. On December 17, Senator Sumner sent Fish a terse
                    note insisting he comply with the resolutions. On January 7, 1870, the House
                    passed a second resolution demanding the same.<note n="12">Charles Sumner to
                        Hamilton Fish, December 17, 1869, Letters Received, Container 188, Fish
                        Papers.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Fish yielded. On December 20, President Grant (the president always transmitted
                    the Department’s response to calls for document with a brief cover letter)
                    responded to the Senate request; in February 1870, he complied with the House
                    request.</p>
                <p>Fish’s compliance with the Congressional resolutions on Cuba reflected no
                    softening in his sentiments about transparency. On the contrary, it hardened his
                    determination to give Congress no more than it specifically requested and caused
                    him to invoke the “incompatible with the public interest” caveat whenever
                    possible to deny legislative branch requests. President Grant also became
                    secretive. In late March he told Fish “not to communicate to Sumner any
                    confidential or important information received at the Department—that he
                    probably without knowing it, is unfair and not accurate in his representation of
                    what he receives from the Department—that he has represented me [Fish] as
                    opposed to the San Domingo Treaty and otherwise misrepresented the
                    administration and its views.”<note n="13">Fish Diary, March 30, 1870, Microfilm
                        Roll 277, Fish Papers.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The tussle with Congress over Cuba also caused Fish to consider abolishing the
                    annual <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes; or rather, not to
                    resuscitate them after 1869. In an unofficial dispatch dated January 17, 1870,
                    Fish told the U. S. Minister to Austria John Jay, Jr. that “the publication of
                    the Diplomatic Correspondence has been discontinued.”<note n="14">Hamilton Fish
                        to John Jay, Jr., January 17, 1870, Letters Sent, Container 277, Fish
                        Papers; <hi rend="italic">New York Herald Tribune</hi>, December 12, 1869;
                            <hi rend="italic">Cincinnati Daily Inquirer</hi>, December 16,
                        1869.</note>
                </p>
                <p>But it wasn’t. As Fish discovered, unless he was willing to repeatedly defy
                    Congress, the decision to release diplomatic correspondence was not his to make.
                    During 1870 Congress passed more resolutions calling for diplomatic
                    correspondence than it would in any subsequent year of the nineteenth century.
                    By year’s end, Fish had provided Congress with 600 documents totaling 859 pages,
                    all of which Congress published in documents that when aggregated equaled the
                    size of a typical <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume. In December
                    1870, Fish resumed the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series, and it
                    has continued uninterrupted to this day.</p>
                <p>Neither Fish’s diary of his tenure as secretary of state or his personal papers
                    reveals his reasons for resuming <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>. But
                    persistent Congressional calls for correspondence in 1869 would appear to have
                    been the deciding factor.<note n="15">I also examined Fish’s correspondence with
                        Sumner as contained in the Charles Sumner Papers, Harvard University.
                        Department Historical Advisor Tyler Dennett said Fish “was forced by the
                        necessities of the case to resume it under the name with which it is now
                        familiar to us,” but does not elaborate. No one else writing on <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> has ventured a guess as to why Fish
                        resumed the series. (Dennett, “Governmental Publications,” 56). Nearly half
                        the 1870 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume dealt with the
                        Franco-Prussian War, most of the remaining correspondence was devoted to
                        American fishing rights in Canadian waters and to the Tientsin massacre and
                        flight of American missionaries from China. A smattering of correspondence
                        pertaining to nations other than Great Britain, France, Prussia, and China
                        rounded out the volume. Perhaps because he had given Congress nearly 500
                        Cuba-related documents during the course of the summer, Fish did not include
                        any subsequent correspondence on the subject.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series survived because Fish came to
                    recognize, as did subsequent secretaries, that the annual volumes provided a
                    relatively painless way of partially satisfying the foreign policy oversight
                    prerogatives of Congress. Because the contents of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> were contemporaneous, the volumes also provided a means for
                    the executive branch to amplify its foreign policy goals or trumpet its
                    successes. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> became emblematic of
                    transparency in government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
