<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s War in the Pacific</title>
                <title type="short">
                    <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s War in the Pacific</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-09-15">September 15, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In the mid-1930s, current and retired U.S. diplomats complained that <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes provided too much transparency
                    for the Department of State’s own good.<note n="1">Cornelius Engert personal
                        telegram to Wallace Murray, November 6, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1099 and
                        DeWitt Poole letter to Secretary of State, June 21, 1937, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1187 in Department of State Central Decimal Files 1930-1939,
                        Record Group 59, Archives II, College Park, Maryland (henceforth DoS CDF
                        1930-1939).</note> In response, the chief of the Division of
                    Publications—and editor of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series—Cyril Wynne explained the careful process that Department historians
                    undertook, in collaboration with other officials, to compile, edit, and
                    declassify documents for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes.<note
                        n="2">Cyril Wynne, “Memorandum on the subject of Dr. D. C. Poole’s letter of
                        June 21, 1937, which includes a statement giving the background of the
                        present system of preparing the Foreign Relations volumes,” July 13, 1937,
                        026 Foreign Relations/1210 and Cyril Wynne memorandum to Acting Secretary,
                        November 12, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1099 in DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note>
                    Wynne placed special emphasis on Ambassador <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/grew-joseph-clark">Joseph Grew’s</ref>
                    support for the series since he “served in the most difficult post in our entire
                    Foreign Service”—Japan.<note n="3">Cyril Wynne memorandum to Acting Secretary,
                        November 12, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1099, pp. 2-3. In 1925, Grew had
                        been Undersecretary of State. In his memorandum explaining the <hi
                            rend="italic">FRUS</hi> production process, Wynne characterized Grew as
                        playing a significant role in crafting the Departmental order that governed
                        the series. See Cyril Wynne, “Memorandum on the subject of Dr. D. C. Poole’s
                        letter of June 21, 1937…” July 13, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1210, p.
                        6.</note> While Grew’s appreciation of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was
                    genuine, the Japanese government had grown both weary and wary of the series by
                    1936.</p>
                <p>In 1925, a Department order established for the first time explicit guidelines
                    for the production of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. One
                    of these guidelines was that the permission of foreign governments had to be
                    obtained before their documents could be published. The order also allowed for
                    documents to be omitted from <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> if necessary to
                    “preserve the confidence reposed in the Department by other governments.”<note
                        n="4">The March 26, 1925 order was first published in the preface to <hi
                            rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United
                            States, 1914 Supplement: The World War</hi> (Washington, DC: Government
                        Printing Office, 1928), pp. iii-iv. Contemporary documentation for the
                        origins of the March 26, 1925 order has not been found. The most detailed
                        explanation for the order appears in Cyril Wynne, “Memorandum on the subject
                        of Dr. D. C. Poole’s letter of June 21, 1937, which includes a statement
                        giving the background of the present system of preparing the Foreign
                        Relations volumes,” July 13, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1210, DoS CDF
                        1930-1939, pp. 4-22. In the 19th century, foreign government “equities” were
                        ignored. See Frederick Frelinghuysen to Philip Morgan, August 28, 1883, pp.
                        657-658, Diplomatic Instructions—Mexico, M77, Reel 116, RG 59, Archives
                        II.</note> During the 1930s, delays in foreign government clearances were
                    the most significant obstacle to accelerating the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> series; Japan proved especially troublesome.</p>
                <p>In the first months of 1934, delays in receiving Japanese clearances postponed
                    publication of the 1919 volume. The Japanese government attributed these
                    “embarrassing” holdups to personnel turnover within the Foreign Office.<note
                        n="5">See <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>., 026 Foreign Relations/ 677 through
                        026 Foreign Relations/ 694, DoS CDF 1930-1939. For the reporting of the
                        Japanese Government’s explanation of the delay, see Joseph Grew despatch to
                        Secretary of State, February 20, 1934, 026 Foreign Relations/688, p.
                        2.</note> In September of that year, after Washington sent documents for the
                    1920 volume to Tokyo, Grew reported that a Japanese official “felt that 1920 was
                    rather recent and that many documents were not ‘dead’ in so short a time; that
                    the Japanese Government felt embarrassment at being compelled to give consent
                    and in other cases to withhold consent for publication.”<note n="6">Joseph Grew
                        despatch to Secretary of State, September 5, 1934, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/761, DoS CDF 1930-1939, p. 2.</note> Early in 1935, Grew reported
                    that the Japanese media interpreted the publication of diplomatic correspondence
                    between the United States and Japan as part of Washington’s campaign to
                    delegitimize Tokyo’s puppet state, Manchukuo.<note n="7">Joseph Grew despatch to
                        Secretary of State, Februar y 2, 1935, 026 Foreign Relations/816, DoS CDF
                        1930-1939.</note> Japanese Foreign Minister Koki Hirota criticized the
                    Department’s policy of determining when a foreign government’s consent to
                    publish a particular document was required; he claimed that Tokyo should be
                    consulted before printing U.S. documents “when they contain views or information
                    specifically forwarded by the Japanese Government as confidential.”<note n="8"
                        >Koki Hirota note to Joseph Grew, April 30, 1935, 026 Foreign Relations/866,
                        DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note> Though the Department assured Tokyo of its
                    “friendly disposition in the matter,” it refused to alter its policies regarding
                    foreign government equities.<note n="9">William Phillips instruction to Joseph
                        Grew, July 15, 1935, 026 Foreign Relations/878, DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note> By
                    the end of the year, the Department had “long since (six months ago) heard from
                    every other government on the publication of their respective documents in the
                    1921 Foreign Relations volume; as usual Japan [was] far behind the others.”<note
                        n="10">Cyril Wynne memorandum to Stanley Hornbeck, December 4, 1935, 026
                        Foreign Relations/938, DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Matters only grew thornier in 1936. In January, the Department sought to publish
                    documents concerning the secret protocol of the 1917 <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Lansing</ref>-Ishii
                    Agreement, wherein both countries agreed to exercise restraint in China during
                    World War I.<note n="11">William Phillips instruction to Joseph Grew, February
                        21, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/987, DoS CDF 1930-1939. Robert Lansing was
                        Secretary of State from 1915 to 1920.</note> Cyril Wynne admitted that this
                    was done primarily to “prevent the Department from being criticized for not
                    publishing the well-known ‘secret clause’ in the 1922 Foreign Relations volume.”
                    If the Japanese Government was responsible for excluding the records, then the
                    Department might escape blame from “those who are a bit critical of what is
                    described as the ‘Hush! Hush!’ policy in publishing Foreign Relations.”<note
                        n="12">Cyril Wynne memorandum, May 19, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1032, DoS
                        CDF 1930-1939.</note> The publication of Robert Lansing’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >War Memoirs</hi> and Samuel Flagg Bemis’s <hi rend="italic">A Diplomatic
                        History of the United States</hi>, both of which quoted the secret protocol,
                    prompted Wynne to suggest that Grew apprise the Japanese Government of the
                    publicity that these revelations received in the United States so that Tokyo
                    could not complain when the Department of State had to explain that the
                    associated documents had been omitted from <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> at Japan’s behest.<note n="13">Cyril Wynne memorandum to
                        Stanley Hornbeck, October 10, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1097 and R. Walton
                        Moore instruction to Erle Dickover, November 2, 1936, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1098 in DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note> When informed that the documents
                    were publically available, the Japanese Government granted permission to print
                    them in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> but requested “in [the] future, when
                    American officials after retirement desire to publish such confidential
                    documents relating to Japan,” that “the consent of the Japanese Government be
                    first sought.”<note n="14">Joseph Grew telegram to Secretary of State, December
                        28, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1125 and Grew despatch to Secretary of
                        State, December 29, 1936, 026 Foreign Relations/1136 in DoS CDF
                        1930-1939.</note>
                </p>
                <p>By 1938, when pressure to accelerate <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> from the
                    academic community led the Department to ask foreign governments if they would
                    agree in principle to the publication of documents on an earlier basis than a
                    fifteen year delay,<note n="15">Raymond Lawrence letter to Secretary of State,
                        November 8, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1262; Cyril Wynne memorandum,
                        November 15, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1263; Raymond Lawrence letter to R.
                        Walton Moore, December 9, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1294; Raymond Lawrence
                        letter to Thomas McMillan, December 9, 1937, 026 Foreign Relations/1296;
                        Fletcher Green letter to Cordell Hull, December 11, 1937, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1299; Dexter Perkins letter to Secretary of State (with enclosed
                        resolutions from the American Historical Association), January 25, 1938, 026
                        Foreign Relations/1325; Louis Hunter letter to Robert Bacon, February 17,
                        1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1346; Cyril Wynne memorandum to George
                        Messersmith, April 21, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1357; Raymond Lawrence
                        letter to R. Walton Moore, February 19, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1374;
                        Cyril Wynne memorandum to Jay Moffat, Charles Hosmer, and George
                        Messersmith, January 26, 1939, 026 Foreign Relations/1400 in DOS CDF
                        1930-1939.</note> officials agreed that even broaching the idea with Tokyo
                    would “result in the Japanese Foreign Office making use of the occasion to
                    insist on widening the present gap rather than shortening it.”<note n="16"
                        >Joseph Grew instruction to Secretary of State, March 31, 1938, 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1357, p. 2, DoS CDF 1930-1939. Wynne used this despatch to explain
                        the difficulties of reducing the fifteen year line to interlocutors in the
                        academic community. See Maxwell Hamilton note, November 16, 1937, 026
                        Foreign Relations/1264; George Messersmith despatch to Joseph Grew, March 2,
                        1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1356a; and Cyril Wynne memorandum to George
                        Messersmith, April 21, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1357 in DoS CDF
                        1930-1939.</note> Japan was not the only foreign power wary of an earlier
                    release of diplomatic documents near the end of the decade; the French
                    Government also opposed accelerating <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi>.<note n="17">Edwin Wilson despatch to Secretary of State,
                        September 9, 1938, 026 Foreign Relations/1388, DoS CDF 1930-1939.</note>
                    Even the nine governments that accepted earlier publication in principle
                    insisted that the U.S. Government continue to submit their own documents for
                        clearance.<note n="18">See <ref
                            target="http://images.library.wisc.edu/FRUS/EFacs/1938v01/reference/frus.frus1938v01.i0024.pdf">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States: Diplomatic
                                Papers 1938, Volume I: General</hi> (Washington, DC: Government
                            Printing Office, 1955), pp. 976-987</ref>; Cyril Wynne memorandum to
                        Ellis Briggs, Wallace Murray, Maxwell Hamilton, Jay Moffat, Charles Hosmer,
                        and George Messersmith, February 20, 1939, 026 Foreign Relations/1402, DoS
                        CDF 1930-1939.</note> In the tense atmosphere of the late 1930s, releasing
                    sensitive documents that drew attention to the post-World War I settlement
                    seemed unnecessarily risky to many in Europe and East Asia, but essential to
                    democratic accountability among academics and Congress. As my next post will
                    show, the conflicting imperatives of transparency and national security grew
                    increasingly tougher to reconcile as the 1930s ended and the Second World War
                    loomed. </p>
                <p>
                    <lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
