<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">International Reaction to Lincoln’s Death</title>
                <title type="short">International Reaction to Lincoln’s Death</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-12-12">December 12, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="lincoln.jpg"/>
                    <head>This photograph of Lincoln was taken on March 6, 1865, shortly before he
                        was assassinated. (Photo credit: Wikimedia Commons)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>April 1865 was an extraordinary month in the history of the Civil War. On the
                    9th, Confederate General Robert E. Lee surrendered to Lieutenant General Ulysses
                    S. Grant at Appomattox Court House, Virginia, effectively ending the war. Just
                    days later, the nation was rocked by the news that President Abraham Lincoln had
                    been assassinated in Washington, DC.</p>
                <p>The news of Lincoln’s death reverberated around the world and led to an
                    extraordinary publication by the Department of State in 1866. In addition to the
                    usual diplomatic correspondence published in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations
                        of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) volumes, a separate
                    volume consisting entirely of condolences was published. The volume, <hi
                        rend="italic">
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1865p4">The Assassination of Abraham
                            Lincoln, Late President of the United States of America, and the
                            Attempted Assassination of William H. Seward, Secretary of State, and
                            Frederick W. Seward, Assistant Secretary, on the Evening of the 14th of
                            April, 1865,</ref>
                    </hi> collected correspondence from every corner of the globe.</p>
                <p>Lincoln was the first U.S. president to be assassinated. Thus, his death was a
                    test for the country and the strength of its constitutional plan of succession.
                    Some countries noted this fact, and their acknowledgement of Andrew Johnson’s
                    presidency demonstrated that his government was viewed as legitimate in the eyes
                    of the world community. The response from China, for example, embodied both
                    regret and reassurance that the transfer of power was perceived as smooth.
                    Prince Kung, Chief Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, wrote on July 8,
                    1865, that the announcement of Lincoln’s death “inexpressibly shocked and
                    startled me.” Nevertheless, the news that “on the same day the Vice-President
                    succeeded to the position without any disturbance, and the assassin had been
                    arrested, so that the affairs of government were going on quietly as usual”
                    seemed to satisfy the Prince’s worry, and he hoped that these facts would also
                    “alleviate your grief at the event.”</p>
                <p>Other governments sent their official expressions of regret and condolence. <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hassaurek-frederick-friedrich">Frederick
                        Hassaurek</ref>, U.S. Minister to Ecuador, reported on May 29 that the
                    Ecuadorian government had ordered “that all the officers and
                    employés<!--not sure how to encode the accented e!--> of the republic of Ecuador
                    shall wear mourning for three days, during which time the Ecuadorian flag shall
                    be displayed at half-mast from all the public buildings.” Additionally,
                    Ecuadorian President Gabriel Garcia Moreno wrote to Hassaurek on May 22 that
                    “The fatal news which arrived by yesterday’s mail has produced a profound and
                    painful impression on me. Never should I have through that the noble country of
                    Washington would be humiliated by such a black and horrible crime; nor should I
                    ever have though that Mr. Lincoln would come to such a horrible end, after
                    having served his country which such wisdom and glory under so critical
                    circumstances.”</p>
                <p>In the United Kingdom, British Foreign Minister Earl Russell wrote to U.S.
                    Minister <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles
                        Francis Adams</ref> on May 1 that Lincoln’s death was a “sad calamity” and
                    recalled that he had already “conveyed to you by letter and in person the deep
                    impression of horror and indignation which so atrocious a crime on the President
                    of the United States had made upon me.” Russell went on to write that “by the
                    command of the Queen, I have directed her Majesty’s minister at Washington to
                    convey to the government of the United States” the condolences of the British
                    government and British people. From Egypt, Agent and Consul General <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hale-charles">Charles Hale</ref> reported
                    on May 5 that “the Pacha of Egypt, has seized the earliest opportunity to
                    express to me the pain with which he has heard the sad tidings of the
                    assassination of the President of the United States, his detestation of the
                    abominable crime, and his sympathy for our country in the grievous loss we have
                    sustained.”</p>
                <p>In the <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-first-volume"
                        >first volume of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    </ref> (and <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/marrs-on-the-first-volume"
                        >here</ref>), Lincoln had urged the United States to recognize Haiti and
                    Liberia, two countries with unique relationships to slavery. The Haitian
                    Revolution at the turn of the nineteenth century terminated slavery in that
                    country, and soon after Liberia was settled by liberated slaves from the United
                    States. In 1862, the United States recognized both countries, and in 1865 both
                    countries reacted to Lincoln’s death. The Liberian proclamation mourned a man
                    who “was not only the ruler of his own people, but a father to millions of a
                    race stricken and oppressed.” Arguing that Lincoln had “died to redeem a nation,
                    a race,” the Liberians predicted that “generations yet unborn shall call him the
                    mighty ruler, the great emancipator, the noble philanthropist.” The Secretary of
                    the Haitian Legation in the United States denounced the assassination as a
                    “horrid crime,” and noted that the death of Lincoln and the attempt on the life
                    of both Sewards “have thrown the whole United States into consternation and
                    mourning, [and] will everywhere excite the same wail of sorrow and
                    condemnation.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="assassination-of-lincoln.jpg"/>
                    <head>This 1865 print from Currier and Ives depicts the assassination. (Photo
                        credit: Wikimedia Commons)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Perhaps one of the most remarkable parts of the volume comes not from the
                    official expressions of sorrow but the messages sent spontaneously from other
                    groups of citizens all over the globe. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> does not
                    usually publish “unofficial,” non-governmental correspondence, but this volume
                    includes a healthy selection of just that type of correspondence. A group of
                    Freemasons in France wrote to President Johnson that they “wish[ed] to express
                    to you their sentiments of admiration, gratitude, and regret for Lincoln, and
                    their profound sympathy for the government of which you are the head. The blood
                    of your martyred magistrate becomes a fecundating dew to give to liberty a new
                    baptism throughout the entire universe.” The residents of Lahaina, in the
                    Hawaiian Islands, passed resolutions in which they “weep together with the
                    republic of America for the murder, the assassination of the great, the good,
                    the liberator Abraham Lincoln, the victim of hell-born treason—himself martyred,
                    yet live his mighty deeds, victory, peace, and the emancipation of those
                    despised, like all of us of the colored races.” A group of workingmen in the
                    Prussian capital of Berlin noted that Lincoln was a laborer’s son and “himself a
                    laborer, he took up the fight for the rights of free labor and carried it to a
                    triumphant termination.” While mourning his death, the laborers noted that “the
                    freedom which has thus been sealed with the blood of one of the noblest men”
                    will ultimately be victorious, and that the U.S. flag will represent “the cause
                    of freedom and civilization” wherever it flies.</p>
                <p>This special volume of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> documents a remarkable
                    outpouring of grief at the news of Lincoln’s death. Official expressions of
                    sympathy from governments were printed side-by-side with resolutions and
                    proclamations from groups of citizens. A century and a half after his time in
                    office, Lincoln still looms large as one of our most significant presidents. The
                    documents in this volume confirm that his stature around the world was already
                    in place at the time of his death.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
