<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">The First <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> Volume of 1861</title>
                <title type="short">The First <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Volume of 1861</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-09-30">September 30, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                    <!-- Start of Brightcove Player -->
                    <div style="display:none"/>
                    <!--By use of this code snippet, I agree to the Brightcove Publisher T and C found at https://accounts.brightcove.com/en/terms-and-conditions/. -->
                    <script type="text/javascript"
                        src="http://admin.brightcove.com/js/BrightcoveExperiences.js"/>
                    <object id="myExperience1177738320001" class="BrightcoveExperience">
                        <param name="bgcolor" value="#FFFFFF"/>
                        <param name="width" value="486"/>
                        <param name="height" value="412"/>
                        <param name="playerID" value="642900215001"/>
                        <param name="playerKey"
                            value="AQ~~,AAAAAGWqYgE~,KxHPzbPALrGbr42hNpx45lOyQ1a-Nw88"/>
                        <param name="isVid" value="true"/>
                        <param name="dynamicStreaming" value="true"/>
                        <param name="@videoPlayer" value="1177738320001"/>
                    </object>
                    <!-- This script tag will cause the Brightcove Players defined above it to be created as soon as the line is read by the browser. If you wish to have the player instantiated only after the rest of the HTML is processed and the page load is complete, remove the line.-->
                    <script type="text/javascript">brightcove.createExperiences();</script>
                    <!-- End of Brightcove Player -->
                </div>
                <p rend="italic">A brief video with accompanying transcript of Dr. Aaron Marrs
                    speaking about his research into why the first volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series was released in 1861
                    amidst the Civil War, the precedents for such a release of foreign relations
                    documentation, and the reception of the first volume.</p>
                <p>I’m Aaron Marrs, a historian at the Office of the Historian in the U.S.
                    Department of State, and I’m here today because I’ve been working on our
                    research project on the sesquicentennial of <ref target="/historicaldocuments"
                        >the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series</ref>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Why was the volume released in 1861?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the summer of 1861, the U.S. Congress was very concerned about the efforts the
                    Confederacy was making to gain recognition overseas. The Confederacy believed
                    that its cotton would be a very powerful weapon and wanted to use this economic
                    leverage to gain recognition from other countries. And so that summer, the U.S.
                    Senate and the House passed resolutions asking the President to inform Congress
                    of all the documentation demonstrating the actions taken by the Department of
                    State to prevent the Confederacy from gaining recognition. So on December 3,
                    1861, the Executive branch responded to those resolutions by releasing <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-first-volume">the
                        first <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume</ref>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Was this the first time the federal government released
                        foreign relations documentation?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>No. In fact, ad hoc releases had been taking place since the beginning of the
                    republic from the administration of President George Washington. Usually what
                    would happen is that when a treaty was signed, Congress would receive
                    documentation along with a copy of the treaty. And so, this had been happening
                    throughout the early republic and antebellum years and therefore represents an
                    important part of the balance of power between the different branches of
                    government. The Executive branch executes foreign policy, but the Legislative
                    branch reserves the right to monitor that policy by requesting this type of
                    documentation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(What makes this volume unique?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There are a couple of reasons. First of all, for the first time <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus"
                        >documents from all over the globe</ref> were brought under a single cover,
                    so rather than just having a single issue be covered, this was about the entire
                    world. Second of all, there was much more public attention given to this volume,
                    obviously because of the ongoing Civil War. And then third, even though they
                    didn’t know it at the time, this would serve to launch the annual regular
                    publication of foreign relations documentation instead of the ad hoc releases
                    that had taken place previously.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Were Lincoln and Seward personally involved with the
                        volume?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Unfortunately, we don’t have a lot of direct information about how the first
                    volume was put together, so we can’t say definitively that Abraham Lincoln or
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                        Seward</ref> chose the documents. However, we do have a lot of indirect
                    evidence about their involvement. First of all, the Department of State was very
                    small in the 1860s—there were only three or four dozen domestic employees,
                    period, in Washington at that time. So, given the size of the Department, and
                    given the importance of this documentation, it is difficult to imagine that
                    Secretary Seward wouldn’t have known about such a project, even if he didn’t
                    select the documents himself. Second of all, we know that in 1864, Seward
                    defended the series against complaints by some of our ministers overseas that
                    important documentations were being released, and in a long letter that he wrote
                    to <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles Francis
                        Adams</ref>, our minister in London, he said that for a democracy of our
                    type, it was important for the federal government to be transparent. So, from
                    that we know that he felt the series was important.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(What was the domestic reaction to the volume?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The domestic reaction was <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus">very
                        positive</ref>. Newspapers up and down the East Coast published portions of
                    the volume as soon as it came out, and then if you look at newspapers moving
                    across the country, we can see how the information spread. Newspapers in the
                    Midwest carried it later in December, and then by January 1862, the information
                    reached California.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Did the volumes continue throughout the Civil War?)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Yes, they did. Volumes were released every year in the Civil War, and the series
                    continued through the present day, as we know it, so we’re celebrating <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history">150 years</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
