<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“Out of the Frying Pan Into the Fire”: The Politics of the
                    Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                </title>
                <title type="short">The Politics of the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                </title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-06-24">June 24, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This paper was prepared for delivery at the SHAFR Annual Conference in
                    Alexandria, VA.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Throughout the 20th century, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series
                    evolved in response to broader transformations in American foreign relations,
                    government institutions, and political culture. The most enduring of these
                    transformations occurred in the 1950s, when the series adapted to the
                    development of the national security state and the globalization of U.S. power.
                    The intense bureaucratic, partisan, and international controversies generated by
                    the 1955 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume for the 1945 Yalta conference helped
                    define the series for the Cold War.</p>
                <p>The Yalta volume precipitated the transformation of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>,
                    though the controversies that it sparked also imperiled the existence of the
                    series. The most enduring legacies of the “Yalta papers” were methodological
                    changes that widened the series’ scope beyond State Department records and the
                    creation of a Historical Advisory Committee to insulate the series from partisan
                    pressures. In the short run, however, the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> also
                    emboldened officials in the U.S. Government skeptical of the value of
                    transparency in a dangerous world.</p>
                <p>The Yalta volume began as a classified policy study for official use within the
                    U.S. Government in November 1947. Unlike contemporary <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> volumes, State Department historians intended from the start to
                    include documents from outside the State Department, especially records from the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff (JCS), the Roosevelt Presidential Library, and the White
                    House in the Yalta compilation. In 1950, the question of wider publication arose
                    as partisan debate over the conference intensified. Bernard Noble, head of the
                    Historical Policy Research Division, advised Secretary of State Dean Acheson
                    that the existing public record was “substantially complete” from the memoir
                    literature and that publishing the documents posed several risks. He warned that
                    portions of conference minutes might embarrass the U.S. and Britain, that the
                    lack of agreed minutes might allow the Soviet Union to release an “alternate”
                    version of the conference to galvanize world opinion against the West, and that
                    the Department’s poor wartime record-keeping left it incapable of satisfying
                    inevitable public demands for releasing the records of the other conferences.
                    Choosing security over transparency, the Department kept the Yalta records
                    secret.</p>
                <p>After Dwight D. Eisenhower’s 1952 election, the new, conservative Congressional
                    majority urged a different choice. On April 22, Senate Majority Leader William
                    Knowland sent a letter to Secretary of State John Foster Dulles characterizing
                    “Department of State archives” as “a rich mine of historical materials of
                    immediate political significance.” The letter blamed “old-line administrators”
                    and “Roosevelt-Acheson supporters” in the State Department for “stalling
                    publications of any political importance for the Republicans.” In addition to
                    accelerating regular <hi rend="italic">FRUS </hi>volumes and a special series on
                    U.S.-Chinese relations in the 1940s, Knowland requested a special series on
                    secret Allied wartime conferences. “If Democratic holdovers in the Division of
                    Historical Policy Research are prevented from excluding key documents,” Knowland
                    predicted, “these publications would be of tremendous value.” </p>
                <p>An investigation of the newly renamed Historical Division (HD) exonerated the
                    office of Knowland’s allegations of partisanship, but allegations of liberal
                    bias dogged its leadership for many years. The most significant critic of HD was
                    Bryton Barron, a staff member assigned the responsibility of compiling the Yalta
                    volume. Barron complained that the Department was rife with New Deal-supporting
                    Acheson disciples and that HD management obstructed the rapid and complete
                    disclosure of the U.S. records of Yalta to the American people. After a brief
                    burst of optimism that the Republican victories in 1952 would purge the
                    Department of these liberals, Barron grew increasingly frustrated as Noble
                    remained in charge of HD and obstacles to fulfilling Knowland’s requests for <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> mounted. To Barron, the difficulties encountered in
                    researching, declassifying, and releasing the Yalta compilation reflected a
                    conspiracy to cover up Roosevelt’s foreign policy failures rather than policy
                    and institutional frictions generated by Cold War tensions and proliferating
                    national security bureaucracies in Washington. Eventually, he leaked information
                    about the contents of the Yalta compilation and internal debates over its
                    release to the press.</p>
                <p>The continued sensitivity of many of the issues discussed at the wartime
                    conferences and the partisan aura of the accelerated production of <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS </hi>alarmed other government agencies and former
                    officials. It took years for HD to gain access to Truman’s papers for the
                    Potsdam compilation, and the office was denied permission to examine the papers
                    of the deceased Yalta Secretary of State, Edward Stettinius. Even some
                    bureaucracies that had cooperated with the original policy study resisted
                    additional requests. The most consequential bureaucratic opposition to releasing
                    the Yalta volume came from the Pentagon. </p>
                <p>Since the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations </hi>series had previously relied
                    almost exclusively on the records found in the central files of the Department
                    of State, the Historical Division had no established procedures for interagency
                    research access or declassification review. In the context of tight deadlines
                    and Congressional scrutiny, the Departments of State and Defense struggled to
                    devise new arrangements fusing conflicting institutional priorities in a messy
                    process of trial, error, and recrimination. Despite the Secretary of Defense’s
                    pledge of cooperation, his chief historian, Rudy Winnacker, repeatedly recoiled
                    at Noble’s efforts to examine military records. Though Winnacker agreed that the
                    wartime conference volumes had to include “high-level” papers containing
                    “official [military] positions and advice,” he and the JCS insisted that this
                    “agreed scope” be defined as narrowly as possible. An April 1954 meeting at the
                    White House between Noble and Winnacker to clarify the Pentagon’s role and
                    responsibilities for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> reduced bureaucratic friction
                    but failed to harmonize thinking between State and Defense. These bureaucratic
                    tensions over <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> continued to plague the project,
                    jeopardizing Congressionally mandated deadlines and, ultimately, the future
                    shape of the series. <hi rend="italic"/>
                </p>
                <p> Over the course of 1954, historians in HD felt increasingly beleaguered. The
                    House Appropriations Committee eliminated all funding for <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> compilation and publishing in the spring, before its Senate
                    counterpart restored the appropriation. More significantly, powerful opponents
                    of publishing the Yalta volume tried to scuttle the project entirely in the
                    second half of the year. In an August 1954 review of the first galley proofs of
                    the volume, Winnacker expressed “a sense of shock when reading in the present
                    EDC atmosphere the actual 1945 plans for the postwar treatment of Germany, its
                    dismemberment, reparations, and standard of living” and thought “the cavalier
                    disposal of smaller countries or the attitude toward France” were “not likely to
                    facilitate our foreign relations.” Winnacker warned that gaps and the selective
                    inclusion of pre-conference documents would discredit the publication. He
                    suggested either abandoning the project, allowing the Senate to publish a
                    revised version in exchange for increased mutual assistance funds to “undo the
                    damage” abroad, or “prohibiting” the volume’s “export or republication in
                    foreign languages.” Although conceding that final authority rested with State,
                    Winnacker ardently believed that publication would harm the national interest. </p>
                <p>The Bureau of European Affairs within the State Department itself also considered
                    the Yalta volume too sensitive to release. To officials responsible for U.S.
                    policy toward Germany, releasing the Yalta compilation seemed recklessly
                    irresponsible. One official reacted to the embarrassing details in the Yalta
                    galleys with a warning that “if the conclusion were to be drawn from this one
                    conference … that all … agreements were too full of risk …, or if the
                    publication of this story … sets a precedent …, we should be out of the frying
                    pan into the fire.” “The cure,” he concluded, “that is apt to suggest itself to
                    a great many people will be ‘no more secrecy,’ whereas what may be needed is ‘a
                    good deal more diplomacy.’” In urging elimination of the pre-conference section
                    and discussions of the German-Polish border, EUR proposed cutting out the heart
                    of the Yalta volume.</p>
                <p>Secretary of State John Foster Dulles rejected EUR’s views, but delayed
                    publication until after the 1954 midterm “so as not to,” as the Assistant
                    Secertary for Public Affairs Carl McCardle put it, “damn the entire operation as
                    political.” The Yalta volume was not out of the woods as the British had to
                    approve the release of joint Anglo-American Combined Chiefs of Staff papers that
                    were included in the compilation. London proved reticent to agree to release
                    such detailed records of British diplomacy under Winston Churchill and Anthony
                    Eden (who had resumed their wartime positions as Prime Minister and Foreign
                    Minister). Although the Foreign Office assented to publication of most British
                    documents, Eden asked to review the entire compilation before publication. In
                    early January 1955, after several weeks of waiting for British approval, Dulles
                    told Eden that the Department would publish “unless you have some personal
                    observations that you would want me to consider.”</p>
                <p>Eden did. On January 13, Eden explained his “very real concern over the
                    publication of all these documents so soon after the event.” He argued that
                    “publication now of such detailed records may cause misunderstanding or create
                    controversy without significantly increasing public knowledge of the events” and
                    warned that British “anxieties about this project and our fear that the
                    publication of such detailed records in the political lifetime of so many of the
                    participants may make it difficult for us to be as frank as we should wish in
                    future conferences.”</p>
                <p>Eden’s message put Dulles and the State Department in a tough position. Senate
                    conservatives complained bitterly when the Yalta compilation was delayed before
                    the 1954 midterm elections, Bryton Barron’s leaks to the press had stoked public
                    interest, and now London raised another roadblock to publishing the volume.
                    Dulles suggested removing <hi rend="italic">all</hi> references to Churchill and
                    Eden from the compilation until Noble explained that such deletions would render
                    the summit meetings incomprehensible and the volume worthless. Dulles grew
                    increasingly frustrated, and when, in late January, McCardle worried that the
                    intense interest in the Yalta volume made leaks inevitable, the Secretary
                    confessed he “wouldn’t mind that.” In the same conversation, he pointed out that
                    Senator Knowland and his conservative colleagues had pushed the State Department
                    to expedite <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> because “they thought there was a lot of
                    stuff which would be useful. Actually there is nothing.” After several weeks of
                    debate, Dulles accepted Noble’s suggestion of limiting access to the galleys
                    (and responsibility for leaks) to Congress.</p>
                <p>But, with the Democrats back in power, this strategy backfired. Congress refused
                    to accept responsibility for classified documents and demanded to know why State
                    didn’t publish the volume itself. Aware that blaming Britain could damage
                    relations with London, the State Department hedged, saying the Yalta papers
                    contained information potentially damaging to “national security and our
                    relations with other powers.” Technically, the compilation was declassified when
                    Dulles approved the volume’s publication in November, but, by justifying
                    continued secrecy on security grounds, the Department worsened its already
                    compromised position.</p>
                <p>As rumors swirled about the contents of the Yalta papers and the true reasons
                    they could not be released, <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> reporter James
                    Reston approached McCardle and offered to publish the Yalta records in full to
                    prevent damage from their piecemeal release. On March 15, 1955, McCardle gave
                    Reston a copy of the Yalta galleys. The <hi rend="italic">Chicago Tribune</hi>
                    quickly caught wind of the scoop and enlisted Illinois Senate Republican Everett
                    Dirksen to demand that Dulles release the volume to everyone. Backed into a
                    corner, Dulles cabled London to explain that he had no choice but to release the
                    volume. Eden accepted the <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="yalta-papers.jpg"/>
                    <head>On March 16, 1955, Department of State officials made copies of the
                        controversial Yalta papers available to domestic and international media
                        representatives. (AP Photo/William J. Smith)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The release of the Yalta papers was headline news across the United States on
                    March 17 and the rest of the world the next day. At home, coverage emphasized
                    Roosevelt’s discussions of the future of Poland and the Far East and Alger
                    Hiss’s role at the summit. Columnists, including Walter Lippmann, debated the
                    propriety of publishing unofficial records of informal conversations and the
                    wisdom of pursuing summit diplomacy in the future. To many on the Left, the
                    transparently political agenda behind the Yalta release was overshadowed by the
                    absence of new evidence for conservative attacks on Roosevelt. Instead of
                    damaging the Democrats with new, sensational disclosures, the Yalta papers
                    showed that the public already knew what happened at Yalta. When Dulles
                    testified before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee in April, Democratic
                    Congressmen gleefully pummeled the Secretary with questions about security
                    breaches and the mishandling of classified information.</p>
                <p>Dulles was right that the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> would prove
                    disappointing to conservatives. To some, though, this only provided additional
                    evidence that the New Deal-Communist conspiracy against the United States had
                    entrenched itself in the State Department and its Historical Division. Barron’s
                    criticism continued after the release of the Yalta galleys, inspiring many on
                    the Right to denounce the integrity of the Department’s history of the
                    conference. Though the Department fired Barron by the end of the year and a 1956
                    Congressional investigation rejected his accusations, Barron continued his
                    campaign against State with books, editorials, speeches, testimony before
                    Congress, and, finally, as head of the Northern Virginia chapter of the John
                    Birch Society.</p>
                <p>In the short-term, U.S. policymakers worried about the international reaction to
                    the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. One area of obvious concern was
                    Anglo-American relations, already strained by disputes over China and U.S.
                    skepticism of Churchill’s hopes for Cold War summit diplomacy. Many foreign
                    observers saw the Yalta release as a State Department gambit to undermine
                    Churchill’s hopes for further “parleys” between world leaders. In public,
                    British leaders took pains to distance themselves from the Yalta papers and
                    downplay their significance. Speaking in Parliament on March 17, Churchill
                    explained that British records reflected a different story than the American
                    documents – though he declined to open the archives to show how. Behind the
                    scenes, Eden reminded Dulles on March 21 that Britain remained opposed to the
                    publication of recent diplomatic records, especially the Potsdam conference <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes that were rumored to be nearing release
                    later in the spring. At a press conference on March 23, President Eisenhower
                    acknowledged that there had been “some difference of opinion” between the United
                    States and Britain while denying that the United States had acted in bad faith
                    in releasing the Yalta papers.</p>
                <p>Another area of concern for U.S. officials was the impending votes in France and
                    Germany to complete ratification of the London and Paris Agreements that brought
                    a rearmed West Germany into NATO. In both countries, debates over ratification
                    made references to the Yalta papers, but did not create new divisions that
                    jeopardized Western unity. Some French politicians used them to illustrate the
                    danger of French isolation and “the empty chair” (the French were not invited to
                    Yalta) while others blamed Anglo-American chauvinism for dividing the continent.
                    Western-leaning Germans explained that the anti-German sentiment exhibited by
                    Roosevelt and Churchill was an inevitable consequence of Nazi aggression and an
                    argument for continuing liberal reforms and contributing to Western security.
                    Neutralist opponents of alignment with the West used the papers to question
                    Western commitment to German unity.</p>
                <p>In the rest of the world, the Yalta papers were headline news and a temporary
                    irritant in relations with the United States. Many foreign newspapers assumed
                    partisan politics had driven release of the Yalta papers, and those hostile to
                    Dulles, such as the <hi rend="italic">Times of India</hi>, saw the Yalta <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> as powerful evidence of his “utter incompetence to
                    handle affairs of nations with necessary tact and discretion.” Smaller countries
                    found in the documents affirmation of the superpowers’ indifference to their
                    fates. Taiwanese officials privately celebrated to U.S. diplomats that the Yalta
                    papers helped prove that the U.S. had “lost” China and therefore had a moral
                    commitment to help liberate the mainland. The State Department could take slight
                    comfort, however, that some newspapers in the emerging post-colonial world,
                    especially in India, Egypt, Bolivia, Venezuela, and El Salvador, lauded
                    Roosevelt’s opposition to British and French colonialism. As irritating as the
                    release of the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS </hi>was for America’s foreign
                    relations, short-term embarrassment did not fester into lasting damage to U.S.
                    interests abroad.</p>
                <p>The Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS </hi>proved more consequential within the U.S.
                    Government. Less than two weeks after the release of the Yalta papers,
                    Winnacker, backed up by the JCS, urged that the Department of Defense insist on
                    “additional terms of reference … to prevent a repetition of the Yalta
                    experience.” Arguing that the National Security Act of 1947 gave Defense a
                    leading role in decision-making affecting the nation’s political and military
                    interests, Winnacker suggested that “the current State Department concept for
                    its Foreign Relations series,” which “provides for the detailed publication of
                    how policy decisions were reached within this Government,” “is no longer
                    appropriate for the U.S. now that we are the major world power.” Unless new
                    Terms of Reference for Defense cooperation could be reached, Winnacker said, “no
                    more classified military documents will be made available to State for this
                    project.”</p>
                <p>Negotiations between State and Defense over terms of reference for future
                    collaboration on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> began in June and continued until
                    October 1955. When Noble received a copy of Winnacker’s memo in May, he pushed
                    back against Winnacker’s expansive claims for Defense authority and his
                    objections to <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, arguing that “the growing complexity
                    of our foreign relations would seem to make it even more important to provide
                    our citizens with the facts of our policy.” In the Pentagon, the JCS urged
                    Defense historians to preserve military institutional prerogatives and force the
                    State Department to pay greater heed to military advice about declassification
                    issues. In October, State and Defense finally agreed on Terms of Reference for
                    future World War II-era <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes that affirmed
                    continued inclusion of military documents and preserved State authority over
                    “political” decisions regarding national interests and declassification.</p>
                <p>As State historians soon discovered, however, opposition to <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> proved tenacious for the remainder of the decade. Within weeks,
                    HD found that the new Terms of Reference gave the Pentagon new tools to withhold
                    essential documents. The JCS narrowly interpreted the new Terms and rejected
                    precedents set by the Yalta and Potsdam compilations to exclude the minutes of
                    JCS meetings from the Cairo-Tehran volume. Defense officials also continued to
                    weigh in on political interest questions, such as coverage of the Dardanelles at
                    Potsdam, which had been reserved for State. Inside the State Department,
                    officials in EUR described the Yalta release as an experience to avoid in the
                    future and their objections ultimately delayed release of the Potsdam volumes
                    until the Kennedy administration. In short, the Yalta volume exacerbated
                    institutional struggles between the State Department and other national security
                    bureaucracies over authority to define national interests and determine the
                    proper balance between security and transparency.</p>
                <p>The most lasting legacy of the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was the
                    formalization of the relationship between State Department historians and the
                    academic community. The politicization of the series sparked serious concerns
                    about its integrity and its survival among the historians, political scientists,
                    and international lawyers who had become major consumers of the series. Many
                    academics were skeptical of the partisan impulses that led the Yalta volume to
                    be published so much earlier than the “regular” volumes for 1945. Though
                    resolutions affirming the desirability of publishing <hi rend="italic">FRUS
                    </hi>volumes chronologically were directed against political pressures from the
                    Right, many academics were also alarmed by conservative accusations of
                    censorship in the Yalta compilation. Prominent diplomatic historians, such as
                    Howard Beale, urged the leadership of the American Historian Association to
                    investigate these charges to safeguard the integrity of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series. </p>
                <p>As HD grappled with intense partisan scrutiny in the wake of the release of the
                    Yalta papers and Barron’s subsequent public campaign to discredit his former
                    colleagues, Noble found the prospect of academic oversight much more congenial
                    than continued Congressional direction. He cooperated with the AHA and other
                    professional organizations as they inquired about the status of <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in 1955. In 1956, the Department began coordinating
                    with the academic community to form a permanent Historical Advisory Committee
                    (HAC) under the authority of the Secretary of State. At the first meeting of the
                    HAC, in December 1957, HD staff briefed the assembled scholars on the challenges
                    that would face <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in the years ahead and solicited
                    advice on key editorial and policy issues, such as the extent of non-State
                    Department documentation that should be included in compilations. In 1959, HD
                    began the practice of employing HAC criticism of excessive delays or excisions
                    in the declassification process as “ammunition for dealing with the geographic
                    bureaus.” In the short-term, HD regarded the HAC as a source of cover from
                    partisan pressures, of guidance for adapting the series to a new Cold War era,
                    and of leverage in bureaucratic battles over declassification. Over time, the
                    HAC became a critical force in shaping the future of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series and the recurrently renegotiated balance
                    between national security and governmental transparency.</p>
                <p>The Yalta <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume was transformative. It
                    was easily the most sensational volume of the series as it was the subject of
                    national and international headlines, a Presidential press conference,
                    Parliamentary debate in London, hearings before an executive session of the
                    Senate Foreign Relations Committee, and a Congressional investigation into
                    Bryton Barron’s charges of censorship. Despite fears that thorough coverage of
                    such recent and controversial negotiations and decisions would prove harmful,
                    the volume proved embarrassing but not damaging to the national security
                    interests and the foreign relations of the United States. Over the long term,
                    the Yalta <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> introduced methodological changes
                    regarding the scope of documentation required to provide thorough coverage that
                    continues to define the series. It also catalyzed a significant institutional
                    transition as the HAC supplanted Congress in providing oversight and shaping the
                    direction of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. The world that the Yalta conference
                    helped to make might have ended in 1989 and 1990, but the series that the Yalta
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume transformed marches on.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
