<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Visualizing Responsible Transparency: Annual <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Production and Timeliness</title>
                <title type="short">Annual <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Production and
                    Timeliness</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2013-12-24">December 24, 2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="JDB" role="editor">
                        <persName>Joshua Botts</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#JDB" when="2013-12-18">Drafted text.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Visualizing Responsible Transparency: Annual <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    Production and Timeliness</head>
                <p>The size and the timeliness of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    documentary history series have changed dramatically over the years since the
                    foundation of the series in 1861. While these metrics may seem like a parade of
                    numbers devoid of much drama, they reflect over 150 years of struggles within
                    the U.S. Government over how to balance protecting security with practicing
                    openness and accountability. The outcomes of these debates are readily
                    discernable in the pages of individual <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes as
                    readers encounter sensitive documents—including, eventually, many from the
                    holdings of agencies other than the Department of State—published by the U.S.
                    Government as well as excisions where even decades-old information remains too
                    sensitive to release. Each of the hundreds of thousands of pages of documents
                    published in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series is not only a
                    record of U.S. foreign policy, but also of subsequent decisions about
                    transparency.</p>
                <p>But focusing on individual documents and excisions can obscure the larger context
                    of transparency norms and practices. We can see results of a different magnitude
                    if we look at <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> more broadly, as an ongoing indicator
                    of the balance of transparency and security over time. The <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/appendix-a"><hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> production and timeliness
                        chart</ref> shows aggregated data for the documents released each year in
                    published <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes. The production
                    dataset reveals short-term volatility but long-term progress in publishing more
                    volumes containing more documents. The lag datasets illustrate the decades of
                    nearly-contemporaneous publication in the 19th century, the lurching delays of
                    the early 20th century, a new period of relative stability in the 1930s and
                    1940s, a steady worsening of the lag from the 1950s to the 1980s, and a
                    slow-down in the growth of the lag since the 1991 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    statute.</p>
                <p>All of these trends have rich stories behind them. To learn these stories,
                    explore the history of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history"><hi
                            rend="italic">Toward “Thorough, Accurate, and Reliable”</hi></ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
