<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">The Proper Selection of Dispatches</title>
                <title type="short">The Proper Selection of Dispatches</title>
                <author>Peter Cozzens</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-12">October 12, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In my last post, <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/real-opinions">“Our Ministers Do
                    Not Express Their Real Opinions,”</ref> I said that I intended to devote this
                    post to a discussion of how the State Department’s reaction to complaints from
                    ministers (ambassadors) that their sensitive dispatches might appear in <hi
                    rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States (FRUS)</hi> volumes
                    dampened candor in their reporting. The nature of historical research being what
                    it often is, you think you know what you need, where to find it, and when to
                    wrap up the research—only to come across something that challenges your
                    assumptions. For this post, I find myself writing on something unexpected.</p>
                <p>My research had led me to conclude that the Department never solicited the input
                    of ministers before submitting diplomatic correspondence to Congress for
                    publication as an annual <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume. That is, until I
                    came across in the State Department records at the National Archives an October
                    1874 letter from U.S. Minister to China S. Wells Williams to Secretary of State
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton">Hamilton Fish</ref>, in
                    which Williams acknowledged a letter of instruction from Fish soliciting
                    ministerial comments on proposed <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> content and offered
                    his recommendations as to which dispatches from Peking were appropriate for
                    publication in <hi rend="italic">FRUS.</hi> <note n="1">S. Wells Williams to
                    Hamilton Fish, October 17, 1874, Roll 43, Despatches from U.S. Ministers to
                    China (hereafter DUSMC), Roll 43, M92, RG 59, NA.</note> </p>
                <p>Intrigued and perplexed, I dug further and found that Fish sent a similar letter
                    to all ministers. The circular letter covered a list of the legation dispatches
                    and asked ministers to advise him if they objected to the publication of any
                    items, in whole or in part.<note n="2">See for example Hamilton Fish to <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/osborn-thomas-ogden">Thomas O. Osborn</ref>,
                    September 16, 1874, Instructions of the Department of State – Argentine
                    Republic, Roll 115, M77, NA.</note> Fish regularized the consultative process in
                    1875 and 1876, sending his request for input in April, with an October
                    deadline.</p>
                <p>I have been unable to determine why Fish decided to involve ministers in the <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> selection process. The ministers to China and Japan both
                    had complained that the local British-owned press habitually used correspondence
                    from <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> to skewer them personally and condemn U.S.
                    policy. And then there was the bitter aftertaste of <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/real-opinions">the Marsh episode</ref>. Perhaps Fish
                    concluded that enhancing ministers’ stake in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> would
                    both spare them future embarrassment and minimize their complaints about the
                    series.</p>
                <p>In any event, in 1875 and 1876, a third of America’s thirty-seven ministers
                    submitted their recommendations of dispatches for publication. Either the first
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/principalofficers/assistant-secretary"
                    >Assistant Secretary of State</ref> (today’s Deputy Secretary) or more often
                    <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/principalofficers/second-assistant-secretary"
                    >Second Assistant Secretary</ref> <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/hunter-william">William Hunter</ref>—a career
                    official—made the final call on <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> content.</p>
                <p>Ministers also often asked that dispatches containing disparaging comments about
                    foreign officials or reporting on tendentious and unresolved issues either be
                    omitted from the annual submission to Congress and <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>,
                    or that sensitive portions be excised. Several also requested that their
                    dealings with other foreign missions also be kept confidential.</p>
                <p> <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="boker-george-h.jpg"/>
                    <head>Minister to Turkey George H. Boker. Poet, sonnet writer, boxer, attorney,
                        and Republican stalwart, Boker proved a talented diplomat. In spite of his
                        ignorance of Turkish and distrust of interpreters, Boker nonetheless
                        cultivated a wide array of close personal contacts within the Ottoman
                        elite.</head>
                    </figure> By way of example, in 1874 U.S. Minister to Turkey <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/boker-george-henry">George H. Boker</ref>
                    asked the Department to withhold two despatches that his predecessor had
                    written. The first conveyed the “designs and diplomatic character of the Russian
                    ambassador, which would not be very acceptable reading to my distinguished
                    colleague.” The second contained unflattering remarks about a prominent figure
                    in the Ottoman Empire, publication of which, Boker said, could cause
                    difficulties “if he were in quest of contemporary opinion as to himself, and he
                    should unfortunately stumble upon the short but all sufficing characterization
                    of his public qualities.” Assistant Secretary William Hunter accordingly
                    instructed the Diplomatic Bureau, which assembled <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>,
                    to omit the offensive material from the 1874 volume.<note n="3">George H. Boker
                    to Fish, October 15, 1874, Despatches from U.S. Ministers to Turkey (hereafter
                    DUSMT), Roll 27, M46, RG 59, NA.</note> </p>
                <p>Senior Department officials generally accepted recommendations from the field,
                    but there were numerous cases in which they overruled ministers. Hunter directed
                    that four dispatches the Minister to Chile recommended for publication not be
                    released, one of which was a lengthy, self-congratulatory report from the
                    minister about his success in uncovering pervasive malfeasance at the Valparaiso
                    consulate.<note n="4">See notation in Hunter’s hand on <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/logan-cornelius-ambrose">C. A. Logan</ref> to
                    Hamilton Fish, July 27, 1875, Despatches from U.S. Ministers to Chile, Roll T20,
                    M10, RG 59, NA.</note> Despite Minister to Turkey <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/maynard-horace">Horace Maynard</ref>’s request
                    that none of his reports on “Affair of Tripoli” appear in <ref
                    target="/historicaldocuments/frus1875v02"><hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    1875</ref>, the Department published every one of consequence.<note n="5">The
                    so-called Affair of Tripoli refers to the dispatching of an American warship to
                    that city after some locals had “insulted” the U.S. consul and his wife. Horace
                    Maynard to Hamilton Fish, September 18, 1875, Roll 29, DUSMT. Maynard had
                    suggested that “the more important dispatches relating to... the affair of
                    Tripoli you will probably not think best to make public until results should
                    have been reached. Because both British press and local press had reported on
                    the affair, the Department probably felt compelled to put something on record.
                    For press coverage of the affair see especially the <hi rend="italic">Daily
                    Levant Herald</hi>, September 20 and 24, 1875.</note> </p>
                <p>Minister to China <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-george-frederick"
                    >George F. Seward</ref> also saw himself overruled. He strongly urged that
                    nothing on Chinese immigration be published, “as the subject is one of a
                    specifically delicate nature.” The Department saw the matter otherwise. No doubt
                    to put its position on record with California Congressmen, for whom the issue
                    was an explosive one, the Department published several long despatches on the
                    topic, including a “long and frank” discussion between Seward and the Chinese
                    Foreign Minister.<note n="6">George F. Seward to Hamilton Fish, September 7,
                    1876, Roll 43, DUSMC. See for example Seward to Fish, June 29, 1876, in <ref
                    target="/historicaldocuments/frus1876v01"> <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi> 1876</ref>, 57-58.</note> </p>
                <p>The experiment in soliciting legation input to <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Relations</hi> died with the Grant administration. No protest arose from the
                    field. Only two ministers took it upon themselves to submit recommendations.
                    <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="foster-john-w.jpg"/>
                    <head>Minister to Mexico John W. Foster. A respected attorney and diplomat,
                        Foster had been a brevet brigadier general in the Civil War. He became
                        secretary of state in the Benjamin Harrison administration and was the
                        grandfather of Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                        Dulles</ref>.</head>
                    </figure> Anticipating a forthcoming special session of Congress in October 1877
                    to review President Rutherford B. Hayes’ refusal to recognize the new Mexican
                    government of Porfirio Diaz, U.S. Minister to Mexico <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/foster-john-watson">John W. Foster</ref>
                    offered his unsolicited advice as to such despatches as “may be desirable to
                    transmit” to Congress. Acting Secretary of State <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-frederick-william">Frederick W.
                    Seward</ref> declined to provide the hostile, Democrat-controlled Congress any
                    of these documents before or during the special session, and only fourteen of
                    forty-eight despatches that Foster had identified as “of a political and
                    historical character suitable for publication” found their way into <ref
                    target="/historicaldocuments/frus1877"> <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    1877</ref>.<note n="7">John W. Foster to Frederick W. Seward, June 27, 1877,
                    Roll 56, M97, RG 59, NA.</note> </p>
                <p>Writing from his home in Galena, Illinois, recently retired Minister to France
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/washburne-elihu-benjamin">Elihu B.
                    Washburne</ref> made known his publication preferences. The Department obliged
                    him.<note n="8">Elihu B. Washburne to William Evarts, October 16, 1877,
                    Despatches from U.S. Ministers to France, M34, Roll T85, RG 59, NA.</note> The
                    next year only the newly arrived Minister to Germany made known his views on <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Seemingly unaware of the unwritten change in policy,
                    Minister <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/taylor-bayard">Bayard
                    Taylor</ref> wrote Secretary <ref
                    target="/departmenthistory/people/evarts-william-maxwell">William M.
                    Evarts</ref> that his staff had informed him “that it is customary at this time
                    of the year, when certain portions of the diplomatic correspondence are selected
                    for publication, for the representatives of the government to indicate such
                    despatches as they may desire for special reasons to be either withheld or given
                    to the public,” and accordingly he drew up a list. The Department compiler
                    accepted his recommendations, the last they received from the field. From 1878
                    onward, ministers confined themselves to grumbling over unwelcome <hi
                    rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> content after its publication.<note n="9"
                    >Bayard Taylor to William M. Evarts, September 2, 1878, Despatches from U.S.
                    Ministers to Germany.</note> </p>
                <p>What can we learn about nineteenth-century <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> from
                    Fish’s short-lived initiative? At a minimum, it offers further evidence that <hi
                    rend="italic">FRUS</hi> content was reviewed at the highest levels of the
                    Department. It also illustrates the absence of clearly articulated criteria for
                    selecting correspondence for submission to Congress and subsequent publication,
                    as ministers seem not to have been informed of the reasons for Department
                    actions upon their recommendations. Finally, the response to Fish’s calls
                    demonstrates that some ministers understood both the benefits and potential
                    pitfalls of transparency in government.</p>
                <p>Fish’s initiative also ended up providing a useful lesson about the practice of
                    history, namely that there’s no substitute to thorough research for fleshing out
                    the full story behind even the things that you think you already know.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
