<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“Our Ministers Do Not Express Their Real Opinions”</title>
                <title type="short">“Our Ministers Do Not Express Their Real Opinions”</title>
                <author>Peter Cozzens</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-09-07">September 7, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>American diplomats reporting from abroad in the latter decades of the nineteenth
                    century wrote openly at their own peril. The Department of State offered no
                    guarantee that their dispatches would remain confidential. In annual volumes
                    called <hi rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> (the precursor to what we now know by the acronym <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>), the State Department published what it considered
                    the most salient diplomatic correspondence of the year. In my research article
                        <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-1872-frus-affair">“A
                        Surprising Manifestation of Backbone”</ref> we see an example of the
                    Department manipulating <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> content to pursue policy
                    goals as well as to shape public opinion and Congressional debate. And, as I
                    implied in that article, there was sometimes a sinister relationship between <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and the spoils system by means of which most
                        ministers<note n="1">The United States did not adopt the title of ambassador
                        for its senior representatives abroad until 1893.</note> and consuls were
                    appointed—that is to say, Secretaries of State permitted the publication of
                    sensitive dispatches for partisan political purposes.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="marsh-george-perkins.jpg"/>
                    <head>George P. Marsh, Minister to Italy</head>
                </figure>
                <p>No one better understood the personal harm that frank reporting might cause than
                    did Minister to Italy <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/marsh-george-perkins">George P.
                        Marsh</ref>, one of America’s most able diplomats. As he was dressing for
                    dinner with the Italian foreign minister one evening in January 1872, Marsh
                    nearly fainted when a servant brought him the afternoon newspaper, which
                    contained excerpts from a scathing indictment of the Italian government he had
                    sent Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/fish-hamilton"
                        >Hamilton Fish</ref> in an encoded, confidential dispatch two years
                        earlier.<note n="2">George W. Wurts to Catherine C. Marsh, September 1,
                        1884, George P. Marsh Papers, University of Vermont; David Lowenthal, <hi
                            rend="italic">George Perkins Marsh, Versatile Vermonter</hi> (New York:
                        Columbia University Press, 1958), 289-90.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In 1870, Italy was wrestling with the question of <ref
                        target="/countries/issues/italian-unification">seizing the Papal State of
                        Rome</ref>, formerly a French protectorate. When it became clear to Marsh
                    that the Italian government in Florence had no fixed policy, he unburdened
                    himself to Fish with complaints about Italian “vacillation, tergiversation, and
                    duplicity,” and its “blind obedience” to the dictates of Napoleon III. The
                    dispatch appeared in <hi rend="italic">FRUS 1870</hi>.<note n="3">
                        <hi rend="italic"> Message of the President of the United States and
                            Accompanying Documents to the Two Houses of Congress at the Commencement
                            of the Third Session of the Forty-First Congress</hi>, 41st Cong. 3d.
                        sess., H. Ex. Doc. 1, Part 1, 450. The less cumbersome title, <hi
                            rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations of the United
                            States</hi>, was adopted the following year.</note> Two years later, the
                    Italian press discovered it. Only Marsh’s friendship with the prime minister and
                    foreign minister, and the passage of time, saved his position. Had the Italians
                    taken note of the document’s publication in 1870, Marsh likely would have been
                    expelled.</p>
                <p>How had Marsh’s sensitive dispatch found its way into <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi>? Both Marsh and his first secretary thought it had been
                    “treacherously printed by the Department of State in the volume of <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> with the malicious object of making the
                    legation in Italy untenable any longer by its minister.”<note n="4">George W.
                        Wurts to Catherine C. Marsh, September 1, 1884, and George P. Marsh to
                        Charles P. Marsh to George Marsh, both in Marsh Papers; George P. Marsh to
                        John Bigelow, March 25, 1872, in Bigelow, <hi rend="italic">Retrospections
                            of an Active Life</hi>, 6 vols. (New York: Doubleday, Page, and Company,
                        1913), 5:18-19.</note>
                </p>
                <p>They were probably right. Republican Congressman John Bingham, a friend and
                    strong supporter of President Ulysses S. Grant and Secretary Fish, wanted the
                    job; the apolitical Marsh, on the other hand, had no comparable allies in high
                    office. What better way to clear the way for Bingham than to let slip a dispatch
                    from Marsh that would enrage the Italians?<note n="5">Bingham’s interest in
                        Marsh’s job is discussed in Lowell (Massachusetts) <hi rend="italic">Daily
                            Citizen and News</hi>, June 21, 1870 and Boston <hi rend="italic">Daily
                            Advertiser</hi>, June 20, 1870.</note>
                </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="christiancy-isaac-peckham.jpg"/>
                    <head>Isaac P. Christiancy, Minister to Peru</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Eleven years later former Minister to Peru <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/christiancy-isaac-peckham">Isaac P.
                        Christiancy</ref> was enraged to see published a “private and personal”
                    letter he had sent Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G.
                        Blaine</ref> on May 4, 1881. Christiancy’s letter discussed the War of the
                    Pacific in general and the “debauched” state of the Peruvian people in
                    particular. “The laboring class [is] sunk beyond redemption,” he told Blaine. As
                    for the ruling class, “there seems to be no fixed principle of honesty, no idea
                    even of that self-sacrificing patriotism which is essential to a proper and
                    honest administration of government. This letter must be treated as perfectly
                    confidential, for your own eye and that of the president alone,” Christiancy
                    reminded Blaine in closing. “My own life would not be safe here for one day if
                    it were made public.”<note n="6">Christiancy to Blaine, May 5, 1881, in <hi
                            rend="italic">War in South America,</hi> 47th Cong. 1st Sess., S. Ex.
                        Doc. 79, (serial 1989), 157-58; New York <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>,
                        February 5, 1882.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Fortunately for his personal safety, Christiancy was no longer in Peru when his
                    letter was published in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and made newspaper headlines
                    nationwide. Most papers condemned the release of so sensitive a document. The
                    New York <hi rend="italic">Herald-Tribune</hi> admonished the State Department
                    toward greater secrecy: “If it is possible for confidential dispatches to be
                    divulged by so important an office as the State Department, the result will be
                    that ministers will not send such dispatches, but prefer to communicate their
                    substance orally”<note n="7">New York <hi rend="italic">Herald Tribune</hi>,
                        February 10, 1882.</note>
                </p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="sargent-aaron-augustus.jpg"/>
                    <head>Aaron A. Sargent, Minister to Germany</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Herald-Tribune</hi> hit the mark. The experiences of Marsh,
                    Christiancy, and other ministers dampened candor in reporting, as ministers were
                    reluctant to express themselves freely for fear that their words might appear in
                    public. After the Department published—and the German press reprinted with angry
                    commentary—a dispatch he had written on the tendentious issue of American pork
                    exports, Minister to Germany <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/sargent-aaron-augustus">Aaron A.
                        Sargent</ref> told the Department that he simply would desist from reporting
                        honestly.<note n="8">J. C. Bancroft Davis to A. A. Sargent, May 23, 183,
                        M77, Roll 68, Record Group 59, National Archives.</note> In 1886, former U.
                    S. Minister to Greece <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/schuyler-eugene"
                        >Eugene Schuyler</ref>, who had left the diplomatic service to teach
                    diplomatic history, warned that “our ministers do not feel free to express to
                    the Secretary their real opinions, for they have always in view the possibility
                    that their dispatches may be published... Even confidential letters do not
                    always tell the whole truth.”<note n="9">Eugene Schuyler, <hi rend="italic"
                            >American Diplomacy and the Furtherance of Commerce</hi> (Charles
                        Scribner’s Sons, 1886), 35-36.</note> Schuyler’s solution was to scrap <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Of course, that did not happen. How the Department responded to complaints and
                    circumspect reporting from its ministers will be the subject of my next blog
                    entry.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
