<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Instruction from <persName>William Seward</persName> to
                        <persName>Charles Francis Adams</persName>
                </title>
                <title type="short">Instruction from <persName>Seward</persName> to
                        <persName>Adams</persName>
                </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-10-24">October 24, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This document was released in conjunction with "<ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/constitutional-basis-of-frus"
                        >The Constitutional Basis of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    </ref>." A scan of the original text is available for download (<ref
                        target="https://static.history.state.gov/frus150/seward-letter.pdf"
                        >PDF</ref>, 1 MB, 9 pp.).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="1"/>
                <p>No. 859</p>
                <p>Department of State</p>
                <p>Washington, 2nd March 1864</p>
                <p>Sir:</p>
                <p>Your dispatch of February 11th, No. 595, has been received, together with reports
                    of the debates which have been held in Parliament upon the condition of our
                    relations towards Great Britain.</p>
                <p>On the 11th of July, last, the information which was before this Department
                    seemed to oblige the Government of the United States to take into immediate
                    consideration a probable failure of all its friendly appeals to Her Majesty's
                    Government against suffering a deeply concerted and rapidly preparing Naval war
                    to be waged against the United States from British ports in Europe and America
                    by British subjects, in British built and armed vessels.</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>Events which have transpired since that time, such as the intended invasion of
                    Johnson's Island from Canada, the case of the Chesapeake, the escape of the
                    Rappahannock, the enlistment of seamen and sailors, the persistent proceedings
                    in the construction of Lairds rams, under false pretences of foreign ownership,
                    and, especially the report of Mallory, the pretended Secretary of the Navy of
                    the insurgents, have proved that the crisis thus apprehended in July was not
                    overestimated, nor too soon anticipated by this Department. The Government of
                    the United States took the subject into consideration with all the seriousness
                    and anxiety that could not fail to be awakened by the seeming approach of a
                    naval conflict with Great Britain in aggravation of our existing civil war.</p>
                <p>The result of the deliberation was set down in the dispatch which I had the honor
                    to address to you on the day before mentioned. That<pb n="3"/> dispatch was
                    addressed to you because the interests of the Government and people of the
                    United States seemed to require that, as the Representative of the United States
                    charged with the conduct of their correspondence with the Govt. of Great
                    Britain, you should be fully informed of the views which had been adopted by
                    your own government. At the same time, in this case, as in all others when you
                    are not specially directed to submit an instruction to Her Majesty's Government,
                    it was left to your own discretion to make so much or so little use of the
                    knowledge thus imparted to you of the views of this Government as you should
                    deem expedient, and to use it in such manner, and at such time, as should seem
                    to you best calculated to avert the evils apprehended.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, in communicating those views to you, I scrupulously took pains,
                    equally to leave no ground for misapprehension of their directness,<pb n="4"/>
                    and to avoid expressing myself in any way that could offend the dignity or wound
                    the sensibility of the British Government or the British people.</p>
                <p>The constitution of the United States requires the President, from time to time,
                    to give to Congress information concerning the state of the Union. In the
                    beginning of our Government a practice obtained according to which the President
                    communicated this information on the assembling of Congress, in a full and
                    comprehensive annual speech or message, to which are appended all the important
                    reports and documents which have been placed by the Heads of Departments before
                    the President as the sources and evidences of the information to be by him
                    submitted to Congress. It is hardly necessary to say that the interest of
                    Congress and the people of the United States in the transactions of the
                    Executive Department, always earnest,<pb n="5"/> became intensified with the
                    breaking out of the civil war. Our foreign affairs have ever since the war began
                    been a subject of anxiety as deep as that which is felt in regard to military
                    and naval events. The Government constantly depends on the support of Congress
                    and the People, and that support can be expected only on the condition of
                    keeping them thoroughly and truthfully informed of the manner in which the
                    powers derived from them are executed. Mutual confidence between the People and
                    the Government is a condition of our national life.</p>
                <p>It has seemed to the President more satisfactory and more in harmony with our
                    system to give to Congress the information prescribed by the constitution, with
                    all possible fulness at the beginning of each meeting of Congress, rather than
                    to await their special calls for it in particular cases, as is generally done in
                    Constitutional governments, where the Executive or its Minister hold seats in
                    the Legislature. </p>
                <pb n="6"/>
                <p>Congress and the Country, at the beginning of the present session, had a right to
                    be put fully in possession of a complete history of the conflicting claims which
                    had arisen between the United States and Great Britain subsequently to the last
                    preceeding annual exposition which had been submitted by the President. They had
                    the same right to see my dispatch to you of the 11th of July, 1863, that they
                    had to see any other parts of the Executive correspondence concerning foreign
                    affairs. The history would be incomplete without that document. It was the
                    President's duty to communicate it, unless special reasons of a public nature
                    existed for withholding it. Only two such special reasons could be allowed,
                    namely, one, that the publication would be incompatible with the public interest
                    by affecting a friendly negotiation on an existing question. But the question
                    which had called out the dispatch had been for a time put at rest; and mutually
                    satisfactory explanations between the two Governments had been made. The other
                    reason was that the publication might give offence to Great Britain. But the
                    document was a communication from this Government not to Her Majesty's
                    Government, but to its own agent; and the paper was believed to be as respectful
                    to the British Government as it manifestly was earnest and sincere. On the other
                    hand, to withhold so important a portion of the Executive correspondence, would
                    have seemed to imply a confession that it was improper in itself, while to
                    practice reserve on so great a question, would be liable to be deemed an abuse
                    of the confidence which Congress and the people had so freely reposed in the
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The President now learns with regret that British statesmen whose opinions he
                    would be the last to undervalue, have declared that in their judgment portions
                    of that communication are disrespectful and<pb n="7"/> menacing towards Her
                    Majesty's Government.</p>
                <p>Comity is not only a property, but even an indispensable element, in diplomatic
                    intercourse. A just and enlightened Government may readily admit, without any
                    sacrifice of its own self respect, that every other Government is entitled to
                    judge for itself what expressions occurring, in its needful intercourse with
                    foreign states, are exceptionable.</p>
                <p>You are therefore authorized to say to Earl Russell, that nothing menacing or
                    disrespectful was intended by any expressions in the dispatch before referred
                    to, and that the paper is now freely referred by the President to Earl Russell's
                    own criticism, with the request that whatever expressions contained in it he
                    shall consider exceptionable be deemed to be hereby withdrawn, with regret on
                    the part of this Government that those expressions, although inadvertently, had
                    been incorporated in a paper, the object of which was not to offend, but to
                    remove out of the way a stumbling block <pb n="8"/>of national offense; not to
                    provoke war, but, by a generous and conciliatory final effort, to save peace and
                    restore harmony between Great Britain and the United States.</p>
                <p>I am, Sir,</p>
                <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>William H. Seward</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
