<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Special <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Volumes: Origins of “The
                    Lansing Papers”</title>
                <title type="short">Special <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Volumes</title>
                <author>David Langbart</author>
                <sponsor>Textual Archives Services Division, National Archives and Records
                    Administration</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-11-30">November 30, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>David A. Langbart is an archivist in the Textual Archives Services Division of
                    the National Archives and Records Administration. He has been working with
                    records of the Department of State for over 30 years. An earlier version of this
                    write-up appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Society for Historians of American
                        Foreign Relations Newsletter</hi>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In February 1940, the Department of State released a special two-volume
                    supplement to the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) series. Those special volumes carried the
                    sub-title “The Lansing Papers, 1914-1919.” <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing</ref>
                    served as Counselor (second in charge in the Department) from April 1914 to June
                    1915 and then as Secretary of State from June 1915 to February 1920. As the
                    preface noted, the volumes contained “an extensive selection from the large body
                    of correspondence of Robert Lansing... secured for the files of the Department
                    of State following Mr. Lansing’s death in 1928.” The preface further explained
                    that the materials included were not available when the Department prepared the
                    regular <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes for the years 1914
                    through 1919 or the special supplementary volumes dealing with World War I and
                    Russia. Realizing the importance of and public interest in the Lansing papers,
                    the Department decided to publish them as a supplement to the series.<note n="1"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States: The Lansing
                            Papers, 1914-1919</hi> 2 volumes (Washington, DC: United States
                        Government Printing Office, 1939), 1: iii.</note></p>
                <p>The first volume contained documentation relating to World War I dating from the
                    period before the United States entered the conflict. Among other subjects, it
                    includes records on peace prospects, recruiting of American citizens, the
                    conduct of foreign diplomats in the United States, the sale of munitions to
                    belligerents, enforcement of U.S. neutrality, and interference by Britain and
                    her allies with U.S. commerce. The second volume included documents relating to
                    U.S. participation in the war, as well as sections on Russia, the Far East, and
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>Short of the explanation that the documents had been “secured” for the Department
                    of State after Lansing’s death, the publication sheds no light on how the
                    Department came to possess his documents.<note n="2"><hi rend="italic"
                        >Ibid</hi>.</note> Fortunately, the files of the Department provide detail
                    on the unusual acquisition of the records.</p>
                <p>As early as September 1921, officials in the Department of State expressed
                    concern about documents on foreign policy that officials of the Wilson
                    administration removed during the presidential transition earlier that year.
                    They were particularly anxious about materials taken away by President Woodrow
                    Wilson and Secretary of State Bainbridge Colby. The Assistant Secretary, Fred
                    Morris Dearing, wanted to know what had been taken and how documents might be
                    returned to Department custody. David A. Salmon, Chief of the Bureau of Indexes
                    and Archives, believed that “polite” and “courteous” requests “might have the
                    desired effect.” If that was not the case, he recommended that the Department of
                    State consider proceeding under Section 47 of the Criminal Code.<note n="3">Fred
                        Morris Dearing to David A. Salmon, September 23, 1921, David A. Salmon to
                        Fred Morris Dearing, September 24, 1921, File 116/121, Central Decimal File,
                        RG 59: General Records of the Department of State, National Archives
                        (hereafter CDF, RG 59, NA). Section 47 read: Whoever shall embezzle, steal,
                        or purloin any money, property, records, voucher, or valuable thing
                        whatever, of the moneys, goods, chattels, records, or property of the United
                        States, shall be fined not more than five thousand dollars, or imprisoned
                        not more than five years, or both.</note> Ultimately, the Department took no
                    action.</p>
                <p>Strangely, no mention was made of the files of Secretary of State Robert Lansing.
                    When Lansing resigned as Secretary of State on February 13, 1920, he removed a
                    large volume of documents from his office, much of it official in nature. He
                    later used those materials in the preparation of his memoirs.<note n="4">See:
                        Robert Lansing, <hi rend="italic">The Peace Negotiations: A Personal
                            Record</hi> Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1921 and Robert Lansing <hi
                            rend="italic">War Memoirs of Robert Lansing</hi> New York: Bobbs-Merrill
                        Co., 1935.</note> During the early and mid-1920s, on a case-by-case basis,
                    Salmon, in his capacity as head of the Department’s archives, secured from
                    Lansing copies of documents needed for official business. The Department,
                    however, made no move towards recovering the official papers for the
                    Department’s files.</p>
                <p>That changed in 1929. On January 16, after departmental officials heard rumors
                    that Lansing’s widow planned to move the files to the Carnegie Institute for
                    International Peace, Secretary of State Frank Kellogg sent Lansing’s widow a
                    letter that began the process of recovering the documents. Secretary Kellogg’s
                    letter explained the Department’s difficulty locating numerous documents during
                    preparation of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                    series, a problem he attributed to the fact that many documents had not sent
                    through the normal channels for recording and filing but “directly to Mr.
                    Lansing without record . . . and incorporated into the files which were removed
                    to his residence” when he resigned. Kellogg explained that the department had,
                    from time to time, obtained copies of needed documents from the former secretary
                    of state and on one of those occasions, Lansing had stated his intention to turn
                    the files over to the department or to have David Salmon to review the files to
                    identify individual documents that should be in the Department’s files. The
                    Secretary now requested permission for Salmon to “go over them and remove such
                    papers as are official or semi official in character for incorporation in the
                    Archives of the Department” before a move took place. The Department would, he
                    noted, replace the originals with copies.<note n="5">Secretary of State Frank
                        Kellogg to Mrs. Robert Lansing, January 16, 1929, File 116/174A, CDF, RG 59,
                        NA. </note></p>
                <p>Mrs. Lansing replied two days later stating in no uncertain terms that she had
                    “no intention of turning over State Department files to the Carnegie Endowment.”
                    Her plan, she explained, was merely to move some of her late husband’s personal
                    files there “for safe keeping.” She also informed the secretary that her nephew
                    Allen Dulles would contact the Department to work on arrangements for return of
                    official material.<note n="6">Mrs. Robert Lansing to Secretary of State Frank
                        Kellogg, January 18, 1929, File 116/174B, CDF, RG 59, NA.</note></p>
                <p>Seven days later, Dulles wrote the Department and stated that it was Mrs.
                    Lansing’s “desire to return to the Department any . . . papers which properly
                    form a part of the official records.” He noted that he had reviewed the files
                    and collected the pertinent papers in one filing cabinet that his aunt was now
                    ready to turn over to the Department. Mrs. Lansing’s only requests, he reported,
                    were that the material in the cabinet be indexed, remain segregated from the
                    general files, and be made available to anyone she might designate. Dulles
                    thought his aunt might eventually select someone to complete her late husband’s
                    unfinished book. Also, Dulles explained that Secretary Lansing had, before he
                    died, indicated that Ray Stannard Baker, who was working on the authorized
                    biography of Woodrow Wilson, would be granted access to the correspondence
                    between Lansing and Wilson. Mrs. Lansing wanted “to be in a position to carry
                    out Mr. Lansing’s expressed desire . . . .”<note n="7">In 1936, the Department’s
                        leadership ultimately decided to provide Baker with access to the documents.
                        See memorandum of Conference in the Secretary’s Office, April 20, 1936,
                        Records of the Executive Secretary of the Policy Planning Council, Entry
                        A1-1583, File “Lansing Diary and Papers,” RG 59, NA.</note> Dulles closed by
                    stating that he foresaw no problems as he had already discussed matters with
                        Salmon.<note n="8">Allen W. Dulles to Secretary of State Frank Kellogg,
                        January 25, 1929, File 116/174C, CDF, RG 59, NA.</note> Kellogg confirmed
                    the arrangements a few days later.<note n="9">Secretary of State Frank Kellogg
                        to Allen W. Dulles, January 29, 1929, File 116/174D, CDF, RG 59,
                    NA.</note></p>
                <p>The files arrived in the Department of State in April 1929. There, they remained
                    as an intact collection until 1933, when the documents were indexed and filed in
                    the appropriate places in the Department’s Central Decimal File.<note n="10"
                        >David A. Salmon, Memorandum, January 11, 1936, Records of the Executive
                        Secretary of the Policy Planning Council, Entry A1-1583, File “Lansing Diary
                        and Papers,” RG 59, NA. The interfiled documents are usually easily
                        identifiable for two reasons: first, the file numbers on the documents are
                        typed instead of being handwritten, as is the case for documents indexed
                        during the period, and most of the documents have a fractional file number
                        (i.e. 861.00/383-1/2).</note></p>
                <p>Subsequently, Departmental officials decided to compile and prepare the special
                    supplemental volumes. In addition to the recognized need to fill a gap in <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s coverage of a critical period, the response to the
                    publication of Secretary Lansing’s memoirs in 1935 indicated academic, public,
                    Congressional, and foreign interest in the documents. During the preparation of
                    the volumes, the Department followed its standard procedure of clearing certain
                    documents with foreign governments, a process that sometimes involved high-level
                        meetings.<note n="11">See memorandum by Cyril Wynne, Division of Research
                        and Publication, April 24, 1936, File 026 Foreign Relations/1017, and
                        memorandum by Cyril Wynne, Division of Research and Publication, of a
                        meeting between Counselor R. Walton Moore and British ambassador to the
                        United States Sir Ronald Lindsay, July 13, 1938, File 026 Foreign
                        Relations/1378, CDF, RG 59, NA.</note></p>
                <p>The Department announced publication of the volumes in two press releases in
                    February 1940.<note n="12">Department of State Press Release No. 78, February
                        19, 1940, and Press Release No. 83, February 23, 1940, Records of the Office
                        of News and Its Predecessors, Press Releases, RG 59, NA.</note></p>
                <p>Securing return of the files made many extremely important documents available to
                    the Department as it prepared the World War I supplementary volumes in the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series. Issuance of the special volumes filled gaps
                    in the existing <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> coverage and made many of the
                    documents available to the academic community, the public, and Congress. In some
                    respects, the preparation of the volumes set the precedent for later
                    supplemental volumes in the series, such as those on Guatemala and the
                    Intelligence Community.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
