<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“A Surprising Manifestation of Backbone”: The 1872 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Affair</title>
                <title type="short">“A Surprising Manifestation of Backbone”</title>
                <author>Peter Cozzens</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-06-21">June 21, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In 1895, the Chicago <hi rend="italic">Inter Ocean</hi> gleefully greeted the
                    annual <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) volume, which contained a hefty sampling of the
                    year’s correspondence between the Secretary of State and his ministers abroad.
                    “As it is made up of dispatches which have passed between [American] foreign
                    representatives and the government, and as they are deferred so long that they
                    are of the quality of last year’s bird’s nests, it is possible the reading
                    public fancies the book must be dry and musty.”</p>
                <p>Quite the contrary, said the <hi rend="italic">Inter Ocean</hi>. In order to
                    convince the reading public to secure a copy of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    “either for perusal at home or as a charming volume for summer outings,” the <hi rend="italic">Inter Ocean</hi> quoted several hyperbolic statements and
                    malapropisms of U.S. diplomats. Among them was this gem from the U.S. minister
                    in Nicaragua, who said that Managua’s forfeiture of the interoceanic canal
                    concession was “the most ghastly stab under the fifth rib of the credit of your
                    own government which could be inflicted by the keenest Damascus blade.” In a
                    more serious vein, the <hi rend="italic">Inter Ocean</hi> added that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> illustrated “the folly of our whole diplomatic
                    system and the following of making appointments helter-skelter or using
                    diplomatic and consular offices as part of the national spoils.”</p>
                <p>Perhaps so. But on occasion, there was a more sinister relationship between <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> and the spoils system—that is to say, Secretaries of
                    State manipulated the contents of volumes for partisan political purposes. I
                    will be writing on this aspect of the 19th Century <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    at a later date. In this article I will present an episode that reflects the use
                    of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> as a public affairs and public diplomacy tool
                    during a delicate and dangerous diplomatic dispute.</p>
                <p>Before doing so, I want to offer some conclusions that I have drawn from my
                    research into the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series during the
                    Gilded Age—conclusions that challenge conventional assumptions about the series,
                    and that perhaps will provide fodder for further discussion.</p>
                <p>The premise guiding my research has been this: We must expand our definition of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series for the period 1870–1897 to
                    include the many Senate and House Executive Documents consisting of collected
                    State Department correspondence that appeared during the era in response to
                    Congressional requests. They should be considered as unacknowledged <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> supplemental volumes. As with the normal <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes, which derived from select State Department
                    diplomatic correspondence of the current year (and occasionally prior years)
                    appended to the president’s annual message to Congress, the president also
                    submitted the documents in response to the Congressional resolutions over a
                    covering letter from the secretary attesting to their completeness.</p>
                <p>Many of the resultant Congressional executive documents ran into the hundreds of
                    pages. My expanded definition of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    series is supported by the 1894 volume, which was published with seven
                    supplemental volumes containing the State Department submissions that appeared
                    as Congressional Executive Documents for that year, or on issues for which
                    Congress had requested documents, but with which the Department had not yet
                    complied.</p>
                <p>In years that Congressional requests were numerous and yielded large executive
                    documents, the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes normally were noticeably
                    thinner. The Department had no cause to republish the material, as the audience
                    in both cases was Congress.</p>
                <p>The choice of documents for annual submissions to Congress (that is to say, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes) appears to have been guided by
                    an intent to include material that clarified or provided justification for the
                    president’s foreign policy priorities and issues that he emphasized or even
                    tangentially referred to in his annual address to Congress. Many of those issues
                    might seem trivial today, but we must judge the contents of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in the context if its day.</p>
                <p>This expanded definition of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> suggests that the
                    contents of the series during the Gilded Age was more complete than many assume
                    them to have been. This is not to say that they were comprehensive. They did not
                    provide the window into Washington decision-making that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> does today. Only correspondence between the Secretary of State or
                    his deputy and U.S. ministers and consuls was included in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>.</p>
                <p>We often speak of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in the
                    context of the issue of transparency in government. But in the 19th Century,
                    transparency in government was seldom cited in public discussion as an argument
                    for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. On the contrary, when documents appearing
                    either in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> or Congressional Executive Reports created
                    difficulties with foreign governments or for U.S. representatives abroad, most
                    newspapers condemned the Department for releasing the offending documents and
                    advocated greater secrecy.</p>
                <p>And now, to the episode that is the subject of my essay, which deals with the
                    high-stakes use of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> as a public diplomacy and public
                    affairs tool.</p>
                <milestone unit="line" rend="centered-asterisks"/>
                <p>Hamilton Fish entered office as Secretary of State in March 1869 determined to
                    kill the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series.
                    Congress had slashed the State Department staff by 40%, from 48 clerks to 31.
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="hamilton-fish.jpg"/>
                        <head>Secretary of State Hamilton Fish. (Library of Congress, Prints and
                            Photographs Division cph.3a37879)</head>
                    </figure> “With such a large reduction,” Fish wrote the Speaker of the House on
                    December 3, 1869, “the business of the Department is already seriously
                    embarrassed.” The date of Fish’s letter was not random; that very day, President
                    Ulysses S. Grant transmitted his annual message to Congress. For the preceding
                    eight years, the collection of selected annual diplomatic correspondence that
                    the GPO published as <hi rend="italic">Papers Relating to the Foreign Relations
                        of the United States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) accompanied the
                    president’s message. But not in 1869. Congressional parsimony came at a cost—no
                    money, no <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, reasoned Fish.</p>
                <p>Fish’s decision would only hurt Congress, which during the Nineteenth Century was
                    the intended audience for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. Although mandated by an
                    act of Congress in 1861 in order to compel the Lincoln administration to reveal
                    its diplomatic correspondence, neither the series nor its utility ended after
                    the Civil War. The State Department continued to select material for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in order to explain and justify the president’s
                    foreign-policy priorities. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, in turn gave Congress a
                    framework for debating policy and holding the executive branch accountable. As
                    Fish was to discover, Congress was not about to relinquish this prerogative.</p>
                <p>Budget cuts aside, Fish had no love for the 41st Congress. “The Senate, in fact
                    Congress, but especially the Senate, has encroached largely beyond the former
                    line of demarcation between their powers and those of the Executive,” he
                    complained privately of the chamber dominated by fellow Republicans. “They wish,
                    practically, to dictate nominations [of ministers], not merely to ‘advise and
                    consent’ and consult. The constitutional power of the Senate is limited to yea
                    or nay upon the names submitted to them.”</p>
                <p>And they were lucky to get names. President Grant and Fish were at loggerheads
                    with the Senate Foreign Relations Committee Chairman Charles Sumner. Senator
                    Sumner, for his part, was offended that Grant had not consulted him on
                    diplomatic appointments, and he made Grant pay in Latin America. Grant wanted to
                    buy Samana Bay from Santo Domingo to build a naval base. Sumner pretended to go
                    along with the plan, but at the same time he quietly subverted it in the
                    Senate.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="insurrection.jpg"/>
                    <head>As the American Public Saw the Cuban Insurrection (Harper’s Weekly,
                        September 11, 1869)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Cuban insurrection was a second wedge between the two branches of government.
                    A growing number of influential Americans, including many of both parties in
                    Congress, wanted the insurgents accorded belligerent status. Fish, on the other
                    hand, considered the rebels to be a feeble and poorly organized force, hardly
                    worth jeopardizing relations with Spain. But Spanish brutality troubled Fish.
                    “The present state cannot be indefinitely prolonged,” Fish warned the Spanish
                    minister. The Grant Administration, he added ominously, “reserved the right of
                    future action.”</p>
                <p>Fish’s refusal to provide Congress with the diplomatic correspondence that was
                    grist for the annual <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> backfired. The New York <hi rend="italic">Herald-Tribune</hi>, a pro-administration newspaper, insisted
                    he produce the Cuba correspondence, and warned Congress against taking “any
                    steps in the dark regarding our foreign relations.”</p>
                <p>Congress agreed. Five days after receiving the president’s annual message, the
                    Senate requested that Fish provide it with all correspondence pertaining to the
                    Cuban revolution. On December 17, Sumner demanded the dispatches of the U.S.
                    minister to Spain. And on January 7, 1870, the House passed a second resolution
                    soliciting the Cuba correspondence.</p>
                <p>Fish yielded. But his compliance with the Congressional resolutions on Cuba did
                    not reflect an intent to resume <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. On the contrary, in
                    January 1870 he assured a U.S. minister embarrassed over the leak of certain
                    compromising letters that “The publication of the Diplomatic Correspondence has
                    been discontinued.”</p>
                <p>But as the year wore on, it became clear to Fish that killing the series would
                    neither be easy nor wise. The drumbeat of Congressional resolutions continued,
                    and Fish found himself transmitting to Congress enough correspondence to fill a
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume.</p>
                <p>Undoubtedly concluding it better to preempt demands whenever possible, Fish
                    resumed <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in December 1870.</p>
                <p>Two years later, Fish was glad he had. The Cuban insurrection was in its fourth
                    year, with no end in sight. Spain not only had failed to deliver on its pledge
                    to emancipate slaves in Cuba and Puerto Rico and undertake municipal reforms and
                    other liberal measures that the Grant administration had urged, but the colonial
                    government in Havana also imposed high tariffs on American imports and began
                    expropriating American estates. Pressure for Grant to act escalated. To inflame
                    public opinion, in July 1872 the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>
                    correspondent in Cuba provoked the Spaniards into arresting him. Fish also
                    learned that Cuban sympathizers in New York were secretly arranging to send
                    provocateurs to the island. <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> editors accused Fish
                    of “blundering mismanagement” of Cuban affairs, and House leaders promised to
                    demand a hard policy on Cuba when Congress reconvened in December 1872.</p>
                <p>Fish had to do something before Congress legislated real trouble. Without
                    consulting Grant, on October 29 Fish told United States Minister in Madrid
                    Daniel Sickles to advise Spain that Administration forbearance had its limits.
                        <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                        <graphic url="daniel-edgar-sickles.jpg"/>
                        <head>U.S. Minister to Spain Daniel E. Sickles, in the uniform of a major
                            general during the Civil War (Library of Congress, Prints and
                            Photographs Division, Civil War Photographs Collection,
                            LC-DIG-cwpb-05563)</head>
                    </figure> Entered into the records as Letter of Instruction No. 270, it was, as
                    Fish biographer Alan Nevins said, “The most menacing document…from the State
                    Department during the Grant Administration.”</p>
                <p>Fish recapitulated both the resistance of the colonial government in Cuba to
                    reforms Madrid had mandated and Spain’s inability to prevent the “causeless
                    seizure” of American estates, asking Sickles rhetorically, “If Spain permits her
                    authority to be virtually and practically defied in that island by a refusal or
                    neglect to carry into effect acts of the home government of a humane tendency,
                    is not this tantamount to an acknowledgment of inability to control?”</p>
                <p>The Administration had repeatedly prevented “reckless adventurers…and other
                    partisans of the insurgents” from using U.S. soil to launch “hostile
                    expeditions” against the colonial government. In “discharging those duties…we
                    are conscious of no neglect,” said Fish, “but the trial to our impartiality by
                    the want of success on the part of Spain in suppressing the revolt is
                    necessarily so severe that unless she shall soon be more successful it will
                    force upon this Government the consideration of the question, whether duty to
                    itself and to the commercial interests of its citizens may not demand some
                    change in the line of action it has thus far pursued.”</p>
                <p>Then the menacing instruction:</p>
                <q rend="blockquote">It is hoped that you will present the views above set forth,
                    and the present grievances of which this Government so justly complains… in a
                    way which, without giving offence, will leave a conviction that we are in
                    earnest in the expression of those views, and that we expect redress, and that
                    if it should not soon be afforded Spain must not be surprised to find, as the
                    inevitable result of delay, a marked change in the feeling and in the temper of
                    the people and of the Government of the United States.</q>
                <p>Sickles received his instructions on November 23 (mail was slow by sea). The day
                    before, Spanish Minister of State Cristino Martos y Balbi had given Sickles a
                    copy of a confidential cabinet agreement to abolish slavery and institute
                    sweeping reforms in Puerto Rico by executive decree. But the cabinet abjured any
                    change of policy in Cuba until the insurgents surrendered.</p>
                <p>Sickles delivered his instructions orally to Martos. After a gathering of the
                    diplomatic corps five days later, he read them again to Martos, who copied the
                    threatening paragraph.</p>
                <p>It was a delicate moment. Anticipating President Grant’s December message to
                    Congress, Martos feared that “anything like a hostile demonstration coming from
                    the United States would greatly embarrass Spain by depriving her concession of
                    that spontaneous character so essential to her independence and dignity.” But,
                    Martos reiterated, the Spanish government could not inaugurate reforms in Cuba
                    until it had pacified the island.</p>
                <p>When he learned that No. 270 had failed, Fish decided to apply more tangible
                    pressure. He persuaded Grant to send with his annual message to Congress a
                    recommendation for high discriminatory duties upon goods from Cuba and Puerto
                    Rico. Fish hoped this would satisfy congressmen sympathetic to the Cuban
                    insurrectionists without exciting jingoism. It also would ruin the powerful
                    Spanish sugar growers, who were the slave holders and opponents of reform.</p>
                <p>Fish advised the Spanish minister of Grant’s impending message, and Spain in turn
                    promised to order emancipation in Cuba.</p>
                <p>Doubting Spain’s sincerity, Fish opted for a middle course. He removed the tariff
                    threat from Grant’s draft message as too menacing. Instead, to show Congress
                    that the Grant Administration nonetheless was serious about Cuba, he inserted
                    Instruction No. 270 into the diplomatic correspondence for publication in <hi rend="italic">FRUS.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Fish was right to doubt Madrid. A bill calling for immediate emancipation in
                    Puerto Rico sailed through the Spanish Senate in late December, but the Spanish
                    government retracted its pledge on Cuba. Meanwhile, in the U.S. Congress,
                    Republican Senator Frank P. Blair introduced a resolution anticipating a joint
                    U.S.-Latin American demarche to Spain for Cuban independence. In the House,
                    Foreign Affairs Chairman Nathaniel P. Banks was drafting a resolution demanding
                    Grant take firm action to protect American interests in Cuba.</p>
                <p> The 1872 <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volume was published on
                    January 8, 1873. The American press greeted Instruction No. 270 with a mix of
                    wonder, admiration, skepticism, and fear. The New York <hi rend="italic">Herald
                        Tribune</hi> was delighted; this “surprising manifestation of backbone on
                    the part of [Secretary Fish] was “a plain hint that a new line of action will be
                    adopted.”</p>
                <p>But the always hostile New York <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> remained skeptical.
                    “Since [No. 270] was written, the State department appears to have relapsed into
                    a state of indifference, being satisfied, we suppose, with having made the usual
                    red-tape demonstration.” The Cincinnati <hi rend="italic">Commercial
                        Tribune</hi> worried that Fish’s “ominous” dispatch might lead to war. “We
                    cannot help thinking that the language of Secretary Fish must have amazed the
                    Spanish government. It is not often that such language is used in diplomatic
                    dispatches unless it be meant as a prelude to hostilities.”</p>
                <p>Praise of Fish turned to mockery when Spain announced it had not seen No. 270.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> wondered, “In whose mouth lives the diplomatic
                    lie?” The <hi rend="italic">Herald Tribune</hi> withdrew its endorsement of
                    Fish’s course. The Spanish denial, it said, was a “dilemma [with] no favorable
                    horn. If Mr. Fish knew his instructions had not been carried out in Madrid,
                    there is an apparent disingenuousness in printing this note…. If he did not know
                    this, the discipline of the Department is extraordinarily lax, and the
                    publication was a piece of reckless thoughtlessness. In any event, the effect of
                    the incident cannot but be unfortunate. But the whole country read yesterday the
                    words in which [Spain] indirectly accuses our government of a deception
                    practiced upon our own people. It is highly desirable that this should be
                    explained.”</p>
                <p>The Spanish Senate (upper chamber of the legislative branch, or Cortes) also
                    demanded an explanation. Brandishing a copy of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, on
                    January 16, 1873, the Conservative opposition called upon the government to
                    follow the American example and provide the <hi rend="italic">Cortes</hi> with
                    its diplomatic correspondence on Cuba. He dismissed the government’s claim not
                    to have received No. 270, and accused it of having granted emancipation in
                    Puerto Rico in a “cowardly attempt to conciliate America,” an act that “could
                    only strengthen the hands of the rebels in Cuba.” Several days of acrimonious
                    debate ensued between Conservatives and government ministers, who reiterated
                    their denial.</p>
                <p>The London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> entered the fray on behalf of the United
                    States, reminding its readers that for two years both the Grant Administration
                    and Her Majesty’s Government had exercised a “gentle pressure” on behalf of
                    Puerto Rican independence, and that the Spanish government “have all along been
                    pledged to emancipation in Puerto Rico instantly, and in Cuba as soon as peace
                    may be restored.”</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, Secretary Fish was trying to limit the damage domestically and bring
                    Spain into line. He told the press that the Spanish government had not, strictly
                    speaking, received his note because he had written it to Sickles, and Sickles
                    had read it to the minister of state. “No copy would be furnished unless asked
                    for, and none was asked for,” averred Fish, “so that, diplomatically speaking,
                    the government has received no such communication; but the Spanish government
                    has full knowledge of the latest views of this government on the subject of
                    slavery in the Spanish West Indian possessions, whatever they may say in the <hi rend="italic">Cortes</hi>.”</p>
                <p>Fish’s explanation left the New York <hi rend="italic">Herald Tribune</hi> cold.
                    “We would suggest that the American people had quite sufficient of this
                    diplomatic humbug…and they would like now a little plain, intelligible language.
                    Let us know where the responsibility rests.”</p>
                <p>Privately, Fish told the Spanish minister to the United States that he had done
                    Spain a favor in publishing No. 270 and related correspondence. Fish noted in
                    his diary that he had told the Spanish minister that the “publication of the
                    letters submitted with the president’s December 2 message to Congress was
                    necessary to satisfy Congress that the administration had the subject in
                    hand—that the danger has been and is one of the question of Congressional
                    debate, which would give occasion to the utterance of many hard things and would
                    agitate the public mind.” Fish begged the minister to ask Madrid to desist from
                    further denials or controversial statements on the matter.</p>
                <p>Whatever Fish’s original intent, he clearly did not have “the subject in hand.”
                    American opinion was hardening in favor of intervention in Cuba. The press
                    expected Grant to take a firm stand in his March 4 inaugural address. On
                    February 3, the House Foreign Affairs Committee reported out a resolution asking
                    Grant to talk informally with European governments about joint measures to
                    protect non-combatants in Cuba, hasten emancipation, and promote peace.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cortes.jpg"/>
                    <head>A Convenient Intervention: Proclaiming the New Republic in the Spanish
                        Cortes, February 1873. The creation of a Republican government in Spain
                        diffused the diplomatic crisis between the United States and Spain caused by
                        the Cuban insurrection. (London <hi rend="italic">Graphic</hi>, March 8,
                        1873)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>But Providence smiled on Fish. On February 9, Spain declared for a republic. The
                    well-meaning but ineffectual King Amadeus abdicated. The two chambers of the <hi rend="italic">Cortes</hi> coalesced into a National Assembly. Fish
                    telegraphed Sickles to recognize the republican government “as soon as it was
                    fully established.” Sickles apparently exceeded his instructions and announced
                    that the United States had “determined to cooperate as far as it depends upon
                    them in bringing the insurrection in Cuba to an end.” Not even the
                    interventionists objected. All America rejoiced at the birth of a new republic
                    in the monarchical Old World.</p>
                <p>Although history has forgotten the No. 270 affair, the fundamental question it
                    posed returned as the core American argument during the 1895 rebellion: that
                    Spanish authority in Cuba had collapsed in Cuba. Unfortunately, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> could not help the U.S. and Spain find a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> in the 1890s.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> that Fish disdained in 1869 turned out to be a
                    useful tool for the Secretary’s public diplomacy in 1873.</p>
                <p>What more does this episode tell us about post-bellum 19th Century <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> using our expanded definition? First, that it could
                    have an impact on policy. Second, that the volumes received high-level scrutiny
                    in the Department; this was not an isolated case of a Secretary reviewing a <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume. Third, it could serve as a public diplomacy
                    and public affairs tool. Fourth, that it was integral to the foreign policy
                    debate between the Executive and legislative branches. And lastly, as the 1872
                    volume did for Dan Sickles, correspondence in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volumes sometimes put ministers in embarrassing predicaments and had a chilling
                    effect on candor in reporting.</p>
                <p>Most 19th Century <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes were noncontroversial, and
                    their publication went largely unnoticed. But incidents such the No. 270 affair,
                    which arose from the engagement of the highest levels of the Department in its
                    composition and the immediacy of its contents, leave little doubt that <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> then lay far closer to the heart of U.S.
                    policy-making than does its comparatively tardy 20th and 21st Century
                    descendents.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>