<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Exploring the History of the First <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> Volume</title>
                <title type="short">The First <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    Volume</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-06-13">June 13, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In 2011, the Department of State celebrates the 150th anniversary of its official
                    documentary history publication, <ref target="/historicaldocuments">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>
                    </ref> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>). Ironically for a project staffed by
                    historians, much of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>’s own history is shrouded in
                    mystery. I am part of a team within the Office of the Historian which has been
                    doing some research to learn more about the series’ past and the context in
                    which it was created. During the year we’ll be highlighting notable and
                    controversial moments in the series’ history here on this website. My own work
                    has focused on the first volume, published in December 1861. <ref
                        target="frus1861">The volume</ref> includes over 400 pages of correspondence
                    between U.S. diplomats abroad and Secretary of State William Seward, and was
                    released as part of President Abraham Lincoln’s annual message to Congress.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="cox-samuel-sullivan.jpg"/>
                    <head>Samuel Sullivan Cox, Democrat from Ohio</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Historians usually start their research with a particular question about the past
                    that they want to answer. The question may be interesting in its own right, or
                    it may help illuminate a contemporary issue. In the case of the first volume of
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, we had two main questions: (1) Was the release
                    of this publication a unique event in the Department’s history? (2) Who made the
                    decision to release the volume? In this blog post, I’ll try to answer these
                    questions as best as our present research allows.</p>
                <p>First, a bit of context: the argument over slavery in the United States had
                    reached a point in 1860 where it could no longer be contained by the country’s
                    political structure. South Carolina seceded from the United States after the
                    election of Abraham Lincoln, and other southern states soon followed. A key
                    diplomatic challenge faced by the United States in 1861 was to prevent the
                    fledgling Confederacy from gaining recognition from foreign powers. In December
                    1861, Lincoln published diplomatic correspondence with 24 countries, most of
                    which focused on this very issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Was the release of this publication a unique event in the
                        Department’s history?</hi> One of the first things we learned was that the
                    United States has a long history of releasing diplomatic documentation to the
                    public, and the tradition predates the release of this volume in 1861. <ref
                        target="http://books.google.com/books?id=unMFAAAAQAAJ&amp;dq=Message%20of%20the%20President%20of%20the%20United%20States%20to%20Congress%20Relative%20to%20France%20and%20Great-Britain.%20Delivered%20December%205%2C%201793&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                        >In 1793, for example,</ref> President George Washington submitted to
                    Congress documentation relative to relations with France and Great Britain. In
                    his introductory statement, Washington noted that the “present situation of the
                    several nations of Europe” would be a “matter of interesting inquiry to the
                    legislature, and may indeed give rise to deliberations, to which they alone are
                    competent.” Therefore, Washington felt it was his “duty to communicate to them,
                    certain correspondences, which have taken place.” Dozens of pages of
                    correspondence followed, including letters between Secretary of State Thomas
                    Jefferson and Citizen Genet, Minister from France. Washington sent the materials
                    to Congress, and Congress published them for public consumption. In the decades
                    leading up to the Civil War, Congress consistently requested—and successive
                    Presidents delivered—documentation relating to foreign relations, usually with
                    the caveat that they would only release what was in the “public interest.” These
                    documents would then be published in the <ref
                        target="http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/amlaw/lwss.html">U.S. Serial Set</ref>.
                    Thus, the correspondence released in 1861 was not unique in that correspondence
                    had been released before. However, the 1861 volume did represent an important
                    evolution, if not a revolution. Prior to 1861, document releases were on an ad
                    hoc basis and tended to be about one issue (relations with one country or the
                    negotiation of a single treaty). The 1861 volume is much more comprehensive and
                    discusses relations around the world under a single cover. It also sparked the
                    regular, annual publication of correspondence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Who made the decision to release the volume?</hi> The request
                    for correspondence came directly from Congress. On July 13, 1861, Samuel
                    Sullivan Cox (Democrat from Ohio) submitted <ref
                        target="http://memory.loc.gov/ll/llcg/057/0100/01350117.tif">a
                        resolution</ref> to the House of Representatives, to which he “presume[d],
                    there will be no objection.” The resolution was promptly “read, considered, and
                    agreed to,” and it stated “<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the President
                    of the United States, at the beginning of the next session of Congress, or at
                    this session, if compatible with the public service, communicate to this House
                    all correspondence with the English, French, Spanish, and other Governments with
                    reference to the right of blockade, privateering, and the recognition of the
                    so-called confederate States.” Another resolution to the same effect passed in
                    the House two days later, and shortly thereafter the Senate passed its own
                    resolution. Although Congress did not get its wish until the end of the year, it
                    is clear that the impetus for the release came from Congress. This Congressional
                    request, combined with what we know about previous releases of documentation,
                    helps us see <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> from a slightly different angle.
                    Although released by the Department of State, it was not a simple creation of
                    the executive branch. Rather, it was a response to the demands of the
                    legislative branch. Thus, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> is an excellent example of
                    the separation of powers in our government: one branch executes foreign policy,
                    another branch keeps a watchful eye on activities by requesting documentation
                    showing how the policies are carried out.</p>
                <p>To sum up, our office’s research into the early history of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> has taught us some important things. First, our government has a
                    history of releasing foreign relations-related documents that stretches back to
                    the beginning of the republic. Second, the releases represent the balance of
                    powers between two branches of government. Today, the Office of the Historian
                    continues to publish important documents relating to foreign relations. And we
                    continue to do so under a Congressional mandate; the series is currently
                    governed by a law passed by Congress in 1991. In this case, the historical
                    questions we began with illuminate the past and help show some links to the
                    present day. In future posts, my colleagues from the Office will be discussing
                    other lessons we can learn from the 150 years of foreign relations
                    documentation. Stay tuned!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
