<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">What Do Those Asterisks Mean?</title>
                <title type="short">What Do Those Asterisks Mean?</title>
                <author>Aaron W. Marrs</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2011-09-13">September 13, 2011</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In my <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/the-first-volume"
                        >previous blog post</ref>, I discussed how historians start their research
                    with a question about the past. In this post, I’ll talk about another question
                    that we in the Office of the Historian have had about <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/frus1861">the first <hi
                            rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume</ref> published in 1861: what material
                    was left out?</p>
                <p>Answering this question seems difficult at first. We know very little about the
                    clerks who compiled the first <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume. The Department
                    was much smaller in the nineteenth century than it is today, with <ref
                        target="http://history.state.gov/about/faq/department-personnel">only 42
                        domestic employees in 1860</ref>. Therefore, it is difficult to imagine that
                    a project of this magnitude would have gone unnoticed by Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                    Seward</ref>. Nevertheless, we have no direct evidence of Seward’s involvement
                    in the publication of the volume, nor do we know the standards by which
                    materials were selected for inclusion.</p>
                <p>This is unfortunate, because some of the documents published in the first volume
                    have excisions; a row of asterisks was printed where material was cut out. This
                    presents historians with a double challenge: not only do we not know what
                    material was excised, but we also don’t know why the editors of the first volume
                    chose to exclude the information.</p>
                <p>But historians don’t give up easily! As it happens, there is another way to
                    investigate this particular question. The <ref target="http://www.archives.gov/"
                        >National Archives</ref> holds some of the original documents published in
                    the first volume. In this blog post, I’ll focus on correspondence between
                    Washington and U.S. diplomats in London. When U.S. Minister to Great Britain
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles
                        Francis Adams</ref> prepared <ref
                        target="http://blogs.archives.gov/TextMessage/2011/03/11/foreign-service-friday/"
                        >a despatch</ref> to send back to Washington, the text was also copied into
                    a book kept at the legation’s office. Those books now sit at the National
                    Archives as part of Record Group 84. Office of the Historian staff member
                    Forrest Barnum has compared the full text of despatches in RG 84 to the copies
                    printed in the first volume, and discovered some interesting things. By looking
                    at the material not included in the volume, we can make inferences about the
                    methodologies used by the clerks at the time.</p>
                <figure rend="smallfloatinline">
                    <graphic url="lord-john-russell.jpg"/>
                    <head>Lord John Russell, British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs during
                        the Civil War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>What we have discovered is that the excisions ranged widely in terms of how they
                    altered the meaning of the original despatch (if at all). Some of the material
                    cut out was of little consequence. For example, information about consular
                    appointments was deleted from the printed volume, which probably has little
                    impact on the utility of the volume to a modern scholar. But in other cases, the
                    information left out of the printed version changes the meaning or tone of the
                    original. On September 28, 1861, Adams sent a despatch to Washington recounting
                    his conversation with British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs Lord John
                    Russell at Abergeldie Castle in Scotland. The editors of the volume decided to
                    print the portion of Adams’s message where he registered a complaint about the
                    reception of an “insurgent privateer” by “authorities at Trinidad” (at the time
                    ruled by the British), but the vast majority of the despatch was left out.
                    Excised material included details about Adams’s trip to Scotland, (he carped
                    that “the invitation was very much as if you were to ask [British Minister to
                    the United States] Lord Lyons to come and see you and talk of business at Auburn
                    instead of Washington, with the exception that the expense of traveling here is
                    about six times greater than in America”), the fact that the journey afforded
                    him “abundant opportunity for full and free conversation” with Lord Russell, a
                    lengthy discussion of European interest in Mexico, and British complaints about
                    “seizure and imprisonment” of British subjects. Adams concluded the despatch by
                    noting that “during the whole of my stay at Abergeldie Castle I thought I
                    perceived the symptoms of a more friendly and cordial feeling than had ever been
                    manifested to me before,” which “fully compensated me for the length and fatigue
                    of the journey.” In this case, the details of Adams’s protest about the
                    treatment of Confederate ships were deemed more important (or less sensitive)
                    than his views of how he was treated by the British by the 1861 <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compiler(s).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="abergeldie-castle.jpg"/>
                    <head>Abergeldie Castle, Scotland, site of a September 1861 meeting between Lord
                        Russell and Charles Francis Adams</head>
                </figure>
                <p>One excision was even starker in terms of its potential impact had it been
                    disclosed in 1861. On August 16, Adams wrote that the effect of Union defeat at
                    Bull Run on July 21 was damaging because of the “ridicule it exposes the country
                    to” rather than because of the “positive loss” stemming from the battle itself.
                    This portion of Adams’s message was omitted from the published volume. Adams
                    noted that the “military spirit of Europe does not reconcile itself to such
                    scenes as have been distinctly painted by the European correspondence of the
                    London Times, and the American press, as well as caricatured in Punch.” Reports
                    in the European press of Federal defeat were clearly not helping the Union
                    cause. In the published portion of the despatch, Adams noted his instructions to
                    speak to Lord Russell about the blockade of Confederate shipping. In the excised
                    portion, Adams admitted that were he to take a “strong tone” in the midst of the
                    atmosphere of ridicule spawned by Bull Run, he would “scarcely likely do more
                    than to provide a smile” on the faces of his interlocutors. Rather, Adams wrote,
                    he should “await an hour doubtless not far distant when the people of the United
                    States will have redeemed their reputation for judgment and skill and courage”
                    and have proven that they can survive war “without the guidance or control of
                    the military or civil officers of the slaveholding States.” Washington’s demand
                    for a conference and its topic stayed in the volume; the embarrassing reasons
                    for Adams’s delay were kept out.</p>
                <p>There are at least three lessons to learn from these excisions. First, some of
                    the excisions were clearly innocuous, so the presence of excisions does not
                    necessarily indicate a grand design to withhold information from the U.S.
                    public. Congress was hardly concerned with the names and arrival dates of
                    consular officials when it requested information about the country’s foreign
                    relations from the Lincoln administration. These excisions should not trouble
                    us.</p>
                <p>A second conclusion is that some of the excised information <hi rend="italic"
                        >was</hi> quite significant. Adams communicated that the United States was
                    embarrassed abroad by the defeat at Bull Run; printing this information in the
                    volume clearly would imperil morale at home. Therefore, we can see why the
                    Lincoln administration might have excluded that portion of Adams’s report when
                    it passed the rest of the document to Congress. It is clear that modern
                    researchers can’t learn everything that they might like simply by reading the
                    printed volume; historians have to look at the full text of the originals as
                    well.</p>
                <p>Yet there is also a third conclusion: even if the printed volume has excisions,
                    this does not mean that it is worthless. Rather, the volume tells us what the
                    Lincoln administration wanted the public to know about foreign relations during
                    the Civil War. The volume served a public relations purpose to inform Americans
                    that the government was energetically combating Confederate efforts to gain
                    foreign recognition. This meant obscuring some unpleasant truths (such as the
                    British reaction to Bull Run). But nevertheless, understanding the material that
                    was left out of the volume can help us learn more about the intent of those who
                    put the volume together.</p>
                <p>I hope this post has demonstrated some of the ways in which historians can work
                    to fill apparent gaps in the historical record and make inferences about the
                    past in the absence of direct evidence. We don’t know if the first <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> compilers made excisions from documents on the basis
                    of formal instructions or their own judgments. We can’t state conclusively why
                    specific material was excised from the 1861 volume. Instead, we have to make
                    intelligent inferences after examining surviving primary sources.</p>
                <p>One of the themes explored in researching the history of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> is the evolution of how the series was produced over time.
                    Informing the public about what type of material has been excised and why
                    represents a clear shift in policy from the nineteenth century to today. We have
                    gone from a series of asterisks to a formal, explicit, rigorous standard which
                    governs today’s <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes. The rules for excisions are
                    encoded in 22 U.S.C. 4351(b): “The editing of records for preparation of the
                    FRUS series shall be guided by the principles of historical objectivity and
                    accuracy. Records shall not be altered and deletions shall not be made without
                    indicating in the published text that a deletion has been made. The published
                    record shall omit no facts which were of major importance in reaching a
                    decision, and nothing shall be omitted for the purpose of concealing a defect of
                    policy.” When material cannot be included in a <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    volume published today, the amount of material excluded is always clearly shown
                    in the text. As a result, today’s <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes embody a
                    great deal more accountability than their earliest ancestors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
