<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">“A Burden for the Department”?: To The 1991 <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> Statute</title>
                <title type="short">To The 1991 <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> Statute</title>
                <author>Joshua Botts</author>
                <sponsor>Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2012-02-06">February 6, 2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This post is adapted from a longer piece on the history of <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. See Joshua Botts, “<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> at 150: The
                    Evolution of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> Series,” paper
                    presented at the 11th International Conference of Editors of Diplomatic
                    Documents, September 20, 2011. Available <ref
                        target="http://www.archives.gov.il/ArchiveGov_Eng/Publications/ElectronicPirsum/EditorsConference2011/EditorsConferenceContents.htm"
                        >online</ref> (accessed February 2, 2011).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Between 1980 and 1991, the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United
                        States</hi> (<hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>) series entered a period of crisis.
                    In the early part of the decade, the academic community grew more concerned
                    about the increasing lag of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> publication from the
                    20-year line formally established for the series by President Richard Nixon in
                        1972.<note n="1">Richard Nixon, memorandum attached to Executive Order
                        11652, March 8, 1972. See <ref
                            target="http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-11652.htm"
                            >http://www.fas.org/irp/offdocs/eo/eo-11652.htm</ref> (accessed February
                        2, 2012).</note> By the end of the decade, these anxieties were supplanted
                    by bitter criticism from academic, media, and Congressional sources of gaps in
                        <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> coverage of pivotal Cold War covert actions. In
                    1991, Congress intervened to shape the future of the series that it had <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/foundation-of-frus"
                        >helped to create</ref> by establishing a statutory mandate for both
                    timeliness and comprehensiveness for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> production.
                    Throughout the entire period, the Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic
                    Documentation (also known as the Historical Advisory Committee, or <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/formation-of-the-hac"
                        >HAC</ref>) played a crucial role in mediating (sometimes unsuccessfully)
                    the tensions generated by clashing demands for openness and for security.</p>
                <p>In response to academic concerns about the growing lag in <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> publication in the early 1980s following the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/1980-rereview">1980
                        re-review</ref>, the Department of State attempted to clarify intra- and
                    interagency arrangements for releasing historical information at a 30-year line.
                    In doing so, the Department rejected academic demands for a 25-year line,
                    arguing that “so many documents of American and foreign origin would require
                    protection that a 25-year line would prove a chimera.” To fill the gap, the
                    Department proposed expanding its publication of more recent unclassified
                    documentation, accelerating the production of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations</hi> volumes covering the Vietnam War, and pursuing selective
                    high-profile special volumes (similar to the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/politics-of-the-yalta-frus"
                        >wartime conference series from the 1950s</ref>) on U.S.-Soviet relations
                    and U.S. policy toward Central America. Even meeting a 30-year line with
                    existing resources would require Department historians to adhere to strict
                    limits on the number of volumes prepared for each subseries (and on the size of
                    each volume). To stay within these limits even as the available documentation
                    continued to grow, the Department proposed augmenting <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> with purportedly labor- and cost-effective microfilm publications
                    to supplement the traditional printed volumes. The Department plan envisioned
                    publishing all the volumes documenting the Eisenhower administration—and thereby
                    meeting a 30-year line for the series—by 1990.<note n="2">Department of State
                        [PA/HO] Staff Study on the Recommendations of the Advisory Committee on
                        Historical Diplomatic Documentation in its Annual Report of December 21,
                        1983, October 1984 (with attached documents and analysis), Folder “June 1991
                        (84 Plan),” Box 1, Lot File 09 D 473, Department of State, Washington, DC.
                        Quote from attached John Hughes memorandum to Secretary of State, January
                        30, 1984, p. 4. See also Ian Black, “Tightened Rules Keep Nation’s Secrets
                        Too Long, Historians Say,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, September
                        10, 1983, p. A3; Lorraine Lees and Sandra Treadway, “A Future for Our
                        Diplomatic Past? A Critical Appraisal of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                            Relations</hi> Series,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of American
                            History</hi> (December 1983), pp. 621-629; and William Slany, “Report by
                        the Historian of the Department of State,” July 1984, P840134-2027,
                        Department of State Microfilmed Central Files, Washington, DC (henceforth
                        DoS P-Reels). Academic concerns about the timeliness of <hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi> publication was not exclusively driven by interest in the
                        volumes themselves. Until the passage of the 1991 law, declassification
                        guidelines for the Department of State’s historical records were devised in
                        conjunction with the clearance of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                        compilations. In other words, when <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was delayed,
                        researcher access to historical Department records was also delayed.</note>
                    President Ronald Reagan issued an interagency directive implementing the
                    Department of State plan on November 12, 1985.<note n="3">Ronald Reagan
                        memorandum for Secretary of State, et al., November 12, 1985, P860009-1020,
                        DoS P-Reels. See also Bernard Kalb memorandum to Secretary of State,
                        December 18, 1985, P860009-0998 and Ronald Spiers cable to all diplomatic
                        posts, February 25, 1986, 1986 State 057676 in Department of State Central
                        Files (SAS), Washington, DC.</note></p>
                <p>As concerned as scholars were about the timeliness of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                    in the early 1980s, later in the decade they focused their attention on
                    disturbing evidence that the integrity of the series was endangered by the
                    difficulties of documenting the shadowy world of Cold War-era covert operations.
                    In 1983, the Department of State released a seriously flawed volume on U.S.
                    policy toward Latin America. Because Department historians lacked access to
                    intelligence community records, they could not include the (well-known) story of
                    a covert operation undertaken by the CIA in Guatemala in their compilation.<note
                        n="4">Bernard Gwertzman, “U.S. Tells of ’54 Guatemala Invasion,” <hi
                            rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, January 4, 1984, p. A3.</note> Though
                    the Guatemala volume did not spark a scholarly revolt, it foreshadowed the
                    explosive controversy that erupted seven years later when a similarly incomplete
                    volume on Iran was published.<note n="5">Al Kamen, “Historians Say Secrecy
                        Distorts Foreign Policy Chronicle,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>,
                        April 16, 1990, p. A13.</note> In the context of increasingly serious
                    omissions and growing declassification problems, the HAC sought access to
                    excised documents so it could examine the troublesome records for itself and
                    determine whether or not <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> indeed represented “a full
                    and honest account of American foreign policy.”<note n="6">Charles Redman
                        memorandum to Ronald Spiers, June 2, 1987, P870122-1080, DoS P-Reels and
                        Warren Cohen, “Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation
                        Report,” <hi rend="italic">Perspectives</hi> (May-June 1989), <ref
                            target="http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/1989/8905/8905NOTE2.cfm"
                            >http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/1989/8905/8905NOTE2.cfm</ref>
                        (accessed August 15, 2011).</note></p>
                <p>By the late 1980s, however, Department officials had grown frustrated with the
                    HAC and its demands. The committee’s insistence on access to excised documents
                    sparked tensions with officials outside of the Historian’s Office. While HO and
                    its parent Bureau of Public Affairs argued that the HAC served an essential
                    function and that cooperation would improve the series and protect the
                    Department from damaging criticism, the Classification/Declassification Center
                    and the Bureau of Management characterized the committee’s support for openness
                    as an inherent conflict of interest. By 1988, hostility to the HAC led one
                    senior official to demand that PA do a better job of managing the committee and
                    to threaten to revoke its charter should it became “a burden for the
                        Department.”<note n="7">Ronald Spiers memorandum to Charles Redman, November
                        10, 1988, P890058-1591, DoS P-Reels.</note></p>
                <p>Though Department officials thought they could use the dispute over access to
                    denied documents to restore control over the HAC, their gambit had unintended
                    consequences that diminished Departmental authority over the direction of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series. When the Department reneged
                    on an agreement to allow the HAC access to documents denied clearance, the
                    committee’s chairman, Warren Cohen, resigned in protest.<note n="8">Warren Cohen
                        letter to James Baker, February 15, 1990, P900159-0985, DoS P-Reels and
                        Warren Cohen, “Gaps in the Record: How State has allowed history to be
                        incomplete,” <hi rend="italic">Foreign Service Journal</hi> (August 1990),
                        pp. 27-29. </note> By 1990, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> was denounced as “a
                    fraud” not only by Cohen and other historians, but also by influential U.S.
                    Senators and the New York Times.<note n="9">Warren Cohen, “At the State Dept.,
                        Historygate,” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, May 8, 1990, p. A29;
                        Bruce Kuniholm, “Foreign Relations, Public Relations, Accountability, and
                        Understanding,” <hi rend="italic">Perspectives</hi> (May-June 1990), pp.
                        1-12, <ref
                            target="http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/1990/9005/9005NOTE1.cfm"
                            >http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/1990/9005/9005NOTE1.cfm</ref>
                        (accessed August 9, 2011); “History Bleached at State,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >New York Times</hi>, May 16, 1990, p. A26; and Claiborne Pell and David
                        Boren, “Why U.S. Foreign Policy Records Are ‘A Fraud,’” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Boston Globe</hi>, May 27, 1990, p. A22.</note> The ensuing
                    Congressional scrutiny of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series in
                    1990-91 both echoed the constitutional origins of the U.S. Government’s release
                    of diplomatic documents and reflected the intervening transformations in U.S.
                    foreign relations, government institutions, and political culture that shaped
                    the evolution of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in the twentieth century.</p>
                <p>The Department’s obstinacy in the face of controversy encouraged Congress to
                    intervene. On October 19, 1990, Senator Claiborne Pell lamented that “questions
                    have been raised about the integrity of our own historical record at the very
                    time that in Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union, and elsewhere we are witnessing a
                    flood of disclosures and new documentation from governments long used to
                    concealing and falsifying the record.” After noting that, “the vigor that
                    democracy draws from the clean breeze of honest information,” Pell warned that
                    “this is no time for the United States to depart from the tradition of providing
                    an accurate and complete historical record of the actions taken by our
                    government in the field of foreign relations.”<note n="10"><hi rend="italic"
                            >Congressional Record – Senate</hi>, vol. 136, pt. 22, October 19, 1990,
                        p. 31389.</note> Along with Senator Jesse Helms of the Foreign Relations
                    Committee and Senators David Boren and William Cohen of the Select Committee on
                    Intelligence, Pell secured Senate approval of a legislative mandate for <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> requiring full access to historical documentation
                    for Department historians and the HAC and publication at a 30-year line.<note
                        n="11">Helen Dewar, “Senate Panel’s Quest: Filling Gaps in History of
                        Foreign Relations,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, June 11, 1990,
                        p. A13.</note></p>
                <p>Although the House of Representatives did not approve the Senate’s bill before
                    the end of the 1990 Congressional session, the Department of State acted to try
                    to preempt legislation in 1991 by proposing modest reforms for <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>. The Department’s proposal envisioned yet another round of
                    Presidential memoranda to spur interagency cooperation, more transparency about
                    the nature of omissions in published <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volumes, and a
                    reaffirmation of the HAC’s role in providing guidance for the series (albeit
                    under a Departmental, and not a Congressional, mandate). Though members of the
                    HAC worked with the Department as it formulated the so-called “A Plan,” they
                    remained suspicious of the Department’s commitment to <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi>’s integrity and supportive of Congressional initiatives to
                    establish a legislative mandate for the series.<note n="12">“A Plan to Improve
                        the Comprehensiveness and Accuracy of the Historical Foreign Affairs Record
                        Published in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>,”
                        February 5, 1991 and William Slany memorandum for the record, February 5,
                        1991 in Folder “Program – A Plan – Feb. 91,” Box 1, Lot File 09 D 473,
                        Department of State, Washington, DC and Warren Kimball letter to James
                        Baker, January 14, 1992, P920042-0683 and Arnita Jones letter to James
                        Baker, April 12, 1990, P900159-0982 in DoS P-Reels; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Congressional Record – Senate</hi>, vol. 136, pt. 22, October 19, 1990,
                        pp. 31391-31399, <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi>; Page Putnam Miller, “The
                        Integrity of the U.S. Department of State’s Historical Series is at Stake,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Government Publications Review</hi> (July-August
                        1991), pp. 317-323; <hi rend="italic">Congressional Record – Senate</hi>,
                        vol. 137, pt. 14, July 29, 1991, pp. 20245-20248, <hi rend="italic"
                            >passim.</hi></note></p>
                <p>In October 1991, the U.S. Congress enacted what became known as “the <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> statute” as part of the Department of State’s Basic
                    Authorities Act. The <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> statute went further than the
                    Department’s “A Plan” to strengthen the integrity of <hi rend="italic"
                    >FRUS</hi>. In an ironic inversion of the dynamic that led to the formation of
                    the HAC in the mid-1950s, Congress replaced the HAC’s existing Departmental
                    mandate with a statutory one to ensure that the Department of State would have
                    to engage the academic community’s judgments about the series. The law mandated
                    that HO historians have access to documents that were aged 26 years or older
                    from all agencies involved in national security and foreign policymaking within
                    the U.S. Government to determine if they should be included in the series. It
                    also empowered the HAC with “need to know” for access to documents that were not
                    cleared for publication in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>.<note n="13">22 USC 4351,
                            <hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>. See also Al Kamen, “Documents Law: 30
                        Years and Out,” <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, October 31, 1991, p.
                        A19 and Page Putnam Miller, “We Can’t Yet Read Our Own Mail: Access to the
                        Records of the Department of State,” in Athan Theoharis, ed., <hi
                            rend="italic">A Culture of Secrecy: The Government Versus the People’s
                            Right to Know</hi> (Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, 1998),
                        pp. 186-210, especially pp. 195-201. The law also had significant provisions
                        mandating the systematic declassification of Department of State records
                        after 30 years. Essentially, the law decoupled the declassification of
                        general Department of State records from the production of <hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi>.</note> The Department of State opposed the statute and, in a
                    signing statement, President George H. W. Bush reminded <hi rend="italic"
                        >FRUS</hi> stakeholders that the new statutory mandate “must be interpreted
                    in conformity with my constitutional responsibility and authority to protect the
                    national security of the United States by preventing the disclosure of state
                        secrets.”<note n="14">George H. W. Bush, “Statement on Signing the Foreign
                        Relations Authorization Act, Fiscal Years 1992 and 1993,” October 28, 1991,
                            <ref target="http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/print.php?pid=20152"
                            >http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/print.php?pid=20152</ref> (accessed
                        August 16, 2011).</note> Just as was the case in the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/constitutional-basis-of-frus"
                        >nineteenth century</ref>, the approval of a statutory mandate for the
                    Foreign Relations series in 1991 led Congress and officials in the executive
                    branch to clarify their constitutional responsibilities.</p>
                <p>The passage of a statutory mandate for <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>
                    in 1991 had significant implications for the series’ production process.<note
                        n="15">See Folders “1992 – HAC Meetings/Briefing Mat.”; “1992 – HAC
                        Declassification of <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>”; and “1992 Advisory
                        Committee &amp; Legislation Materials” in Box 1, Lot File 99 D 041 and
                        Folder “Declassification – transfer of Function,” in Lot File 10 D 061,
                        Department of State, Washington, DC.</note> The requirement that <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> be “thorough, accurate, and reliable” and include
                    “comprehensive documentation of major foreign policy decisions and actions of
                    the United States Government” facilitated timely researcher access to a broader
                    range of records than ever before.<note n="16">See Folder “<hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi> – Memos of Understanding – Access 1992,” Lot File 09 D 480
                        and Folder “1992 – HAC Memos of Understanding/Agreements,” Lot File 99 D
                        041, Department of State, Washington, DC.</note> Surpassing the traditional
                    scope for <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>, volumes produced after the statute
                    quickly established new expectations for comprehensive coverage.<note n="17">See
                        Peter Hahn, “Glasnost in America: <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                            United States</hi> and the Middle East, 1955-1960,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Diplomatic History</hi> (October 1992), pp. 631-642 and Robert
                        Schulzinger, “Transparency, Secrecy, and Citizenship,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Diplomatic History</hi> (Spring 2001), pp. 165-178. For additional
                        assessments of the consequences of the 1991 statute (and the strengthening
                        of the HAC), see Betty Glad and Jonathan Smith, “The Role of the Historical
                        Advisory Committee, 1990-1994, in the Declassification of U.S. Foreign
                        policy Documents and Related Issues,” <hi rend="italic">PS: Political
                            Science and Politics</hi> (June 1996), pp. 185-192 and Page Putnam
                        Miller, “We Can’t Yet Read Our Own Mail: Access to the Records of the
                        Department of State,” pp. 201-208.</note> Unfortunately, the statute’s
                    provisions for expediting declassification did not have the same rapid effect.
                    Steadily lengthening declassification reviews, a steadily worsening “start line”
                    for each <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> subseries, and periodic disruptions caused
                    by staff turnover have prevented HO from meeting the statute’s requirement to
                    publish volumes “not more than 30 years after the events recorded.” Efforts to
                    streamline the production process and leverage new technologies, including
                    digital publication, mitigated some of these difficulties, but could not
                    overcome them. The ongoing failure to meet the statutory deadline has been a
                    source of recurrent criticism from the scholarly community.<note n="18"
                        >Documentation related to the HAC can be found in Department of State lot
                        files scheduled for permanent retention in the National Archives and Records
                        Administration. Pre-1991 HAC files are in 96 D 292. The post-1991 HAC files
                        are located in 99 D 041 (1991-1995 HAC meetings), 00 D 512 (1996-1997 HAC
                        meetings), 02 D 213 (1998-1999 HAC meetings), 03 D 130 (1992-1995 HAC
                        meetings), 04 D 446 (2000-2002 HAC meetings), 09 D 473 (1992-2007 HAC
                        meetings), and in current PA/HO office files. The lot files contain recorded
                        minutes of HAC meetings as well as a variety of briefing materials prepared
                        within PA/HO. Some HAC meeting minutes from the mid-1990s to the present are
                        also available online at <ref target="/about/hac/meeting-notes"
                            >http://history.state.gov/about/hac/meeting-notes</ref> and <ref
                            target="http://www.fas.org/sgp/advisory/state/"
                            >http://www.fas.org/sgp/advisory/state/</ref> (both accessed August 1,
                        2011). The fas.org website, maintained by Steven Aftergood, also includes
                        links to the HAC’s annual reports since 1995.</note> Just as the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/eureka-the-1925-frus-order"
                        >1925 order</ref> could shape, but not settle, disputes over <hi
                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi> in <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/frus-war-in-the-pacific"
                        >1930s</ref> and <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history/research/frus-at-war">1940s</ref>,
                    the 1991 statute provided a foundation for the future of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations</hi> series but could not dictate its course.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
